<topics>
<item>
<Question>
Work begins on the Cuicuilco Pyramid in Mexico. It is the oldest man-made structure in North America.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 7000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Work begins on the circular monument at Stonehenge, England. Dismantled and rebuilt several times during the next 2,000 years, the large rings of standing stones are of unknown use.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 3100 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Work begins on the Great Pyramids at Giza. Originally covered in limestone, these tombs for the pharaohs tower over the landscape.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 2575 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ziggurat at Ur. Made of hard-baked brick, the ziggurat, its exact use unknown, stands as a monument to man's desire to eternalize himself.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 2100 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Work begins on the Palace at Knossos. The rambling structure was expanded over the centuries, and at its largest contained dwellings, storerooms, and a theatre.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 2000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
"Treasury of Atreus." Actually a large beehive tomb, this structure was misnamed by its discoverer, Heinrich Schliemann, who thought it was a storehouse.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1300 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hypostyle Hall, Temple of Amon-Re, Karnak. This hall was intended to re-create the effect of the reeds of the life-giving Nile.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1290 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Lion Gate, Mycenae. This massive triangular relief with elaborate lions stands guard over the outer gate of a fortress-palace.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1250 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sargon II's palace at Khorsabad, now in Iraq, is dedicated. Built in monumental dimensions, this structure covers more than 23 acres (9 hectares).
</Question>
<Choice>706 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ishtar Gate. Part of the grand approach to the sacred precinct of Bel-Zeus, the lions decorating the walls give a sense of forward motion.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 575 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Palace of Darius, Susa. The remaining elements show that the palace was constructed of stone, brick, and wood.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 510 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Royal Audience Hall, Persepolis. Destroyed by Alexander the Great to symbolize defeat of the Persians, even the ruins of this palace show how impressive it was.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 500 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Temple of Hera II (or Temple of Neptune), Paestum. With its massive columns closely spaced, this provincial temple shows the Doric at its most powerful.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 460 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ictinus and Callicrates begin work on the Parthenon. Built by the city of Athens, this complex includes the temple of Athena Nike.
</Question>
<Choice>447 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Erechtheum, a temple of Athena built on the Acropolis at Athens, Greece, is completed. It is noted for its fine details and Ionic capitals.
</Question>
<Choice>405 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Philippeum is built. Featuring Corinthian half columns, it is an example of a Greek tholos.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 390 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Construction begins on the Ellora Caves. Eventually 34 in number, these rock-cut temples are highlighted by Kailasa, which was excavated downward to receive sunlight.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 200 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Altar of Zeus, Pergamum. The altar, with its sculpture spilling out onto the steps, brings the action to the audience.
</Question>
<Choice>175 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Temple of Hathor is completed. One of the best-preserved temples in Egypt, it features an elaborate hypostyle hall.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 37 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Work begins on the Colosseum, Rome. The site of ancient spectacles, the Colosseum was designed for gladitorial games, and could be flooded to re-create naval battles.
</Question>
<Choice>70</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
North African city of Thamugadi is founded by Emperor Trajan. A stunning example of Roman city planning, with its clear and geometrical organization.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 100</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Rebuilding of the Pantheon, Rome. A stunning and influential example of Roman mastery of concrete; a single concrete dome covers the interior.
</Question>
<Choice>118</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Work begins on Hadrian's Wall. Built across the width of northern Britain to guard against barbarians, the divider covers 73 miles (118 km) and features fortlets, forts, and towers.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 122</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The "Treasury," Petra. This massive structure, cut into solid rock, shows the experimentation with classical form in which later Roman architecture delighted.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 200</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Work begins on the Baths of Caracalla. This complex, which included hot and cold rooms, is testament to the sophistication of Roman culture and the role social bathing played within it.
</Question>
<Choice>206</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The basilica at Leptis Magna, Libya, is dedicated. One of the finest surviving examples of Roman architecture, it is elaborately adorned with marble and granite.
</Question>
<Choice>216</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Covering an area of 7 acres (3 hectares), the Palace of Diocletian is the largest and best-preserved example of Roman palatial architecture.
</Question>
<Choice>305</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Basilica of Constantine is finished. This vast basilica uses complex engineering and architectural devices to achieve the spacious openness of its interior.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 313</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Work begins on Old Saint Peter's Basilica, Rome. One of the most influential buildings ever, its design has influenced the form for churches up until the present day.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 326</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Completion of the Hagia Sophia, Constantinople. Originally a church, this vast building was converted after the Ottoman conquest in 1453 to a mosque, when the minarets were added.
</Question>
<Choice>537</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
San Vitale, Ravenna. The stark, plain exterior of this early church hides the brilliant vivid byzantine mosaics of the interior.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 540</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Puuc architectural style begins to flourish in Mexico. Characterized by limestone construction with plaster finishes, it is fully realized at Uxmal.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 600</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Horyu Temple is built. Destroyed by fire in 670 but later rebuilt, it is the central building of a Japanese Buddhist temple complex featuring some of the most ancient wooden buildings in the world.
</Question>
<Choice>607</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Great Mosque of Damascus is built. Its marble grilles are the earliest examples of geometric interlace in Islamic architecture.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 715</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Benedictine abbey, Sankt Gallen. The regimented order of monastic life is made visible in this plan, with the church building as its focus.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 720</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Work begins on the Mosque of Córdoba, Spain. By employing the hypostyle form, architects were able to repeatedly expand this mosque in the 9th and 10th centuries without disturbing its stylistic unity.
</Question>
<Choice>784</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Work begins on the Palatine Chapel of Charlemagne, Aachen, Germany. Thought to have been inspired by San Vitale, this church lacks the brilliance of its model, but its clear ordering makes its interior stunning.
</Question>
<Choice>790</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Borobudur is constructed. Enclosing a small hill, the massive Buddhist temple is shaped like a stepped pyramid and is topped by more than 70 bell-shaped stupas.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 850</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Completion of the Great Mosque, Samarra', Iraq. The largest mosque in the Islamic world has a wooden roof covering half of its ten-acre area. Its spiral minaret is of an interesting and unique form.
</Question>
<Choice>861</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Baptistery of St. John, Florence. Delicacy and classical elements combined make this one of the principal monuments of the Florentine Romanesque.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
St. Michael's Church, Hildesheim. With its massive blank walls and entrances grouped on the side, this building emphasizes length and massing.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Stave churches begin to appear in Norway.</Question>
<Choice>c. 1000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Beginnings of the Cathedral Group of Pisa (baptistery, cathedral, campanile). An impressive grouping of Romanesque buildings, the Leaning Tower is the best-known element.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1050</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Saint-Étienne, Caen. An example of Norman Romanesque, the stark exterior of the church hides a complex internal rhythm.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1060</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
San Miniato al Monte, Florence. The coloured marble facade is a break with earlier church building traditions, which emphasized more austere designs. It is one of the best examples of Tuscan Romanesque.
</Question>
<Choice>1062</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Reconstruction of San Marco Basilica, Venice, completed. The brilliantly coloured mosaics and multiple domes are evidence of the Byzantine connections of this Italian trading city.
</Question>
<Choice>1071</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Saint-Sernin, Toulouse. The grand scale and striking tower of this Romanesque church reflect the popularity of pilgrimage at this time.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1077</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A second, smaller dome is added to the Great Mosque of Esfahan. A structural masterpiece, it is known for its proportion and size.
</Question>
<Choice>1088</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Work begins on Durham Cathedral, England. While extensively altered on the exterior, the interior retains its stark Romanesque qualities.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1093</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Work begins on Angkor Wat. The temple complex represents the zenith of Khmer architecture.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1113</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Benedictine abbey of Saint-Denis, Paris. Influenced by the philosophy of Abbot Suger, the church is a prime example of early Gothic architecture.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1140</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Krak des Chevaliers is built in Syria. Incorporating Byzantine and Muslim innovations, the virtually impregnable fortress is an excellent example of medieval military architecture.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1142</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Work begins on Chartres Cathedral. One of the first High Gothic buildings, it employs flying butresses to increase the feeling of lightness by allowing for a larger clerestory.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1145</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Work begins on the cathedral of Notre-Dame, Paris, and continues until about 1350. This early Gothic building still has some Romanesque elements, notably the bay system.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1163</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Work begins on the cathedral of Saint-Étienne, Bourges. Though High Gothic, this church retains some older, Romanesque features such as the smaller clerestory.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1195</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Works begins on the Cathedral of Notre-Dame, Amiens. An excellent example of High Gothic, further developing the design ideas set forth in Chartres
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1220</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Founding of Salisbury Cathedral. A typical example of English Gothic, its plan influenced the design of Winchester Cathedral. Its notable facade places a distinct emphasis on the horizontal.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1220</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Consecration of Sainte-Chapelle, built to house what St. Louis IX believed was the Crown of Thorns. In the Rayonnant Gothic style, the whole building is reduced to a framework for the magnificent stained glass.
</Question>
<Choice>1248</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Work begins on the Public Palace (Palazzo Pubblico), Siena. The palace includes many great works of art, and the surrounding town square is an example of early Renaissance city planning.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1297</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Completion of the church of Santa Maria Novella, Florence. Graced with frescoes by Lippi, Uccello, Masaccio, and others, its facade was later finished by Alberti.
</Question>
<Choice>1350</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German mason Petr Parlér begins work on the cathedral church of St. Vitus, Prague, ultimately yielding a Gothic style freer than that in Germany or France.
</Question>
<Choice>1353</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Completion of the Alhambra, the last Muslim stronghold in Spain. The exuberant complex, finished after 80 years' work, contains a citadel and palace.
</Question>
<Choice>1358</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Filippo Brunelleschi begins work on the dome of Florence Cathedral. Constructed with machines of Brunelleschi's own design, the dome was one of the great engineering feats of its day.
</Question>
<Choice>1420</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Work begins on the Porta della Carta, Doges' Palace, Venice. Built and rebuilt several times, the palace's exotic appearance testifies to both its maritime wealth and connections with the Orient.
</Question>
<Choice>1438</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Florentine architect Michelozzo di Bartolommeo begins work on the Palazzo Medici-Riccardi. The home of the Medici family, it is one of the best examples of early Renaissance architecture.
</Question>
<Choice>1444</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pope Nicholas orders Bernardo Rossellino to begin work on St. Peter's Basilica. The most important church in Roman Catholicism, it will absorb the attention of numerous architects, including Michelangelo.
</Question>
<Choice>1452</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Leon Battista Alberti designs a facade for Santa Maria Novella, Florence, using a series of geometric conceits: the entire face can be inscribed in a square, and the upper portion can be inscribed in one quarter of that square.
</Question>
<Choice>1456</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Benedikt Ried begins work on Vladislav Hall, Prague. With its interweaving and truncating ribs, this unique late Gothic style building was later an inspiration for the Czech Baroque.
</Question>
<Choice>1493</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Donato Bramante designs the Tempietto, Rome. Supposedly marking the site of St. Peter's crucifixion, this high Renaissance "Little Temple" appears to be an oversized reliquary.
</Question>
<Choice>1502</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian Renaissance architecture is introduced to France in the form of the exceptional five-story octagonal staircase at Blois.
</Question>
<Choice>1515</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Rebuilding of Château de Chambord begins under French king Francis I. Originally a rural hunting lodge, the castle represents the first major French translation of Italian design values of symmetry and balance.
</Question>
<Choice>1519</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Work begins on the Medicean-Laurentian Library, Florence, under the direction of Michelangelo. His staircase design was finished by Giorgio Vasari and Bartolomeo Ammanati in 1559.
</Question>
<Choice>1523</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Giulio Romano begins work for Duke Federigo Gonzaga II on the Palazzo del Te, Mantua. An example of Mannnerist architecture, the building, which breaks all classical rules, is interestingly confusing and confounding.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1525</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sebastiano Serlio begins publishing his influential treatise that emphasizes the practical rather than theoretical aspects of architecture.
</Question>
<Choice>1537</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Michelangelo begins work on the Capitoline Square. The design shows his brilliance not only as an architect but as an urban planner as well.
</Question>
<Choice>1538</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Michelangelo finishes the Palazzo Farnese. The main design by Antonio da Sangallo dated to 1517; Michelangelo's work gave the High Renaissance design a Mannerist cast.
</Question>
<Choice>1546</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Andrea Palladio, the preeminent architect of late 16th-century Italy, designs the Villa Rotonda, Vicenza. A centralized and stylized building, it is still influential today.
</Question>
<Choice>1550</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Work begins on Saint Basil the Blessed. The ornate Russian cathedral is topped by magnificent onion-shaped domes.
</Question>
<Choice>1554</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Juan de Herrera begins work on the monumental Escorial, near Madrid. Under his direction (from 1572), the Escorial becomes one of the greatest expressions of Spanish imperial culture and wealth.
</Question>
<Choice>1563</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Emergence of Baroque style in Western art and architecture.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1600</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mehmed Aga begins work on his masterpiece, the Sultan Ahmed Cami, Istanbul. Perfectly symmetrical in design, it is known as the Blue Mosque because of its coloured tiles.
</Question>
<Choice>1609</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Inigo Jones designs the great Banqueting House at Whitehall. Strongly influenced by Palladio and using familiar motifs, it is nonetheless a highly distinctive composition.
</Question>
<Choice>1619</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Francesco Borromini is commissioned to design San Carlo alle Quattro Fontane, Rome. Its deeply sculptured facade and unusual, fluid floor plan mark the church as an early example of Baroque design.
</Question>
<Choice>1634</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Work begins on Gian Lorenzo Bernini’s design for St. Peter's Square. The square is united with St. Peter's through Bernini's colonnade, which mimics a human embrace.
</Question>
<Choice>1656</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Great Fire of London. Christopher Wren, in charge of reconstruction (with others), designs 53 churches in the rebuilt city. Most notable is St. Paul's Cathedral, which takes 35 years to complete.
</Question>
<Choice>1666</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Guarino Guarini begins work on Santa Sidone (the Chapel of Holy Shroud), Turin. The church is notable for its dome, which appears to swirl upward toward a dove representing the Holy Ghost.
</Question>
<Choice>1667</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Claude Perrault, Louis Le Vau, Charles Le Brun, and François d'Orbay design the Colonnade, the eastern facade of the Louvre, Paris, a brilliant hybrid of Italian Renaissance and French architectural forms.
</Question>
<Choice>1667</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Louis Le Vau, painter Jules Hardouin-Mansart, and gardener André Le Nôtre begin work on the Palace of Versailles. Originally a small chateau, Versailles became a symbol of monarchial wealth and power.
</Question>
<Choice>1669</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Christopher Wren begins reconstructing St. Paul's Cathedral, London. The cathedral, which took 35 years to finish, remains a masterpiece of English architecture and one of the finest churches in the world.
</Question>
<Choice>1675</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian Baroque master Jakob Prandtauer begins renovating the Benedictine Abbey at Melk, Austria. Prandtauer transformed the abbey, founded in 1089, into a stunning exemplar of Baroque design.
</Question>
<Choice>1702</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Bavarian Baroque master Christoph Dientzenhofer begins work on the Church of St. Nicholas, Prague. The complex syncopated geometry of the interior is one of the design's defining features.
</Question>
<Choice>1703</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Theatre designer John Vanbrugh begins work on Blenheim Palace, Oxfordshire. The palace is a highly theatrical complex and the finest example of English Baroque.
</Question>
<Choice>1705</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German architect Matthäus Pöppelmann begins work on the Zwinger, Dresden. The exuberant brilliance of South German Baroque is clearly evident in this complex.
</Question>
<Choice>1709</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English architect Nicholas Hawksmoor, a former assistant of Christopher Wren, designs Christ Church, Spitalfields, London. Christ Church is among the finest Baroque churches in England.
</Question>
<Choice>1714</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German architect Balthasar Neumann designs the pilgrimage church at Vierzehnheiligen, near Bamberg. A fine southern German Baroque church, its complex plan eschews the use of straight lines.
</Question>
<Choice>1743</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French architect Jacques-Germain Soufflot designs the Neoclassical Panthéon in Paris. Initially christened Sainte-Geneviève, the building was given its present name after the French Revolution.
</Question>
<Choice>1755</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John Wood the Younger begins work on the Royal Crescent, Bath, Eng. A cross between architecture and city planning, the Crescent is a major element of the fashionable spa town.
</Question>
<Choice>1767</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Thomas Jefferson begins work on his estate, Monticello. Jefferson tore down his half-completed original structure and redesigned it in 1793, after visiting Paris.
</Question>
<Choice>1768</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Claude-Nicolas Ledoux designs the Arc-et-Senans, Salines de Chaux. The stark, geometric plan represents a significant evolution in Ledoux's architectural vision.
</Question>
<Choice>1775</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Étienne-Louis Boullée designs his famous Newton Cenotaph. Grotesquely oversized and never realized, Boullée's work shows the raw power of architecture to create symbols.
</Question>
<Choice>1784</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Claude-Nicolas Ledoux designs a series of tollhouses for Paris. All were raw, massive, geometric structures, resolutely defining the edges of Paris; only four survive.
</Question>
<Choice>1785</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Thomas Jefferson designs the state capitol building, Richmond, Va. Jefferson intended the stately building to be an architectural representation of Republican government.
</Question>
<Choice>1785</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Construction begins on the Massachusetts State House, Boston. Designed by Charles Bulfinch, the building is an American remembrance of the Neoclassical English tradition.
</Question>
<Choice>1795</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pierre Vignon, La Madeleine, Paris. Originally built to honour Napoleonic soldiers, but converted to a church, this Roman Neoclassical temple creates a link between the Napoleonic Empire and ancient Rome.
</Question>
<Choice>1806</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Thomas Jefferson begins work on his architectural masterpiece, the University of Virginia (opened in 1825). The Neoclassical campus was organized around a graceful lawn, capped by the elegant Rotunda.
</Question>
<Choice>1809</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sir John Soane designs his own house in Lincoln's Inn Fields, London. Designed in part to hold the architect's plaster cast collection, the house, with various interpenetrating spaces, is idiosyncratic but brilliant.
</Question>
<Choice>1812</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John Nash begins work on the Royal Pavilion, Brighton, Sussex. Nash created a fanciful dream of a Hindu palace for British royalty on the southern coast of England.
</Question>
<Choice>1815</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Karl Friedrich Schinkel begins work on the Altes Museum, Berlin. Completed in 1830, its Greek design gives expression to Prussian political and cultural ambitions.
</Question>
<Choice>1822</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Charles Barry and A.W.N. Pugin begin work on the Houses of Parliament, London. The buildings, finished in 1867, became a major monument of English Neo-Gothic and established Pugin as its greatest talent.
</Question>
<Choice>1836</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Henrí Labrouste begins work on the Bibliothèque Ste. Geneviève, Paris. Completed in 1850, the library's interior makes good decorative use of exposed iron supports.
</Question>
<Choice>1843</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Joseph Paxton's Crystal Palace opens to the public in London. The first modern exhibition building, it is a spectacular construction of cast iron and glass and is a symbol of Victorian ingenuity.
</Question>
<Choice>1851</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Baron Georges-Eugène Haussmann becomes prefect of the Seine département, Paris, and (until 1870) directs a variety of projects that transform the city, adding boulevards, sewers, and monuments.
</Question>
<Choice>1853</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Philip Webb designs the Red House, Kent. The first house of the Arts and Crafts Movement, the Red House was built for one of the movement's leaders, William Morris.
</Question>
<Choice>1859</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Charles Garnier begins work on the Opera House, Paris. Crowning a great new boulevard, the opulently sumptuous Opera House is designed as a place to both see and be seen.
</Question>
<Choice>1860</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Growth of the Arts and Crafts Movement in England. Led by William Morris, the movement sought to recapture the spirit and workmanship of medieval design and production.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1861</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Joseph Poelart designs the Palais de Justice, Brussels. A gargantuan and almost inhuman building, the Palais seems to be more about punishment than justice.
</Question>
<Choice>1862</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Richard Norman Shaw, one of England's most versatile and talented domestic architects, designs Leyswood, Sussex. The project marks the transfer of small-scale domestic design to large country estates.
</Question>
<Choice>1866</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The use of concrete in architecture increases with the development of reinforced concrete. Embedded with metal, it displays great tensile strength.
</Question>
<Choice>1867</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Frank Furness designs the Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts, Philadelphia. This polychromed, eclectic museum and art school is one of the masterpieces of this unique American architect.
</Question>
<Choice>1872</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
H.H. Richardson designs Trinity Church, Boston, which established his popularity as an architect in Boston. With its large bulk and massive tower, the Romanesque style Richardson favoured is well adapted in this building.
</Question>
<Choice>1872</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
George Edmund Street begins work on the Law Courts, London. The last major monument of the English Gothic revival, this building, by a master of Victorian Gothic, fits into the streetscape despite its bulk.
</Question>
<Choice>1874</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Richard Norman Shaw begins work on Bedford Park, the first modern suburb, outside London.
</Question>
<Choice>1876</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Chicago School of architecture emerges. The members of this influential group developed the modern skyscraper and contributed to the development of modernism.
</Question>
<Choice>1880</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chicago architects Dankmar Adler and Louis Sullivan form the partnership of Adler and Sullivan. The firm produced some of the most important buildings of the century and trained Frank Lloyd Wright.
</Question>
<Choice>1881</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
H.H. Richardson designs the Marshall Field Warehouse, Chicago. Richardson, a master of the Romanesque, fills an entire Chicago block with powerful but subtly articulated masonry.
</Question>
<Choice>1885</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dankmar Adler and Louis Sullivan win the commission to design the Auditorium Building, Chicago. The building presaged modern multiuse structures and signaled Sullivan's professional maturity.
</Question>
<Choice>1886</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Charles Follen McKim, of McKim, Mead, and White, designs the Boston Public Library. One of the best examples of 19th-century American Neoclassical, it signaled the firm's shift from residential to institutional design.
</Question>
<Choice>1887</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ebenezer Howard publishes Tomorrow: A Peaceful Path to Social Reform, an influential book that lay the intellectual groundwork for the Garden City movement.
</Question>
<Choice>1889</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Paris Exhibition features two cast iron masterpieces that show the transformation of engineering to art: Gustave Eiffel’s 100-metre tall Eiffel Tower and Dutert and Contamin’s Palais des Machines.
</Question>
<Choice>1889</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Daniel Burnham and John W. Root design the Monadnock Building, Chicago. A massive yet elegant 16-story structure, it is the tallest building supported by its exterior walls rather than an internal iron or steel framework.
</Question>
<Choice>1889</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
William Le Baron Jenney designs the Fair Store, Chicago. The first modern skyscraper, its weight is carried by an interior structural steel frame rather than the exterior walls.
</Question>
<Choice>1892</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Frank Lloyd Wright designs the Winslow House, River Forest, Ill. Solidly elegant, the restrained and symmetrical front facade of this house strongly contrasts with its less disciplined rear.
</Question>
<Choice>1893</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The World's Columbian Exposition is held in Chicago. The designers, headed by Daniel Burnham, created a new American Renaissance, establishing Neoclassicism as the dominant style for public architecture.
</Question>
<Choice>1893</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dankmar Adler and Louis Sullivan begin work on the Guaranty Building, Buffalo, N.Y. A pioneer of modern architecture, Sullivan established for skyscrapers the tripartite order of base, shaft, and cap.
</Question>
<Choice>1894</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Fashionable Beaux-Arts architect Richard Morris Hunt completes the Breakers, Newport, R.I. This mansion-sized summer "cottage" is a testament to the splendid opulence of the Gilded Age.
</Question>
<Choice>1895</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Victor Horta designs the Maison du Peuple, Brussels. In this pioneering moderist design, native brick and stone architecture is combined with iron to serve the socialist cause.
</Question>
<Choice>1896</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Victor Horta designs the Maison du Peuple, Brussels. In this pioneering moderist design, native brick and stone architecture is combined with iron to serve the socialist cause.
</Question>
<Choice>1896</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hendrik Petrus Berlage begins work on the Amsterdam Stock Exchange, one of the most influential buildings of the early 20th century.
</Question>
<Choice>1897</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Joseph Maria Olbrich designs the Secession building, Vienna. Crowned by a giant ball of gilded laurel leaves, the building was home to the Wiener Sezession (Vienna Secession), a centre of early modernism.
</Question>
<Choice>1898</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Otto Wagner, one of the founders of European modern architecture, designs the Majolika house, Vienna. Its tiled facade, with the spreading flower pattern, was intended as a model for modern, hygienic housing.
</Question>
<Choice>1898</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Louis Sullivan designs his late-career masterpiece, the Carson Pirie Scott Building, Chicago. Though the steel structural frame is clearly visible, Sullivan adds a masterful cast-iron ornament to the facade.
</Question>
<Choice>1899</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Emergence of the Prairie style of architecture. Centred in the Midwest, its practitioners created low buildings, anchored to the ground with large chimneys, that appeared to be extensions of the land.
</Question>
<Choice>1900</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Antoni Gaudí designs the Villa Bell Esguard, Barcelona. The highly idiosyncratic Gaudí designed buildings that featured sinuous, undulating lines borrowed from nature and complex textured surfaces.
</Question>
<Choice>1900</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hector Guimard designs the Métro Station, Paris. One of the three types of Metro stations designed by Guimard, the small glass and iron pavilion is easily recognizable.
</Question>
<Choice>1900</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Charles Rennie Mackintosh designs Hill House, Helensburgh, Scot. The house, with its simple lines and plain surfaces, demonstrates this Scottish master's design ability.
</Question>
<Choice>1902</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Auguste Perret designs an apartment block at 25 rue Franklin, Paris. Perret, a French pioneer in ferro-concrete construction, created the first apartment block designed to be built in concrete.
</Question>
<Choice>1903</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
McKim, Mead, and White design Pennsylvania Railway Station, New York City. Modeled on classical Roman baths, this station was a remarkable gateway to the city and an exemplar of American Neoclassical.
</Question>
<Choice>1904</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Frank Lloyd Wright designs the Larkin Building, Buffalo, N.Y. This design was the architect's solution to the problems posed by the modern office building.
</Question>
<Choice>1904</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Tony Garnier designs his Cité Industrielle. Garnier's plan for an entire city, including housing, factories, and offices, was never fully realized but showed the possibilities of modern planning.
</Question>
<Choice>1904</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Albert Kahn receives his first commission--the new Packard Motor Car factory in Detroit. He would go on to revolutionize factory design and become the father of modern industrial architecture.
</Question>
<Choice>1904</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Otto Wagner designs the Postal Savings Bank, Vienna. Its striking facade, with the bolt heads in its unadorned flat facade, yields to an even more striking glass and steel interior.
</Question>
<Choice>1904</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Josef Hoffmann designs the Palais Stoclet (Stoclet House), Brussels. The massive, elegant house, designed in conjunction with the Wiener Werkstätte, is one of Hoffmann's finest works.
</Question>
<Choice>1905</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Antonio Gaudí begins work on the Casa Milá, Barcelona. Though apparently molded out of concrete or stucco, this sinuous building, which almost pulsates with life, is covered in cut stone.
</Question>
<Choice>1905</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Frank Lloyd Wright designs the Unity Temple, Oak Park, Ill. One of his most successful designs, the church displays a masterful use of concrete and a simple but powerful arrangement of space.
</Question>
<Choice>1906</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hermann Muthesius and Henry van de Velde found the Deutscher Werkbund. Devoted to applying crafts standards to mass-produced goods, the group has had a strong influence on 20th-century architecture.
</Question>
<Choice>1907</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
J.M. Olbrich designs the Hochzeitsturm and Exhibition buildings, Darmstadt, Ger. Both structures show his shift from the Art Nouveau of the Vienna Secession to a more mature and sophisticated style.
</Question>
<Choice>1907</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Charles and Henry Greene design the Gamble House, Pasadena. An example of California bungalow style, the Gamble House features natural materials and a design that mixes indoor and outdoor space.
</Question>
<Choice>1908</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Frank Lloyd Wright designs the Robie House, Chicago. The epitome of Wright's Prairie style, this long, low house, built of Roman brick, seems to rise out of the earth.
</Question>
<Choice>1908</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Cass Gilbert begins work on the Woolworth Building, New York City. Cloaked in a Gothic skin, this skyscraper was nicknamed the "Cathedral of Commerce."
</Question>
<Choice>1908</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Industrial designer Peter Behrens begins work on the AEG turbine factory, Berlin. With its powerful massing and curtain glass wall, it is one of the great monuments of modern architecture.
</Question>
<Choice>1909</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Adolf Loos designs the Steiner House, Vienna. Undecorated, planar surfaces, punctuated by windows, contribute to the overwhelming simplicity of this building.
</Question>
<Choice>1910</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Antonio Gaudí devotes himself full-time to work on the Templo Expiatorio de la Familia Sagrada, Barcelona. Gaudí's most ambitious project by far, the massive church was still unfinished at his death.
</Question>
<Choice>1910</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Adolf Loos designs the Goldman and Salatsch Building. The extreme simplicity of the building's dictum that "ornament is crime."
</Question>
<Choice>1910</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Walter Gropius and Adolf Meyer design Faguswerk, Alfeld-an-der-Leine. Gropius, formerly an assistant to Peter Behrens, produced a clean, innovative design with large expanses of glass wall.
</Question>
<Choice>1911</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Peter Behrens designs the German Embassy, St. Petersburg, Russia. Powerful and brooding forms turned the building into an emblem of the power of modern government.
</Question>
<Choice>1911</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Henri Sauvage designs an apartment block at 25 rue Vavin, Paris. Deeply concerned with creating reasonable modern housing, Sauvage covered his building in tile and created set-back terraces.
</Question>
<Choice>1912</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Edwin Lutyens, designer of New Delhi, India, begins work on the Viceroy's House. The pomp and circumstance of British India are well expressed in this massive building of the new capital.
</Question>
<Choice>1913</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Max Berg designs the Jahrhunderthalle (Centennial Hall), Breslau, Ger. Made of ferro-concrete, this commemorative hall demonstrated the plasticity and limitless potential of concrete buildings.
</Question>
<Choice>1913</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Henry van de Velde designs the theatre for the Werkbund Exhibit, Cologne. The sinuous lines of the theatre announce its Belgian Art Nouveau lineage.
</Question>
<Choice>1914</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Bruno Taut designs his Glass Pavilion for the Werkbund Exhibit, Cologne. Taut's small, crystalline building exemplifies the fascination with glass that characterized Expressionist architecture.
</Question>
<Choice>1914</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Antonio Sant'Elia designs La Città Nuova. Sant'Elia, who never realized a structure, strongly influenced the Futurists and later movements.
</Question>
<Choice>1914</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Le Corbusier designs the Domino House. A simple solution for the production of cheap mass housing, the basic frame could be multiplied to create larger houses.
</Question>
<Choice>1916</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Irving Gill designs the Dodge House, Los Angeles. Its stark and unadorned walls presaged International style.
</Question>
<Choice>1916</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
De Stijl, a Dutch movement in the modern arts and architecture, coalesces around the journal De Stijl. Its members include Piet Mondrian, Gerrit Rietveld, and J.J.P. Oud.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1917</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Walter Gropius becomes head of the Bauhaus, a school of design and art. One of the most influential schools of the 20th century, the Bauhaus trained and inspired a generation of modern architects.
</Question>
<Choice>1919</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hans Poelzig designs the Grosses Schauspielhaus, Berlin. With its stalactite-like forms, the theatre's cavernous interior was one of the major monuments of Expressionist architecture.
</Question>
<Choice>1919</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Erich Mendelsohn designs the Einstein Tower, Potsdam, Ger. The tower, with its sinuous forms, is one of Mendelsohn's best works and a masterpiece of Expressionist architecture.
</Question>
<Choice>1919</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Russian Constructivism movement, inspired by the work of Vladimir Tatlin, emerges with the publication of the Realist Manifesto in Moscow.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1920</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Vladimir Tatlin proposes a Monument to the Third International. Dynamically open and expressive, the tower is typical of the avant-garde architecture produced in the Soviet Union in the 1920s.
</Question>
<Choice>1920</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ludwig Mies van der Rohe proposes a Glass Skyscraper, Berlin. While unbuilt, this model for the first all-glass skyscraper was symbolic of a new era in architecture.
</Question>
<Choice>1921</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Michel de Klerk designs the Eigen Haard Housing Estate, Amsterdam. The estate used brick and small scale to create a nonthreatening environment.
</Question>
<Choice>1921</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Le Corbusier proposes his City of Three Million People project. Featuring a series of cruciform skyscrapers in Paris, Le Corbusier's plan had an unfortunately strong influence on modern city planning.
</Question>
<Choice>1922</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Chicago Tribune Tower competition draws submissions from all over the world and in every conceivable style. The winning design was a Neo-Gothic skyscraper by Raymond Hood and John Mead Howells.
</Question>
<Choice>1922</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Auguste Perret completes his great church, Notre-Dame de Raincy, in France. Perret, already a subtle master of concrete design, produced a building of remarkable lightness and ethereal spirit.
</Question>
<Choice>1923</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Le Corbusier publishes his influential Vers une architecture (Toward a New Architecture), a polemic praising the value of functionalist, machine-inspired design.
</Question>
<Choice>1923</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Erik Gunnar Asplund begins work on the Stockholm City Library, Stockholm, a prime example of the Scandinavian interpretation of modernized classicism.
</Question>
<Choice>1924</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Gerrit Rietveld designs the Schroeder House, Utrecht, Neth. A masterpiece inspired by De Stijl, this small villa's interior could be reshaped according to the user's needs.
</Question>
<Choice>1924</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Construction begins on the Chrysler Building, New York City. Designed by William Van Alen, this famous Art Deco skyscraper features ornaments based on stylized car parts.
</Question>
<Choice>1926</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Le Corbusier designs the Villa Stein, Garches, France. The strict symmetry of the building's front facade is counterbalanced by the asymmetrical placement of the terrace in the rear.
</Question>
<Choice>1927</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Deutscher Werkbund sponsors the Weissenhof Siedlung housing exhibition in Stuttgart, Ger. With entries by Gropius, Le Corbusier, and others, it summarized the state of modern architecture.
</Question>
<Choice>1927</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Alvar Aalto designs the Viipuri Library, Finland. Aalto creates a building that blends into the wooded landscape and is an important regional adaptation of the International Style.
</Question>
<Choice>1927</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American inventor Buckminster Fuller displays his Dymaxion Dwelling Machine, a six-sided, prefabricated house made of metal and suspended from a tower.
</Question>
<Choice>1927</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Willem M. Dudok begins work on the Town Hall, Hilversum, Neth. A reliance on strict geometry and the play of shapes and shadows marks the work of this Dutch master.
</Question>
<Choice>1928</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
First meeting of the Congres Internationaux d'Architecture Moderne (CIAM).
</Question>
<Choice>1928</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Johannes Brinkman and Ludewijk van der Vlugt begin work on the Van Nelle Tobacco Factory, Rotterdam, one of the best modern buildings in The Netherlands.
</Question>
<Choice>1928</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Le Corbusier begins work on his masterful Villa Savoye, Poissy, France. This villa realized Le Corbusier's architectural philosophy and design elements announced in the Citrohan House design in 1922.
</Question>
<Choice>1929</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mies van der Rohe designs the Barcelona Pavilion, a reception hall for the 1929 International Exhibition. The pavilion makes majestic use of luxurious materials and is one of Mies's masterpieces.
</Question>
<Choice>1929</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mies van der Rohe, Tugendhat House, Brno, Czech Republic. The house takes advantage of its steeply graded site by having an entire wall of glass.
</Question>
<Choice>1930</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
George Howe and William Lescaze design the Philadelphia Savings Fund Society (PSFS) building, Philadelphia, the first major work of European-style modernism in America.
</Question>
<Choice>1931</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Henry-Russell Hitchcock and Philip Johnson introduce the term "International Style" into general circulation with their eponymous show at the Museum of Modern Art in New York City.
</Question>
<Choice>1932</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Nazi takeover of Germany forces a large number of Europe's leading architects to immigrate to the United States, transforming America into the world's centre for architectural theory and practice.
</Question>
<Choice>1933</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Giuseppe Terragni designs the Casa del Fascio, Como, Italy. This intensely modernist building shows that fascist architecture is not necessarily retardataire.
</Question>
<Choice>1934</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Frank Lloyd Wright plans Broadacre City. His solution to the problem of urban overcrowding, Broadacre City created zones of varying density.
</Question>
<Choice>1936</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Albert Speer designs the Zeppelinfeld, Nürnberg, Ger. Speer, favouring Neoclassical architecture, blows its proportions wildly out of scale, creating an overpowering and dehumanizing structure.
</Question>
<Choice>1936</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Frank Lloyd Wright designs his masterful Fallingwater, Bear Run, Pa. Designed to fit into its landscape, this building is a mature refinement of Wright's ideas on organic architecture.
</Question>
<Choice>1936</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Albert Speer and Adolf Hitler develop their plan for Berlin. The inhuman scale of the plan reveals the baseness of its creators.
</Question>
<Choice>1937</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Alvar Aalto designs the Finnish Pavilion, World's Fair, New York City. The sympathetic use of wood marks a highly public break with the technological fascination so prevalent in modern architecture.
</Question>
<Choice>1939</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Frank Lloyd Wright begins work on the Guggenheim Museum, New York City. Completed in 1959, its massive spiral form breaks out of the typical urban streetscape and draws the viewer in.
</Question>
<Choice>1943</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mies van der Rohe begins work on the Farnsworth House, Plano, Ill. Mies's essay at producing a perfect space for dwelling, this house seems to float above the ground.
</Question>
<Choice>1946</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Philip Johnson designs his Glass House, New Canaan, Conn. One of Johnson's first works, this building derives from the work of Mies van der Rohe.
</Question>
<Choice>1949</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Finnish-born American architect Eliel Saarinen begins work on his late masterpiece, the Christ Lutheran Church, in Minneapolis, Minn.
</Question>
<Choice>1949</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Le Corbusier begins work on Notre-Dame-du-Haut, Ronchamp, France. The powerful church, with its sweeping roof, marks a turn to a more plastic and sculptural style for the master architect.
</Question>
<Choice>1950</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Le Corbusier begins work on the Chandigarh, India, Parliamentary centre. Designed on a massive scale, Le Corbusier's buildings are more like sculpture on the landscape than architecture.
</Question>
<Choice>1950</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Gordon Bunshaft, of Skidmore, Owings & Merrill, designs the Lever House, New York City. One of the first modern skyscrapers in New York, the tower of the Lever House seems to float above its base.
</Question>
<Choice>1952</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The term "New Brutalism" is applied to the more vigorous forms designed by Le Corbusier and other architects in the 1950s.
</Question>
<Choice>1954</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Finnish-born American architect Eero Saarinen begins work on the Trans World Airways Building, New York City. The sweeping concrete shape of the terminal is reminiscent of a giant bird.
</Question>
<Choice>1956</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mies van der Rohe begins work on the Seagram Building, New York City. The ultimate modernist skyscraper, it features a restrained but sophisticated use of materials.
</Question>
<Choice>1956</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pier Luigi Nervi designs the Sports Palace, Rome, a concrete dome structure that relates to both Berg's Jahrhunderthalle and the Pantheon.
</Question>
<Choice>1957</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Louis Kahn begins designing the Richards Medical Research Building, Philadelphia. The building marks Kahn's first use of his typology of "servant" and "served" spaces, a feature of his mature work.
</Question>
<Choice>1957</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Eero Saarinen begins work near Washington, D.C., on the Dulles International Airport terminal, a masterpiece of sculptural design and his most famous building.
</Question>
<Choice>1957</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Louis Kahn begins work on the Jonas Salk Institute, La Jolla, Calif. Kahn's design is a cool and balanced masterpiece, situated on a bluff overlooking the Pacific Ocean.
</Question>
<Choice>1959</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Oscar Niemeyer begins work on the city plan for Brasília, Brazil. The inland capital employed the International Style to advertise Brazil's political and economic modernity.
</Question>
<Choice>1959</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Robert Venturi designs the Vanna Venturi House, Chestnut Hill, Philadelphia. This house is a gentle parody of domestic architecture and one of the major buildings of postmodernism.
</Question>
<Choice>1963</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The 1967 Montreal Expo is dominated by the United States Pavilion, a massive geodesic dome designed by Buckminster Fuller.
</Question>
<Choice>1967</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Renzo Piano and Richard Rogers begin work on the Pompidou Centre, Paris. Completed in 1977, the building was at first notorious, then became a popular tourist attraction.
</Question>
<Choice>1971</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Robert Venturi, Denise Scott Brown, and Steven Izenour coauthor Learning from Las Vegas, an exuberant and influential study of the architectural value of garish, commercialized Las Vegas.
</Question>
<Choice>1972</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sydney Opera House, designed by the Danish architect Jørn Utzon, is completed. An imaginative and dynamic structure, its design features a series of saillike shells.
</Question>
<Choice>1973</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At a height of 1,454 feet (443 metres), Sears Tower in Chicago stands as the world's tallest building until the late 1990s.
</Question>
<Choice>1974</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Richard Meier begins work on the Atheneum, New Harmony, Ind. Firmly grounded in the principles of modernism, it nonetheless marked an evolution in Meier's style away from strict modernism.
</Question>
<Choice>1975</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ricardo Bofill begins work on Les Espaces d'Abraxas, Marne-la-Vallée, France. The postmodern design continued the rich 20th-century tradition of architects working on public housing projects.
</Question>
<Choice>1978</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Frank Gehry designs the Gehry House, Santa Monica, Calif. Using mundane and unglamorous materials and broken forms, Gehry almost single-handedly invents "deconstructivist" architecture.
</Question>
<Choice>1979</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Norman Foster begins designing the Hongkong Bank, Hong Kong. Completed in 1986, the internal atrium is reminiscent of Frank Lloyd Wright's Larkin Building.
</Question>
<Choice>1979</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Pritzker Architectural Prize is founded. It is among the highest awards in the field.
</Question>
<Choice>1979</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
José Rafael Moneo begins work on the Museum of Roman Art, Mérida, Spain. The museum's modernized classical forms and "Roman" brick construction relates to its subject through form and material.
</Question>
<Choice>1980</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Michael Graves designs the Portland Public Service Building, Portland, Ore. Bright colours, oversized Art Deco, and Egyptian ornament marks this building as postmodern.
</Question>
<Choice>1980</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
I.M. Pei begins designing his glass pyramid addition to the Grand Louvre, Paris. Originally a source of much controversy, the pyramid has become as beloved as the surrounding building.
</Question>
<Choice>1981</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Cesar Pelli begins work on the World Financial Center and World Financial Center Plaza, New York City. The complex shows Pelli's mastery of urban form and the return to publicly oriented spaces.
</Question>
<Choice>1981</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Philip Johnson's AT&T Building opens in New York City. Featuring a top that looks like a Chippendale cabinet, the building announces Johnson's turn to postmodernism.
</Question>
<Choice>1982</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
James Stirling completes Neue Staatsgalerie, Stuttgart, Ger. Numerous citations to other buildings and the use of masonry and painted metal make this building a classic of postmodernism.
</Question>
<Choice>1984</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Christian de Portzamparc begins work on his City of Music. On the edge of the Parc de la Villette, Paris, this rambling series of structures creates a cultural city within a city.
</Question>
<Choice>1984</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hans Hollein designs the Haas House, Vienna. Situated across from St. Stephen's cathedral, Hollein's building asserts its individuality while reflecting surrounding styles.
</Question>
<Choice>1985</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese architect Isozaki Arata's Los Angeles Museum of Contemporary Art establishes him as one of the world's foremost designers.
</Question>
<Choice>1986</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Peter Eisenman's Wexner Center for the Visual Arts opens. Its intersecting passageways and white scaffolding create a sense of impermanence that contrasts with traditional art museums.
</Question>
<Choice>1989</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Robert Venturi's Sainsbury Wing of the National Gallery, London, opens. Venturi's addition is respectful of the original building and bears the mark of the architect's unique style.
</Question>
<Choice>1991</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Tadao Ando's Japan Pavilion opens in Expo '92, Sevilla, Spain. It showcases Ando's ability to meld Western and Japanese architectural ideas, and his fascination with space and light.
</Question>
<Choice>1992</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Vitra furniture factory complex opens in Weil am Rhein, Germany. Its many notable buildings include a fire station designed by Iraqi-born deconstructivist architect Zaha Hadid.
</Question>
<Choice>1993</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Frank Gehry's American Center opens in Paris. The Center, with its complex layout and references to traditional French architecture, establishes Gehry as one of the major architects of his generation.
</Question>
<Choice>1994</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dominique Perrault's Bibliotheque Nationale de France (National Library of France) is completed. It is one of many architecturally significant libraries built in the 1990s and one of the most controversial.
</Question>
<Choice>1995</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Tokyo International Forum, designed by Rafael Viñoly, is completed. Its enormous self-supporting Glass Hall (about 200 metres long) is both a technological and aesthetic tour de force.
</Question>
<Choice>1996</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Petronas Twin Towers in Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia, are among the world's tallest buildings, beating the Sears Tower in Chicago by 29 feet (8.9 metres).
</Question>
<Choice>1996</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The billion-dollar Getty Center, designed by Richard Meier, opens in Los Angeles. The hilltop complex includes a garden designed by the conceptual artist Robert Irwin.
</Question>
<Choice>1997</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Frank Gehry's Guggenheim Museum in Bilbao, Spain, opens. The much-discussed building features curved exterior surfaces sheathed in gleaming titanium and cavernous interior spaces.
</Question>
<Choice>1997</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the largest enclosed public spaces in the world, the new Hong Kong International Airport opens on the artificial island Chek Lap Kok.
</Question>
<Choice>1998</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Rem Koolhaas, described as "the architect of the new millennium," is selected to design the new campus centre at the Illinois Institute of Technology in Chicago.
</Question>
<Choice>1998</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Millennium Dome opens in London. Initiated to house an exhibition for the approach of the 21st century, it is the largest dome in the world.
</Question>
<Choice>1999</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sir Norman Foster finishes the renovation and redesign of the Reichstag. A study of line and light, the historic German building is topped by a magnificent glass dome.
</Question>
<Choice>1999</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Green Architecture, a movement to construct buildings that are environment friendly, continues to gain in popularity around the world, especially in Europe.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Sony Center opens in Berlin. The building's transparent feel epitomizes German architect Helmut Jahn's use of steel and glass.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The length of the Great Wall of China increases after a western section, measuring 310 miles (500 km), is discovered.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Museum of Contemporary Art in Los Angeles opens a comprehensive exhibition of Rudolph M. Schindler's designs, signaling a renewed interest in his Modernist homes.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Michael Graves wins the Gold Medal of the American Institute of Architects, the AIA's lifetime achievement award.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jacques Herzog and Pierre de Meuron, designers of London's Tate Modern museum, are awarded the Pritzker Architecture Prize.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Barcelona celebrates the "International Year of Gaudi" to mark the 150th anniversary of Antoni Gaudi's birth. The Catalan architect is noted for his unconventional buildings.
</Question>
<Choice>2002</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Australian architect Glenn Murcutt wins the Pritzker Prize.
</Question>
<Choice>2002</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polish-born architect Daniel Libeskind is selected to rebuild the World Trade Center site in New York City. His plans include a tower that will stand 1,776 feet, which would be the tallest building in the world.
</Question>
<Choice>2003</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Iraqi-born British architect Zaha Hadid, noted for her radical deconstructivist designs, becomes the first woman to be awarded the Pritzker Architecture Prize.
</Question>
<Choice>2004</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The U.S. National Trust for Historic Preservation estimates that more than 38,000 historic structures in New Orleans were affected by Hurricane Katrina and many are beyond saving.
</Question>
<Choice>2005</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first tenants move into Turning Torso, Spanish architect Santiago Calatrava's mixed-use residential tower in Malmö, Sweden. Fifty-four stories high, it is the tallest building in Scandinavia.
</Question>
<Choice>2005</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Seven World Trade Center opens in New York City. The 52-story office tower is the first new building to be built on the site of the September 11, 2001, attacks.
</Question>
<Choice>2006</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Paulo Mendes da Rocha wins the Pritzker Architecture Prize, becoming the second Brazilian architect to receive the honour. His buildings--which are often constructed of plain, unfinished concrete--are known for their bold shapes.
</Question>
<Choice>2006</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American architect Philip C. Johnson's minimalistic Glass House in New Canaan, Conn., is opened to the public for the first time.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Federal Building, designed by American architect Thom Mayne, opens in San Francisco. A leading example of green architecture, it does not have air conditioning, using instead a system of exterior sunshades and screens to keep the building cool in hot weather.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The rising popularity of prefabricated housing is underscored when the Museum of Modern Art in New York City commissions five architects to assemble prefab homes in a lot next to the museum as part of an exhibit on factory-produced architecture.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Peter Zumthor of Switzerland receives the Praemium Imperiale prize for architecture, one of the six categories of global arts prizes awarded annually by the Japan Art Association.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian architect Renzo Piano's new wing for the Art Institute of Chicago opens. Measuring 264,000 square feet, it is the largest-ever addition to the museum.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Just months before its completion, Dutch architect Rem Koolhaas's Mandarin Oriental hotel, part of the CCTV building complex in Beijing, is seriously damaged after being accidentally set on fire by festival fireworks.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Burj Khalifa, the world's tallest building to date, officially opens in Dubai, U.A.E.
</Question>
<Choice>2010</Choice>
</item>
</topics>