<topics>
<item>
<Question>
The Panaramittee rock-art style appears in parts of Australia and Tasmania. It is characterized by circles, crescents, and radiating lines, as well as footprints and animal tracks.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 30,000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Statuette known as "Venus of Willendorf" and other early fertility icons show exaggerated female forms.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 25,000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Paintings in a cave near Lascaux, France, reveal the human capacity for lively representation. Expertly fitted to cave surfaces, the painted animals may have served a ritual function.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 15,000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The "Palette of Narmer" depicts Egyptian King Narmer in battle. The best-known work from the Early Dynastic Kingdom, this carved slate piece displays the mature ancient Egyptian style.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 2900 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A slate statue group of King Menkaure and his sister-queen decorates the last pyramid at Giza. It displays classic Egyptian proportions, delicacy of modeling, and tender interaction of figures.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 2530 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Early developments are made in Chinese calligraphy, one of the oldest and most fundamental forms of Chinese art.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1700 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The so-called "Toreador Fresco" from the Palace at Knossos, Crete, depicts a ritual game involving athletes and bull.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1550 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Egyptian pharaoh Akhenaton establishes monotheistic worship of Aton. Under his reign artistic works, which had previously depicted pharaohs in timeless settings, take on a new narrative specificity.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1350 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Olmec people of Mexico begin carving tremendous "colossal heads." The stone monuments are characterized by flat faces and helmetlike headgear.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1150 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Emergence of the Geometric style in Greek art. Centred in Athens, it combined geometric motifs and bands with figures of humans and animals. The Dipylon vases (c. 750) are exemplars of the style.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 900 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Assyrian artists develop a mature and sophisticated style of relief carvings, depicting their subjects--usually military conquests and battles--with great economy of means.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 875 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek potters develop a freer and more exotic style of decoration as trade and travel give Greek artists sustained exposure to Near Eastern artistic styles.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 700 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek potters at Corinth develop black-figure pottery, in which images are drawn on a vase's clay surface in black pigment. Animal friezes are the most popular early subjects.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 700 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Beginnings of the Archaic period in Greek art, characterized by greater naturalism, attention to human anatomy, and representation of narrative scenes from literature or mythology.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 650 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Athenian vase painter and potter Cleitias paints the elaborately decorated François Vase, one of the finest extant examples of Archaic period pottery.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 570 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Attic pottery painter Exekias emerges as a master of black pottery painting. A surviving amphora, depicting Achilles and Ajax playing a board game, replaces traditional animal subjects with people.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 550 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Development of red-figure painting technique, in which details are painted, not incised, on clay. It permits greater expressiveness, flexibility, and a fuller use of foreshortening.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 530 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Brygos Painter's vase, "The Sack of Troy," displays a masterful grace and illustrates the importance of mythological and historical subjects in Greek art.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 490 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The "Doryphoros" ("Spear-Bearer") by Polyclitus exemplifies the classical Greek art. The subject's body is poised in graceful, balanced movement.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 450 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Greek sculptor Phidias directs construction of the Parthenon. His statue of Zeus, carved around 430, is considered one of the Seven Wonders of the Ancient World.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 447 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scythian weavers produce the oldest surviving examples of embroidery. Paintings indicate that embroideries were made and worn earlier in both Egypt and Greece.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 400 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Nok of Africa begin producing well-fired clay animal sculptures and human figures that often feature tubular heads.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 400 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek sculptor Praxiteles, adjusting classical proportions, carves an utterly relaxed, sensuous "Hermes Carrying the Infant Dionysus."
</Question>
<Choice>c. 350 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chares of Lindos completes the immense bronze "Colossus of Rhodes," a monument commemorating the lifting of the siege of 305-304. Contrary to popular belief, it did not straddle the harbour entrance.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 280 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman nobles establish the practice of assembling works of art--in this period, plundered Greek treasures--into personal collections. This marks the beginning of serious art collecting in the West.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 250 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The "Venus de Milo" is carved by a Hellenist sculptor in Antioch, Phrygia. One of the most famous ancient sculptures, it is endowed with great grace and nobility.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 150 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek sculptors Polydorus, Agesander, and Athenodorus create the "Laocoön" group, showing Laocoön and his sons attacked by sea serpents. The date of its creation is uncertain.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 40 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Bronze equestrian statue of Emperor Marcus Aurelius is cast during a late period of Imperial stability.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 80</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Portland Vase, the finest example of Roman cameo glass (made from two pieces of glass blown together and then etched), is produced by an unknown artist.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 100</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
First appearance of Christian art, decorating Roman catacombs. Early Christian art appropriated and adapted local or classical styles but did not flourish until the conversion of Constantine I in 313.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 150</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Development of Coptic art, which combines Egyptian artistic style with Christian subjects.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 200</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the wake of the fall of Rome, the Merovingians take control of western Europe. Their art blends Roman classical with Germanic-Frankish styles.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 480</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine art begins to develop a highly sophisticated and formal style, mainly concerned with religious subjects, and most fully expressed in church design and mosaics.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 550</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Increased contact between Ireland and England leads to the development of the Hiberno-Saxon style of decoration, characterized by geometric designs and complicated interlace patterns.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 650</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Manuscript illumination develops as an artistic form in England, particularly in Canterbury and Northumbria. The centres draw upon Roman and Irish styles, respectively.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 680</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Rapid expansion of Islam gives rise to the development of new styles of decorative arts, drawing on northern African and Middle Eastern (especially Persian) sources and traditions.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 700</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Large stone statues begin to be constructed on Easter Island; the early busts are characterized by rounded heads and short bodies.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 700</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Conquest of the Iberian Peninsula by Muslim forces leads to development of the Mozarabic style of Christian art, which combines Islamic motifs and designs with Christian subjects.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 711</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Emperor Leo III begins the Iconoclastic Controversy and prohibits the production or display of religious images. They return to favour definitively in 843.
</Question>
<Choice>730</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Charlemagne's patronage of the arts leads to the establishment of a neoclassical, Carolingian style in art and architecture.
</Question>
<Choice>768</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Book of Kells, teeming with Celtic knotwork and animal designs, is finished at the monastery of Kells. Its elaborate calligraphy and decoration represent the height of the Hiberno-Saxon style.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 800</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Muslim artists develop the arabesque style of decoration into a highly sophisticated form of nonrepresentational art, based on botanical and abstract motifs.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Bronze doors for the Church of Saint Michael at Hildesheim, Germany, are commissioned by Bishop Bernward. They are one of the finest examples of Ottonian art.
</Question>
<Choice>1015</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese sculptor Jocho achieves the perfection of the joined-wood technique in "Amida Myorai."
</Question>
<Choice>1053</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Bayeux Tapestry is probably completed. The embroidered linen band depicts William the Conqueror's invasion of England.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1075</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The growth and geographical diffusion of monastic orders leads to the emergence of the Romanesque style in art and architecture; it draws on Roman, Carolingian, Byzantine, and other diverse sources.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1083</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
New developments in church architecture, starting in northern France and spreading to England and western Europe, signal the beginning of the Gothic period.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1120</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English Romanesque illustrations in the Bible of the Abbey of St. Edmund at Bury distill colour and gesture for narrative effect, producing one of the great medieval illuminated manuscripts.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1130</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Gislebertus completes his Last Judgement tympanum relief over the western door of the cathedral of St. Lazare, Autun, Fr. The expressionistic carving encourages pilgrims to keep faith.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1135</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Portal sculptures at Chartres Cathedral are among the finest examples of Gothic art.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1150</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese sculptor Unkei begins work on statues of the Nio for the Todai Temple in Nara. The large figures reveal the dynamic style that is characteristic of his work.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1168</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mu-ch'i, a leading Chinese Ch'an (Zen) Buddhist painter, paints the triptych "Six Persimmons."
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1279</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Giotto di Bondone probably paints the remarkable frescoes at the Church of San Francesco, Assisi. This and his later work establish Giotto as one of the first Italian masters.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1300</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jean Pucelle's delicately executed Belleville Breviary presents religious text and imagery surrounded by an abundance of marginal flora and fauna.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1325</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ambrogio Lorenzetti begins a series of murals in Siena city hall, including "Good and Bad Government," a landscape with receding space and carefully observed detail.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1337</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Claus Sluter begins his monumental late Gothic tomb for Philip the Bold in Dijon, Burgundy. The weight and simplicity of its weeping figures give them great emotional power.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1395</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Tempera painting, which combines pigment powder with an emulsion (usually egg yolks and water), is the preferred medium for early Renaissance painters. It is later displaced by oils.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1400</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Lorenzo Ghiberti wins the competition to design the bronze doors of the Baptistery of San Giovanni in Florence, which thus establishes his reputation. The project lasts until 1424.
</Question>
<Choice>1402</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Florentine architect Filippo Brunelleschi conducts experiments that lead to his rediscovery of linear perspective, one of the fundamental advances in Renaissance art.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1410</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese artist Kichizan paints "The Hut in the Valley," which reveals the influence of Chinese landscape art.
</Question>
<Choice>1413</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Donatello completes "St. Mark" and "St. George," marble statues at Or San Michele, Florence. The graceful, confident sculptures represent a breakthrough in naturalism.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1415</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Illuminations in the Limburg brothers' Très Riches Heures du duc de Berry represent a breakthrough in the depiction of landscape, space, and naturalistic detail.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1416</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Engraving is developed in Italy and Germany. In this process, lines are cut into a metal plate, which is inked and pressed onto paper. Engraving supports more detailed pictures than woodcuts.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1420</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Lorenzo Ghiberti begins work on the second set of bronze doors for the Baptistery of San Giovanni in Florence. The "Gates of Paradise" use perspective and landscape to suggest depth.
</Question>
<Choice>1425</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Donatello casts the bronze statue of a youthful "David," reintroducing the free-standing male nude of antiquity into the sculptural language of the Renaissance.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1425</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Florentine painter Masaccio first uses linear perspective in his fresco "The Trinity," Santa Maria Novella, Florence.
</Question>
<Choice>1427</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Flemish "Master of Flémalle" (probably Robert Campin) uses oil paint, empirical perspective, effects of light, and intense observation of domestic setting in the revolutionary "Mérode Altarpiece."
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1428</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jan van Eyck paints "The Madonna of Chancellor Rolin," a virtuoso exploration of empirical perspective, texture, light, character, and distant landscape.
</Question>
<Choice>1432</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Flemish painter Rogier van der Weyden begins work on his "Descent from the Cross." Completed around 1440, it is a harmonious, flowing composition of great emotion.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1435</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Renaissance writer Leon Battista Alberti publishes the first description of linear perspective in De Pictura ("On Painting").
</Question>
<Choice>1435</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Andrea Mantegna creates his Ovetari Chapel fresco cycle at the Church of the Eremitani in Padua, featuring a bold perspective view from below ground level and consequent foreshortening.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1455</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Paolo Uccello paints the three-panel "Rout of San Romano." It combines Gothic colours and decorative motifs with Renaissance foreshortening and forms to create an electrifying battle scene.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1455</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Piero della Francesca completes his "Flagellation of Christ." This highly influential work displays the artist's mastery of the still-new technique of perspective construction.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1460</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Venetian school of painters, sculptors, and architects loses its first master, Jacopo Bellini. Its members would include such leading Renaissance painters as Titian, Tintoretto, and El Greco.
</Question>
<Choice>1470</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Venetian painter Giovanni Bellini, using oil paints to reveal his interest in light and detailed landscape, creates the panel painting "St. Francis in Ecstasy."
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1480</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German artist Martin Schongauer, the leading engraver of the period, begins the technically and compositionally sophisticated "Temptation of St. Anthony," a masterpiece of late Gothic engraving.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1480</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Leonardo da Vinci begins work on his mural, the "Last Supper," at Sta. Maria delle Grazie. The fresco, created with an unknown technique, marks the beginning of the High Renaissance in Italy.
</Question>
<Choice>1495</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sixteenth-century Venetian painters create the modern method of oil painting, exploring the artistic possibilities of the medium and replacing wood with canvas as the preferred support.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1500</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The most imposing of Albrecht Dürer's self-portraits, the Christlike "Self-portrait in Furred Coat," reflects artists' growing status and self-consciousness in western European culture and society.
</Question>
<Choice>1500</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Michelangelo begins sculpting his famous marble "David"—conceived as an adolescent in poised readiness, brimming with power not yet realized.
</Question>
<Choice>1501</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Leonardo da Vinci begins painting the psychologically intriguing "Mona Lisa," building atmosphere and texture through multiple layers of paint.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1503</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Albrecht Dürer, the first northern European artist to embrace Italian Renaissance ideals for the human figure, engraves "Adam and Eve."
</Question>
<Choice>1504</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Venetian painter Giorgione paints "The Tempest," in which interest in landscape and weather supplants human narrative.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1505</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch artist Hiëronymus Bosch begins painting "The Garden of Earthly Delights," a work of disturbing inventiveness. Bosch's work would earn him accusations by colleagues of practicing the occult arts.
</Question>
<Choice>1505</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Michelangelo begins four years' work on the "Genesis" fresco on the ceiling of the Sistine Chapel in the Vatican. The work stuns his contemporaries with its power.
</Question>
<Choice>1508</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Raphael begins the "School of Athens," in the Stanza della Segnatura in the Vatican. Completed in 1511, it is a masterpiece of High Renaissance art and one of Raphael's best-known frescoes.
</Question>
<Choice>1508</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German painter Matthias Grünewald creates his masterpiece, the wings of the Isenheim Altarpiece. The work is based on the Revelations of St. Bridget of Sweden.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1515</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German painter Albrecht Altdorfer, founder and leader of the Danube school, establishes the genre of "pure" landscape painting in western Europe, which concentrates on scenery rather than people.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1517</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Venetian painter Titian begins his "Bacchus and Ariadne." One of his many paintings of mythological scenes, it demonstrates Titian's virtuoso use of colour and texture.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1520</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Emergence of Mannerism, a style emphasizing self-conscious attention to technique and artifice. It spread from Italy throughout western and northern Europe and was popular until the 1590s.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1520</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The nude reappears in northern European art, in the work of Lucas Cranach the Elder. Inspired in part by Italian painters, he paints a series of studies of Venus, including "Venus and Cupid" in 1530.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1530</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-born Hans Holbein the Younger, working at the court of King Henry VIII of England, paints "The Ambassadors," a stunning meditation on power and mortality.
</Question>
<Choice>1533</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Michelangelo returns to the Sistine Chapel to paint the "Last Judgment." Completed in 1541, the fresco's writhing forms convey a darker vision than his ceiling frescoes, completed in 1512.
</Question>
<Choice>1534</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Death of Parma-based painter Correggio, whose sensuous mythological paintings--"Danae," "The Rape of Ganymede," and "Jupiter and Io"--strongly influence a later generation of Baroque artists.
</Question>
<Choice>1534</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian painter Parmigianino, elongating the human form and introducing radical disparities of scale, paints his "Madonna of the Long Neck."
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1534</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian Mannerist sculptor Benvenuto Cellini, working for French monarch Francis I, completes his masterpiece of Renaissance metalwork, a lavish gold saltcellar.
</Question>
<Choice>1540</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Florentine court artist Il Bronzino paints his erotic, allegorical "Venus, Cupid, Folly, and Time."
</Question>
<Choice>1545</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Flemish artist Pieter Bruegel the Elder paints "Peasant Dance," depicting village life with movement and lively characterization.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1568</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Paolo Veronese, a leader of the Venetian school, paints "Feast in the House of Levi." Secular in tone, vast in scale, and rich in colour, the painting depicts an extravagant banquet.
</Question>
<Choice>1573</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek-born, Italian-trained El Greco paints an intensely spiritual "Assumption of the Virgin" after his arrival in Spain, using a personal vocabulary of figures, space and colour.
</Question>
<Choice>1577</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Venetian Tintoretto finishes "The Last Supper," in San Giorgio Maggiore; it exploits interior light and shadow and deep perspective for dramatic effect.
</Question>
<Choice>1594</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Annibale Carracci begins the Galleria ceiling fresco in the Palazza Farnese, Rome. A witty, illusionistic work, it is an imaginative combination of painting, architecture, and sculpture.
</Question>
<Choice>1597</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roguish, brilliant painter Caravaggio brings dramatic lighting and visceral force to "The Conversion of St. Paul," introducing elements that will characterize the Baroque era.
</Question>
<Choice>1601</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
After study in Italy, Antwerp-trained Peter Paul Rubens exploits diagonal composition, lighting contrasts, and larger-than-life figures in "The Raising of the Cross."
</Question>
<Choice>1607</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Guido Reni begins the "Aurora" ceiling fresco, using a diagonal, upward-moving procession and keen use of colour to illustrate theme of dawn.
</Question>
<Choice>1613</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch Baroque painter Willem Claesz Heda creates his earliest known still life, "Vanitas." His works are characterized by sustained attention to detail and a sensuous yet restrained style.
</Question>
<Choice>1621</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Still-life painting emerges as a major genre in Dutch painting.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1625</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman artist Artemisia Gentileschi creates an oeuvre depicting heroic women. Most dramatic are her several paintings of Judith's killing of the Roman general Holofernes, painted between 1610 and 1625.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1625</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch painter Frans Hals demonstrates his characteristic loose-brushwork style and raffish characters in works such as "Gypsy Girl," completed in 1630.
</Question>
<Choice>1628</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish Baroque painters Francisco de Zurbarán and José de Ribera create works of stark, devout emotionalism, such as Zurbarán's "Holy House of Nazareth."
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1630</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pietro da Cortona's ceiling fresco in the Barberini Palace, Rome, imagines a sculptural canopy with multitudes of foreshortened heavenly figures coursing through it.
</Question>
<Choice>1633</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French Baroque painter Nicolas Poussin begins work on his series of "Seven Sacraments," completed in 1642. Poussin's rational classicism influenced pictorial classicism.
</Question>
<Choice>1634</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sir Anthony Van Dyck, a student of Rubens working for the English court, paints his outdoor, leisurely "Portrait of Charles I Hunting." The work greatly influences aristocratic portraiture.
</Question>
<Choice>1635</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French painter Georges de La Tour paints "The Lamentation over St. Sebastian." Like most of his works, the scene is illuminated by candlelight, which gives clarity of line and volume.
</Question>
<Choice>1645</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Gian Lorenzo Bernini begins his marble "Ecstasy of St. Theresa." Completed in 1652, the remarkable sculpture marks a high point of Baroque sensualism in the service of religion.
</Question>
<Choice>1645</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Landscape painter Claude Lorrain paints his "The Embarkation of the Queen of Sheba," notable for its use of light. Lorrain's idealized landscapes profoundly affected art, garden design, and aesthetics.
</Question>
<Choice>1648</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Diego Velázquez paints his masterwork, "Las Meninas." Apparently capturing a moment with the Spanish royal family, it is one of the most remarkable paintings of all time.
</Question>
<Choice>1656</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Rembrandt van Rijn paints "Jacob Blessing the Sons of Joseph." Its deeply felt, intimate treatment and glowing light are characteristic of Rembrandt's later work.
</Question>
<Choice>1656</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jan Vermeer begins "Young Woman with a Water Jug." The play of light and surface and the pleasures and limits of vision are more important in the work than the subject herself.
</Question>
<Choice>1658</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jacob van Ruisdael paints "Jewish Cemetery." The painting's ruinous, glowering scene exemplifies the trend toward turbulence in Dutch landscape at mid-century.
</Question>
<Choice>1660</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Antoine Watteau depicts the nobility of love and leisure in "La Partie Quarree" (completed in 1714), a work that contributes to the development of French Rococo.
</Question>
<Choice>1713</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French painter Jean-Baptiste-Siméon Chardin completes "Le Bénédicité" ("The Grace"). Like most of his work, this study of an intimate domestic scene is marked by sobriety of colour.
</Question>
<Choice>1740</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
William Hogarth executes his moralizing series of paintings and engravings "Marriage à la Mode," which satirize English upper-class life. (The engravings were printed in 1745.).
</Question>
<Choice>1743</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian Giovanni Battista Tiepolo begins the ceiling fresco in the palace at Würzburg. Completed in 1752, it consists of groups of winged and cloud-borne figures seen completely from below.
</Question>
<Choice>1750</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jean-Honoré Fragonard brings erotic wit and deft use of light to "The Swing," painted in the style of François Boucher's outdoor party scenes.
</Question>
<Choice>1766</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An American-born painter working in England, Benjamin West paints the first contemporary "history" scene, "The Death of General Wolfe."
</Question>
<Choice>1771</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss-born Henry Fuseli, working in England, paints the first of several versions of "The Nightmare," expressing the fantastic and sexual qualities of dream life.
</Question>
<Choice>1781</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jacques-Louis David's "Oath of the Horatii" helps define Neoclassical style in France, drawing on the theme of liberty shortly before the French Revolution.
</Question>
<Choice>1784</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Fashionable English painter Thomas Gainsborough paints "Mrs. Sheridan," a portrait in which soft landscape textures surround the subject.
</Question>
<Choice>1785</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Louvre Museum opens to the public as the Central Museum of the Arts in Paris. It subsequently undergoes numerous expansions and acquires one of the world's most impressive painting collections.
</Question>
<Choice>1793</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English poet, painter, and engraver William Blake's visionary "Pity" bases its imagery on classical and Christian sources yet uses his unique cosmology.
</Question>
<Choice>1795</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German Alois Senefelder invents lithographic process, which allows a variety of graphic effects and inexpensive production.
</Question>
<Choice>1798</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Thomas Bruce, 7th Earl of Elgin, begins sending ancient Greek sculptures to England. The "Elgin Marbles" are a subject of controversy at their debut in the British Museum.
</Question>
<Choice>1802</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French artist J.-A.-D. Ingres, intrigued by harem scenes, paints the coolly erotic "Valpinçon Bather."
</Question>
<Choice>1808</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Responding to the Napoleonic occupation of Spain, Francisco de Goya highlights atrocities in "The Third of May, 1808."
</Question>
<Choice>1814</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English painter John Constable looks to the English countryside, rather than to classical topography and figures, for inspiration in landscapes like "Boatbuilding near Flatford Mill."
</Question>
<Choice>1815</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French Romantic painter Théodore Géricault begins "The Raft of the Medusa." Based on a contemporary shipwreck, it uses a turbulent setting and pyramidal composition to heighten pathos and heroism.
</Question>
<Choice>1818</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Romantic expressiveness and spirituality are conveyed in German landscapist Caspar David Friedrich's "Moonrise over the Sea."
</Question>
<Choice>1822</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English-born American painter Thomas Cole celebrates unpeopled autumn scenery in the atmospheric "Schroon Mountain, Adirondacks."
</Question>
<Choice>1838</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
After visiting Morocco French painter Eugène Delacroix paints the "Jewish Wedding," reflecting the Romantic taste for "exotic" customs and dress, bright colours, and striking southern light.
</Question>
<Choice>1839</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The forces of nature swirl together into an abstraction in British painter J.M.W. Turner's "Snow Storm."
</Question>
<Choice>1842</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British painters Dante Gabriel Rossetti, William Holman Hunt, and John Everett Millais form the short-lived but influential Pre-Raphaelite Brotherhood.
</Question>
<Choice>1848</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French painter Gustave Courbet sparks controversy with his "The Stone-Breakers." The painting's realistic execution and subject draw accusations of "vulgarity."
</Question>
<Choice>1849</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jean-François Millet monumentalizes farmwork in "The Sower," in which an anonymous and timeless figure sweeps across the canvas.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1850</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Establishment of the Barbizon school of French naturalist landscape painters. Its leaders were Théodore Rousseau and Jean-François Millet, who settled in the village of Barbizon.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1855</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French lithographer and painter Honoré Daumier paints his "Third-Class Carriage." It sympathetically portrays ordinary people in an introspective mood.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1862</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Édouard Manet's "Luncheon on the Grass" sardonically brings pastoral nudity to a clothed picnic scene. It shocks sensibilities and introduces protomodernist flatness amid play of light and shadows.
</Question>
<Choice>1863</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Camille Corot, a member of the French Barbizon group, which practices on-the-spot study of nature and effects of light, paints "Souvenir de Mortefontaine."
</Question>
<Choice>1864</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mathew Brady, Timothy O'Sullivan, and Alexander Gardner record the horrors of the American Civil War in photographs such as "Ruins of the Gallego Flour Mill."
</Question>
<Choice>1865</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Plein air painting, in which oil paintings of landscapes are executed in the field, begins to attract the attention of critics following the work of Claude Monet.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1870</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
James McNeill Whistler begins "Arrangement in Grey and Black No. 1: The Artist's Mother." Completed in 1872, it shows Japanese art's influence.
</Question>
<Choice>1871</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French painter Claude Monet's "Impression: Sunrise" uses patches of colour to capture fleeting effects of light.
</Question>
<Choice>1872</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Timothy O'Sullivan's monumental photograph "Canyon de Chelly," depicting majestic rock forms in the American Southwest, embraces a new subject matter and composition style.
</Question>
<Choice>1873</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A journalist reviewing a show by Monet, Renoir, Pisarro, and others dismisses them as "Impressionists," drawing on an 1872 painting by Monet. The group adopts the epithet as their name.
</Question>
<Choice>1874</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American Realist painter Thomas Eakins paints his masterpiece, "The Gross Clinic." The painting demonstrates his command of human anatomy, but its subject meets with disfavour among contemporaries.
</Question>
<Choice>1875</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pierre-Auguste Renoir applies Impressionist technique to the crowd in "Le Moulin de la galette," which depicts pleasures of urban life.
</Question>
<Choice>1876</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Compositional effects owing much to both Japanese prints and an interest in ballet movement and dress are central to the work of Edgar Degas, such as his "Prima Ballerina."
</Question>
<Choice>1876</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French painter Berthe Morisot, a former student of Edouard Manet, paints "Young Woman Powdering Her Face." Her work is admired for its masterful use of color.
</Question>
<Choice>1877</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sir Edward Burne-Jones, one of the last major painters inspired by the Pre-Raphaelites, establishes his reputation at an exhibit featuring "The Beguiling of Merlin" and "The Mirror of Venus." .
</Question>
<Choice>1877</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Paul Cézanne withdraws from the Impressionists, marking the beginnings of Postimpressionism. The movement would flourish in the 1880s.
</Question>
<Choice>1878</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French sculptor Auguste Rodin begins his ambitious project "The Gates of Hell." Though never completed, it proves a source of inspiration for his later commercially and critically successful work.
</Question>
<Choice>1880</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Known for large-scale murals in pastel tones and monochromes, Pierre Puvis de Chavannes begins his "The Sacred Grove," which features dreamlike mythological figures.
</Question>
<Choice>1883</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Formation of the Neo-Impressionists, a group devoted to precise and scientific method of painting, in contrast to the apparently spontaneous style of the Impressionists.
</Question>
<Choice>1884</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Eadweard Muybridge photographs sequences of human movement in "Figure Hopping" and other photo series.
</Question>
<Choice>1884</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American painter and watercolourist Winslow Homer's interest in the forces of nature and virtuosity in rendering the play of light mark his heroic fishing scene, "The Herring Net."
</Question>
<Choice>1885</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The psychologically intense paintings of Edvard Munch, Vincent van Gogh, and James Ensor signal the beginnings of Expressionism.
</Question>
<Choice>1885</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French painter Georges Seurat completes "Sunday Afternoon on the Island of La Grande Jatte." In this and other works he develops his Pointillist technique, based on study of colour, light, and vision.
</Question>
<Choice>1886</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Harnessing the expressive power of brushstroke and colour, eccentric Dutch-born painter Vincent van Gogh creates his masterpiece, "Starry Night."
</Question>
<Choice>1889</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Paul Gauguin moves to Tahiti. There he paints Pacific scenes in a flat, brightly coloured style he developed in France.
</Question>
<Choice>1891</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American Mary Cassatt paints "The Bath." Influenced by Japanese prints, it evokes the intimacy of mother and child in a flat, bold style.
</Question>
<Choice>1892</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Henri de Toulouse-Lautrec, influenced by Degas and drawn to the subjects of nightclub dancers, prostitutes, and drinkers, paints the lurid "At the Moulin Rouge: The Dance."
</Question>
<Choice>1890</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Norwegian Expressionist Edvard Munch paints "The Cry" (also known as "The Scream"), which reverberates in an abstracted landscape.
</Question>
<Choice>1893</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Henry O. Tanner, a student of Thomas Eakins and the first prominent African-American painter, paints "The Banjo Lesson." Its suffused, soft interior light gives its figures an understated intimacy.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1893</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English graphic artist Aubrey Beardsley illustrates Oscar Wilde's "Salomé" with grotesque fin de siècle elegance.
</Question>
<Choice>1894</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Louis Comfort Tiffany's innovative designs of Favrile glass make him a leader in the Art Noveau movement.
</Question>
<Choice>1896</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American photographer Alfred Stieglitz, seeking to elevate photography's status as a medium for artistic expression, founds the Photo-Secession group.
</Question>
<Choice>1902</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Paul Cézanne paints one of his Mont Sainte-Victoire studies. His Postimpressionist restructuring of the visible world flattens space and breaks objects into coloured planes.
</Question>
<Choice>1902</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The young Pablo Picasso paints his elegiac "Woman Ironing," which reveals the depth and distinctive vision of his Blue Period.
</Question>
<Choice>1904</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Henri Matisse begins his "Joy of Life." The modernist touchstone features a radical flattening of picture plane, pure colour, and simplified shapes.
</Question>
<Choice>1905</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Gustav Klimt, leader of Vienna Secession, maximizes the decorative possibilities of fin de siècle sexuality in his elaborate, decadent "The Kiss," completed in 1908.
</Question>
<Choice>1907</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Romanian-born Constantin Brancusi, working in Paris and influenced by non-Western sculpture, carves "The Kiss," a powerfully abstracted statement of unity and intimacy in wood.
</Question>
<Choice>1908</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Working in the Realist tradition, American George Bellows, a member of the Ashcan School, paints the gritty boxing scene "Stag at Sharkey's."
</Question>
<Choice>1909</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian poet Filippo Marinetti publishes his Futurist Manifesto. It inspires a circle of Italian writers, artists, and architects with the power of engineering and technology.
</Question>
<Choice>1909</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pablo Picasso and Georges Braque begin to develop Analytical Cubism, in which structure and mass are reorganized into angular components.
</Question>
<Choice>1910</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian Oskar Kokoschka's portrait "Auguste Forel" exemplifies the artist's distinctive, sinuous brushstroke, as well as his interest in exploring the psychology of his subjects.
</Question>
<Choice>1910</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Painter Wassily Kandinsky, finding his creativity restricted by traditional subjects, begins to experiment with abstract forms in paintings such as "Improvisation XIV."
</Question>
<Choice>1910</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian-born Marc Chagall, drawing subject matter from Jewish life, creates a dreamily surreal world in "I and the Village."
</Question>
<Choice>1911</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Marcel Duchamp, echoing Futurists and extending Analytical Cubism to describe movement, represents the human figure as a set of planes in "Nude Descending a Staircase, No. 2."
</Question>
<Choice>1912</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Cubists begin to experiment with collage technique during the movement's Synthetic Cubism period, emphasizing surface and prominently situating reflexivity of painting in the 20th century.
</Question>
<Choice>1912</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Armory Show, an exhibition of avant-garde and other modern European and American art in New York City, shocks critics and the public but inspires a generation of American artists.
</Question>
<Choice>1913</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Eerie landscape of harsh light and buildings in steep perspective in "The Red Tower" characterizes the Metaphysical painting of Greek-born painter Giorgio de Chirico.
</Question>
<Choice>1913</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian Futurist sculptor Umberto Boccioni emphasizes movement of a figure in its environment in his bronze statue "Unique Forms of Continuity in Space."
</Question>
<Choice>1913</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jacques Lipschitz carves limestone "Man with a Guitar" in Cubist style.
</Question>
<Choice>1916</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American painter Joseph Stella, inspired by the Italian Futurists' enthusiasm for technology, paints "Brooklyn Bridge."
</Question>
<Choice>1917</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Marcel Duchamp, now a member of the Dada movement, challenges the definition of art with his "ready-mades," including "Fountain," an ordinary urinal he exhibits in an art museum.
</Question>
<Choice>1917</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian Vladimir Tatlin begins work on a model for his massive, unbuilt Constructivist "Monument to the Third International," which swirls upward with revolutionary energy.
</Question>
<Choice>1919</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Emergence of the American movement Precisionism, which applies machine aesthetics to painting.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1920</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss painter and Bauhaus member Paul Klee develops an abstract, artistic language of signs, used in such works as "Twittering Machine."
</Question>
<Choice>1922</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German photographer Albert Renger-Patzsch, an ally of the New Objectivity movement, celebrates beauty in ordinary places in "Driving Shaft of a Locomotive."
</Question>
<Choice>1923</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French poet André Breton writes "The Surrealist Manifesto," promoting the role of chance and the unconscious in art and naming one of the most important movements in 20th-century art.
</Question>
<Choice>1924</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Käthe Kollwitz' lithograph "Nie Wieder Krieg" ("Never Again War") crowns an oeuvre of graphic work intensely concerned with social justice.
</Question>
<Choice>1924</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Considered variously a realist and an abstract painter, American Georgia O'Keeffe focuses on the interior of a flower in "Black Iris III."
</Question>
<Choice>1926</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hungarian-born Bauhaus member László Moholy-Nagy experiments with recording images directly on photographic film, producing abstract works called photograms.
</Question>
<Choice>1926</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Romanian-born Constantin Brancusi's bronze "Bird in Space" uses great economy of means to express upward movement.
</Question>
<Choice>1928</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Belgian René Magritte brings a philosophical note to Surrealism in "The Betrayal of Images." His best-known works explore and blur the line between representation and reality.
</Question>
<Choice>1929</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Museum of Modern Art, the first major American museum devoted to 20th-century and avant-garde art, is founded in New York City.
</Question>
<Choice>1929</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German artist John Heartfield employs the technique of photomontage, used by Dadaist and Futurist artists, to create vivid leftist, anti-Nazi images.
</Question>
<Choice>1929</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mexican muralist Diego Rivera begins a mural for the National Palace, Mexico City. His bold, stylized work and grand themes make him one of the best-known and best-respected Latin-American artists.
</Question>
<Choice>1930</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American Precisionist Charles Demuth, influenced by European moderns and fascinated by industrial civilization, paints his hard-edged "Buildings, Lancaster."
</Question>
<Choice>1930</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish painter Salvador Dalí creates the Surrealist icon "The Persistence of Memory," imagining distorted watches in a barren landscape.
</Question>
<Choice>1931</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Group f.64 is founded in the U.S. by Ansel Adams, Imogen Cunningham, Edward Weston, and Willard Van Dyke. It exalts sharp, detailed, technically virtuosic photographs over soft-focus composition.
</Question>
<Choice>1932</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Socialist Realism becomes the official style for literature and art in the Soviet Union, encouraging works of art of impeccable political purity and grinding mediocrity.
</Question>
<Choice>1932</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish painter Joan Miró's teeming "Composition" brings a note of humour and warmth to Surrealism.
</Question>
<Choice>1933</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Working with a 35-mm camera for greater flexibility and speed, French photographer Henri Cartier-Bresson documents the effects of the Spanish Civil War in "Children in Seville, Spain."
</Question>
<Choice>1933</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American photographer Dorothea Lange conveys the desperate plight of Dust Bowl refugees in "Migrant Mother, Nipomo, Calif."
</Question>
<Choice>1936</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nazi propagandists stage the Degenerate Art exhibition. The combination of official hostility and the emigration of many artists end Germany's contribution to the modern art movement.
</Question>
<Choice>1937</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
After the German Luftwaffe's Condor Legion bombs the Basque village of Guernica, Pablo Picasso paints "Guernica," revealing Cubism's power to express horror and tragedy.
</Question>
<Choice>1937</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Grandma Moses, then in her late 70s, begins painting folk works of rural life in the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1938</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American Alexander Calder's "Lobster Trap and Fish Tail" brings balance and movement to sculpture. Calder, the son and grandson of sculptors, invented the mobile.
</Question>
<Choice>1939</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Former Group f.64 member Edward Weston publishes his retrospective California and the West. This and other works establish him as one of the century's most important photographers.
</Question>
<Choice>1940</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American painter Edward Hopper's "Nighthawks" captures late-night urban introspection and isolation.
</Question>
<Choice>1942</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Peggy Guggenheim's Art of This Century Gallery opens in New York City, fueled by the presence of important European artists and intended to encourage young Americans.
</Question>
<Choice>1942</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ansel Adams, with characteristic mastery of tonal properties and an unfailing eye for composition, photographs "Mount Williamson--Clearing Storm."
</Question>
<Choice>1944</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American painter Arshile Gorky paints active, spontaneously rendered biomorphic forms in "The Liver Is the Cock's Comb."
</Question>
<Choice>1944</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British sculptor Henry Moore begins work on his elmwood "Reclining Figure," using void as well as mass to suggest the human form.
</Question>
<Choice>1945</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Abstract Expressionism, a movement that would dominate painting in the 1950s and establish America as the world centre for modern art, begins to develop.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1948</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In "Chicago 1949" and other works, American photographer Aaron Siskind pursues abstraction in photographs by taking weathered and marked surfaces as his subjects.
</Question>
<Choice>1949</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American Jackson Pollock creates nonrepresentational "Autumn Rhythm" by dripping and pouring paint on the canvas.
</Question>
<Choice>1950</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first of Willem de Kooning's "Woman" series hints at representation within the vigorous brushwork of Abstract Expressionism.
</Question>
<Choice>1950</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French painter Jean Dubuffet, rejecting conventions of beauty, creates primitive, or childlike, "raw" works like "Metafisyx (Corps de dame)."
</Question>
<Choice>1950</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The aged Henri Matisse begins to create large-scale, brightly coloured gouache "cutouts" in which shape and colour juxtapositions take precedence over subject matter.
</Question>
<Choice>1950</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American painter Helen Frankenthaler stages her first one-woman show. Her work is noted for its brilliant colour and lyric style.
</Question>
<Choice>1951</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British painter Francis Bacon appropriates from Old Masters, adding a distinctively gruesome, distorting vision, in "Head with Sides of Beef."
</Question>
<Choice>1954</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American Mark Rothko paints "Orange and Yellow." In it, rectangles of colour with subtle variations and blurred edges are juxtaposed, creating emotional resonance.
</Question>
<Choice>1956</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Collage by British artist Richard Hamilton, drawing on popular images and postwar commercialism, marks the beginning of the Pop art movement.
</Question>
<Choice>1956</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hungarian-born French artist Victor Vasarely builds on optical experiments, painting "Vega," a characteristic work of Op art.
</Question>
<Choice>1957</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Diane Arbus quits work as a fashion photographer to concentrate on photographing New York City and its people. The unusual and often freakish nature of her subjects proves unsettling for many viewers.
</Question>
<Choice>1957</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Exhibition of paintings of flags and targets by American Jasper Johns, reintroducing representation into modern art, unsettles art world.
</Question>
<Choice>1958</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss-born photographer Robert Frank publishes The Americans, in which images of ordinary small-town scenes add up to a national portrait.
</Question>
<Choice>1959</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hans Hofmann, whose teaching deeply influenced the Abstract Expressionists, paints "Smaragd Red and Germinating Yellow."
</Question>
<Choice>1959</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Andy Warhol's silk-screen process "Marilyn Diptych," consisting of multiple images of actress Marilyn Monroe, draws attention to reproducibility and commodification of pop icons.
</Question>
<Choice>1962</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Influenced by Matisse's cutouts, American Ellsworth Kelly explores relationships between flat, hard-edged shapes painted in single colours, as in "Red Blue Green."
</Question>
<Choice>1963</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Isolating and radically enlarging frames from comic strips, Roy Lichtenstein adopts the stylized violence of popular images in "Whaam!"
</Question>
<Choice>1963</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American Frank Stella explores effects of pinstripe lines following the shape of nonrectangular canvas in "Empress of India."
</Question>
<Choice>1965</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Minimalism in painting, sculpture, and music emerges. In the visual arts, minimalism was a reaction against the subjectivity of Abstract Expressionism.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1968</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German artist Joseph Beuys's performance art piece, "Coyote," at a New York gallery, combines political and spiritual aims.
</Question>
<Choice>1974</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In her untitled "Untitled Film Stills" series (completed in 1980), American photographer Cindy Sherman, serving as her own model, creates film-noir-style images that question stereotypes and identity.
</Question>
<Choice>1977</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German Neo-Expressionist Anselm Kiefer, struggling with the legacy of Nazism, paints "To the Unknown Painter," in which haunting images emerge from encrusted paint and straw.
</Question>
<Choice>1983</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An exhibit of the work of American photographer Robert Mapplethorpe draws criticism because of its sadomasochistic and homoerotic themes.
</Question>
<Choice>1989</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An exhibit of Lucian Freud's work opens at New York City's Metropolitan Museum of Art, generating controversy for its realistic and intense nudes.
</Question>
<Choice>1993</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The cleaning of the artwork in the Sistine Chapel is completed, restoring Michelangelo's famous frescoes to their original vividness and brightness.
</Question>
<Choice>1994</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The popularity of art exhibits continues to grow as some 965,000 people attend the Claude Monet exhibit at the Art Institute of Chicago.
</Question>
<Choice>1995</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Bulgarian-born environmental sculptor Christo (famous for wrapping large objects, including islands) and his wife, Jeanne-Claude, wrap the Berlin Reichstag in silver fabric.
</Question>
<Choice>1995</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A retrospective show of 158 works by Abstract Expressionist Jackson Pollock (1912-56) opens at the Museum of Modern Art in New York City.
</Question>
<Choice>1998</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A retrospective show of 115 works by Abstract Expressionist Mark Rothko (1903-70) runs at the National Gallery of Art in Washington, D.C.
</Question>
<Choice>1998</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Art Institute of Chicago opens a show dedicated to the work of American expatriate painter and printmaker Mary Cassatt (1844-1926).
</Question>
<Choice>1998</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A four-city U.S. tour begins of Chuck Close's work, including his large-scale paintings of human faces.
</Question>
<Choice>1998</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The National Gallery of Art, Washington, D.C., kicks off a multiyear presentation of the largest and most complete collection of Alfred Stieglitz's work. Many of the prints have never been published.
</Question>
<Choice>1999</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Paul Cézanne's "Still Life with Curtain, Pitcher, and Bowl of Fruit" sells for $60.5 million at auction.
</Question>
<Choice>1999</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The art auction house Sotheby's begins selling items on the Internet.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Whitney Museum of American Art holds the first comprehensive exhibition of painter Alice Neel's work which includes her well-known portraits noted for their poignant record of the human condition.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss video installation artist Pipilotti Rist stages her first solo shows. Her provocative and often humorous work makes her a leader in the genre.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Tate Modern, a new art museum in London, opens.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Noted realist painter Balthus dies.</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Getty Museum stages an exhibit of photographer August Sander's work. His portraits document German people in the early 20th century.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Henri Loyrette is named the new director of the Louvre Museum in Paris. He is one of the youngest persons to head the acclaimed museum.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Tretyakov Gallery in Moscow holds the first comprehensive exhibit of Russian women's art. Spanning some 500 years of work, it features such artists as Maria Bashkirtseva and Lyubov Popova.
</Question>
<Choice>2002</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese photographer Hiroshi Sugimoto has his first major solo exhibition in the U.K. He is noted for using lengthy exposures to produce a meditative quality.
</Question>
<Choice>2002</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the largest collections of the drawings of Leonardo da Vinci opens at the Metropolitan Museum of Art in New York City.
</Question>
<Choice>2003</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pablo Picasso's Boy with a Pipe (1905) sells for a record $104 million.
</Question>
<Choice>2004</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Christo and Jeanne-Claude attract much attention with The Gates, Central Park, New York, 1979-2005. For the work, the artists erected 7,503 steel gates with saffron-coloured cloth panels along more than 20 miles of walkway in Central Park.
</Question>
<Choice>2005</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
With the soaring popularity of digital photography, Nikon and Konica Minolta announce that they will cease producing most or all of their film cameras.
</Question>
<Choice>2006</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Authorities recover Edvard Munch's The Scream (1893), which had been stolen from Norway's Munch Museum in 2004.
</Question>
<Choice>2006</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Photographer Diane Arbus's complete archives--including photographic equipment and diary pages--are gifted to the Metropolitan Museum of Art in New York City.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British artist Damien Hirst's For the Love of God, a cast platinum human skull encrusted with some 8,600 diamonds, reportedly sells for about $100 million--the highest price ever paid for a work by a living artist.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Magnum Photos, the agency established by Robert Capa, George Rodger, David Seymour, and Henri Cartier-Bresson, celebrates its 60th anniversary.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The issue of looted antiquities is highlighted when the Metropolitan Museum of Art in New York City returns a number of items--most notably the Euphronios krater, a 2,500-year-old Greek bowl--to Italy. The Italian government had long alleged that the krater had been plundered from a tomb near Rome.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Museum of Islamic Art, designed by I.M. Pei, opens in Doha, Qatar.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Cai Guo-Qiang becomes the first Chinese artist to be given a one-person retrospective at the Guggenheim Museum in New York.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Tate Britain recreates William Blake's only solo exhibition--held in 1809 in his brother's print shop in London--to celebrate the show's 200th anniversary.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American painter Andrew Wyeth--noted primarily for his realistic depictions of the buildings, fields, hills, and people of his private world--dies.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A selection of paintings from the Prado Museum in Spain can be viewed online using Google Earth's zoom-in feature, thereby revealing details previously unseen.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Artist Bruce Nauman's design for the U.S. Pavilion at the Venice Biennale wins the festival's Golden Lion for best national participation.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Egypt announces the discovery in Alexandria of a temple featuring numerous sculptures of Bastet; archaeologists believe the temple may have been dedicated to the ancient Egyptian goddess.
</Question>
<Choice>2010</Choice>
</item>
</topics>