<topics>
<item>
<Question>
Word lists found at Ur and tablets of text found at Abu Salabikh suggest the existence of formal scribal education in Mesopotamia.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 2600 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An Egyptian Old Kingdom text, The Maxims of Ptahhotep, describes how a vizier to a fifth dynasty king trained his son in official duties.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 2400 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first Mesopotamian schools are established by King Shulgi at Nippur and Ur. The Sumerian name for scribal academy is edubba, "tablet house."
</Question>
<Choice>c. 2100 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Maxims of Ani exhorts Egyptian men to be good to their mothers for having taught them to write at about age five.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 2000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Code of Hammurabi provides the first written rules for apprenticeships. For thousands of years apprenticeships are an important means of training children in arts and crafts.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1700 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Children's swings are used for recreation on the island of Crete.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1600 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Students in New Kingdom Egypt learn the scribal craft by copying Middle Kingdom literary works.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1400 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ten-year-old Egyptian Prince Ramses becomes a captain in his father's army. He would later achieve historical renown as pharaoh Ramses II.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1290 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sparta, the military centre of Greek culture in the Archaic era, flourishes. Beginning at age seven, Spartan boys are apprenticed in the art of war through games and exercises.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 700 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Renowned for his superior military and scholarly education, the young Crown Prince Ashurbanipal becomes king of Mesopotamia. He is the last great Assyrian king.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 668 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
According to legend, a war between Rome and Alba Longa is settled by combat between two groups of young brothers, the Horatii and the Curiatii. The Romans are victorious.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 642 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Sparta, infants are presented to a committee of elders who decide whether a baby is sufficiently well formed to be raised as a Spartan.
</Question>
<Choice>550 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Representations of childhood in Greek art frequently picture children with toys, dolls, and games, confirming the importance ascribed to play in Plato's Laws.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 540 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In a female initiation rite known as arkteia, young Greek girls meet in the sanctuary of the goddess Artemis, the goddess of wild animals and hunting.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 500 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek historian Herodotus describes schools (didaskaleion, "a place for instruction") with separate sites for different learning activities.
</Question>
<Choice>496 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Confucianism elaborates the concept of xiao (hsiao), or filial piety, which requires that the duty of elders be placed above duty to children.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 490 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Archaeological evidence indicates that Greek infants played with bronze and terracotta; when they were a little older, they played with clay toys formed in animal shapes.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 410 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The legend of Romulus and Remus, the young male founders of Rome, is thought to have originated.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 380 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Plato's Laws articulates the concept of paideia, an education that emphasizes the importance of civic virtue and the responsibilities of Greek citizenship in the training of young men.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 375 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Close family ties in Greek society are indicated by Attic vase paintings of toddlers with arms extended toward a mother figure.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 365 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek festivals often feature processions of children. Philostratus's Heroica describes Athenian children three years of age adorned with wreaths of flowers in the celebration known as Anthesteria.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 350 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Children's recreational objects in Greek culture often take the form of horse-shaped figures with wheels, one type of which is equipped with jars for playing "going to the market."
</Question>
<Choice>c. 340 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek children play with a variety of domesticated animals, among which dogs are the most popular. Vase paintings depict teams of elaborately harnessed dogs pulling carts in which children sit.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 320 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese reformer Shang Yang puts new taxes on households, forcing the breakup of extended families.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 220 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Romans consider the family as the natural milieu in which the child should grow and be educated. The role of the mother as educator extends beyond the early years and often has lifelong influence.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 190 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Diodorus Siculus's summary of formal education in Egypt notes that priests teach two kinds of writing to their sons, one sacred and the other for the transmission of everyday information.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 60 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Augustus dedicates the Ara Pacis frieze, a public art work which represents civic identity through family portraiture and commemorates his program for promoting family life and child-rearing.
</Question>
<Choice>9 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jesus Christ, the most important child in the Christian religious tradition, is born. Sources give slightly conflicting information about his exact birth date.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 6 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Quintilian argues that children have individual needs and should be educated and allowed to develop in ways appropriate to their age.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 70</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Roman Emperor Trajan instigates the first official large-scale welfare program to make public funds (alimenta) available for the support of Italian children.
</Question>
<Choice>99</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek physician Soranus of Ephesus writes about the care of infants and diseases of later childhood. His writings set medical opinion concerning pregnancy and infant care for nearly 1,500 years.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 130</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The rule of Marcus Aurelius permits illegitimate children to be entered on the official birth register. However, they are not granted customary property rights under patria potestas.
</Question>
<Choice>147</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jewish records of the 2nd century mention 13 as the age of religious manhood.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 150</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman law recognizes the right of children to succeed their mother if she should die intestate.
</Question>
<Choice>178</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Agnes, the future patron saint of girls, grows up in Rome. According to tradition, she refuses marriage at age 13, declaring that she can have no spouse but Jesus Christ.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 320</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Feast of the Holy Innocents, commemorating the massacre of children by King Herod in his attempt to kill the infant Jesus, begins to be kept as a separate festival.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 450</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The prototype of Western monasticism in Monte Cassino is founded by Benedict of Nursia. The presence of young boys to be educated is fundamental to the institution's mission.
</Question>
<Choice>529</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Ostrogothic Italy and Carthage, schools and private teachers teach ancient grammar and rhetoric, maintaining the pedagogical tradition of classical culture.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 670</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Anglo-Saxon theologian and historian the Venerable Bede writes De natura rerum, a textbook on natural science. It is among several "schoolroom letters" young students read.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 750</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the Islamic world, the maktab emerges as an institution for teaching the Qur'an to young boys.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 800</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Otto III becomes Holy Roman emperor at age three. During his reign he makes plans to recreate the glory and power of the ancient Roman empire in a universal Christian state governed from Rome.
</Question>
<Choice>983</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Seven-year-old William I is accepted as Duke of Normandy. Thirty-one years later he leads the Norman conquest of England, earning the title William the Conqueror.
</Question>
<Choice>1035</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German Prince Henry IV is crowned king at Aix-la-Chapelle at age three and is engaged the following year. He later becomes Holy Roman emperor.
</Question>
<Choice>1054</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
During the papacy of Gregory VII (1073-85), all bishops are asked to see that the art of grammar is taught to children in their churches.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1075</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first important review of childhood illness, an anonymous European work called The Children's Practice appears.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1150</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Eleazar ben Judah's Sefer ha-Roqeah, "Book of the Perfumer," provides the earliest account of Talmudic education.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1190</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In a religious movement known as the "Children's Crusade," thousands of children set out to conquer the Holy Land from the Muslims by love instead of by force. The crusade fails.
</Question>
<Choice>1212</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A Lateran Council decrees that grammar-school masters should be appointed not only in the cathedral church but also in others that can afford it.
</Question>
<Choice>1215</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Geoffrey Chaucer writes the Treatise on the Astrolabe for his son "little Lewis."
</Question>
<Choice>1391</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Vittorino Da Feltre, the leading humanist schoolmaster of the Renaissance, opens La Giocosa ("The House of Joy"), one of Europe's first boarding schools.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1423</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
According to the famous Catasto of 1427, 41.5 percent of male servants and 34 percent of female servants in Florentine households are between 8 and 17 years old.
</Question>
<Choice>1427</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Renaissance man Leon Battista Alberti begins work on his Della famiglia ("On the Family"), a series of dialogues presenting ancient ideas about family and education to modern audiences.
</Question>
<Choice>1432</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
King Henry VI founds Eton College for boys with high scholastic promise. He founds King's College, Cambridge, for Eton graduates in 1441.
</Question>
<Choice>1440</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Under Ottoman rule, Christian boys from the Balkans are conscripted by Muslims through the system of devsirme. They are converted to Islam, educated, and employed in a variety of posts.
</Question>
<Choice>1453</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
"Books of Courtesy," such as The Babees Boke, begin to appear, indicating a new concern for cultivating children's sociability.
</Question>
<Choice>1475</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The schoolboy Desiderius Erasmus begins composing sophisticated classical Latin verse. He becomes the greatest European scholar of the 16th century.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1476</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Upon the death of his elder brother Arthur, young English Prince Henry becomes heir to the throne. Seven years later he is crowned Henry VIII.
</Question>
<Choice>1502</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Children of the Chapel emerges as one of the most important children's acting companies in England. Often the first to stage works by Ben Jonson, the troupe continues to perform until 1615.
</Question>
<Choice>1509</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Broadside ballads become a lively commodity in the wake of the invention of the printing press. Some popular broadsides, like the story of Robin Hood, remain favourites for generations.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1510</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Led by William Cornish, the Children of the Chapel emerge as one of England's most significant companies of child actors. It disbands in 1615 after losing favour with King James I.
</Question>
<Choice>1515</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Martin Luther argues that the primary purpose of a humanist education should be to promote piety through reading Scripture and that all children must be permitted to attend school.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1525</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Ursulines, a Roman Catholic religious order named for St. Ursula, is founded by Angela Merici at Brescia, Italy. It is the first institute for women dedicated exclusively to the education of girls.
</Question>
<Choice>1535</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A portrait of English Prince Edward, later King Edward VI, painted by Hans Holbein the Younger, shows the toddler dressed in brocade and velvet and clutching a silver rattle.
</Question>
<Choice>1539</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Book of Common Prayer is authorized for liturgical use in the Church of England, making religious instruction of children the duty of heads of household.
</Question>
<Choice>1549</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Publication of Jakob Rueff's De conceptu et generatione hominis, a widely used handbook for midwives. One childbirth scene shows an astrologer casting the newborn's horoscope.
</Question>
<Choice>1554</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Queen Elizabeth I reestablishes the Westminster School in London. It becomes one of the best-known public schools in England.
</Question>
<Choice>1560</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Thirteen-month-old Prince James becomes king of Scotland after his mother, Mary, abdicates the throne. At 16 he is kidnapped by one of his earls and spends a year in captivity.
</Question>
<Choice>1567</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Children's companies consisting of boy actors become popular in English theatre.
</Question>
<Choice>1575</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hornbooks become popular as aids to literacy. They consist of a piece of wood with a printed alphabet on paper or parchment pasted on and enclosed behind a transparent sliver of horn.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1595</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Institution of a Young Nobleman, written by James Cleland, advocates a balanced and rounded rather than strictly classical education.
</Question>
<Choice>1607</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The hook-nosed character Pulcinella appears on puppet stages in Italy. An international star, he becomes Polichinelle in France, Petrushka in Russia, and Punch (of Punch and Judy fame) in England.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1610</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Eight-year-old Prince Louis becomes king of France after the assassination of his father, Henry IV. He is married at 14, to a daughter of Philip III of Spain.
</Question>
<Choice>1610</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first book on deaf education, by Juan Pablo Bonet, is published, inaugurating the field of special education.
</Question>
<Choice>1620</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The poor of the Jewish community of Padua are required to send their sons to study with the community's Catholic schoolmaster until they reach the age of 13.
</Question>
<Choice>1624</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Boston Public Latin School is founded. It is the oldest secondary school in the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1635</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The number of middle schoolers in France is estimated at about 65,000, of which more than 40,000 are educated by Jesuits.
</Question>
<Choice>1650</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nicholas Culpeper's Directory for Midwives discusses the vexed question of whether babies should be breast-fed by mothers or wet-nurses.
</Question>
<Choice>1651</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Publication of Orbis Sensualium Pictus (The Visible World in Pictures) by Moravian educator John Amos Comenius. It is the first picture book for children.
</Question>
<Choice>1658</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
First printed reference to an alphabet rhyme, a rhyme composed to help children learn their letters.
</Question>
<Choice>1671</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The controversial Mme de Maintenon founds the Maison Royale de Saint-Louis for orphan girls descended from noble families.
</Question>
<Choice>1686</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In his Traité de l'éducation des filles, the archbishop of Cambrai argues that girls should pursue religious and moral, rather than scholarly education, since they tend to moral corruption.
</Question>
<Choice>1687</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The widely taught alphabet rhyme of the New England Primer, published by Benjamin Harris, combines moral messages with the learning of letters: "In Adam's fall" and "We sinned all" is an example.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1688</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A member of the famous Chamberlen medical family uses obstetrical forceps, invented by Peter Chamberlen the Elder about 1630, to deliver a child to the future Queen Anne of Britain.
</Question>
<Choice>1692</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Publication of John Locke's Some Thoughts Concerning Education. A manual for the mental conditioning of young English gentlemen, it stresses character building and practical learning.
</Question>
<Choice>1693</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Charles Perrault writes The Tales of Mother Goose. Reprinted and retold over the centuries, the tales are among the most famous children's stories.
</Question>
<Choice>1697</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The last child of Britain's Queen Anne dies, ending her hopes of providing herself with a successor. Although pregnant 18 times, only five of Anne's babies are born alive.
</Question>
<Choice>1700</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The beginnings of English children's literature are marked by the publication of a tiny, 12-page work called A Little Book for Little Children by "T.W."
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1707</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian Emperor Peter I the Great founds an Academy of Sciences, which includes a gimnaziya (secondary school). Its secular and scientific characteristics set the tone for Russian education.
</Question>
<Choice>1724</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Thomas Boreman begins publishing educational works for children. In 1742 he produces a recreational story, Cajanus, the Swedish Giant, aimed specifically at a juvenile market.
</Question>
<Choice>1730</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Eight-year-old Joseph Haydn moves to Vienna to serve as a church chorister. He later becomes one of the most important figures in the development of classical music.
</Question>
<Choice>1740</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first specialized children's hospitals, such as the London Foundling Hospital, are opened. These hospitals later become major centres for training in pediatrics.
</Question>
<Choice>1745</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dr. William Cadogan's Essay upon Nursing, and the Management of Children criticizes practices such as swaddling. He calls the habit of hanging a swaddled baby on the wall a form of "crucifixion."
</Question>
<Choice>1748</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Children's literature begins to develop as a specific literary genre, spurred by rising child literacy rates and family incomes in the wake of the Industrial Revolution.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1750</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first educator of poor deaf children, Charles-Michel abbé de l'Epée, develops a system for spelling out French words with a manual alphabet and expressing whole concepts with simple signs.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1750</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pierre Brouzet's Essai sur l'éducation médicinale, des enfants, et sur leurs maladies offers four pages of advice on the proper method for rocking cradles.
</Question>
<Choice>1754</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French genre and portrait painter Jean-Baptiste Greuze initiates a mid-18th-century vogue for sentimental and moralizing anecdotes in painting.
</Question>
<Choice>1755</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Creation of the realschule in Germany, a secondary school teaching practical subjects.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1760</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Five-year-old Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart begins composing short musical pieces. The child prodigy develops into one of the West's great musical talents.
</Question>
<Choice>1761</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jean-Jacques Rousseau's best-seller Émile suggests that children should not be prematurely forced into adulthood and that nature should serve as the child's primary educator.
</Question>
<Choice>1762</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian empress Catherine II founds the Smolnyï Institute to educate daughters of the nobility and upper classes. She goes on to found a number of other schools.
</Question>
<Choice>1764</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Johann Friedrich Oberlin, an Alsatian Lutheran pastor, founds the first salle d'asile, or infant school, for the care and instruction of very small children while their parents work in the fields.
</Question>
<Choice>1767</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Thomas Gainsborough paints "The Blue Boy," one of his most famous pictures. The subject is depicted in Anthony Van Dyck dress, following an 18th-century fashion in portraiture.
</Question>
<Choice>1770</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Michael Angelo's Juvenile Sports and Pastimes features a woodcut entitled "Six Boys Playing Cricket" along with a description of the game.
</Question>
<Choice>1776</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Young Napoleon Bonaparte, arrives at the military school of Brienne in France and is subjected to hazing and humiliation. He later conquers much of Europe.
</Question>
<Choice>1779</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first Sunday school is founded in Gloucester, Eng., by Robert Raikes, a publisher and philanthropist. A few years later the Sunday School Society is founded.
</Question>
<Choice>1780</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Educator Valentin Haüy opens the National Institution of Blind Youth in Paris.
</Question>
<Choice>1784</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dissected puzzles become very popular as both teaching devices and recreational objects. They later evolve into jigsaw puzzles.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1785</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first Sunday school opens in the U.S., in Philadelphia. Its founding reflects the growing popularity of Sunday schools in Europe and America.
</Question>
<Choice>1791</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Edward Jenner inoculates an eight-year-old boy with smallpox matter, resulting in the development of a vaccine against the disease.
</Question>
<Choice>1796</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scientific attempts to educate mentally retarded children begin with the work of French physician Jean-Marc-Gaspard Itard.
</Question>
<Choice>1797</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Richard and Maria Edgeworth collaborate on their widely-read Practical Education. The manual discourages learning by rote and advocates the use of "rational toys" that teach through play.
</Question>
<Choice>1798</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The flat boat-shaped feeding bottle appears, made in large numbers in earthenware by such English manufacturers as John Davenport and Josiah Wedgwood.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1800</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Joseph Lancaster opens a school at Southwark, Eng., based upon the "monitorial" system in which the more proficient pupils instruct the other students.
</Question>
<Choice>1801</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first lycée, or upper-level secondary school, is established in France. It is organized around classical, modern, and scientific studies.
</Question>
<Choice>1801</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Health and Morals of Apprentices Act is passed in Britain. It marks the beginning of government efforts to ameliorate the lot of factory workers and regulate child labour.
</Question>
<Choice>1802</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
"Alphabets Personified"--a lithographed acrobatic "Posture Master" figure, which contorts its physique into the letters of the alphabet--becomes a popular tool for teaching children their ABCs.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1803</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Child actor William Betty appears at Covent Garden, London. The crowd trying to see the young star is so large that troops are called out to preserve order.
</Question>
<Choice>1804</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ann and Jane Taylor strike a new note of sweetness with "Twinkle, Twinkle, Little Star," included in their Rhymes for the Nursery. It becomes one of the most popular nursery rhymes.
</Question>
<Choice>1806</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jean-Marc-Gaspard Itard's classic The Wild Boy of Aveyron tells of his effort to train and educate an 11-year-old boy found running naked and wild in the woods.
</Question>
<Choice>1807</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Marc-Antoine Jullien publishes a practical educational plan for young students. It advises a strict schedule for sleep, study, and exercise.
</Question>
<Choice>1808</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Reform Judaism replaces Bar Mitzvah, a ritual and family celebration commemorating the religious adulthood of a boy on his 13th birthday, with the confirmation of boys and girls together.
</Question>
<Choice>1810</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The toy theatre, also known as the juvenile drama, originates with the engraved sheets that begin to be printed in London as souvenirs of current plays.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1811</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Brothers Grimm begin publishing their fairy tales based on traditional folk tales.
</Question>
<Choice>1812</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A number of punitive devices, such as dunce's hats and finger-stocks, are used to humiliate children in Victorian Dames' Schools.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1813</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Picture discs, which combine wood engravings for children to colour with corresponding letters of the alphabet on the reverse side, are marketed in England for about one shilling.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1815</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Scottish reformer Robert Owen founds his Institute for the Formation of Character, which serves approximately 100 children of the workers in his cotton mills.
</Question>
<Choice>1816</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The kaleidoscope is patented and soon begins to be sold as a children's toy.
</Question>
<Choice>1817</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Glazed porcelain (Dresden) doll heads and unglazed bisque (ceramic) heads become popular.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1820</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first high school opens in Boston. Initially called the English Classical School, it aims to educate the sons of the "mercantile and mechanic classes."
</Question>
<Choice>1821</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Deportment, or correction, chairs are designed by Sir Astley Cooper, surgeon to King George IV, specifically to straighten children's backs.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1823</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
While a student at the National Institute for Blind Children in Paris, 15-year-old Louis Braille develops a six-dot "cell" system that enables blind students to read.
</Question>
<Choice>1824</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Middle-class European families begin to limit their birth rate, reversing the traditional notion that many children were necessary to assure a family's long-term economic survival.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1825</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Gustavus Hamilton's Elements of Gymnastics, for Boys, and of Calisthenics, for Young Ladies describes sports intended to improve the health of children and specifies gender-specific activities.
</Question>
<Choice>1827</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hand-blown glass boat-shaped feeding bottles begin to replace earthenware models. Easier to keep clean than the pottery types, they are considered safer for babies.
</Question>
<Choice>1829</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman Catholic father Ferrante Aporti establishes Italy's first infant school in Cremona. Its curriculum combines moral, intellectual, and physical education, and manual labour.
</Question>
<Choice>1829</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Crippled at a young age, Anna Sewell begins to edit the works of her mother, a deeply religious, popular author of juvenile best-sellers. She later writes the children's classic Black Beauty.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1830</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Samuel Gridley Howe begins teaching blind children at his father's house. He later founds the Perkins School for the Blind, in Boston.
</Question>
<Choice>1832</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Britain's Parliament passes the Factory Act, after years of agitation by reformers like Michael Sadler. It regulates children's working hours and requires children under 13 to attend school.
</Question>
<Choice>1833</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch author Hans Christian Andersen publishes the first volume of his children's tales.
</Question>
<Choice>1835</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first McGuffey reader is published and the series quickly becomes the standard text in nearly all U.S. elementary schools.
</Question>
<Choice>1836</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Friedrich Froebel opens the first kindergarten. It puts into practice his theory of early childhood development as a special phase during which children express themselves through play.
</Question>
<Choice>1837</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Oliver Twist, Dickens's novel about the evils encountered by a poor boy in London, appears with engravings by George Cruikshank, one of the first artists to provide spirited pictures for children's books.
</Question>
<Choice>1838</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the first modern textbooks of pediatrics, by Frédéric Rilliet and Antoine Barthez, is published in France. It describes numerous studies of common childhood diseases.
</Question>
<Choice>1838</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Domino-Spel, a set of 28 engraved cards with comical scenes incorporating domino spots, is marketed as a means of teaching children arithmetic.
</Question>
<Choice>1839</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The use of anesthesia in childbirth is condemned by some church officials as contrary to the Bible. Its use by Queen Victoria helps to quiet such opponents.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1840</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In one of the first formal studies of child psychology, Charles Darwin begins a record of the growth and development of one of his own children.
</Question>
<Choice>1840</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A new genre of children's literature, romantic historical fiction, appears with the publication of Frederick Marryat's The Children of the New Forest.
</Question>
<Choice>1847</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Artist and political satirist Honoré Daumier's caricature The Dangerous Boys depicts a bourgeois couple frightened by the sight of the young Mobile Guard in control of the streets of Paris.
</Question>
<Choice>1848</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
"Butter's Tangible Arithmetic and Geometry for Children," a box of 144 oak cubes and an accompanying book of instructions and diagrams, goes on sale in England.
</Question>
<Choice>1852</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The flying trapeze is invented and becomes a major attraction at the circus.
</Question>
<Choice>1859</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Psychiatrist Edouard Séguin, author of Traitment moral, hygiene et education des idiots, a classic work in psychology, begins work with retarded children in the asylum at Randall's Island, N.Y.
</Question>
<Choice>1863</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Lewis Carroll's literary masterpiece Alice's Adventures in Wonderland marks a transition from an emphasis on moral training to pleasure in children's literature.
</Question>
<Choice>1865</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
"Crandall's Building Slabs," wooden alphabet bricks that can be joined together to make words, are patented by H. Jewitt & Co. in London.
</Question>
<Choice>1867</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Based on her recollections of her own childhood, Louisa May Alcott's Little Women traces the differing personalities and fortunes of four sisters as they emerge from childhood.
</Question>
<Choice>1868</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
F.A.O. Schwarz opens a modest toy shop in New York City. By 1908 it becomes a mammoth store offering 16,000 items.
</Question>
<Choice>1870</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russell Frisbie of Cromwell, Conn., manufactures the first toy steam engine.
</Question>
<Choice>1871</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
New York becomes the first state to legislate protection for children. It serves as a model for other states, all of which begin to legislate statutes designating child abuse as a criminal offense.
</Question>
<Choice>1875</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mark Twain publishes The Adventures of Tom Sawyer, a classic of American children's literature.
</Question>
<Choice>1876</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Robert Louis Stevenson writes Treasure Island, a fast-paced adventure tale. He later writes A Child's Garden of Verses, Kidnapped, and The Strange Case of Dr. Jekyll and Mr. Hyde.
</Question>
<Choice>1881</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German psychophysiologist W.T. Preyer publishes Die seele des kindes ("The Mind of the Child"), a milestone in the early history of child psychology.
</Question>
<Choice>1882</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The National Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Children is incorporated in Great Britain and helps to promote children's rights.
</Question>
<Choice>1884</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The safety bicycle is popularized by the Rover Safety model, manufactured by John K. Starley. It is a significant advance over earlier, more dangerous models of bicycle.
</Question>
<Choice>1885</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first juvenile court is established in Chicago. Its originators consider it futile and unjust to punish a child for wrongdoing, preferring rehabilitation instead.
</Question>
<Choice>1889</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jacob Riis publishes How the Other Half Lives, a realistic and powerful photographic record of the lives of slum dwellers. His work spurs Progressive era use of photography to document social ills.
</Question>
<Choice>1890</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American educational psychologist G. Stanley Hall establishes the Pedagogical Seminary, a periodical devoted to child psychology and pedagogy.
</Question>
<Choice>1891</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian educators Rosa and Carolina Agazzi combine the pedagogical methods of Aporti and Froebel in their scuola materna, or Italian maternal school.
</Question>
<Choice>1892</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The box kite, a tailless kite that flies on one edge, is invented by Australian Lawrence Hargrave.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1893</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American educator John Dewey founds the first Laboratory School in Chicago. It helps to establish the University of Chicago as a leading centre of social science research.
</Question>
<Choice>1894</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Queen Victoria presents her great-grandson, Prince Albert, the future King George VI, with a marble bust of his departed namesake at his christening.
</Question>
<Choice>1895</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French psychologist Alfred Binet founds the journal L'Année Psychologique. He also founds a laboratory for research in childhood education, beginning a long and influential career in the field.
</Question>
<Choice>1895</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Tom Brown's tramps "Weary Willie and Tired Tim" are the first characters to appear regularly in British comic strips. The first American comic strips appear in the New York World that same year.
</Question>
<Choice>1896</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The progressive education movement takes form in Europe and the United States. Critical of traditional education's narrow scope and strictness, it seeks to educate the "whole child."
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1897</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The world's first children's museum is established, in Brooklyn, N.Y.
</Question>
<Choice>1899</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In his Interpretation of Dreams, Freud theorizes the Oedipus complex, attributing it to children ages three to five. His writings on child sexuality are among the most controversial of Freud's work.
</Question>
<Choice>1899</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English author Beatrix Potter publishes the Tale of Peter Rabbit. Potter's charming and well-illustrated stories establish her as one of the most beloved children's writers of the 20th century.
</Question>
<Choice>1900</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
As the European middle class redefines leisure in terms of personal improvement and family cohesion; group activities like family reading become common pastimes.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1905</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The psychological principles needed to adapt education to individual children are expounded in Édouard Claparède's influential Psychologie de l'enfant et pédagogie experimentale.
</Question>
<Choice>1905</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sigmund Freud theorizes that infants have several psychosexual stages of child development, beginning with the oral stage.
</Question>
<Choice>1905</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Alfred Binet and Theodore Simon begin to develop their highly influential scales for the measurement of intelligence of children.
</Question>
<Choice>1905</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Maria Montessori opens her Casa dei Bambini (The Children's House). The educational philosophy of the Montessori school movement stresses individual student interests and self-directed learning.
</Question>
<Choice>1907</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ovide Decroly opens his École de l'Ermitage (School of the Hermitage) near Brussels. Unlike the Montessori school, Decroly's school emphasizes group learning.
</Question>
<Choice>1907</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Boy Scouts are founded in Great Britain by Lieutenant General Robert S.S. Baden-Powell. The movement eventually spreads around the world.
</Question>
<Choice>1908</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American sociologist-turned-photographer Lewis Hine documents the exploitation of child labour in American factories in "Child Labor in the Carolinas" and "Day Laborers Before Their Time."
</Question>
<Choice>1909</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Robert Baden-Powell founds the Girl Guides as a parallel to the Boy Scouts. The first Girl Scout troop is founded in the U.S. two years later.
</Question>
<Choice>1910</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American novelist Edgar Rice Burroughs publishes the first of his Tarzan stories about the son of an English nobleman raised by apes in the African jungle.
</Question>
<Choice>1912</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hull House veteran Julia Lathrop is named chief of the newly created U.S. Children's Bureau. The bureau brings progressive ideas and concerns about child welfare to the federal level.
</Question>
<Choice>1912</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Tinkertoys are created by Charles Pajeau. In the succeeding decades the rugged wooden toys become a staple of toy boxes throughout Europe and America.
</Question>
<Choice>1914</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Eighteen-month old American toddler Jackie Coogan appears in his first film, Skinner's Baby. As an adult he plays Uncle Fester on the television show The Addams Family.
</Question>
<Choice>1916</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Lincoln Logs, a simple toy for building houses and other structures, are popularized by John Lloyd Wright, son of the famous American architect Frank Lloyd Wright.
</Question>
<Choice>1916</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Seventeen-year-old Anastasia, grand duchess of Russia, and her family are executed by Bolshevik revolutionaries. In the following decades numerous stories circulate claiming that Anastasia survived.
</Question>
<Choice>1918</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first chapter of Save the Children is founded in Great Britain. Established to provide relief to European children, it later grows into an international organization.
</Question>
<Choice>1919</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Daily Express begins publishing "Rupert, the Adventures of a Little Lost Teddy Bear." It is the first children's comic strip to appear in an adult newspaper.
</Question>
<Choice>1920</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
State-run kindergartens are established in Russia under the supervision of N.K. Krupskaya. Soviet educators hope to use preschools as instruments of political education.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1920</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British educator A.S. Neill opens Summerhill, a revolutionary school designed for self-development.
</Question>
<Choice>1921</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Social worker Grace Abbott succeeds Julia Lathrop as head of the U.S. Children's Bureau. Like Lathrop, Abbott is a veteran of Jane Addams's Hull House and observer of Chicago Progressive era reforms.
</Question>
<Choice>1921</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian author Maksim Gorky calls for a new children's literature to educate children about and build loyalty to the Soviet regime.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1922</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dr. Truby King's Mothercraft movement, with its maxim "Breast-fed is Best-fed," brings breast-feeding back into fashion.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1924</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A.A. Milne publishes Winnie-the-Pooh. The chronicles of Christopher Robin and his toy animals, including Pooh, Tigger, and Eeyore, become children's classics.
</Question>
<Choice>1926</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Struggling animator Walt Disney creates a new character, a mouse named "Mickey." Mickey Mouse becomes one of the best-known animated characters on the planet.
</Question>
<Choice>1927</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Modern pinball machines originate. Their popularity fades in the late 20th century with the advent of electronic games.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1930</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French author and artist Jean de Brunhoff creates Babar the Elephant, one of the most beloved characters in children's literature.
</Question>
<Choice>1931</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Melanie Klein publishes The Psychoanalysis of Children. Influenced by Freudian theory, it presents her object-relations theory of child analysis.
</Question>
<Choice>1932</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hollywood director Hal Roach discovers George McFarland in a film advertisement for Wonder Bread and casts him as "Spanky," the leader of Our Gang, later known as the Little Rascals.
</Question>
<Choice>1932</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Children and Young Persons Act is passed in Great Britain. It sets standards for the rehabilitation of delinquent and neglected children and declares the state's interest in curbing child abuse.
</Question>
<Choice>1933</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Shirley Temple sings her signature "On the Good Ship Lollipop" in the motion picture Bright Eyes. The film helps to establish her as one of Hollywood's most popular stars.
</Question>
<Choice>1934</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Irish-born American Freddie Bartholomew stars in Little Lord Fauntleroy. His work in movie adaptations of such literary classics as David Copperfield and Kidnapped makes him a leading child actor.
</Question>
<Choice>1936</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the United States, the Fair Labor Standards Act is signed, setting the minimum ages of employment for children.
</Question>
<Choice>1938</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Superman, defender of "truth, justice, and the American way," makes his cartoon debut. He becomes one of the most famous characters of 20th-century popular culture.
</Question>
<Choice>1938</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The California legislature enacts the Child Actors Bill, popularly called the "Coogan Law," to protect the rights of child movie actors. The law is named after popular child actor Jackie Coogan.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1938</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Little League is founded in Williamsport, Pa. It admits girls in 1974. Little League teams have spread all over the world: its World Series draws on more countries than the professional version.
</Question>
<Choice>1939</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Theodor Seuss Geisel (Dr. Seuss) publishes Horton Hatches the Egg. Dr. Seuss's whimsical pictures and tongue-twisting rhymes make him a favourite with American parents and children.
</Question>
<Choice>1940</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Thirteen-year-old Anne Frank, her family, and four fellow Jews go into hiding in Amsterdam to avoid Nazi persecution. Her diary of her years in hiding becomes a classic of war literature.
</Question>
<Choice>1942</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Education Act of 1944 is passed in Great Britain. The act requires state-aided primary and secondary schools to begin the day with collective worship.
</Question>
<Choice>1944</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Psychologist Bruno Bettelheim becomes head of the Sonia Shankman Orthogenic School at the University of Chicago, where he conducts research on autistic and emotionally disturbed children.
</Question>
<Choice>1944</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Benjamin Spock publishes Common Sense Book of Baby and Child Care. The book, which encourages parents to trust their instincts over expert advice, shapes the childhoods of millions of baby boomers.
</Question>
<Choice>1946</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Lego, a building toy invented in 1932 by Dutch carpenter and toymaker Ole Kirk Christiansen, begins to be manufactured in plastic as well as wood. Lego becomes one of the world's most popular toys.
</Question>
<Choice>1947</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jean Piaget develops his theory of cognition in children, which features four stages of development. Piaget's work in child psychology made him one of the central figures in the discipline.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1950</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Victor Mills begins developing the disposable diaper.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1950</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Apgar Score System is introduced. Based on a point system where a maximum score of 10 is best, it evaluates the condition of newborn babies.
</Question>
<Choice>1952</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The field of child psychiatry is officially recognized as a specialty by the American Board of Psychiatry and Neurology. This contributes to the development of child psychiatry as a separate field.
</Question>
<Choice>1954</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Salk vaccine for infantile paralysis (poliomyelitis) is made available commercially. It and the Sabin vaccine virtually eliminate what had been one of the most feared childhood diseases.
</Question>
<Choice>1955</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Film studio Walt Disney Productions opens a theme park in Anaheim, Calif. Disneyland's immense popularity and movie tie-ins help consolidate the company's central place in American popular culture.
</Question>
<Choice>1956</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Barbie makes her debut at a toy fair in New York City. Created by Ruth Handler, the doll, named after her daughter, becomes one of the best-known icons of postwar American popular culture.
</Question>
<Choice>1959</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Initial Teaching Alphabet, designed by Sir James Pitman, is adopted by experimental schools in England. The special alphabet is designed to make it easier for children to learn to read.
</Question>
<Choice>1960</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ruth Handler, creator of the Barbie doll and cofounder of Mattel toy company, unveils Ken, a companion to the by-now wildly popular Barbie. The new doll is named after her son.
</Question>
<Choice>1961</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Emergence in Japan of modern-type juku, or "cram schools," designed to help students study or prepare for exams. The term juku dates from the Tokugawa shogunate.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1964</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The United Nations International Children's Emergency Fund (UNICEF) receives the Nobel Peace Prize for its work in international child welfare.
</Question>
<Choice>1965</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first Special Olympics are held in Chicago's Soldier Field. In 1977 the first winter Special Olympics are held in Streamboat Springs, Colo.
</Question>
<Choice>1968</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Debut of the Children's Television Workshop's popular television program Sesame Street. Its main characters, including Big Bird and Cookie Monster, are the brainchild of muppet-maker Jim Henson.
</Question>
<Choice>1969</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Inner London Education Authority bans corporal punishment in primary schools. The move signals a larger decline in the popularity of corporal punishment in Europe and America.
</Question>
<Choice>1973</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The United States Congress establishes the National Center on Child Abuse and Neglect.
</Question>
<Choice>1974</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
George Lucas's Star Wars debuts. The movie creates a set of characters that become part of popular consciousness and establishes the value of toy and video-game franchises based on movies.
</Question>
<Choice>1977</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Steven Spielberg's E.T. The Extra-Terrestrial, which features an alien creature befriended and aided by children, is one of the year's most popular children's movies.
</Question>
<Choice>1982</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Brazilian street children organize the National Movement for Street Boys and Girls, an advocacy group that helps craft new child protection laws. Previously street children had been targets of torture and murder.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1985</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Founding of CHILDHOPE, an international nongovernmental organization serving the needs of "street children," some of whom live in homes but are forced by economic circumstance to work on the street.
</Question>
<Choice>1986</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The United Nations Convention on the Rights of the Child is passed by the General Assembly. One of the most popular human rights conventions, by 1995 it is ratified by 180 nations.
</Question>
<Choice>1989</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mortal Kombat becomes the most popular title in the fast-growing home video-game market.
</Question>
<Choice>1993</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first Beanie Baby is sold at a toy fair. The animal-shaped beanbags create a frenzy among collectors around the world and in 1996 an estimated 100 million are sold.
</Question>
<Choice>1993</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Political instability, famine, and civil war lead to millions of Third World children being orphaned or separated from their parents. Millions of others are displaced with their families.
</Question>
<Choice>1994</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The United States launches a "Back to Sleep" campaign, which encourages parents to put infants to sleep on their backs to reduce the incidence of sudden infant death syndrome (SIDS).
</Question>
<Choice>1994</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Mighty Morphin Power Rangers, created by Japanese company Bandai, become an international hit, leveraged into toys, television shows, and movies.
</Question>
<Choice>1994</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The popularity of toys based on movies such as Toy Story and The Lion King (1994) demonstrates the growing popularity of alliances between toy companies and Hollywood studios.
</Question>
<Choice>1995</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the United States, Congress eliminates Depression-era welfare entitlements, adversely affecting millions of impoverished children.
</Question>
<Choice>1995</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the absence of adequate assistance for families, the number of children in foster care in the United States increases, from a low of 250,000 in 1983 to 460,000 in 1995.
</Question>
<Choice>1995</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sweden hosts the first World Congress Against Commercial Sexual Exploitation of Children.
</Question>
<Choice>1996</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Tyco Toys Inc.'s Tickle Me Elmo becomes the most popular toy of the Christmas season.
</Question>
<Choice>1996</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Tamagotchi "virtual pets," introduced in Japan in 1996, reach the United States. Other new electronic toys include ActiMates Barney, a version of the popular purple dinosaur.
</Question>
<Choice>1997</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>The animatronic toy Furby debuts.</Question>
<Choice>1998</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese video game manufacturer Nintendo launches the interactive toy Pokémon in the American market.
</Question>
<Choice>1998</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At Columbine High School in Littleton, Colo., two students kill 12 fellow students and a teacher and wound more than 20 others before taking their own lives.
</Question>
<Choice>1999</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The U.S. Supreme Court declares that schools may be liable for failing to stop student-on-student sexual harassment.
</Question>
<Choice>1999</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
More than 1.5 million students are home schooled in the United States, as parents grow concerned about the quality of traditional education and the safety of the school environment.
</Question>
<Choice>1999</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At the World Education Forum, it is reported that some 113 million children, most of which are girls, do not have access to primary education.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The world's largest rollercoaster, the Steel Dragon 2000, opens in Japan. It is 97 metres (318 feet) tall and 2.4 km (1.5 miles) long.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The 100th anniversary of L. Frank Baum's children's classic The Wonderful Wizard of Oz is celebrated.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Disney opens a new amusement park, California Adventure.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Coalition to Stop the Use of Child Soldiers reports that at least 300,000 children under the age of 18 are fighting as soldiers in 41 countries.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American animator Chuck Jones, who helped create such popular cartoon characters as Bugs Bunny, Daffy Duck, and Elmer Fudd, dies.
</Question>
<Choice>2002</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish children's author Astrid Lindgren, the creator of the Pippi Longstocking series, dies at age 94. The adventures of her mischievous, red-haired heroine were translated into more than 80 languages.
</Question>
<Choice>2002</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Fred Rogers, better known as "Mister Rogers," dies. He was the beloved host of the children's program Mister Rogers' Neighborhood, which ran on American television for more than 30 years.
</Question>
<Choice>2003</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Since its creation in 1988, the Global Polio Eradication Initiative, the largest public-health campaign ever undertaken, has vaccinated at least two billion children against the highly infectious virus.
</Question>
<Choice>2004</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Chronicles of Narnia: The Lion, the Witch, and the Wardrobe, a film adaptation of the first of C.S. Lewis's series of children's books, is released.
</Question>
<Choice>2005</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scientists announce that they have found a gene that increases the risk of developing Type 2 diabetes, a form of the disease once limited to adolescents and adults that is becoming increasingly common in children.
</Question>
<Choice>2006</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nintendo releases Wii, an innovative video game console featuring a wireless remote that users move to replicate the motions of such items as a tennis racket or baseball bat. Wii quickly becomes a leader in the industry.
</Question>
<Choice>2006</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British author J.K. Rowling completes the last book in the Harry Potter series, Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows. The chronicles of a young sorcerer in training have been a phenomenal success with both children and adults.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Millions of children's toys manufactured in China are recalled due to lead paint and other safety reasons.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Children in the United States begin receiving the five-in-one vaccine, Pentacel. It is the first combination vaccine to immunize against diphtheria, tetanus, pertussis, polio, and Haemophilus influenzae type B.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Researchers move closer to developing a blood test for expectant mothers that would detect Down syndrome in their unborn children.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Two men are executed in China for their involvement in a tainted-milk scandal that led to a worldwide recall of Chinese-made dairy products in 2008. Milk tainted with melamine, a toxic chemical, sickened some 300,000 children.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A film version of Maurice Sendak's children's classic Where the Wild Things Are (1963) is released to critical acclaim.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. First Lady Michelle Obama launches a major initiative to combat childhood obesity; according to a U.S. surgeon general's report, "nearly one in three children are overweight or obese" in the country.
</Question>
<Choice>2010</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The scientific journal The Lancet retracts a widely disseminated paper--which it had orginally published in 1998--that suggested an association between autism and childhood vaccination; investigations revealed that the paper had violated research ethics and contained false claims.
</Question>
<Choice>2010</Choice>
</item>
</topics>