<topics>
<item>
<Question>
The dog is domesticated by humans. The first animal to be domesticated, it will diversify into hundreds of specialized breeds.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 12,000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Cow's milk becomes a part of the human diet in the West.
</Question>
<Choice>9000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Humans discover how to fashion vessels from clay and harden them by heat; refined versions of this earthenware pottery will be made in every era.
</Question>
<Choice>7000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Domesticated pigs are raised in Jarmo (modern-day Iraq).
</Question>
<Choice>6750 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Stone Age comes to an end as craftsmen in Anatolia (modern-day Turkey) begin to fashion objects of copper.
</Question>
<Choice>6500 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Cattle are domesticated in Greece and on Crete; lentils and a variety of cereal grains, including wheat, are also cultivated.
</Question>
<Choice>6000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Beer, made from barley, is brewed in Sumeria and Babylonia, indicating knowledge of the process of fermentation.
</Question>
<Choice>5900 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Vitis vinifera, the wine grape, enters cultivation in the Middle East.
</Question>
<Choice>4000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The horse is domesticated. For thousands of years it is one of the most valuable domesticated animals, helping to shape travel, war, and agriculture.
</Question>
<Choice>4000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Egyptians use cosmetics such as eye makeup and scented unguents. Some samples are still fragrant when discovered in the 19th century.
</Question>
<Choice>3950 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Chinese develop methods of raising silkworms and of weaving silk fabrics. The fabric's characteristics inspire creativity in weavers and tailors.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 3600 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A Sumerian pictograph documents the invention of the wheel.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 3500 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Corn is in widespread cultivation in the Americas; beans (Phaseolus), chili pepper, avocados, amaranths, and other food crops are also grown.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 3480 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Olive trees are being cultivated on the island of Crete. By the end of the 20th century there will be 500 million olive trees in Europe.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 3450 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The man later called the Iceman dies in the Alps. His remaining scalp hairs will present the earliest archaeological evidence of haircutting.
</Question>
<Choice>3300 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Bronze Age begins in Greece and China as humans learn how to smelt copper and tin to form implements of metal.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 3000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Rice cultivation begins in India. Both wetland and dry-land varieties will be developed, enabling it to grow in many climates. The grain becomes a staple in the Asian world.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 2990 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first insurance contracts are created, to protect investments on maritime trade.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 2980 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Tea, made from the leaves of Camellia sinensis, achieves popularity as a beverage in China.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 2737 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Chairs appear in Egypt.</Question>
<Choice>c. 2650 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Egyptians learn to control the interaction of dough and yeast, leading to the creation of leavened bread.
</Question>
<Choice>2600 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The potato is domesticated in Peru. It eventually spreads to Europe and North America, where it becomes a staple food.
</Question>
<Choice>2500 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Egyptians are producing beads made of glass, having refined an even more ancient process that had originated in Mesopotamia.
</Question>
<Choice>2490 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Egyptians proclaim the cat a sacred animal. Thousands of cats are mummified after their deaths to assure them eternal life and human (and divine) attention.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 2470 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The horse, domesticated since about 4000 BC, is widely employed as a mount by the nomadic peoples of Central Asia. One group, the Scythians, later invents the stirrup.
</Question>
<Choice>2000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indigo, one of the most important and popular dyes, is in use in Asia, Egypt, and the Mediterranean.
</Question>
<Choice>1500 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Advances in mining and metallurgy in the Middle East and southeastern Europe usher in the Iron Age.
</Question>
<Choice>1200 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first recorded use of the pen, by Chinese calligraphers.
</Question>
<Choice>1000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The ancient Egyptians invent the sundial as a means of telling time.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 710 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Homeric epics, the Iliad and the Odyssey, document that the nuclear family is the primary unit of residence and domestic economy in Western society.
</Question>
<Choice>700 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Cockfighting is introduced into Greece from Persia. The practice continues in Europe until outlawed in the mid-1800s. It is still played in Asia, Africa, and parts of Latin America.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 500 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Knotted Oriental carpets are being produced in Persia. Some of their design motifs will remain popular to the present day.
</Question>
<Choice>400 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
From soybeans the Chinese learn to prepare tofu, a cheap, versatile, and nutritious protein source.
</Question>
<Choice>200 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Temple reliefs portray the sari and dhoti as standard Indian costume. The styles persist to the present day.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 190BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Syrians invent glassblowing, enabling the creation of hollow objects such as drinking vessels, bottles, and vases.
</Question>
<Choice>100 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Julian calendar is introduced into use in the Western world. It is used until 1582, when it is replaced by the Gregorian calendar.
</Question>
<Choice>8</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Soap, previously considered to be medicinal, comes into common use as a cleaning agent.
</Question>
<Choice>100</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Chinese develop a process for making paper. The technology moves west, reaching Baghdad in 793.
</Question>
<Choice>105</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Baths of Caracalla are completed in Rome; 1,600 bathers can be accommodated at the 28-acre site's therapeutic and hygienic facilities.
</Question>
<Choice>216</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Romanesque style of architecture and design, based on those of ancient Rome, becomes prevalent in northern Europe.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 800</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
European arrival of the komondor, a large working dog bred by the Magyar to protect sheep from wolves and other predators. It is one of many species of herd dogs developed over the centuries.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 850</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In China, the first printed book, a copy of the Buddhist Diamond Sutra, is produced using carved wooden blocks to print the text on paper.
</Question>
<Choice>868</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Archaeological evidence suggests Maya smokers have invented an early version of the modern cigar.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 900</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The chimney is adopted in Europe as a means of carrying off smoke and heat from the fireplace.
</Question>
<Choice>1200</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The buttonhole is adopted in Europe from Moorish tailors as a means of fastening garments; previously, buttons had been fastened to loops of fabric.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1250</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese potters of the Yuan dynasty develop the formula for producing hard-paste porcelain; the first piece of porcelain will be introduced to Europe by Marco Polo.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1279</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The English develop standardized shoe sizes, making it possible to produce well-fitting shoes in large numbers, rather than make each pair based on an individual's measurements.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1305</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The kimono, derived from Chinese court costume, is adapted as an outer garment for women in Japan.
</Question>
<Choice>1340</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
King Htai Tjong of Korea orders the production of 100,000 bronze characters, the first metal movable type.
</Question>
<Choice>1403</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Coffee is introduced into cultivation in Arabia from its native East Africa.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1430</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Johannes Gutenberg publishes his Forty-two-Line Bible on a printing press with movable type. The printing press will revolutionize Western culture.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1455</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In France, King Louis XI sets up a national mail-delivery system, the Royal Postal Service, staffed with 230 mounted couriers.
</Question>
<Choice>1477</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Newsbooks are being issued at the rate of 20 per year in England and on the Continent. They provide information on major events and public issues.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1490</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Peter Henlein of Germany invents the mainspring as a means of driving a clock; this invention enables the invention of the watch.
</Question>
<Choice>1500</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Portuguese traders open an ocean route from India to Europe, bringing spices from the East much more quickly by ship than the tedious overland route.
</Question>
<Choice>1501</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish explorer Hernán Cortés is served a chocolate drink at the court of Montezuma in Mexico. Until about 1850 most chocolate will be consumed as a beverage.
</Question>
<Choice>1519</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
La Lotto di Firenze is established, in Florence, Italy. It is the first public lottery to offer monetary prizes.
</Question>
<Choice>1530</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first university in the Western Hemisphere is founded, at Santo Domingo (on Hispaniola), by the Spanish.
</Question>
<Choice>1538</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Tobacco cultivation begins in Europe. Tobacco becomes an important cash crop in the New World for trade with Europe.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1550</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The potato is introduced into Europe from South America. Although initially suspected of being poisonous, by the end of the 17th century it will be a major food crop.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1550</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first cafés are operating in Constantinople (Istanbul). Cafés appear in France, Italy, Germany, and England in the 1600s.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1560</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Gregorian calendar is introduced into use in the Western world. It replaces the Julian calendar, which had been in use since Roman times.
</Question>
<Choice>1582</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The invention of the knitting machine by William Lee eliminates the need to hand knit stockings and enables the mass production of fine-gauge garments.
</Question>
<Choice>1589</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English courtier John Harington invents the flush toilet. He has one installed for Queen Elizabeth I at her palace in Richmond, Surrey.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1590</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pajamas are introduced to the West as lounging attire. They are not adopted as sleepwear (for men) until the 1870s.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1601</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
King James I of England introduces the game of golf to London from Scotland.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1608</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Johann Carolus of Strasbourg issues the Relation, considered to be the first modern newspaper. A German paper is also issued.
</Question>
<Choice>1609</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The mass production of glass bottles and the development of cork stoppers begins to make possible the controlled aging of wine.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1650</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In France, during the reign of King Louis XIV, the fork begins to achieve popularity as an eating implement. Formerly, only knives and spoons had been used.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1667</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Newfoundland dog breed is created in North America. This large dog has an oily coat and webbed feet and is specially bred for water and rescue work.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1670</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The hospice of St. Bernard of Montjoux begins using large dogs, later called St. Bernards, to search for and rescue lost Alpine travelers. The dogs save some 2,500 lives over the next 300 years.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1680</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Fire insurance is developed in London in the wake of the great fire of 1666.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1680</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Life insurance policies begin to come into use in Europe.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1690</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Old English sheepdog, bred to herd and protect sheep, is developed in England.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1700</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Queen Anne style furniture begins to gain great popularity; featuring the graceful cabriole leg, the style remains popular through the 20th century.
</Question>
<Choice>1702</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Boston News-Letter, the first officially sanctioned newspaper in North America, begins publication.
</Question>
<Choice>1704</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The hoop skirt, a basket-like framework worn as a petticoat, becomes fashionable in England and France; it displays the fine fabrics and trimmings of the elaborate costume of the era.
</Question>
<Choice>1710</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The graceful and elegant Rococo style originates in France and supercedes the Baroque style in western Europe.
</Question>
<Choice>1720</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A German farmer produces fish by artificial fertilization, greatly advancing the practice of aquaculture, or fish farming.
</Question>
<Choice>1733</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Industrial Revolution promotes the growth of cities, the factory system, and a myriad of other changes to everyday life in Europe.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1740</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The collie is bred in Great Britain. Its intelligence and loyalty make it highly valued as a herd dog and as a companion to humans.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1750</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The symphony, an orchestral work in sonata form, is codified during the Classical period of western music.
</Question>
<Choice>1750</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Archaeological finds in ancient Greece and Rome stimulate development of Neoclassical style. Unlike Renaissance classicism, it draws on real ancient buildings rather than ancient architectural theory.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1752</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>The first shoe factory opens, in Massachusetts.</Question>
<Choice>c. 1760</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
J.B. Delaborde of France invents the first electric musical instrument, an electric harpsichord.
</Question>
<Choice>1761</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first steel scissors are produced by English industrialist Robert Hinchliffe. Scissors in various forms had been in use in Asia and Europe since ancient times.
</Question>
<Choice>1761</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The word "tattoo" is introduced into the English language from Polynesian by James Cook.
</Question>
<Choice>1769</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English chemist Joseph Priestly gives the name "rubber" to caoutchouc resin because it can rub out marks.
</Question>
<Choice>1770</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Thomas Jefferson raises tomatoes at Monticello, Va. A native of South America, the fruit is introduced to North America from Europe.
</Question>
<Choice>1781</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English surgeon Edward Jenner successfully inoculates eight-year-old James Phipps against smallpox, introducing the era of vaccination.
</Question>
<Choice>1796</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Neoclassicism evolves into the Empire style in France, the Regency style in England, and the Federal style in the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1800</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English potter Josiah Spode II adds calcined bone to his porcelain formula and creates strong, chip-resistant bone china.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1800</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Advanced manufacturing techniques and increases in building size lead to the development of central heating.
</Question>
<Choice>1800</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Frenchman Nicolas Appert develops a process for canning food by sealing it in airtight containers and sterilizing it with heat.
</Question>
<Choice>1809</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Englishman Peter Durand patents the tin can for food storage, replacing the glass bottles previously used.
</Question>
<Choice>1810</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The modern form of trousers, cut to follow the lines of the body, becomes the standard male costume in Europe.
</Question>
<Choice>1820</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first animal welfare society, the Society for the Prevention of Cruelty to Animals, is founded in England.
</Question>
<Choice>1824</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Stockton & Darlington Railway begins carrying passengers as well as freight. Henceforth, most transportation will rely on mechanical rather than animal power.
</Question>
<Choice>1825</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English chemist John Walker invents a match that will light by friction.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1827</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first William H. McGuffey reader is published. The six-volume set becomes one of the most popular and influential reader textbook series of all time.
</Question>
<Choice>1836</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German educator Friedrich Froebel opens a school for young children in Prussia that he calls a "kindergarten."
</Question>
<Choice>1837</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Abner Doubleday of Cooperstown, N.Y., invents-or will receive credit for inventing-the game of baseball, which will become known as the American national pastime.
</Question>
<Choice>1839</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
England issues the first postage stamps, which require the sender to prepay the delivery fee rather than collecting it from the recipient.
</Question>
<Choice>1840</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Stiff crinoline petticoats and tight-laced corsets set the ideal for the woman's fashionable figure. The style persists for the next 40 years.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1840</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first printed Christmas cards go on sale in London; the greeting includes wishes for "a Happy New Year." Many Christmas traditions have their origins in Victorian England.
</Question>
<Choice>1843</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American Elias Howe patents the sewing machine, a device that eliminates much tedious work for the housewife.
</Question>
<Choice>1846</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The balloon-frame house becomes popular. Requiring relatively little wood and labour, it is hugely popular in the 19th-century American Midwest and West.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1848</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In an effort to give women freedom of movement, Amelia Jenks Bloomer invents a "rational dress," which includes a jacket, skirt, and the now-famous bloomers.
</Question>
<Choice>1850</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Levi Strauss begins selling dry goods to California miners and develops denim jeans for them.
</Question>
<Choice>1850</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German furniture maker Michael Thonet and his sons set up a corporation for the manufacture of bentwood chairs.
</Question>
<Choice>1853</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The screwdriver comes into popular use after advances in precision machining make the manufacture of screws easier.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1855</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
William Perkin receives a patent for the aniline dye, the first important synthetic dye used in clothing and consumer goods.
</Question>
<Choice>1856</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
New York City's Haughwout Department Store introduces the first passenger elevator. Using steam power, it climbs five stories in less than a minute.
</Question>
<Choice>1857</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Charles Frederick Worth, a Briton, opens the first great couture house in Paris.
</Question>
<Choice>1858</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The term "monkey wrench" comes into use to describe a popular type of adjustable wrench invented by Charles Moncky.
</Question>
<Choice>1858</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American inventor Joseph Rechendorfer patents a combination pencil and eraser.
</Question>
<Choice>1858</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Great Atlantic & Pacific Tea Company, Inc., opens its first store in New York City, beginning the modern chain store merchandising concept.
</Question>
<Choice>1859</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Petroleum discovered in Pennsylvania begins to replace whale oil for illumination.
</Question>
<Choice>1859</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ebenezer Butterick develops paper patterns to be used for the home sewing of clothing.
</Question>
<Choice>1859</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Louis Pasteur discovers the principles of the process of heating foods to kill microorganisms. It is called pasteurization in his honour.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1860</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
J.H. Kellogg and C.W. Post develop processed breakfast cereal as a health food in Battle Creek, Mich.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1860</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Frenchmen Pierre Michaux and his son Ernest invent the velocipede, the first pedal-powered bicycle.
</Question>
<Choice>1861</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first subway line is opened, in London. Many other cities, including Boston and Budapest, will construct their own systems later in the century.
</Question>
<Choice>1863</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The ice-cream soda is invented in Philadelphia, the centre of ice-cream making in the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1874</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Robert Wood Johnson begins to manufacture antiseptic bandages and wound dressings; with his brother he founds the company Johnson & Johnson.
</Question>
<Choice>1874</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American inventor Thomas A. Edison demonstrates his electric light bulb.
</Question>
<Choice>1879</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Frank Woolworth founds the first of a chain of "five-and-ten"-cent variety stores; by 1904 the chain has grown to 120 stores.
</Question>
<Choice>1879</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
James A. Bonsack receives the first patent for a cigarette-making machine, paving the way for the mass-production of cigarettes and the growth of the cigarette industry.
</Question>
<Choice>1880</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Germany is the first country to institute compulsory national social insurance programs, beginning with health insurance.
</Question>
<Choice>1883</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A plan formulated by Canadian Sandford Fleming for defining 24 time zones is adopted. It creates a standard framework for worldwide timekeeping.
</Question>
<Choice>1884</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Lewis E. Waterman receives a patent for his fountain pen. The modern fountain pen takes its shape in the late 1800s, as various inventors work to improve it.
</Question>
<Choice>1884</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Belgian sheepdog is developed in the village of Groenendaal, Belg. It is the latest of a number of dogs bred to manage and protect sheep.
</Question>
<Choice>1885</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Lever brothers of Great Britain begin selling wrapped bars of soap made from animal and vegetable fats; they also pioneer aggressive marketing.
</Question>
<Choice>1885</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ottmar Mergenthaler's first Linotype machines are put into work setting the type for the New York Tribune; they soon set the standard for mechanical typesetting.
</Question>
<Choice>1886</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John S. Pemberton of Atlanta, Ga., concocts the formula for a "tonic," which is named Coca-Cola.
</Question>
<Choice>1886</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German Louis Dobermann breeds the Doberman pinscher. Dobermans become popular as guard and police dogs, largely owing to their intelligence, strength, and courage.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1887</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Golf becomes an organized sport in the United States with the opening of the St. Andrews Golf Club in Yonkers, N.Y.
</Question>
<Choice>1888</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At the Paris Exhibition fabrics made of rayon, an artificial fibre, are introduced to the public by their inventor, Hilaire Bernigaud, comte de Chardonnet.
</Question>
<Choice>1889</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American inventor Thomas A. Edison and his French counterparts, Auguste and Louis Lumière, introduce the first motion pictures.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1890</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first cafeteria is established at the YWCA in Kansas City, Mo., to provide low-cost meals for working women.
</Question>
<Choice>1891</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Coca-Cola Company is founded. By the late 20th century, its sweet, carbonated drink is one of the world's best-selling beverages and a cultural institution in the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1892</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Belgians Henry van de Velde and Victor Horta originate the Art Nouveau style, based on graceful, organic forms.
</Question>
<Choice>1893</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The prototype of a slide fastener is exhibited by Whitcomb L. Judson at the World's Columbian Exposition in Chicago; it is later renamed the zipper.
</Question>
<Choice>1893</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
New Zealand grants suffrage to women. Women win the right to vote in national elections in the United States in 1920.
</Question>
<Choice>1893</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first modern Olympic Games competitions are held in Athens; 280 men from 13 countries participate.
</Question>
<Choice>1896</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
William Randolph Hearst publishes the first weekly colour comic-strip supplement in the Morning Journal.
</Question>
<Choice>1896</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Colgate Ribbon Dental Cream, the first toothpaste in a tube, is marketed.
</Question>
<Choice>1896</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A German chemical and pharmaceutical company, which later adopts the name Bayer AG, develops aspirin and markets it as an effective analgesic.
</Question>
<Choice>1899</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hydrogenated solid shortening is developed from cottonseed oil; it replaces liquid oils or animal fats in cooking.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1900</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Photography begins its rise as a popular art, thanks largely to the efforts of George Eastman. His "Brownie" camera, the first easy-to-use amateur instrument had been introduced in 1900.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1901</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American inventor Willis Haviland Carrier develops the air conditioner to control indoor levels of temperature and humidity.
</Question>
<Choice>1902</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
King Camp Gillette begins selling the first safety razor and blade, which soon makes the straight-edge razor obsolete.
</Question>
<Choice>1903</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An ice cream vendor devises the ice cream cone at the World's Fair in St. Louis, Mo.
</Question>
<Choice>1904</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first pizzeria in the United States opens in New York City; pizza, of Neapolitan origin, soon becomes an international favourite.
</Question>
<Choice>1905</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German animal trainer Carl Hagenbeck opens a zoo in Hamburg, Ger., with barless, moated display areas that mimic natural habitats.
</Question>
<Choice>1907</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Great Britain enacts social welfare legislation including the first unemployment insurance.
</Question>
<Choice>1908</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Henry Ford's Detroit, Mich., factory begins manufacturing the Model T, the first automobile priced within the range of the middle class.
</Question>
<Choice>1908</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Leo Hendrik Baekeland invents Bakelite, the first major thermosetting plastic.
</Question>
<Choice>1908</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Max Factor devises makeup especially for the needs of actors in black-and-white motion pictures.
</Question>
<Choice>1910</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The 16th Amendment to the Constitution of the United States is ratified, enabling the federal government to levy an income tax.
</Question>
<Choice>1913</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mass production is developed at the Ford Motor plant in Dearborn, Mich. It lowers the cost of many consumer goods and profoundly affects the lives of industrial workers.
</Question>
<Choice>1913</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The trench coat is designed for British officers in World War I. Fashion designer Coco Chanel will later popularize the style for both men and women.
</Question>
<Choice>1914</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Reformer Margaret Sanger publishes The Woman Rebel. The magazine provides information about birth control in defiance of social and legal proscriptions.
</Question>
<Choice>1914</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The practical and convenient wristwatch is popularized for men. Prior to World War I, the pocket watch was the more popular style.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1918</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Weimar, Ger., Walter Gropius founds the Bauhaus school. The architecture, design, and applied arts produced there help define 20th-century culture.
</Question>
<Choice>1919</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Agatha Christie publishes her first mystery novel, The Mysterious Affair at Styles, introducing the cerebral Belgian detective Hercule Poirot.
</Question>
<Choice>1920</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The National Football League is founded in Canton, Ohio, with Jim Thorpe as its first president.
</Question>
<Choice>1920</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
KDKA, the first commercial U.S. radio station, begins broadcasting in Pittsburgh, Pa. It covers the Harding-Cox presidential election returns.
</Question>
<Choice>1920</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The suntan begins to be a sign of affluence and exotic travel, thanks to the influence of designer Coco Chanel. Formerly, sun-browned skin had been associated with outdoor labour.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1921</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Kansas City, Mo., the first unified shopping mall, Country Club Plaza, is opened by the J.C.Nichols Company.
</Question>
<Choice>1922</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Credit cards are introduced in the United States. Issued first by hotels and gas stations, the industry explodes after World War II.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1923</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Marcel Breuer, inspired by bicycle handlebars, designs an innovative chair with a tubular metal frame; the design is widely imitated.
</Question>
<Choice>1925</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Book-of-the-Month Club is founded in the United States. In addition to popularizing serious books, it invents the "negative option" form of mail order sales.
</Question>
<Choice>1926</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sound is introduced to motion pictures; The Jazz Singer, starring Al Jolson, is a hit, and the silent movie era ends.
</Question>
<Choice>1927</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Cartoonist Walt Disney introduces Mickey Mouse in the animated cartoon Steamboat Willie.
</Question>
<Choice>1928</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Clarence Birdseye begins the widespread retail sale of quick-frozen foods.
</Question>
<Choice>1929</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Michael Cullin opens the King Kullen grocery store, the first modern supermarket.
</Question>
<Choice>1930</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
"The Puddle Family" show is broadcast on radio, sponsored by Procter & Gamble; it is soon known as the first "soap opera."
</Question>
<Choice>1932</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Allen Lane founds Penguin Books, which in the next decade becomes one of the most important publishers of serious, yet popular books.
</Question>
<Choice>1935</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The U.S. Social Security Act establishes federal pensions in an effort to alleviate the effects of poverty on retired workers, dependent children, the blind, and the disabled.
</Question>
<Choice>1935</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Action Comics introduces Superman, the man of steel, written by Jerry Siegel and drawn by Joseph Shuster.
</Question>
<Choice>1938</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French chef Prosper Montagné publishes the Larousse Gastronomique, an encyclopedic documentation of the recipes and techniques of classic French cuisine.
</Question>
<Choice>1938</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scientists at du Pont invent nylon. The material becomes a widely used synthetic fabric thanks in part of its popularization during World War II.
</Question>
<Choice>1938</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first jet aircraft flight, in a plane powered by an engine designed by Hans Pabst von Ohain, takes place successfully in Germany.
</Question>
<Choice>1939</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The ball-point pen, developed by Lazlo Biro, a Hungarian living in Argentina, becomes popular in Great Britain and, soon, worldwide.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1940</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
America enters World War II. The war would popularize many new inventions and products, including margarine, nylons, Hershey Bars, and the jeep.
</Question>
<Choice>1941</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Martha Stewart is born on August 3. In 30 years she will launch a counterrevolution signaling a glorification of the domestic arts.
</Question>
<Choice>1941</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The autobahns are completed in Germany. Featuring limited access and the elimination of cross streets, they make up the first national expressway system.
</Question>
<Choice>1942</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The U.S. Congress passes the Serviceman's Readjustment Act. Better known as the G.I. Bill of Rights, it helps make college education accessible to millions of American veterans.
</Question>
<Choice>1944</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John H. Johnson founds Ebony, the first U.S. mass-market magazine aimed at a black audience.
</Question>
<Choice>1945</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Construction begins on Levittown, the archetypal mass suburban housing development, in Long Island, N.Y.
</Question>
<Choice>1946</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mobster Bugsy Siegel opens the Flamingo Hotel in Las Vegas, Nev. The desert city's boom in gambling and entertainment begins.
</Question>
<Choice>1946</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Procter & Gamble develops Tide, the first synthetic laundry detergent. In 1949, they will introduce Joy, the first synthetic liquid detergent.
</Question>
<Choice>1946</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French fashion designer Christian Dior introduces the feminine "New Look," with full skirts and tight waists, in marked contrast to practical wartime styles.
</Question>
<Choice>1947</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A daring two-piece style of women's bathing suit, the bikini, comes into fashion. It is named after a Pacific island on which atomic bomb tests are being conducted.
</Question>
<Choice>1947</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Kevin Tuohy develops the modern plastic contact lens.
</Question>
<Choice>1948</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The National Basketball Association is formed to market professional basketball.
</Question>
<Choice>1949</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French writer Simone de Beauvoir publishes The Second Sex, one of the founding texts of the mid-20th-century women's liberation movement.
</Question>
<Choice>1949</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Firm evidence points to tobacco smoking as a cause of lung cancer and other serious illnesses. Campaigns to educate consumers begin.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1950</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
First used on airplanes, seatbelts begin to be featured in automobiles.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1950</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Cattle raisers begin to routinely feed antibiotics to livestock as a preventive measure.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1952</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Colour television broadcasting is launched in the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1954</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ray Kroc opens his first McDonald's fast food restaurant, in Des Plaines, Ill.
</Question>
<Choice>1955</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Disneyland opens near Los Angeles. Walt Disney World, a second and much larger theme park, will open in Orlando, Fla., in 1971.
</Question>
<Choice>1955</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Seamstress Rosa Parks of Montgomery, Ala., is arrested for refusing to give up her bus seat to a white man. The event helps spark the Civil Rights movement.
</Question>
<Choice>1955</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Elvis Presley releases "Heartbreak Hotel." Presley helps popularize rock and roll among white audiences and is a permanent fixture of American culture even after his death in 1977.
</Question>
<Choice>1956</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Boeing 707, the first American jetliner, goes into service.
</Question>
<Choice>1958</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The U.S. Food and Drug Administration approves the development of hormone-based oral contraceptives; their availability triggers the sexual revolution of the 1960s.
</Question>
<Choice>1960</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Haloid Xerox Company markets a plain-paper photocopier, revolutionizing office practices and ringing the death knell for carbon paper.
</Question>
<Choice>1960</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>The water bed debuts.</Question>
<Choice>c. 1960</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Women adopt a combination garment, panty hose, as a replacement for the nylon stockings that had been developed in the 1940s to supplant silk stockings.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1961</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Rachel Carson's Silent Spring warns of widespread environmental damage from pollution, helping to launch an era of environmental activism.
</Question>
<Choice>1962</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
"Beatlemania" sweeps across the United States; the ensuing British invasion establishes a new kind of rock music.
</Question>
<Choice>1964</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The miniskirt, at first mid-thigh length and later even shorter, is introduced as part of the mod fashions of the 1960s.
</Question>
<Choice>1965</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Communes become popular among members of the counterculture in the U.S. and Europe. Most collapse within a few years but some survive for decades.
</Question>
<Choice>1968</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Patrons of the Stonewall Inn in New York City riot after a police raid. The event is often considered the start of the gay rights movement in the U.S.
</Question>
<Choice>1969</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Civil divorce is legalized in Italy, although it is not recognized by the dominant Roman Catholic church.
</Question>
<Choice>1970</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Boeing 747 is introduced into commercial service. The jumbo jet helps make transcontinental air travel faster, easier, and more popular.
</Question>
<Choice>1970</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The U.S. Supreme Court establishes, in Roe v. Wade, a woman's right to have an abortion, but the national debate continues.
</Question>
<Choice>1973</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Apple II, the first mass-produced practical home computer, is developed by Steven P. Jobs and Stephen G. Wozniak; the IBM PC will follow in 1981.
</Question>
<Choice>1977</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Citicorp builds a network of automated teller machines. In the 1980s, ATMs become immensely popular for conducting basic banking transactions.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1978</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Internet is established to link computer users worldwide and enable them to share all manner of data; E-mail is one primary use.
</Question>
<Choice>1983</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Microsoft Corporation releases the Windows operating system, a sequel to its popular MS-DOS; software developer Bill Gates will eventually become the richest man in the world.
</Question>
<Choice>1985</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first CD encyclopaedia is introduced. Within a decade, electronic encyclopedias become hugely popular: more CDs are given away in the 1990s than print sets are sold in the previous 200 years.
</Question>
<Choice>1985</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Oprah Winfrey Show is nationally syndicated. Winfrey's compassion and honesty attract a wide audience and the talk show becomes a leader of the genre.
</Question>
<Choice>1986</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The video game industry, only 20 years old, exceeds annual revenues of $10 billion.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1990</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sears, Roebuck and Co. ends publication of its popular mail-order catalog, "the big book," after 97 years.
</Question>
<Choice>1993</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian comedian-director Roberto Benigni's La vita è bella (1997; Life Is Beautiful), a tragicomedy set in a Nazi concentration camp, enjoys international success.
</Question>
<Choice>1998</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
As the world population passes the six billion mark, a study is issued that projects a serious crisis in 2100 if the current rate of growth is not slowed.
</Question>
<Choice>1999</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Anxiety over computer system problems associated with the rollover to the year 2000--the so-called "Y2K Bug"--emerges as unfounded in the early days of January.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American businessman Steve Case oversees the biggest merger in history as his Internet company, America Online (AOL), and Time Warner, Inc., become AOL Time Warner.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Animated movies, including Chicken Run and Toy Story 2, continue to gain in popularity and prove to be as successful with adults as with children.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Reports indicate that more people--some 27 million--are enslaved today than ever before.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The success of the second installment of the Survivor series suggests that reality-based shows will become a mainstay on American television.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
George W. Bush is sworn in as the 43rd president of the United States after defeating Al Gore in one of the country's most heated and controversial elections.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Terrorists hijack commercial airplanes and fly them into the World Trade Center in New York and the Pentagon in Washington, D.C., killing some 3,000 people. The threat of future attacks becomes a frequent concern.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Broadway musical The Producers wins a record-setting 12 Tony Awards.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The euro becomes the sole currency in 12 European countries, and such monetary units as the mark and lira cease to be legal tender.
</Question>
<Choice>2002</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Bibliotheca Alexandrina formally opens in Egypt. Costing more than $120 million, it was named in honour of the original Library of Alexandria, which was the most renowned of antiquity.
</Question>
<Choice>2002</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The U.S. stock market and investors are sent reeling following a series of corporate scandals involving accounting abuses and executive wrongdoing.
</Question>
<Choice>2002</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The U.S. Department of Homeland Security becomes fully operational. Created in response to the terrorist attacks on September 11, 2001, its primary responsibility is to protect the country from future attacks.
</Question>
<Choice>2003</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The international community officially recognizes that the campaign of repression, executions, rapes, and forced relocations in the Darfur region of The Sudan is of sufficient scale to be designated genocide.
</Question>
<Choice>2004</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hurricane Katrina devastates the U.S. Gulf Coast area, destroying much of New Orleans. The lack of preparation and inadequate initial government response draws much criticism.
</Question>
<Choice>2005</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An earthquake measuring 7.6 on the Richter scale strikes Pakistan, Afghanistan, and India, killing some 80,000 people.
</Question>
<Choice>2005</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Phantom of the Opera becomes the longest-running Broadway musical, surpassing Cats. Both musicals are the work of British composer Andrew Lloyd Webber.
</Question>
<Choice>2006</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Airport restrictions on liquids are implemented after British police uncover a terrorist plot to blow up airliners using liquid explosives.
</Question>
<Choice>2006</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first sudoku world championship is held in Lucca, Italy. An international phenomenon, the puzzle game requires players to use logic in order to fill in each cell on a 9 x 9 grid with numbers.
</Question>
<Choice>2006</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Democratic Party takes control of the U.S. Congress after more than 12 years of Republican rule. The Democratic gains are credited in part to voters' growing opposition to the Iraq War.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Kevin Rudd and the Australian Labor Party defeat John Howard and the Liberal Party in the Australian general elections, bringing to an end more than a decade of conservative government.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A subprime mortgage crisis hits the U.S. economy and quickly spreads around the world. A number of American banks and businesses receive billions of dollars from the federal government.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Terrorists attack several sites in Mumbai (Bombay), leading to the death of nearly 200 people.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Kosovo formally declares its independence, though Russia and Serbia, among others, refuse to recognize it as a country.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Beijing hosts the Summer Games; it is the first time the Olympics have been held in China.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Barack Obama is sworn in as the 44th president of the United States, becoming the first African American to hold the office.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A heat wave combines with dry conditions and strong winds to spark wildfires in Victoria, Australia, that kill some 200 people and obliterate several small towns to the northeast of Melbourne.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Twelve years after the release of his blockbuster Titanic, director James Cameron returns to feature films with Avatar; the special-effects thriller becomes the top-grossing movie of all time.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A magnitude-7.0 earthquake strikes Haiti, causing extensive damage and killing more than 150,000 people.
</Question>
<Choice>2010</Choice>
</item>
</topics>