<topics>
<item>
<Question>
First known stone-tipped spear, a weapon that makes people far more dangerous to other large mammals and probably plays a role in the numerous extinctions of the late Pleistocene Epoch.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 20,000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Approximate end of Siberian migrations across the Bering Strait and the beginning of the settlement of the Americas.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 13,000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The dog is domesticated, starting a long history of human-canine relations and setting a precedent for domestication of many other animals.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 12,000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Many large mammals in the Americas--elephants, giant sloths, lions, camels, horses--are driven extinct, probably by human hunting.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 10,000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Beginnings of agriculture and plant domestication, probably in the foothills of Turkey's Taurus Mountains. For many millennia agriculture is the greatest agent of environmental change.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 9000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Domestication of the sheep in the Middle East. Henceforth, humans increasingly control livestock and intensity of grazing. Herding is central to pastoral nomadic society.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 9000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
First known domestication of pigs, in modern-day Iraq.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 6750 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
First known irrigation, on a small scale, near Jericho in ancient Palestine. Irrigation is one of the crucial technologies for manipulating environments for human ends.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 6500 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
First agriculture in the Americas involves peppers and avocados. The first corn (maize) farming begins around 3500 BC in Mexico.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 6000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
First agriculture in the Indian subcontinent, in the Indus River valley.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 6000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
First agriculture in China, in the north. Millet becomes the major crop in early Chinese history.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 6000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
First agriculture in sub-Saharan Africa, in the Lake Chad basin.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 5000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Introduction of irrigation to the Nile River delta leads to a durable agricultural system, perhaps the only large-scale sustainable irrigation system in world history.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 5000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first mining, smelting, and metallurgy occurs in the Balkans. Metals provide more formidable tools (such as axe and sickle blades) with which to cut trees and harvest crops.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 5000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>The pigeon is domesticated in Mesopotamia.</Question>
<Choice>c. 4500 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
First domestication of the horse, probably on the steppe, north of the Black Sea. This enhances the viability of pastoral nomadism in Eurasia.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 4000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The development of corn (maize) farming in the Americas marks the beginning of fully agricultural societies in the Western Hemisphere.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 3600 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The invention of wheeled vehicles in Mesopotamia opens the door for trade and transport of bulk commodities over longer distances, encouraging timber, grain, and other trades.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 3500 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
First plows in use, in Sumer (modern-day Iraq). These radically increase the area that a given farmer could cultivate and encourage land clearance.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 3000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Domestic cats are declared sacred in Egypt. Their hunting of mice in granaries is an early example of ecological competition between animals in civilized areas.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 2500 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Agriculture begins in Japan, with attendant clearance of forests and faster population growth.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 2500 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Salt buildup in irrigated areas of Mesopotamia begins to reduce wheat yields, causing a shift to barley and abandonment of some croplands.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 2400 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The epic of Gilgamesh reveals a cavalier attitude toward forest and wildlife probably characteristic of ancient Mesopotamian civilizations.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 2000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first mechanical device for lifting water, a counterpoise-lift commonly known as shaduf, is invented. It expands the scope for irrigation by making water more easily available.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1500 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Rice paddies are established in China. This is the beginning of a durable and highly productive agro-ecosystem that, with modification, is still in use.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1500 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Iron working is introduced to India. With iron tools, the clearing of the forests of the Gangetic plain accelerates and cultivation expands.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1200 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In China, the empress Tanki establishes one of the first known zoological gardens. For thousands of years royalty around the world would found zoos, botanical gardens, and game reserves.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1150 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Land clearing and agricultural expansion appear to accelerate in the Great Lakes region of Africa after the introduction of iron smelting in sub-Saharan Africa.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 810 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Arabian camel is domesticated in the Middle East. A hardy traveler and valuable source of wool and meat, it is later adopted by traders and nomads in North Africa, Central Asia, and India.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 800 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A Chinese book offers the earliest-known documentation of fish farming. Later known as aquaculture, it is one of the fastest-growing sectors in world food production by the end of the 20th century.
</Question>
<Choice>460 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Malaria becomes endemic in ancient Greece, reducing the prosperity of affected lowlands. The disease had been described by Hippocrates in the 400s.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 350 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Appius Claudius tries to drain the Pontine Marshes near Rome, the first of six major attempts in the Roman era.
</Question>
<Choice>312 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Appius Claudius builds the first major aqueduct serving Rome. The completed system supplies more water than the Tiber River and provides Rome with cleaner water than most cities before 1850 AD.
</Question>
<Choice>312 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek naturalist Theophrastus, a student of Aristotle, writes Inquiry into Plants, the most ecologically astute treatise of the ancient Greek world.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 300 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In northern India, Mauryan emperor Ashoka, a recent convert to Buddhism, issues edicts on nature conservation. These are inspired in part by his new religious beliefs.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 250 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Cast-iron mouldboard plow comes into wide use in China, improving efficiency of plowing and encouraging land clearing for agriculture.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 200 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Smelting of metals comes to Japan, intensifying fuelwood demand and accelerating forest clearance.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 200 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Silk Road opens linking China, India, the Middle East, and Europe. It increases overland trade and leads to several biotic exchanges across Asia.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 200 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The peach is introduced into the Mediterranean world from China.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 150 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman lead smelting leads to a sharp increase in ambient air pollution. Roman lead levels are still detectable in Greenland's glaciers and provide evidence of ancient environmental conditions.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 150 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Invention of the horse collar in China allows efficient use of horses for pulling heavy loads, such as plows, and increases the area that a farmer can till.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 100 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman general Lucullus introduces the cherry from Asia Minor to Italy. The Romans, like many conquerors, experiment with plant introductions throughout their empire.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 79 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman poet Lucretius writes De rerum natura. While devoted mainly to Epicurus's atomic theory of matter, this long poem voices the pessimistic view that humankind is degrading nature.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 55 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Lions are driven extinct in ancient Greece. Wildlife depletion and extinctions are routine in the ancient Mediterranean.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 50 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman mints use 50 tons of silver per year to make coins. Supplying the mints requires mining of five million tons of rock and ore annually.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 50 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pliny the Elder publishes his Natural History. This encyclopedic survey of the natural world is a major reference work in the Western world until the Renaissance.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 75</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
To celebrate Trajan's conquest of Dacia, 11,000 captured wild animals are slaughtered in Rome. Romans delight in hunting, blood sport, and slaughter of animals.
</Question>
<Choice>107</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Beginning of 15 years of epidemic in the Roman world. The plague, brought from Mesopotamia by Roman soldiers, is perhaps smallpox and reduces Mediterranean populations by about a quarter.
</Question>
<Choice>165</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman road network reaches 53,000 miles of major highways and many more miles of smaller roads. The roads mark the land for centuries to come and unite inland ecosystems as never before.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 200</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A second round of epidemic ravages the Roman world until 266. The Mediterranean world takes several centuries to recover from the effects of new diseases in circulation after 165.
</Question>
<Choice>251</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Neoplatonist philosopher Plotinus develops the concept of the Great Chain of Being. Elaborated over the centuries, it has a significant impact on biological thought in the West.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 260</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The plagues of Justinian begin. For a quarter century the Mediterranean world suffers from an epidemic, perhaps bubonic plague, that spreads from Egypt and kills up to half the population.
</Question>
<Choice>541</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Windmills come into use in Iran. These extend the possibilities of irrigation by allowing farmers to tap deeper groundwater.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 600</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The newly-opened Grand Canal links China's north and south in a single economy. Expansion of southern rice farming follows, as farmers are now able to transport their crops more quickly and reliably.
</Question>
<Choice>610</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The horse collar reaches Europe from the East. By allowing for more efficient use of horsepower, the collar contributes to a surge of deforestation and land clearing north of the Alps.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 800</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Japanese emperor issues regulations on peasant woodcutting to protect farmland. The order shows an understanding of vegetation, soil, and hydrologic dynamics.
</Question>
<Choice>821</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polynesians arrive in New Zealand, beginning human settlement of the world's last sizeable unoccupied landmass.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A surge of metallurgical production in Sung China drives a wave of deforestation and atmospheric pollution. The latter is still detectable in samples of Greenland's glaciers.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1100</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Arab geographer ash-Sharif al-Idrisi issues the first of many warnings that the Sahara desert is advancing southward. He is right: eight centuries of higher rainfall ends around 1100 in West Africa.
</Question>
<Choice>1154</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Francis of Assisi founds the Franciscan order, which preaches the importance of humans' kinship with nature. According to legend, Francis himself delivered sermons to animals.
</Question>
<Choice>1209</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Castile, King Alfonso X charters the sheep owners association (the Mesta) and delineates land use rights of pastoralists and farmers.
</Question>
<Choice>1273</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
First commission of inquiry into levels of smoke in the city of London. Coal burning would be banned (ineffectively) in 1307.
</Question>
<Choice>1287</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Start of the Black Death. Reaching from India to Iceland, it reduces population in Asia and Europe by a quarter or a third. It is the last time global population declines.
</Question>
<Choice>1346</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Dutch use windmills to accelerate the drainage and reclamation of the Netherlands. Over the centuries they create the world's largest reclaimed landscape.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1400</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nahua kings of Chapultepec (Mexico) create nature reserves for their own enjoyment. A zoo exists on the site today.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1430</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Portuguese open the Atlantic slave trade. For more than four centuries this trade foments exchange of plants, animals, and diseases between Africa, Europe, and the Americas.
</Question>
<Choice>1441</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
King Nezahualcóyotl of Texcoco (Mexico) enacts strict forest preservation laws. This is an attempt to slow the progressive deforestation of Central Mexico in the 15th century.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1450</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Christopher Columbus's first transatlantic voyage between Europe and the Americas inaugurates a vast biological exchange of animals, plants, and diseases between Afro-Eurasia and the New World.
</Question>
<Choice>1492</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Syphilis makes its first known appearance in Europe in the aftermath of a French invasion of Italy. It is referred to as the "French disease" or "Italian disease."
</Question>
<Choice>1495</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
King Ferdinand and Queen Isabella enact the first forest conservation law in Spain.
</Question>
<Choice>1496</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Extinction of the moa, a giant flightless bird of New Zealand, after about 500 years of pressure from Maori hunters.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1500</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Corn (maize) is established in the Mediterranean world. It is the first important crop from the Americas to succeed in Afro-Eurasia and becomes a staple in many parts of the Old World.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1520</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Galapagos Islands are discovered. Their unusual flora and fauna are of special interest to naturalists and contribute to Charles Darwin's studies on natural selection.
</Question>
<Choice>1535</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first sugar boom in the Americas begins in Brazil. It stimulates forest clearance and fuelwood cutting, while an expanding slave trade promotes biological and human exchange with Africa.
</Question>
<Choice>1540</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first modern botanical garden opens at the University of Pisa, Italy. Previously maintained for pleasure or for growing medicinal plants, they have evolved into centres for conservation and research.
</Question>
<Choice>1543</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Discovery of the silver mountain of Potosí (Bolivia) leads to mercury pollution from silver processing and deforestation of surrounding country for fuelwood and cultivation of land to feed miners.
</Question>
<Choice>1545</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Escaped Spanish horses reestablish wild horse populations in North America. They quickly change the way of life of Plains Indians, who adopt the horse for transport and hunting.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1550</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss naturalist Conrad Gesner publishes the first volume of his Historiae animalium, a massive survey of all recorded information on animal life.
</Question>
<Choice>1551</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Philip II of Spain declares forests, pastures, and waters of New Spain (Mexico) common property but tries to restrict shifting cultivation, a traditional agricultural technique of the local population.
</Question>
<Choice>1559</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A century of accelerated deforestation begins in Japan, leaving the islands south of Hokkaido substantially denuded. Population growth and vast construction projects drive this forest clearance.
</Question>
<Choice>1570</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish establishment of Manila and the Manila galleons inaugurates a biological exchange between Mexico and the Philippines.
</Question>
<Choice>1571</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Portuguese merchants establish a trading post at Luanda (Angola). A centre of the slave trade, the post facilitates exchange of diseases, plants, and animals between Africa and South America.
</Question>
<Choice>1576</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Corn (maize) reaches Kongo (west-central Africa) from the Americas. Its arrival and cultivation dramatically improve the food supply.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1580</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Cassava reaches Kongo from the Americas. It spreads rapidly in equatorial Africa and becomes the staple crop in many societies.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1610</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Francis Bacon publishes Novum Organum, one of his several works advocating systematic use of natural philosophy to further human dominion over nature.
</Question>
<Choice>1620</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The last known aurochs (an ancestor to modern cattle) dies in Poland. Their demise is one of only a handful of modern mammalian extinctions.
</Question>
<Choice>1627</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first anticruelty law is enacted by the Massachusetts Bay Colony. Puritans in England likewise condemn cruelty toward animals in the same period.
</Question>
<Choice>1641</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Yellow fever, imported from West Africa probably via the slave trade, is firmly established in the Americas. The disease increases demand for West African slaves, who are resistant to the disease.
</Question>
<Choice>1647</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The population of the Americas bottoms out after its collapse in the wake of Columbus. Accordingly, forest cover of the Americas reaches its modern maximum.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1650</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch settlers establish a permanent European colony at the Cape of Good Hope. They bring new crops, plants, animals, and diseases to southern Africa.
</Question>
<Choice>1652</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John Evelyn publishes Fumifugium, a ponderous polemic against urban smoke. London and other coal-burning cities suffer from serious air pollution.
</Question>
<Choice>1661</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Japan, new forest management regulations are promulgated in response to timber shortages and soil erosion problems. Japan evolves a comprehensive forest protection policy in the coming decades.
</Question>
<Choice>1666</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
First sighted in about 1507, the dodo, a flightless bird of Mauritius, becomes extinct.
</Question>
<Choice>1681</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first small steam engine is built by Thomas Savery, presaging increased coal use by industry.
</Question>
<Choice>1698</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Newcomen steam engine is installed in a coal mine. It is used especially for pumping water out of coal mines, which allows deeper mining and increased coal production.
</Question>
<Choice>1712</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the first modern zoological gardens in Europe, the Schönbrunn Tiergarten (Imperial Menagerie), opens on the grounds of Schloss Schönbrunn, in Vienna.
</Question>
<Choice>1752</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
James Watt patents a more efficient steam engine, one of the key components of the industrial revolution and the fossil fuel age.
</Question>
<Choice>1769</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Anglo-Irish settlement of Australia begins, which involves the introduction of numerous new plants and animals and some extinctions of indigenous flora and fauna.
</Question>
<Choice>1788</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Gilbert White publishes The Natural History and Antiquities of Selborne, a classic of nature writing and inspiration to amateur naturalists in Europe and America.
</Question>
<Choice>1789</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Thomas R. Malthus publishes An Essay on the Principle of Population. The work inaugurates systematic discussion of the consequences of population growth.
</Question>
<Choice>1798</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Spanish parliament announces its plan to convert almost all common-property forests in Spain and Spanish America to private property. Deforestation accelerates as a result.
</Question>
<Choice>1813</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A decades-long cholera pandemic begins with transmission from endemic centres in Indonesia to China. In 1832 cholera attacks Egypt, Europe, and America, and it reappears in 1842 and 1848.
</Question>
<Choice>1819</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>World population reaches one billion.</Question>
<Choice>c. 1820</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The world's first railway, the Stockton & Darlington, opens in England. Railroads allow cheaper transport of bulk goods and animates resource frontiers around the world.
</Question>
<Choice>1825</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John James Audubon begins publishing his four-volume book, The Birds of America. A conservation society is later established in his name for the protection of birds and other animals.
</Question>
<Choice>1827</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The London Zoo opens in Regent's Park. It grows to become one of the largest and best-equipped zoos in the world and a centre for conservation and scientific research.
</Question>
<Choice>1828</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Japan, forest policy and plantation forestry achieve sustained wood yields, stabilizing the country's forest area. This feat is all the more remarkable because of Japan's high population density.
</Question>
<Choice>1830</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The last major bubonic plague epidemic in the West strikes Egypt. Plague remains endemic within certain rat populations in America and Eurasia but has not affected humans.
</Question>
<Choice>1835</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Systematic British settlement of New Zealand begins, leading to the decline of the Maori population and introduction of numerous alien species of flora and fauna to the islands.
</Question>
<Choice>1840</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Royal Botanic Gardens open in Kew, near London. Formerly part of a royal park, the gardens become the British Empire's centre for botanical research, acclimatization, and economic botany.
</Question>
<Choice>1841</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John B. Lawes opens a superphosphate factory in Hertfordshire, Eng., inaugurating the era of chemical fertilizers in world agriculture.
</Question>
<Choice>1842</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A new breed of wheat called Red Fife, imported from Russia via Scotland, opens colder parts of Ontario and the Canadian Prairie Provinces to agricultural settlement.
</Question>
<Choice>1842</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The great auk, a flightless seabird that sailors find a useful source of food, is driven extinct in its home in Iceland.
</Question>
<Choice>1844</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Beginning of the Irish Potato Famine, the last great famine in the Western world. It kills more than one million of Ireland's eight million people and forces many others to emigrate.
</Question>
<Choice>1845</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Whaling boom in the Pacific depletes populations of sperm and right whales.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1845</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first major sheep runs open on New Zealand's South Island, causing major changes in vegetation and land use.
</Question>
<Choice>1846</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Great Britain becomes the first sizeable country in the world in which more than half of the population lives in cities.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1850</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
World's total use of inanimate energy surpasses one billion megawatts for the first time. The main source is coal used in steam engines.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1850</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Henry David Thoreau publishes Walden. His influential reflections on man and nature, which help spur the conservation movement, draw on Romantic philosophy and New England transcendentalism.
</Question>
<Choice>1854</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Successful hard-rock drilling for oil in Titusville, Pa., inaugurates the age of intensive oil use in world history.
</Question>
<Choice>1859</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Charles Darwin's On the Origin of Species proposes the theory of evolution by natural selection and posits links between humans and lower animals.
</Question>
<Choice>1859</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Thomas Austin introduces English rabbits to Australia. In the absence of disease and predators, the rabbit population grows to half a billion within a century.
</Question>
<Choice>1859</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Cinchona, a South American plant that produces the antimalarial quinine, is cultivated in India and the Dutch East Indies. Cinchona seeds had been smuggled out of Peru by European botanists in the 1850s.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1860</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Increased global demand for coffee leads to the clearing of large parts of the Brazilian Atlantic forest. The growth of railroad lines allows planters to move deeper into the forest than they could previously.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1860</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
George Perkins Marsh publishes Man and Nature. This classic of conservation thinking laments the damage perpetrated by human action in the Mediterranean world and the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1864</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Great Britain, river pollution reaches such proportions that a Royal Commission is appointed to look into the matter. Part of its report is written with River Calder water instead of ink.
</Question>
<Choice>1865</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German philosopher-zoologist Ernst Haeckel coins the word "ecology" to mean the science of the relations between living things and their external world.
</Question>
<Choice>1866</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Australia legislates the protection of a natural wonder, the Jenolan Caves near Sydney, N.S.W.
</Question>
<Choice>1866</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
First use of refrigerated railway cars allows long-distance transport of perishables such as meat and dairy. They also permit expanded ranching and pastoralism in the U.S., Canada, and Argentina.
</Question>
<Choice>1867</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The completion of the Suez Canal allows the aquatic biota of the Red Sea to infiltrate the Mediterranean Sea, linking biogeographic provinces that had been separate for millions of years.
</Question>
<Choice>1869</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first national park, Yellowstone, is established in the United States. Its opening reflects the growing power of preservationist thinking and is soon followed by parks around the world.
</Question>
<Choice>1872</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nikolaus A. Otto invents the four-stroke internal-combustion engine, leading to automobiles, trucks, tractors, and subsequent revolutions in land use, air pollution, and much more.
</Question>
<Choice>1876</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Indian Forest Act appropriates 100,000 square miles of forest to the state in the British colony of India in the name of conservation.
</Question>
<Choice>1878</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
First major use of refrigerated ships encourages ranching in regions remote from big markets such as New Zealand, Australia, and Argentina.
</Question>
<Choice>1882</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indonesia's Krakatoa has one of the most catastrophic eruptions in history. Explosions are heard 2,200 miles (3,541 km) away and spewing ash reaches heights of 50 miles (80 km).
</Question>
<Choice>1883</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Karl Benz builds the first practical automobile.</Question>
<Choice>1885</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Canada creates its first national park at Banff, Alta.
</Question>
<Choice>1885</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Rinderpest, a lethal cattle disease, breaks out in Ethiopia and spreads throughout East and southern Africa. By 1900 it kills up to 95 percent of cattle and devastates pastoral societies.
</Question>
<Choice>1888</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Sudbury, Ont., a nickel-smelting complex opens. It is destined to be one of the greatest single sources of air pollution and acid rain in North America.
</Question>
<Choice>1888</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The boll weevil, a cotton pest, enters the U.S. from Mexico and becomes the scourge of cotton planters in the South.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1890</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American bison, some 50 million strong in 1865, are reduced to less than one million by demand for meat and hides and the U.S. Army's strategy to destroy the "Indians' commissary."
</Question>
<Choice>1890</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
First mass-produced gasoline tractors (in the U.S.) signal the beginning of fossil fuel agriculture and the declining importance of animal power on farms in the Western world.
</Question>
<Choice>1892</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John Muir and associates found the Sierra Club, the most powerful and influential American conservation organization for most of the 20th century.
</Question>
<Choice>1892</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Offshore oil-drilling is pioneered in Californian waters. Subsequent undersea drilling in the North Sea, Gulf of Mexico, and elsewhere proves a major oil pollution source.
</Question>
<Choice>1894</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The world's last bubonic plague pandemic, originating in China, strikes the ports of Canton and Hong Kong, from which it spreads to India in 1898.
</Question>
<Choice>1894</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Britain the National Trust is founded to safeguard cultural and natural heritage against destruction.
</Question>
<Choice>1895</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish scientist Svante Arrhenius describes the physics of the atmosphere's greenhouse effect, whereby solar energy is trapped on Earth. He also predicts global warming.
</Question>
<Choice>1896</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At the Ashio Copper Mine in central Japan, air and water pollution motivate a series of peasant protests, including marches on Tokyo.
</Question>
<Choice>1897</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the Transvaal republic (South Africa), President Paul Kruger creates the first game reserve in response to anxieties about wildlife depletion. It later becomes Kruger National Park.
</Question>
<Choice>1898</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A major sleeping sickness epidemic in East Africa begins. Colonial disruptions of land use practices bring on devastating epidemics and famines in Central and East Africa about 1880-1920.
</Question>
<Choice>1900</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chicago authorities reverse the flow of the Chicago River, sending the untreated sewage of Chicago away from the city's water supply (Lake Michigan) and to the Mississippi River instead.
</Question>
<Choice>1900</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The pioneering work of plant genetics done in the 1860s by monk Gregor Mendel is rediscovered and disseminated. This opens the way for systematic plant breeding and more bountiful harvests.
</Question>
<Choice>1900</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Urban use of horses peaks. In London about a million tons of horse manure are removed from the city streets yearly.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1900</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Australia the debut of "Federation wheat," a new drought-resistant breed developed by agricultural researcher William Farrer, propels the wheat frontier onto Australia's interior plains.
</Question>
<Choice>1901</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The U.S.'s Reclamation Act establishes the bureaucracy (Bureau of Reclamation) that oversees federal dam building and irrigation in the West.
</Question>
<Choice>1902</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Trans-Siberian Railroad opens up a major resource frontier and encourages timber, mining, and other extractive industries in Siberia.
</Question>
<Choice>1904</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The world's first geothermal electricity generation plant opens in Lardarello, Italy.
</Question>
<Choice>1904</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Norwegians pioneer the exploitation of whales in Antarctic waters, the world's richest whaling grounds, bringing most species to the edge of extinction within decades.
</Question>
<Choice>1904</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The word smog, an amalgam of smoke and fog, is coined in England. It achieves wide currency only with the photochemical smogs of motorized cities after 1950.
</Question>
<Choice>1905</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Leo Baekeland invents Bakelite, the first major thermosetting plastic. Plastics relieve pressure on forests, but plastic debris proves a durable variety of pollution.
</Question>
<Choice>1908</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
First international meeting of nature protection societies takes place in Paris, involving only European countries.
</Question>
<Choice>1909</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ford Motor Company pioneers assembly line production, leading to cheaper cars and the motorization of the U.S. and eventually much of the world.
</Question>
<Choice>1913</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Haber-Bosch ammonia synthesis inaugurates era of artificial nitrogen fertilizers, improving crop yields.
</Question>
<Choice>1913</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The North American passenger pigeon is driven extinct. Once numbering about five billion, the species is destroyed by commercial hunting after 1865.
</Question>
<Choice>1914</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
President Venustiano Carranza creates the first national park in Mexico, Desert of the Lions. In the late 1930s, some 40 more parks would open in Mexico.
</Question>
<Choice>1917</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Worldwide influenza pandemic kills perhaps 30 million people. Troop movements associated with World War I and subsequent demobilizations spread the disease to every continent.
</Question>
<Choice>1918</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Soldier settlement schemes to reward war veterans are established in Canada, Australia, and New Zealand. Hundreds of thousands take up farming, often on marginal lands, which are soon abandoned.
</Question>
<Choice>1918</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The U.S. becomes a predominantly urban nation, as more than half of the population lives in cities.
</Question>
<Choice>1920</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The consolidation of colonial rule in Africa brings secular population growth through disease reduction and substitution of food crops by export crops like rubber, tobacco, palm oil, and cotton.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1920</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Thomas Midgley, Jr., recommends the use of tetraethyl lead in gasoline to permit higher compression engines. Automobile exhausts begin to disperse lead into the atmosphere and biosphere.
</Question>
<Choice>1921</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Alexander Fleming discovers antibiotic properties of mold, leading to the production of penicillin and other antibiotics, which improve longevity and boost population growth.
</Question>
<Choice>1928</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Thomas Midgley, Jr., invents chlorofluorocarbons, useful as refrigerants but eventually discovered to damage Earth's stratospheric ozone layer.
</Question>
<Choice>1929</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Stalin's First Five-Year Plan collectivizes agriculture and industrializes the Soviet Union. Industrialization leads to intense air and water pollution and massive famine in the 1930s.
</Question>
<Choice>1929</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Airplane-assisted migration of the West African mosquito (Anopheles gambiae) to Brazil touches off the largest malaria epidemic in Brazilian history.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1930</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>World's population surpasses two billion.</Question>
<Choice>c. 1930</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The numbers of tractors in use in the U.S. surpasses one million. By 1950 it would reach four million, and the farm horse would be obsolete in America.
</Question>
<Choice>1930</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Tennessee Valley Authority (TVA) is established by the U.S. Congress and begins an enormous program of building dams, hydroelectric generating stations, and flood-control projects.
</Question>
<Choice>1933</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Darkest hour of the American Dust Bowl--in which drought and unwise cultivation lead to massive topsoil erosion--reduces farmers to penury.
</Question>
<Choice>1934</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The nickel-smelting complex at Norilsk, in northwest Siberia, opens. The world's single largest source of atmospheric sulphur dioxide, it emits more of the pollutant in the 1980s than all of Italy.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1937</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss chemist Paul Müller discovers DDT's properties as an insecticide. Initially successful against most insects, DDT also damages birds, amphibians, and other animals and by 1970 would be widely restricted.
</Question>
<Choice>1939</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Cereal yields begin a sharp upward climb in Europe, North America, Australia, and Argentina under the impact of chemical fertilizers and mechanization.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1940</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
St. Louis, Mo., pioneers the first comprehensive smoke reduction program in any industrial city, generally sharply reducing smoke, soot, and air pollution.
</Question>
<Choice>1940</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Enrico Fermi oversees the first sustained nuclear chain reaction (in a squash court at the University of Chicago). This leads directly to atomic bombs and the development of civilian nuclear energy.
</Question>
<Choice>1942</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Penicillin-resistant bacteria is detected in London hospitals. Henceforth, pathogens and medical research are locked in a race between human ingenuity and microbial evolution.
</Question>
<Choice>1946</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Al-Ghawar, the world's largest oilfield, is discovered. Middle East oil strikes lower energy prices and drive a great burst of energy intensification in the Western world.
</Question>
<Choice>1948</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Posthumous publication of Aldo Leopold's A Sand County Almanac, the most influential American conservation and ecological book of the first half of the 20th century.
</Question>
<Choice>1949</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
World's total use of inanimate energy surpasses 20 billion megawatts for the first time, reflecting the rapid expansion of fossil fuel use.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1950</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Australian authorities intentionally introduce a Brazilian rabbit disease, myxomatosis, in an effort to control the rabbit population. It works.
</Question>
<Choice>1951</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An acute smog episode in London kills about 4,000 people and serves to mobilize popular and political efforts against urban air pollution.
</Question>
<Choice>1952</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Soviet "Virgin Lands" program begins in an effort to plow up 115 million acres of steppe in Russia and Kazakhstan, the last major conversion of grassland to arable in world history.
</Question>
<Choice>1954</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
World's total motor vehicle population surpasses 100 million.
</Question>
<Choice>1955</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Calder Hall, Eng., the world's first commercial nuclear power plant opens. Optimists imagine electric power would soon be "too cheap to meter."
</Question>
<Choice>1956</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Britain the Clean Air Act, a response to the London smog of 1952, regulates coal smoke. Oil and gas soon replace coal as the domestic fuel of choice, improving British urban air quality.
</Question>
<Choice>1956</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The U.S. begins construction of its interstate highway system, ending the ascendancy of railroads and reorganizing American landscapes.
</Question>
<Choice>1956</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Soviet military nuclear accident at Kyshtym in the Ural Mountains. Seventy to eighty tons of radioactive material escape and 11,000 people are evacuated--an official secret until 1989.
</Question>
<Choice>1957</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Monitoring of the atmosphere's carbon dioxide content begins and quickly reveals that CO2 levels are rising as a result of fossil fuel burning and deforestation.
</Question>
<Choice>1957</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Fishermen in the Japanese village of Minamata attack the Chisso factory, which so polluted the local bay with methyl mercury as to ruin fisheries and cause severe neurological damage and several deaths among the local population.
</Question>
<Choice>1959</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>World's population reaches three billion.</Question>
<Choice>c. 1960</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Proportion of human population living in urban as opposed to rural areas surpasses one-quarter.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1960</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The number of tractors in Germany surpasses the number of farm horses, signaling the triumph of fossil fuel based agriculture in western Europe (two or three decades behind the U.S.).
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1960</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Irrigation projects in Soviet Central Asia divert water from the Aral Sea, which soon begins to shrink in size.
</Question>
<Choice>1960</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Brasília-Belém highway, a section of the Transamazonian highway, opens Amazonia to rapid colonization and inaugurates an era of quick deforestation in the world's largest rainforest.
</Question>
<Choice>1960</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The World Wildlife Fund is established in London, partly in response to reports of dwindling wildlife populations in East Africa.
</Question>
<Choice>1961</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Rachel Carson's Silent Spring, an exposé of the biological costs of chemical pesticides in wide use in the U.S., is published and helps foment a new environmental consciousness.
</Question>
<Choice>1962</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Oil surpasses coal as a proportion of total world energy production.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1962</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Using recent technological advances, Peru exploits its coastal anchoveta and mackerel fisheries to become the world's leading fishing country.
</Question>
<Choice>1963</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Soviet scientists and intellectuals begin speaking out against pollution of Lake Baikal, a unique ecosystem imperiled by wastes.
</Question>
<Choice>1963</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Green Revolution's package of new crop breeds and fertilizers (and often irrigation and farm equipment) sharply increases yields of rice, wheat, and corn (maize) around the world but reduces the variety of cultigens in use.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1965</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
World population growth reaches its all-time maximum at about 2.06 percent per year.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1965</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The U.S. and Mexico sign an agreement promoting U.S. industry in northern Mexico. Rapid industrialization follows and allows many U.S. firms to move polluting operations to the easier regulatory environment of Mexico.
</Question>
<Choice>1965</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Lunar Orbiter satellite transmits the first photographs of planet Earth seen as a lonely oasis in space, fueling concerns about environmental degradation.
</Question>
<Choice>1966</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
With the bloody coup and civil war that brought General Suharto to office, Indonesian forests become open for foreign concessionaires. A timber boom and widespread deforestation result.
</Question>
<Choice>1966</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Japan, asthma sufferers sue the Yokkaichi petrochemical complex for damages, one of several lawsuits that quickly changes both law and environmental quality in Japan.
</Question>
<Choice>1967</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The apogee of large-dam (taller than 50 feet) construction in the world. More dams were built in 1968 than in any year before or since.
</Question>
<Choice>1968</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Aurelio Peccei convenes what would become the Club of Rome, which publicized pessimistic visions about resource depletion and other environmental concerns. The Limits to Growth (1972) summarizes this position.
</Question>
<Choice>1968</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Apollo spacecraft lands on the barren and lifeless Moon, an event seen on television by millions. It emphasizes Earth's unique suitability for life.
</Question>
<Choice>1969</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hundreds of thousands of Americans--perhaps millions--participate in Earth Day demonstrations and teach-ins, one of the largest demonstrations in American history.
</Question>
<Choice>1970</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The U.S. establishes the Environmental Protection Agency, charged to administer federal laws related to the environment. It soon becomes the largest regulatory agency in the country.
</Question>
<Choice>1970</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Completion of the Aswan High Dam on the Nile River in Egypt helps to protect Egypt from floods and stores water for use in droughts but ends a 5,000-year old fully sustainable irrigation agriculture system.
</Question>
<Choice>1970</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greenpeace is founded in Vancouver, B.C., in response to nuclear testing in the Pacific. It soon becomes the largest direct action environmental group with branches in dozens of countries.
</Question>
<Choice>1971</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Peru's anchoveta and mackerel fishery collapses under the impact of overfishing and the century's largest El Niño event to date.
</Question>
<Choice>1972</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
United Nations conference on the environment is held in Stockholm. This is the first general international environment conference and leads to the UN Environment Programme, which is mainly concerned with pollution issues.
</Question>
<Choice>1972</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
OPEC oil embargo raises world energy prices for the first time since 1945, causing brief economic dislocation but spurring energy conservation technology and ideology.
</Question>
<Choice>1973</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Beginning of the Chipko Movement in India, a popular resistance movement to logging in northern India. Chipko becomes one of the major environmental movements in the less-developed world.
</Question>
<Choice>1973</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Convention on International Trade of Endangered Species of Wild Fauna and Flora (CITES), which is designed to reduce economic incentives to destroy threatened wildlife, is signed.
</Question>
<Choice>1973</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The new Endangered Species Act requires that the U.S. government must protect all wildlife threatened with extinction.
</Question>
<Choice>1973</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mario Molina and F. Sherwood Rowland publish their work outlining the potential consequences of CFCs on the stratospheric ozone layer.
</Question>
<Choice>1974</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>World's population surpasses four billion.</Question>
<Choice>c. 1975</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Eighteen nations adopt the Mediterranean Action Plan, an agreement designed to limit pollution of the Mediterranean Sea.
</Question>
<Choice>1975</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Eradication of smallpox, a long-time scourge of human populations, is the first recorded deliberate species extinction and is sponsored by the World Health Organization.
</Question>
<Choice>1977</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The National Council of Women of Kenya organizes the Green Belt Movement, which is dedicated to afforestation and planting and led by anatomy professor Wangari Maathai.
</Question>
<Choice>1977</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At Love Canal near Niagara Falls, N.Y., officials announce that hazardous chemicals dumped over previous decades are a health hazard to residents. Toxic waste becomes a hot political issue.
</Question>
<Choice>1978</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The oil tanker Amoco Cadiz spills its contents on the coasts of Brittany, in the Atlantic Ocean, covering about 180 miles of shoreline in oil.
</Question>
<Choice>1978</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
China promulgates its one-child policy in an effort to slow population growth. The Chinese population approaches one billion.
</Question>
<Choice>1979</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
China passes its first environmental protection law. Many more follow, but enforcement remains lax; China's urban air and water quality are quickly worsening.
</Question>
<Choice>1979</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The partial meltdown of an atomic reactor at Three Mile Island in Pennsylvania shatters the prestige of the nuclear energy industry in the U.S.
</Question>
<Choice>1979</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A major rise in oil prices by OPEC member states further boosts the momentum toward energy efficiency.
</Question>
<Choice>1979</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Darién National Park is established in Panama. Acting as a barrier between Central and South America, it is home to diverse wildlife and also halts the northern spread of certain infectious diseases.
</Question>
<Choice>1980</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mount Saint Helens in Washington, U.S., erupts in one of the greatest volcanic explosions ever recorded in North America. Thousands of animals are killed and 10 million trees are blown down.
</Question>
<Choice>1980</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Kenya establishes a Department of the Environment to coordinate, administer, and enforce environmental policy. By this date, scores of countries have departments or ministries of the environment.
</Question>
<Choice>1980</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Work begins on the Great Man-Made River (GMR) in Libya. One of the world's largest water-transmission projects, it is designed to carry fresh water from under the Sahara to the Libyan coast.
</Question>
<Choice>1983</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Green Party enters the West German parliament with 27 members. It is the first new party in the Bundestag (Federal Diet) in three decades.
</Question>
<Choice>1983</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At Bhopal, India, a leak at a Union Carbide chemical plant kills several thousand people.
</Question>
<Choice>1984</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The zebra mussel arrives in the North American Great Lakes, probably from the U.S.S.R. It reproduces prolifically, clogging water intakes of factories and city water systems.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1985</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Oil cartel ceases to control crude oil prices and world energy prices fall, reducing the pressure for energy conservation.
</Question>
<Choice>1985</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
World's total motor vehicle population surpasses 500 million.
</Question>
<Choice>1985</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British scientists detect sharp seasonal reductions in the Earth's stratospheric ozone layer, which protects life from harmful ultraviolet radiation.
</Question>
<Choice>1985</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An accident in one of the atomic reactors at Chernobyl in the Soviet Ukraine leads to the worst disaster in civilian nuclear power.
</Question>
<Choice>1986</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
International moratorium on whaling is implemented. The agreement reduces hunting pressure on whales, permitting some recovery in populations of most species.
</Question>
<Choice>1986</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the Montreal protocol, 24 nations of the world agree to limit production of CFCs. Subsequent accords tighten the agreements, slowing the deterioration of stratospheric ozone.
</Question>
<Choice>1987</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A Green Party is formed in Mexico in reaction to air pollution and other forms of environmental degradation.
</Question>
<Choice>1987</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Deforestation rate in Brazil's Amazonia region peaks and attracts increased international concern.
</Question>
<Choice>1988</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The worst oil spill in U.S. history occurs in Prince William Sound after the Exxon Valdez runs aground, spilling more than 10 million gallons of crude oil and badly damaging the sound's ecosystem.
</Question>
<Choice>1989</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Society for Ecological Restoration (SER) holds its first annual conference. By the end of the 20th century the practice of healing damaged lands and waters will take on a new urgency.
</Question>
<Choice>1989</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Netherlands introduces its first National Environmental Policy Plan, the most comprehensive national environmental program in the world.
</Question>
<Choice>1989</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>World's population surpasses five billion.</Question>
<Choice>c. 1990</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
World's total use of inanimate energy surpasses 80 billion megawatts, reflecting the spread of high-energy societies beyond Europe and North America.
</Question>
<Choice>1990</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Rio de Janeiro hosts the United Nations Conference on Environment and Development (UNCED), popularly known as the Earth Summit.
</Question>
<Choice>1992</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Construction begins on the Three Gorges Dam, to be the world's largest, on the Yangtze River in China after nearly 40 years of planning and controversy.
</Question>
<Choice>1993</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The murder of two Brazilian conservationists suggests the growing political and social power, and the potential danger, of conservation movements in the Third World.
</Question>
<Choice>1993</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scientists report a 65-70 percent decrease in the ozone layer over the Faraday research base in Antarctica, further evidence of a long-term erosion of this section of the Earth's atmosphere.
</Question>
<Choice>1994</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Continued debate over global warming dominates environmental news in 1995, as climatologists announce evidence of long-term warming trends.
</Question>
<Choice>1995</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A variety of studies show that Eastern European nations are among the most polluted in the world. Eighty-two percent of Poland's forests are damaged by acid rain.
</Question>
<Choice>1995</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The World Health Organization reports that 350 Parisians die from air pollution annually. Globally, it was 10 to 100 times more dangerous to live in a city than inside a nuclear power plant.
</Question>
<Choice>1996</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Kyoto, Japan, conference on global climate change produces a treaty designed to reduce greenhouse gas emissions and slow climate change.
</Question>
<Choice>1997</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The International Year of the Reef (IYOR) is declared to heighten awareness of the threat to coral reefs.
</Question>
<Choice>1997</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Human population reaches 5.9 billion, of whom about 48 percent live in urban areas.
</Question>
<Choice>1998</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hurricane Mitch reaches Category 5 intensity, killing more than 9,000 people and rendering one million homeless in Central America.
</Question>
<Choice>1998</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Brazilian government announces that it will set aside 25 million hectares (62 million acres) of the Amazon rain forest for conservation.
</Question>
<Choice>1998</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Thailand holds its first National Elephant Day to honour the country's endangered national animal.
</Question>
<Choice>1999</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A conservation group places the Snake River atop its list of the most endangered U.S. rivers.
</Question>
<Choice>1999</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The World Conservation Union announces that a quarter of the world's coniferous tree species are under threat of extinction.
</Question>
<Choice>1999</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In an effort to protect the Amazonian forest and its wildlife, Peru doubles the size of the Bahuaja-Sonene National Park. Much of the added area had been previously marked for oil drilling.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A report suggests that the Himalayan mountains are eroding at a rapid rate.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An environmental battle over the Arctic National Wildlife Refuge in Alaska erupts as the U.S. government begins talks to consider opening the refuge for oil drilling.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Julia Carabias Lillo wins the J. Paul Getty Conservation Prize for doubling the protected-habitat system in Mexico.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The largest botanical garden in the world, the Eden Project, opens in Cornwall, England.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scientists report the discovery of a dwarf gecko, which, at 0.75 inch (1.9 cm), is the world's smallest reptile.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Floriade, an international exhibit of horticulture, is staged in The Netherlands. The event, which is held every 10 years, takes place on more than 160 acres.
</Question>
<Choice>2002</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An international report finds that the dugong, a marine mammal similar to the manatee, is in danger of extinction.
</Question>
<Choice>2002</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A study is published on the discovery of the fossilized remains of a four-winged, feathered dinosaur in China. Scientists believe the animal glided, which sheds new light on the origins of avian flight.
</Question>
<Choice>2003</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Due in part to worries over air pollution, the popularity of hybrid cars greatly increases, with the demand for some models resulting in lengthy waiting lists.
</Question>
<Choice>2004</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Kyoto Protocol, designed to reduce the emission of greenhouse gases, comes into effect. Ratified by 141 countries, it is hailed as a landmark achievement, although critics questioned its effectiveness, citing modest goals and the U.S.'s refusal to sign the treaty.
</Question>
<Choice>2005</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Researchers announce that the ivory-billed woodpecker, believed to be extinct, was spotted in Arkansas.
</Question>
<Choice>2005</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scientists announce that numerous new animal and plant species have been discovered in a remote jungle in Indonesia. Among their findings are 20 new frog species and 4 new butterflies.
</Question>
<Choice>2006</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The United Nation's Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change releases a report that calls evidence of global warming "unequivocal" and cites human activity as the leading cause.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Arabian Oryx Sanctuary in Oman, home to the first reintroduced population of Arabian Onyx, becomes the first site to be deleted from UNESCO's World Heritage List after it was announced that the sanctuary would reduce the size of protected area by 90%.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
East Timor establishes its first national park, Nino Konis Santana National Park. Notable animals include the endangered green pigeon.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scientists announce the discovery of the world's longest insect, Phobaeticus chani, also known as Chan's megastick. With its legs fully extended, the insect is 22 inches (56 cm) long.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Researchers report that an estimated 125,000 Western lowland gorillas have been discovered in a swamp forest in the Republic of the Congo. The total population of these critically endangered animals was previously believed to be less than 50,000 worldwide.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
China bans the distribution of free plastic shopping bags, citing the need to fight the “white pollution” that clogs many of the country’s landfills.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The polar bear is put on the World Wildlife Fund's annual list of nine threatened species to watch. The group cites habitat loss and climate change as the primary factors in the animal’s declining population.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A computer hacker releases private e-mails from the Climatic Research Unit of the University of East Anglia; global-warming skeptics claim that some of the messages show evidence of data manipulation and suppression, while climate scientists contend the messages were taken out of context.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
World leaders convene in Copenhagen to draw up and affirm a climate treaty; during the contentious two-week negotiation, all 192 attending countries take note of a nonbinding agreement to work to limit the rise in average global temperature to 2 °C (3.6 °F).
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
</topics>