<topics>
<item>
<Question>
Egyptians perhaps begin maritime exploration of the Indian Ocean, reaching the "land of Punt" on the Somali coast.
</Question>
<Choice>2900 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Egyptian king sends the trader Harkhuf south to Nubia, the geographic and economic intermediary in African-Egyptian trade for incense, ebony, ivory, slaves, skins, and exotic animals.
</Question>
<Choice>2250 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Construction of an irrigation canal through the Isthmus of Suez by 12th dynasty Egyptians promotes trade in the northwestern Indian Ocean until it is filled in AD 775.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1850 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Archaeological evidence suggests trade of goods and ideas between Mesopotamian civilizations and the Shang dynasty China.
</Question>
<Choice>1750 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Seafaring skill of the Mycenaean civilization promotes long-distance trade networks within the Aegean Sea and elsewhere in the Mediterranean and Middle East.
</Question>
<Choice>1600 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
For almost half a century, New Kingdom Egyptian soldiers, administrators, diplomats, and merchants travel widely to seek new technologies and cultural innovations.
</Question>
<Choice>1539 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
From this time Egyptians begin to use camels, which had been domesticated a millennium earlier in Arabia, for cross-desert trade and travel.
</Question>
<Choice>1500 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
During her reign, Egyptian Queen Hatshepsut dispatches the first recorded maritime expedition down the Red Sea to open direct trade with coastal Africa for myrrh, ebony, animal skins, and gold.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1460 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Malay navigators and sailors spread out across the Pacific and Indian oceans, settling thousands of islands.
</Question>
<Choice>1000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Lacking navigable rivers and raw materials, ancient Greeks turn to sea trade. Phoenicians in Carthage develop a formidable navy and establish a trading network that spans the Mediterranean.
</Question>
<Choice>800 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Alleged circumnavigation of Africa by Phoenician ships under orders of the Egyptian pharaoh Necho II.
</Question>
<Choice>610 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek ambassadors seeking an audience with Persian King Darius I journey to the capitol city, Susa. The journey, on royal roads that connect provinces with the heart of the Persian empire, takes three months.
</Question>
<Choice>522 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Darius I dispatches Greek geographer Scylax of Caryanda to explore the Indus River. Scylax reaches the Indus and returns via the Red Sea. His is the first known Western account of India.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 515 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Beginning of a dispersal of Bantu-speaking people across Africa that by AD 1000 results in development of Pan-African traditions and practices.
</Question>
<Choice>500 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek scholar Hecataeus of Miletus pioneers the field of geography in his two-part book of travels discussing Europe and Asia, which includes Egypt and North Africa.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 500 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Birth of Herodotus, one of the most famous Greek explorers and writers. His famous geography and world map are based on personal observations made during many years of travel.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 484 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Legend tells of an underwater descent by Alexander the Great in a glass barrel or cage.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 330 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek voyager Pytheas sails around Britain and discovers a place he names Thule (possibly the Shetland Islands, Iceland, or Norway), which for centuries is considered the end of the Earth.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 300 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Arawak voyagers from northeastern South America reach and gradually move up the islands of the Lesser Antilles into the Greater Antilles (Cuba, Hispaniola, Jamaica, and Puerto Rico).
</Question>
<Choice>300 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Silk Road, connecting China and the Middle East across Central Asia, becomes an important conduit for exchanging agricultural goods, manufactured products, ideas, and people.
</Question>
<Choice>150 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At the behest of Han dynasty Emperor Wu-ti, General Chang Ch’ien leads the first of 18 imperial expeditions across Central Asia exploring the route of the Silk Road.
</Question>
<Choice>128 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The author of The Periplus of the Erythraean Sea bases his description of pre-Islamic Indian Ocean trade on his own voyages in the Red Sea, Persian Gulf, and Indian Ocean.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 100 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek historian-geographer Strabo finishes his 17-volume summary of classical knowledge of geography. The great work combines tradition, myth, and information gathered during his own wide travels.
</Question>
<Choice>23</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The apostle Paul, a Jew from the Greek city Tarsus, converts to Christianity and travels on Roman roads from Syria-Palestine through Greece to convert Gentiles and establish Christian communities.
</Question>
<Choice>40</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pliny the Elder finishes his Natural History. A monumental and influential work, its observations on plants, animals, geography, and peoples are a rich combination of fact and fiction.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 77</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ptolemy writes his Guide to Geography, an influential work that assembles geographic knowledge, confirms the spherical nature of Earth, and establishes the latitude-longitude grid.
</Question>
<Choice>127</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Silk merchant-travelers sent by Emperor Marcus Aurelius Antoninus arrive at the court of the Chinese emperor Huan-ti. They are the first Roman delegates to reach Han China.
</Question>
<Choice>161</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Gupta empire in northern India straddles important long-distance trade routes between the Roman Empire and southeastern and eastern Asia.
</Question>
<Choice>320</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Helena, mother of Emperor Constantine, converts to Christianity and travels to Jerusalem. Her travels help popularize Christian pilgrimages to the Holy Land.
</Question>
<Choice>327</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Easter Island, 2,200 miles off the coast of South America, is inhabited by Polynesians from the Marquesas Islands.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 400</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese Buddhist Monk Faxian initiates Sino-Indian relations during his pilgrimage to India. He returns to China with many Sanskrit Buddhist texts, which he translates into Chinese.
</Question>
<Choice>402</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian and Sri Lankan merchants develop an all-sea trade route via the Strait of Malacca between China and the Mediterranean, replacing the lengthy overland trek across the Malay peninsula.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 500</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Cosmas of Alexandria, a merchant who had traveled around the Red Sea and Indian Ocean, writes the Topographia Christiana, a geographic treatise that defends the Biblical view of the Earth.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 547</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Irish Monk St. Brendan seeks Paradise by sailing westward in the Atlantic Ocean. During his travels he reaches the Hebrides, Scotland, and perhaps Wales and Brittany.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 550</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Amerindian voyagers begin to use ocean currents to travel northward from the Inca empire of Peru to Aztec lands in southern Mexico.
</Question>
<Choice>600</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Tang empire in China supports travel by Buddhists to shrines. It later reverses policy and destroys Buddhist monasteries, creating a population of wandering, impoverished monks.
</Question>
<Choice>618</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese Buddhist pilgrim Xuanzang leaves China to journey through India during the reign of Harsha. His travels are chronicled by the fervent Buddhist poet and warrior Vardhana.
</Question>
<Choice>629</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Irish Abbot St. Adamnan writes De locis sanctis, an account of the travels of German Bishop Arculf through the Middle East and Egypt. Arculf had been diverted by storms to the Hebrides on his way home.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 685</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Trans-Saharan trade involves the exchange of salt needed by sub-Saharan Africans for gold dust. The trade expands by 1100 to include slaves and tropical goods wanted in Europe.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 740</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The astrolabe, invented some time in the 6th century and used in medieval Europe and the Mediterranean, becomes popular among astronomers and navigators in the Islamic world.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 750</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Arab and Persian seafarers begin to write detailed instructions on sailing in the Indian Ocean. These sailing manuals compile information on navigation, winds, currents, coasts, and ports.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 800</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Founding of the coastal city of Seylac, Somalia. For a millennium, the city is a centre of African-Arabian trade, exporting ivory and slaves and importing cloth and metals.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 820</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Arab seafarers’ mastery of lateen sail rigging creates a class of ships that dominate the Indian Ocean trade for centuries. Lateen rigging is used through much of the Islamic world.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 850</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Vikings begin three centuries of exploration throughout the Arctic region. During their travels they colonize Iceland, settle Greenland, and visit North America.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 900</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Collapse of the Tang dynasty in China disrupts the eastern end of the Silk Road. It remains severed until the 13th century, when it is restored by Mongol rulers.
</Question>
<Choice>907</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Exiled from Iceland for manslaughter around 980, Viking Eric the Red discovers Greenland. After three years he returns to Iceland and organizes colonization voyages to the new land.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 982</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Bjarni Herjulfsson accidentally sights North America, possibly Newfoundland, when he gets lost in fog en route to Greenland from Iceland.
</Question>
<Choice>986</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Carib voyagers reach the Lesser Antilles and drive the Arawaks north into the Greater Antilles. From the West Indies, Caribs and Arawaks make voyages to the North American mainland.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polynesian explorer-mariners sail from the Marquesas Islands to New Zealand.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Leif Eriksson, son of Eric the Red, sails to North America and winters in Vinland, possibly Nova Scotia.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Icelander Thorfinn Karlsefni, a relative of Leif Eriksson, and his wife, Gudrid, attempt to establish a permanent Viking colony in Vinland. By 1020 Vikings abandon all Vinland settlements.
</Question>
<Choice>1004</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Muslim scientist al-Biruni improves a device for determining latitude as he and other Arab geographers revise Ptolemy to suggest that the Indian Ocean flows into the Atlantic.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1020</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Founding of the port city of Mombasa in eastern Africa. Port cities were an important link in a network connecting landlocked African states with trading partners across the Indian Ocean.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1050</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
First naval application of the magnetic compass occurs when Chinese traders reach the Middle East, the Philippines, and possibly more distant points.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1090</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pope Urban II calls for Christians to wrest Jerusalem and the Holy Sepulchre from its Muslim rulers. The ancient city is taken by European forces in 1099, in the first of eight crusades.
</Question>
<Choice>1095</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
For 200 years, Tahitian mariners cross 2,000 nautical miles to Hawaii.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1100</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A letter appears in Europe, purportedly from Christian Priest-King Prester John, promising to help conquer the Holy Sepulchre, spurring crusaders and explorers to seek his kingdom.
</Question>
<Choice>1165</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
First European reference to the magnetic compass, by English Monk Alexander Neckam. The instrument offers an absolute scale for defining space and extends the times and seasons of seafaring.
</Question>
<Choice>1187</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
First appearance of the wind rose on Italian and Spanish maps. Its eight points show the direction of principal winds at different locations.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1200</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The rise to power of Genghis Khan revitalizes the Silk Road. Mongol policies facilitate rapid movement of people and ideas from one end of Eurasia to the other.
</Question>
<Choice>1206</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Franciscan Friars Giovanni da Pian del Carpini and Benedict the Pole trek across Central Asia to the Tartar capital in an unsuccessful attempt to convert the great khan.
</Question>
<Choice>1245</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
King Louis IX sends the French Dominican Friar Andrew of Lonjumel to Asia to investigate a rumour that the great khan had embraced Christianity.
</Question>
<Choice>1247</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pilots learn to use winter monsoons to sail to Africa and summer monsoons to return to India. Trade expands along the East African coast, giving rise to city-states such as Great Zimbabwe.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1250</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Geographic discoveries made by Franciscan Friar Willem van Ruysbroeck en route to investigate rumours of the conversion of the great khan to Christianity are communicated to the West by Francis Bacon.
</Question>
<Choice>1253</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Venetian traveler Marco Polo departs on his 24-year journey across all of Asia to the ocean. His account inspires a persistent ambition in Europe to find easier routes to Asia.
</Question>
<Choice>1271</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Two Christian Turks, Rabban bar Sauma and his disciple Marcus, tour western Europe as ambassadors of the Mongol Khans.
</Question>
<Choice>1287</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian Franciscan Friar Giovanni da Montecorvino arrives in Peking with a letter from the pope to the great khan. Twelve years later he becomes the first archbishop of Peking.
</Question>
<Choice>1294</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mariners use portolans, or harbor-finding charts, the first maps that attempt to reflect close, continuous observation of the Earth's surface.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1300</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Syrian historian and geographer Abu al-Fida' writes his Taqwim al-buldan (Locating the Lands), an influential compilation of geographic writings.
</Question>
<Choice>1321</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On a pilgrimage to Mecca, the ruler of the West African empire of Mali tells of a transatlantic voyage attempted by his predecessor Mansa Muhammad.
</Question>
<Choice>1324</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Friar Odoric of Pordenone lives for three years in China before returning to Padua by way of Central Asia. Once home, he dictates an account of his travels that gains widespread popularity.
</Question>
<Choice>1337</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Francesco Balducci Pegolotti, agent for a Florentine banking family, produces a valuable guidebook for merchant-travelers in the East.
</Question>
<Choice>1343</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Florentine Friar Giovanni dei Marignolli travels across Russia to Peking, home of the Mongol emperor's court. His return trip to Avignon takes him through India, Ceylon, and the Middle East.
</Question>
<Choice>1338</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ibn Battutah, the greatest Muslim traveler of the Middle Ages, dictates his Rihlah (Travels), an account of 30 years' and 75,000 miles' travels throughout the Islamic world and China.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1355</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English publication of the fabulous The Travels of Sir John Mandeville. Regarded as the greatest medieval European traveler, Mandeville was a fictional character; the true author of the Travels is unknown.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1375</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Birth of Prince Henry the Navigator of Portugal, who establishes a centre for cartography, shipbuilding, and navigation in Sagres, Port., and instigates 40 years of exploration of the western coast of Africa.
</Question>
<Choice>1394</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Bavarian crusader Johann Schiltberger is captured by Turks and spends 31 years as a slave of the Ottoman sultan and the Tartar Timur. He writes a fanciful but valuable account of his life.
</Question>
<Choice>1396</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish nobleman Ruy González de Clavijo journeys to Samarkand, Turkistan, headquarters of the great Timur, to offer an alliance with King Henry III of Castile.
</Question>
<Choice>1403</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
First of seven voyages led by Zheng He demonstrates the power and grandeur of the Ming dynasty to lands on the China Sea and Indian Ocean. After 1433, Chinese interest in exploration dissipates.
</Question>
<Choice>1405</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A Latin translation of a world geography attributed to Ptolemy teaches European mariners how to compute their location at sea and encourages empirical measurement of the Earth.
</Question>
<Choice>1409</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A delegate from one of the trading cities on the Swahili coast of East Africa creates a stir in China by presenting the emperor with a giraffe. The gift prompts Zheng He to voyage to Africa.
</Question>
<Choice>1414</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Venetian merchant Niccolò dei Conti travels through Arabia and India to Java. He speculates that European merchants could reach the Spice Islands directly by circumnavigating Africa.
</Question>
<Choice>1419</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Reputedly discovered in 1427 by Diogo de Senill (or Sevilha), the Azores are settled by the Portuguese and quickly become a key link in their exploration and trading network.
</Question>
<Choice>1432</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Portuguese navigator Gil Eannes passes Cape Bojador in southern Morocco, until then an impassable barrier to Portuguese exploration south along the African coast.
</Question>
<Choice>1434</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Gil Eannes reaches the watered and populated land of sub-Saharan Africa and returns from Cape Branco with the first human cargo from Africa.
</Question>
<Choice>1441</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Portuguese navigator and explorer Dinís Dias reaches the mouth of the Sénégal River and later rounds Cape Verde, the western tip of Africa.
</Question>
<Choice>1445</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Invention of the printing press by Johannes Gutenberg spreads Ptolemy's Guide to Geography and other ancient geographic and navigational texts throughout Europe.
</Question>
<Choice>1454</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Venetian explorer Alvise Ca' da Mosto calls caravels "the best ships that sailed the seas." Discoverers choose them for their shallow draft, small size, and ability to sail close to the wind.
</Question>
<Choice>1456</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Serving Prince Henry, Alvise Ca' da Mosto explores the Cape Verde Islands, ascends the Sénégal and Gambia rivers, and writes one of the earliest European descriptions of western Africa.
</Question>
<Choice>1457</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Lisbon merchant Fernão Gomes contracts with the Portuguese crown to explore 300 miles of African coast each year for five years in return for a monopoly of the Guinea trade.
</Question>
<Choice>1469</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Martin Behaim adapts the astrolabe for nautical use, enabling the calculation of latitude from measurement of the meridian altitude of the Sun using astronomical tables.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1480</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
King John II ascends the Portuguese throne. His patronage of explorers searching for a sea route to India ushers in the next great age of Portuguese seafaring.
</Question>
<Choice>1481</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Diogo Cão explores the western African coast, discovering the mouth of the Congo River and initiating the European practice of setting up stone markers topped by a cross as proof of first discovery.
</Question>
<Choice>1482</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Joseph Vizinho departs on a voyage to record the declination of the Sun along the whole Guinea coast in order to develop a technique for determining latitude by the height of the midday Sun.
</Question>
<Choice>1485</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On an overland expedition sponsored by King John II of Portugal, Pêro da Covilhã seeks information about Arab seafaring and hears reports of a practical sea route to India around Africa.
</Question>
<Choice>1487</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Bartolomeu Dias becomes the first European explorer to get around the southern tip of Africa when he sails past the Cape of Good Hope in a storm and sights the Indian Ocean.
</Question>
<Choice>1488</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The great Arab master navigator Ahmad ibn Madjid writes a nautical science compendium for the Red Sea and Indian Ocean. Later he pilots Vasco da Gama's expedition across the Indian Ocean.
</Question>
<Choice>1490</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Christopher Columbus makes the first of four voyages from Europe to the Americas.
</Question>
<Choice>1492</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Columbus leads a 17-vessel armada on a second voyage to Hispaniola, discovering the Lesser Antilles, Jamaica, and Puerto Rico and exploring the south coast of Cuba.
</Question>
<Choice>1493</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The pope brokers an agreement between Spain and Portugal, the Treaty of Tordesillas, dividing all unknown lands along an imaginary line down the centre of the North Atlantic Ocean.
</Question>
<Choice>1494</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Vasco da Gama rounds the Cape of Good Hope. He reaches Calicut, India, in 1498, with the aim of opening direct Portuguese trade with Asia.
</Question>
<Choice>1497</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In search of a short sea route to Asia, John Cabot steers a northern transatlantic course and reaches Labrador, Newfoundland, or Cape Breton Island, providing a basis for British claim to Canada.
</Question>
<Choice>1497</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On his third expedition Christopher Columbus discovers Trinidad and sights the mainland of South America. Insisting on the Asiatic identity of Cuba, he surmises it is the earthly location of Paradise.
</Question>
<Choice>1498</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Merchant-explorer Amerigo Vespucci, who calculated the most accurate estimate of the Earth's circumference to date, explores the South American coast for the Spanish government.
</Question>
<Choice>1499</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mapmaking becomes a big business in Europe as printers and dealers begin to specialize in this popular market.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1500</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Seeking favourable winds en route to East India, Pedro Álvares Cabral swings west in the South Atlantic and sights South America's eastern coast, laying the basis for Portugal's claim to Brazil.
</Question>
<Choice>1500</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ships from a fleet commanded by Portuguese explorer Gaspar Côrte-Real return with kidnapped natives from Newfoundland. Gaspar, who continues exploring southward, is never heard from again.
</Question>
<Choice>1501</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Amerigo Vespucci follows the South American coast from Latin America into Patagonia and concludes that the land is a new continent. It is named for him in Martin Waldseemüller's 1507 world map.
</Question>
<Choice>1501</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Christopher Columbus departs on his fourth voyage in which he still does not discover that Cuba is an island. He dies in 1506 believing that he had explored the eastern coast of Asia.
</Question>
<Choice>1502</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Explorer-fisherman Jean Denys becomes the first of many Frenchmen to fish off the Newfoundland coast. By 1519 French fishermen begin curing their catches ashore at Saint-Malo.
</Question>
<Choice>1504</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Juan Ponce de León conquers the island of Boriquén (modern Puerto Rico). It serves as a launching pad for expeditions to southeastern Florida in search of the fountain of youth.
</Question>
<Choice>1508</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Vasco Núñez de Balboa, a Spanish adventurer inspired by native reports, mounts an expedition to cross the mountainous Isthmus of Panama to the Pacific Ocean.
</Question>
<Choice>1513</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ferdinand Magellan departs on his famous circumnavigation during which he discovers the strait named for him at South America's tip and christens the Pacific Ocean. He dies in the Philippines in 1521.
</Question>
<Choice>1519</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hernán Cortés launches an attack on the Aztec empire. He and native allies capture the capitol city, Tenochtitlán, after fierce fighting, winning Mexico for Spain.
</Question>
<Choice>1519</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Portuguese shipowner José Alvarez Faguendez coasts along southern Newfoundland and enters the Gulf of St. Lawrence, returning later to establish a short-lived shore station for curing codfish.
</Question>
<Choice>1520</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Juan Sebastián de Elcano is honoured by the Spanish emperor for completing the first circumnavigation of the Earth after Magellan's death in the Philippines.
</Question>
<Choice>1522</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sailing for the French, the Italian mariner Giovanni da Verrazzano explores almost the entire North American coast, but his valuable reconnaissance is not followed by further French voyages.
</Question>
<Choice>1524</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish fortune hunter Francisco Pizarro defeats Incan Emperor Atahuallpa in the valley of Cajamarca, setting the stage for the end of Incan rule by 1535.
</Question>
<Choice>1532</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French navigator Jacques Cartier claims Canada for France by entering the St. Lawrence estuary and exploring the Charles River inland to modern-day Montreal.
</Question>
<Choice>1535</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Gugielmo de Lorena designs a diving bell for exploring sunken ships in Italy's Lake Nemi.
</Question>
<Choice>1535</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish explorer Francisco Vázquez de Coronado commands a large expedition into the modern-day southwestern U.S. They conquer several Pueblo Indian communities and discover the Grand Canyon.
</Question>
<Choice>1540</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish soldier-explorer Francisco de Orellana follows the Amazon River from the Peruvian Andes to the Atlantic Ocean, becoming the river's first European explorer.
</Question>
<Choice>1541</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Searching for a northeast passage, English pilot Richard Chancellor is separated from his commander and reaches the Russian city of Archangel by sailing around North Cape, Nor.
</Question>
<Choice>1553</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On a voyage between Peru and Chile, Spanish pilot Juan Fernández sights an island subsequently named for him.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1563</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Flemish navigator Olivier Brunel explores Russia's northern coast, seeking a route to China and the East Indies. In 1576 he becomes the first western European to travel overland to Siberia.
</Question>
<Choice>1565</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Spaniard Álvaro de Mendaña de Neira, nephew of the governor of Peru, stumbles upon the Solomon Islands while searching for the great southern continent.
</Question>
<Choice>1568</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Gerardus Mercator transforms mapmaking for the secular world through his projection that allows sailors to lay out courses on flat charts that account for the Earth's sphericity.
</Question>
<Choice>1569</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Publication of the first portable modern geographic atlas transforms the pursuit of geographic knowledge into a cooperative international enterprise.
</Question>
<Choice>1570</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Martin Frobisher explores Canada's northeast coast, discovering the bay named for him. His three voyages fail commercially but lay the foundation for British colonies in the 17th century.
</Question>
<Choice>1576</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Francis Drake's voyage around the world, the first English circumnavigation, demonstrates the open route to the Pacific south of the tip of South America.
</Question>
<Choice>1577</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch traveler Jan Huyghen van Linschoten sails to Goa. His descriptions of his many years' travels help stimulate the Dutch to compete with the Spanish and Portuguese for the East Indian trade.
</Question>
<Choice>1583</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English explorer Sir Humphrey Gilbert claims lands in Newfoundland, probably to serve as a base for the English North Atlantic fishery. His ship is lost at sea on the return voyage.
</Question>
<Choice>1583</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In a series of three voyages in search of a northwest passage, English navigator John Davis explores Cumberland Sound, Davis Strait, and Baffin Bay and sails north of the Arctic circle.
</Question>
<Choice>1585</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Richard Hakluyt publishes the first volume of his monumental The Principall Navigations, Voiages and Discoveries of the English Nation.
</Question>
<Choice>1589</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John Davis becomes the first European explorer to sight the Falkland Islands as he seeks a passage through the Strait of Magellan.
</Question>
<Choice>1592</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Dutch navigator Willem Barents, for whom the Barents Sea is named, inadvertently becomes the first European to winter in the Arctic while searching for a northeast passage to Asia.
</Question>
<Choice>1594</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Founding of the East India Company, the first of several European companies that compete for the rich Indian Ocean trade in spices and luxury goods.
</Question>
<Choice>1600</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pedro Fernández de Quirós, searching for the southern continent, reaches the New Hebrides. Luis de Torres, commander of the expedition's other ship, discovers the Torres Strait.
</Question>
<Choice>1605</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The invention of the telescope provides a powerful new tool for astronomy and exploration.
</Question>
<Choice>1608</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Henry Hudson ascends the Hudson River in search of a northwest passage to China after pack ice frustrates earlier efforts to find a northeast passage.
</Question>
<Choice>1609</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Henry Hudson is marooned by his mutinous crew while exploring the Hudson Bay.
</Question>
<Choice>1611</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French explorer and founder of the city of Quebec, Samuel de Champlain, becomes the first European to record seeing the Great Lakes.
</Question>
<Choice>1615</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Seeking a better route to the Pacific than the Strait of Magellan, Dutch explorers Willem Schouten and Jakob Le Maire explore and name Cape Horn then find Le Maire Strait.
</Question>
<Choice>1616</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In search of the Northwest Passage, William Baffin pilots the ship Discovery farther into Baffin Bay than Davis had earlier but concludes that it did not lead to India.
</Question>
<Choice>1616</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch captain Dirck Hartog sights western Australia when blown off course on a voyage from the Netherlands around South Africa to Java.
</Question>
<Choice>1616</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch inventor Cornelis Drebbel tests one of the first functional submarines in England's River Thames.
</Question>
<Choice>1620</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French North American explorer Jean Nicolet seeks the Northwest Passage by crossing Lake Huron and passing through the Straits of Mackinac. He discovers Lake Michigan and sails to Green Bay.
</Question>
<Choice>1634</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Oxford astronomer John Greaves makes a two-year scientific journey to the East and returns with copies of the Samarkand Tables, the most accurate astronomical observations made to this time.
</Question>
<Choice>1637</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch navigator Abel Janszoon Tasman explores the southern coast of Australia and discovers the island of Tasmania, opening up the South Indian Ocean and the Southwest Pacific Ocean for trade.
</Question>
<Choice>1642</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Salvagers using diving bells recover canon from the sunken Swedish warship Vasa at a depth of 110 feet in Stockholm harbor.
</Question>
<Choice>1663</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Founding of the Hudson's Bay Company, whose trappers and fur traders collect information about the people, geography, and flora and fauna of North America.
</Question>
<Choice>1670</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Death of Evliya Çelebi, an Ottoman diplomat who traveled to Europe, the Middle East, and Russia. His Seyahatname (Book of Travels) is a vivid, detailed, and sometimes fanciful account of his travels.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1684</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Buccaneer William Dampier publishes his A New Voyage Round the World. It inspires Pacific exploration and other voyaging tales, most notably Daniel Defoe's novel Robinson Crusoe.
</Question>
<Choice>1697</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English astronomer and Royal Society fellow Edmond Halley (of Halley's Comet fame) commands a scientific voyage through the South and North Atlantic to study terrestrial magnetism.
</Question>
<Choice>1698</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On a circumnavigation of the globe and search for the southern continent, Dutch admiral Jacob Roggeveen discovers the mysterious Easter Island and sights Samoa.
</Question>
<Choice>1722</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Vitus Jonassen Bering, a Dane in the Russian service, discovers the strait between Asia and North America and lays the basis for Russian claims in North America.
</Question>
<Choice>1728</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English mathematician and instrument-maker John Hadley invents the quadrant, a device for measuring the altitude of the Sun.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1730</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Russian government follows Bering's discovery with the Great Northern Expedition, a 10-year expedition that gathers information on the Arctic and North Pacific coasts.
</Question>
<Choice>1733</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French explorer Jean-Baptiste-Charles Bouvet de Lozier seeks the southern continent south and west of South Africa, but finds only a small island named for him.
</Question>
<Choice>1739</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
George Anson begins his four-year circumnavigation of the world, later described in his book Voyage Round the World.
</Question>
<Choice>1740</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French naturalist and mathematician Charles-Marie de La Condamine journeys from Quito, Ecuador, to the mouth of the Amazon River.
</Question>
<Choice>1743</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Rising popularity of the sextant, a more precise instrument than the quadrant for measuring the altitude of the Sun.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1750</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish naval surgeon James Lind demonstrates the efficacy of citrus fruits in preventing and curing scurvy, long a major health hazard in long-distance sea travel.
</Question>
<Choice>1753</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chronometer built by Englishman John Harrison keeps time during a nine-week voyage, winning a prize offered by Parliament for the invention of a practical way of finding longitude at sea.
</Question>
<Choice>1761</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English astronomer royal Nevil Maskelyne publishes the first edition of the Nautical Almanac, an invaluable reference work for British navigators.
</Question>
<Choice>1766</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Louis-Antoine de Bougainville leads a French naval expedition, including naturalists and other scientists, on a voyage of exploration focusing on the South Pacific.
</Question>
<Choice>1766</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British explorer Samuel Wallis discovers Tahiti while his expedition's other ship, commanded by Philip Carteret, finds Pitcairn Island and some of the Solomons previously discovered by Álvaro de Mendaña.
</Question>
<Choice>1767</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
James Cook begins the first of three expeditions to the South Pacific. He surveys the islands of New Zealand, discovers the Great Barrier Reef, and charts over 4,000 miles of coastline.
</Question>
<Choice>1769</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ironically, the magnificent natural harbor of San Francisco Bay is discovered on an overland expedition from the south led by Spanish explorer Gaspar de Portolá.
</Question>
<Choice>1769</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish explorer James Bruce discovers Lake Tana, the headstream of the Blue Nile River, which he mistakenly believes to be the main source of the Nile River.
</Question>
<Choice>1770</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hudson's Bay Company agent Samuel Hearne leads an overland expedition to the shores of the Arctic Ocean, claiming the coast for the company.
</Question>
<Choice>1770</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French navigator Yves-Joseph de Kerguélen-Trémarec searches for a southern continent in the Indian Ocean but discovers only an uninhabitable island named for him.
</Question>
<Choice>1772</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On his second voyage, James Cook continues his search for the southern continent. In 1773 he crosses the Antarctic Circle.
</Question>
<Choice>1772</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish missionary Silvestre Vélez de Escalante explores western Colorado and journeys north into Utah, almost reaching the Great Salt Lake.
</Question>
<Choice>1776</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On his third voyage, James Cook searches for a northwest passage but concludes that none exists. He dies in a skirmish in Hawaii in 1779.
</Question>
<Choice>1776</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English naturalist Joseph Banks becomes head of the Royal Society of London and an influential advocate of scientific and geographic research and exploration.
</Question>
<Choice>1778</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
After a mutiny on his ship Bounty, William Bligh and loyal crewmen survive nearly seven weeks in an open boat with little food and water and no charts, drifting from near Tonga to Timor.
</Question>
<Choice>1789</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
George Vancouver surveys the coast of North America from San Francisco to British Columbia. While he proves that no northwest passage exists, his work stimulates development of North Pacific trade.
</Question>
<Choice>1792</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish fur trader Alexander Mackenzie reaches the coast of British Columbia, traveling overland from the Great Slave Lake along the Mackenzie River to the Arctic Ocean.
</Question>
<Choice>1793</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The African Association of London sends Scottish surgeon Mungo Park to explore the course of the Niger River. He discovers that it flows eastward and returns to write a popular account of his travels.
</Question>
<Choice>1795</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Alexander von Humboldt embarks on his self-financed scientific travels through Central and South America, making important contributions to geography, botany, geophysical science, and meteorology.
</Question>
<Choice>1799</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English navigator Matthew Flinders departs on his second voyage to Australia. He circumnavigates Australia and charts much of its coastline.
</Question>
<Choice>1801</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
President Thomas Jefferson sends Captain Meriwether Lewis and Lieutenant William Clark on the first U.S. overland expedition from St. Louis, Mo., to the Pacific.
</Question>
<Choice>1804</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. Army Lieutenant Zebulon Pike explores the Arkansas and Red rivers, discovering Pikes Peak (Colorado) as he seeks information about Spanish military defenses and trade in the region.
</Question>
<Choice>1806</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Canadian fur trader Simon Fraser follows the Fraser River to its mouth near Vancouver, B.C., on the last great overland expedition across North America.
</Question>
<Choice>1808</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British naval officer James Tuckey explores Africa, seeking a connection between the Congo and Niger rivers. He travels 300 miles up the Congo before dying of fever.
</Question>
<Choice>1816</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Captain John Ross confirms William Baffin’s discoveries of two centuries earlier. He mistakes several sounds for bays but still adds greatly to scientific knowledge of the arctic region.
</Question>
<Choice>1818</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Fabian Gottlieb von Bellingshausen, in service of the Russian tsar, begins a recapitulation of James Cook's Antarctic voyage, during which he sights land along the Antarctica peninsula.
</Question>
<Choice>1819</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Trader Jedediah Smith begins nearly a decade-long exploration of Montana, Idaho, Utah, and Nevada and becomes the first American to enter California from the east and return via an overland route.
</Question>
<Choice>1822</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
William E. Parry's third expedition in search of a northwest passage ends a geographic failure but a scientific success, leading to advances in navigation, cartography, and natural history.
</Question>
<Choice>1824</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Charles Sturt journeys down the Murrumbidgee and Murray rivers in one of the greatest explorations of the interior of Australia.
</Question>
<Choice>1829</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Founding of what is now known as the Royal Geographical Society in London. During the 19th century the society sponsored expeditions to Latin America, Australia, Africa, and the Arctic.
</Question>
<Choice>1830</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Charles Darwin leaves England aboard the Beagle to spend five years exploring South America, the Galápagos Islands, and the Pacific. The voyage establishes Darwin as a promising young naturalist.
</Question>
<Choice>1831</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On a privately funded expedition to the Canadian Arctic, James Clark Ross discovers the north magnetic pole.
</Question>
<Choice>1831</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
During the U.S. exploring expedition to Antarctica, the Pacific Ocean, and South America, Lieutenant Charles Wilkes explores 1,500 miles of Antarctic coastline and surmises that it is a continent.
</Question>
<Choice>1838</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The steamers Great Western and Sirius cross the Atlantic Ocean under steam power alone, inaugurating regular transatlantic steamship service.
</Question>
<Choice>1838</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
James C. Ross commands an Antarctic expedition in search of the south magnetic pole, discovering the Ross Sea and Victoria Land in 1841 and earning knighthood upon his return to England in 1843.
</Question>
<Choice>1839</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American explorer and mapmaker John C. Frémont surveys the western route to Wyoming, beginning several years of careful mapping of the U.S. territory west of the Mississippi River.
</Question>
<Choice>1842</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
After two overland expeditions in the Canadian Arctic, Sir John Franklin sails from England in search of the Northwest Passage. In spite of many rescue efforts, all the expedition members perish.
</Question>
<Choice>1845</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English naturalist T.H. Huxley joins HMS Rattlesnake as assistant surgeon and spends four years investigating the zoology of the southern seas and lands.
</Question>
<Choice>1846</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German missionary-explorer Johannes Rebmann becomes the first European to view the African mountain Kilimanjaro. His account of his travels promotes exploration of the Nile River sources and basin.
</Question>
<Choice>1848</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English explorer Henry W. Bates begins an 11-year exploration of the Amazon Valley, during which he collects zoological specimens and observes animals, native people, and natural phenomena.
</Question>
<Choice>1848</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American hydrographer Matthew F. Maury inaugurates the first program of deep ocean soundings, a precursor to transatlantic submarine telegraph surveys.
</Question>
<Choice>1849</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
William Lewis Herndon leads an expedition sponsored by the U.S. Navy to explore the Amazon basin area.
</Question>
<Choice>1850</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Searching for the lost John Franklin expedition, Irish explorer Robert John Le Mesurier McClure becomes the first to traverse the Northwest Passage, albeit using two ships with foot travel between.
</Question>
<Choice>1850</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John Rae learns of the terrible fate of the John Franklin expedition from the Eskimo, while surveying Boothia Peninsula. Rae is among the first explorers to adopt Eskimo survival practices.
</Question>
<Choice>1853</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Missionary-doctor David Livingstone embarks on a series of treks through southern and central Africa, tracing the course of the Zambezi River and naming Victoria Falls.
</Question>
<Choice>1853</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ferdinand V. Hayden begins a 30-year survey of the western U.S., contributing to the foundation of the U.S. Geological Survey and helping to create Yellowstone National Park.
</Question>
<Choice>1853</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Alfred Russel Wallace gathers Malaysian and Moluccan animals and plants, formulating a theory of natural selection later published simultaneously with Charles Darwin's.
</Question>
<Choice>1854</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Searching for the Nile River's origin, English explorers Richard Burton and John Speke discover Lake Tanganyika.
</Question>
<Choice>1858</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Seeking records of John Franklin's doomed expedition, Charles Francis Hall begins his first of three Arctic travels and proves Frobisher Strait to be a bay.
</Question>
<Choice>1860</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Samuel White Baker, traveling with his future wife Florence von Sass, discovers Lake Albert and determines it to be a source of the Nile River.
</Question>
<Choice>1864</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Geologist John Wesley Powell begins his series of scientific explorations of the Green and Colorado rivers and the Rocky Mountains. Later he directs federal surveys of public western lands.
</Question>
<Choice>1867</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American geologist Clarence King undertakes a 10-year scientific survey of the 40th parallel, mapping and exploring mineral resources along a proposed railroad route.
</Question>
<Choice>1867</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The completion of the Suez Canal, which links the Mediterranean and Red seas, dramatically reduces sailing times from Europe to Asia and triggers a massive switch from sail to steam power.
</Question>
<Choice>1869</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German pioneer archaeologist Heinrich Schliemann begins the excavation of what he believes to be the ancient city of Troy. His discovery helps establish the modern field of archaeology.
</Question>
<Choice>1871</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
While tracing the course of the Nile River, David Livingstone meets journalist Henry Morton Stanley on his publicity jaunt to search for the "lost" missionary.
</Question>
<Choice>1871</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The British Challenger begins its nearly four-year expedition. Its survey of deep-sea life inaugurates systematic scientific investigation of the oceans.
</Question>
<Choice>1872</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Arctic explorer Karl Weyprecht discovers Franz Josef Land after his ship is caught in polar ice and drifts for more than a year. He later becomes an advocate of international polar research.
</Question>
<Choice>1872</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British explorer Verney L. Cameron becomes the first European to cross equatorial Africa from sea to sea. He recovers some of David Livingstone's papers and traces the Congo-Zambezi watershed.
</Question>
<Choice>1875</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Journalist-turned-explorer Henry Morton Stanley descends the Congo River to its mouth, charting its course and dubbing its 220 miles of rapids and cataracts Livingstone Falls.
</Question>
<Choice>1877</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Adolf Erik Nordenskiöld finally conquers the Northeast Passage aboard the Swedish steam vessel Vega.
</Question>
<Choice>1879</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Geophysicist Karl Weyprecht instigates the first International Polar Year, which rejects nationalistic geographic exploration in favour of systematic coordinated observations from stations set up by 10 countries.
</Question>
<Choice>1882</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish naturalist and explorer Joseph Thomson, whose name is given to the eastern African gazelle, completes a Royal Geographical Society expedition to find the shortest route from Zanzibar to Uganda.
</Question>
<Choice>1882</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hungarian Count Sámuel Teleki and Austrian naval officer Ludwig von Höhnel explore the east African highlands, climb Kilimanjaro and Mount Kenya, and discover several lakes and an active volcano named for Teleki.
</Question>
<Choice>1887</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German geographer Hans Meyer ascents to the summit of Kibo, the central cone of Kilimanjaro and the highest point in Africa.
</Question>
<Choice>1889</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Explorer-oceanographer Fridtjof Nansen departs in the specially designed ship Fram to drift in pack ice across the polar basin. In 1895 he leaves the ship to sledge farther north than previous explorers before returning to Norway.
</Question>
<Choice>1893</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Aboard Belgica, Belgian naval officer Adrien de Gerlache explores the west coast of the Antarctic peninsula, inaugurating a new wave of scientific polar exploration and inadvertently wintering in the Bellingshausen Sea.
</Question>
<Choice>1897</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Norwegian Otto Sverdrup leads an Arctic expedition that spends an unprecedented four winters in the north, claiming much land for Norway and accomplishing important scientific work.
</Question>
<Choice>1898</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Southern Cross expedition leaves Carsten Borchgrevink at Cape Adare to spend the first winter on the Antarctic continent.
</Question>
<Choice>1899</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British geographer Halford John Mackinder conquers the summit of Mount Kenya and assumes the first directorship of the Oxford School of Geography.
</Question>
<Choice>1899</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Albert Peter Low commands Neptune on the first Canadian Arctic exploring mission employing science to bolster Canadian claims to sovereignty.
</Question>
<Choice>1903</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Young American mechanics Wilbur and Orville Wright construct the first powered, heavier-than-air aircraft and succeed in flying it over North Carolina's Outer Banks.
</Question>
<Choice>1903</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Norwegian Roald Amundsen becomes the first to navigate the Northwest Passage on the small sloop Gjöa. This accomplishment inspires a lifetime of polar adventuring.
</Question>
<Choice>1903</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Luigi, duke d'Abruzzi and son of King Amadeus of Spain, conquers the summits of the east-central African Ruwenzori Range and conducts a scientific survey, building on his previous achievement of scaling Alaska's Mount St. Elias.
</Question>
<Choice>1906</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On the Nimrod expedition, Ernest H. Shackleton leads a sledging party to within 97 miles of the South Pole and claims Victoria Land Plateau for Britain. Another party from the expedition reaches the magnetic pole.
</Question>
<Choice>1909</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On his third attempt to reach the North Pole, Robert Peary and his African-American associate Matthew Henson reach their goal only to return to news that Frederick Cook, later discredited, claims to have preceded them.
</Question>
<Choice>1909</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roald Amundsen reaches the South Pole on a carefully planned and executed sled-dog journey involving preliminary forays to deposit supplies for his return trip.
</Question>
<Choice>1911</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American historian and archaeologist Hiram Bingham discovers the ancient Inca city of Machu Picchu.
</Question>
<Choice>1911</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British polar explorer Robert Falcon Scott arrives at the South Pole, only to find that Amundsen beat him by a month. He and his party perish during their return trek.
</Question>
<Choice>1912</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The British Imperial Trans-Antarctic Expedition, led by Ernest Shackleton, is stranded on ice floes after its ship is crushed. Six men escape in whaleboats and return to rescue the others.
</Question>
<Choice>1914</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Salvagers recover the submarine F-4 sunk in 306 feet of water off the coast of Honolulu. It is the deepest recovery of an entire vessel to date.
</Question>
<Choice>1915</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German oceanographers in the Meteor begin a series of expeditions to study the South Atlantic Ocean, map the seafloor using sonar, and collect data on salinity and temperature at various depths.
</Question>
<Choice>1925</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Richard Byrd claims to be the first to fly over the North Pole. Evidence from his journal found in 1996 suggests that he did not actually reach it.
</Question>
<Choice>1926</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American explorer Lincoln Ellsworth crosses the North Pole in a dirigible three days after Richard Byrd's flight.
</Question>
<Choice>1926</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In his monoplane Spirit of St. Louis, Charles A. Lindbergh arrives in Paris after accomplishing the first nonstop solo transatlantic flight.
</Question>
<Choice>1927</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
George Hubert Wilkins and copilot C.B. Eielson make the first successful heavier-than-air flight in Antarctica, discovering several new islands.
</Question>
<Choice>1928</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Richard Byrd sets a lasting pattern for overland sledging and aerial reconnaissance to explore Antarctica from a base camp as he prepares to be the first to fly over the South Pole.
</Question>
<Choice>1929</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
William Beebe and Otis Barton, inventors of the bathysphere, dive in it to 3,028 feet off Bermuda.
</Question>
<Choice>1934</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Thirty-four nations participate in the Second International Polar Year, which concentrates its scientific energies in the Arctic regions.
</Question>
<Choice>1932</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nazi Germany mounts the Ritscher expedition to establish German territorial claims in Antarctica.
</Question>
<Choice>1938</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jacques-Yves Cousteau and Émile Gagnan perfect the first practical, automatically-regulated underwater breathing apparatus, opening up the depths for direct exploration by humans.
</Question>
<Choice>1943</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Richard Byrd coordinates the U.S. Navy’s Operation High Jump, a massive enterprise involving 13 ships and 25 airplanes that explores and maps vast stretches of the Antarctic.
</Question>
<Choice>1946</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ethnologist and adventurer Thor Heyerdahl attempts to prove that Easter Island and Hawaii had been settled by ancient people from the Americas by sailing his balsawood raft Kon-Tiki westward from Peru.
</Question>
<Choice>1947</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American pilot Chuck Yeager breaks the sound barrier, flying an experimental X-1 rocket craft. He sets a world speed record of 1,650 miles per hour in 1953.
</Question>
<Choice>1947</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Norwegian-British-Swedish expedition in the Antarctic sets the precedent for modern style and themes of an international scientific research program.
</Question>
<Choice>1949</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
New Zealand mountaineer Edmund Hillary and his Sherpa partner, Tenzing Norgay, reach the summit of Mount Everest. They are the first humans to reach the summit and return.
</Question>
<Choice>1953</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
International Geophysical Year brings big science to Antarctica and inaugurates a geophysical inventory of the continent and oceans and atmosphere surrounding it.
</Question>
<Choice>1957</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In October the Soviet Union shoots into orbit the small satellite Sputnik 1. The United States responds three months later with its own satellite. The space race is on.
</Question>
<Choice>1957</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jacques Piccard and Don Walsh descend to a record 35,800 feet in the submersible Trieste in the Mariana Trench, the deepest area of the seas.
</Question>
<Choice>1960</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Start of the five-year International Indian Ocean Expedition in which three dozen ships from many nations cooperate to investigate currents, biologic productivity, seismology, and geology.
</Question>
<Choice>1960</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Beginning of the ill-starred Mohole Project in which scientists try to drill through the Earth's crust to the mantle.
</Question>
<Choice>1961</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On April 12 Soviet cosmonaut Yury Gagarin becomes the first human to travel in space. His flight aboard a Vostok 1 spacecraft lasts 1 h 29 min.
</Question>
<Choice>1961</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Less than one month after Yury Gagarin's flight, American astronaut Alan B. Shepard, Jr., makes a 15-minute suborbital flight in the Mercury capsule Freedom 7 on May 5.
</Question>
<Choice>1961</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronaut John H. Glenn, Jr., orbits the Earth three times in Friendship 7, splashing down in the Atlantic Ocean near the Bahamas.
</Question>
<Choice>1962</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American inventor Edwin A. Link builds and occupies the first undersea station for 14 hours at a depth of 60 feet.
</Question>
<Choice>1962</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A French crew led by Jacques-Yves Cousteau lives in an underwater habitat for seven days during the Conshelf I program.
</Question>
<Choice>1962</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pilots of the bathyscaphe Trieste locate the wreckage of the American nuclear-powered submarine Thresher, which had sunk four months earlier but fail to determine the cause of the accident.
</Question>
<Choice>1963</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Soviet cosmonaut Valentina Tereshkova becomes the first woman to travel into space. Her Vostok 6 spacecraft is launched on June 16 and spends 71 hours in orbit.
</Question>
<Choice>1963</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Deep-diving submersibles Alvin, Aluminaut, and Cubmarine locate a lost hydrogen bomb in 2,500 feet of water off Spain.
</Question>
<Choice>1966</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The three-man crew of Apollo 1 are the first casualties of the U.S. space program when a flash fire sweeps their space capsule during a launch simulation.
</Question>
<Choice>1967</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Deep-sea drilling voyages of Glomar Challenger, collecting core samples in waters as deep as 20,000 feet, continue through 1983 and revolutionize earth science by supporting the hypothesis of seafloor spreading.
</Question>
<Choice>1968</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Americans Neil A. Armstrong and Edwin E. "Buzz" Aldrin, Jr., become the first humans to walk on the Moon.
</Question>
<Choice>1969</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
First all-woman aquanaut team, including famous scientist-diver Sylvia Earle, lives and works for two weeks in the habitat Tektite II off the U.S. Virgin Islands.
</Question>
<Choice>1970</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Following the launch of the first U.S. space station Skylab, three teams of astronauts spend several months carrying out scientific and medical investigations in space.
</Question>
<Choice>1973</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polynesian crew led by Ben Finney use traditional navigational methods to sail a 62-foot ocean double canoe called Hokulea from Hawaii south to Tahiti.
</Question>
<Choice>1976</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Two unmanned U.S. spacecraft land on Mars and begin investigating its atmosphere and soil. No evidence of life is detected.
</Question>
<Choice>1976</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scientists on the deep-sea submersible Alvin discover clams, crabs, and worms living alongside hot, sulfuric vents in the Mid-Atlantic Ridge.
</Question>
<Choice>1977</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The U.S. inaugurates its space shuttle program featuring the reusable space vehicles, Columbia, Challenger, Discovery, and Atlantis, which are designed to glide to a terrestrial landing.
</Question>
<Choice>1981</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The wreckage of the RMS Titanic is discovered at a depth of about 13,000 feet by a team of oceanographers led by Robert Ballard. The ship had sunk in 1912.
</Question>
<Choice>1985</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The space shuttle Challenger explodes shortly after liftoff, killing its entire crew and delaying the shuttle program for two years.
</Question>
<Choice>1986</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Soviets launch Mir, their third generation of space stations, which provides large and flexible laboratory and living areas in space but is plagued by technical problems.
</Question>
<Choice>1986</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The successful repair of the Hubble Space Telescope ends a year in space exploration otherwise marked by a number of significant failures, most notably the loss of the Mars Observer.
</Question>
<Choice>1993</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Fragments of a recently discovered comet--Shoemaker-Levy 9--crash into Jupiter, causing a spectacular show of tall, vivid plumes. The event creates new interest in astronomy.
</Question>
<Choice>1994</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian ice-core drillers in Antarctica pass 3,100 metres (10,170 feet)--a depth at which the ice is 300,000 years old.
</Question>
<Choice>1995</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The U.S. space shuttle Atlantis docks with the Russian space station Mir, opening a new period of international collaboration in space research and exploration.
</Question>
<Choice>1995</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Japanese submersible Kaiko plants a sign at the bottom of the Mariana Trench, 35,798 feet deep.
</Question>
<Choice>1995</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scientists using images taken by a U.S. Navy satellite in the 1980s produce a new and more accurate map of the ocean seafloor.
</Question>
<Choice>1995</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Oceanographers observe volcanic activity on Loihi Seamount, an underwater volcano 3,280 feet deep.
</Question>
<Choice>1996</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mars Pathfinder's arrival on the Red Planet is the most notable event in space exploration and marks the renaissance in NASA interplanetary missions.
</Question>
<Choice>1997</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Oceanographer Robert Ballard discovers eight ancient ships 760 metres (2,500 feet) underneath an old trade route. The finding gives rise to deep-sea archaeology.
</Question>
<Choice>1997</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scientists at the Los Alamos (N.M.) National Laboratory announce evidence of large quantities of water lying in the sunless craters of the polar regions of Earth's Moon.
</Question>
<Choice>1998</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronaut John Glenn returns to space after a 36-year hiatus. At age 77 he is the oldest human to travel in space.
</Question>
<Choice>1998</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Astronomers observe light from an object 12.2 billion light-years from Earth, the most distant object yet discovered.
</Question>
<Choice>1998</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In July the Liberty Bell 7 is recovered from the Atlantic Ocean. It had sunk in 1961, becoming the only manned spacecraft to have been lost after a successful mission.
</Question>
<Choice>1999</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The U.S. Lunar Prospector is deliberately crashed into the Moon as telescopes watch for spectral signatures unique to water. None are seen, but other data indicates that water is present.
</Question>
<Choice>1999</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The U.S. unmanned satellite Chandra X-ray Observatory is launched, transmitting highly detailed images of the universe, including the Crab Nebula.
</Question>
<Choice>1999</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronomer Geoffrey Marcy continues his search for planets in other solar systems. By the beginning of the 21st century, he and his team have discovered 19 such planets.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In November a three-man crew arrives at the International Space Station, which officials hope will be a permanent habitation in space.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Near Earth Asteroid Rendezvous probe becomes the first spacecraft to land on an asteroid.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scientists report that a meteorite from Mars contains evidence of possible ancient life on the planet.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Russian space station Mir is abandoned and falls into the Pacific Ocean. It had been in service for more than 14 years.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chris A. Hadfield becomes the first Canadian astronaut to walk in space.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Astronomers report that if the universe was viewed from afar, it would appear to be beige in colour.
</Question>
<Choice>2002</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The question whether Pluto should be considered a planet is reexamined after scientists discover a large trans-Neptunian object, a description that some believe best fits Pluto.
</Question>
<Choice>2002</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The U.S. space shuttle Columbia breaks up catastrophically as it returns from a mission. All seven crew members, including an Israeli astronaut, are killed.
</Question>
<Choice>2003</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
China becomes the third country to put a human into space when taikonaut Yang Liwei reaches orbit aboard a Shenzhou 5 rocket.
</Question>
<Choice>2003</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The spacecraft Cassini becomes the first to enter into orbit around Saturn. Its mission, scheduled to last four years, is to study the planet and its ring system and numerous moons.
</Question>
<Choice>2004</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Malaysia announces that it plans to put a man on the Moon by 2020.
</Question>
<Choice>2005</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
After traveling for seven years, the U.S. spacecraft Stardust returns to Earth with comet and interstellar dust particles. Scientists hope the material will offer information on the solar system's origins.
</Question>
<Choice>2006</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The International Astronomical Union removes Pluto from the list of planets and gives it the new classification of dwarf planet.
</Question>
<Choice>2006</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
NASA's Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter sets a record for most scientific data gathered by a Mars spacecraft.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A father and son uncover what is perhaps the largest and most important Viking hoard found in Britian in 150 years. The treasure includes 617 silver coins, a gold armband, and ingots.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sir Edmund Hillary--who, with Sherpa mountaineer Tenzing Norgay, was the first to reach the summit of Mount Everest--dies in New Zealand.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
NASA's Messenger spacecraft records the first photographs of Mercury's previously unseen side. The images reveal that the planet once had volcanic activity.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
China takes the next step toward the completion of a permanent space station when it stages its first successful space walk.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chandrayaan-1, India's first lunar space probe, is launched; it is expected to be in orbit for some two years.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
UNESCO and the International Astronomical Union proclaim this to be the International Year of Astronomy, in celebration of the 400th anniversary of Galileo’s first use of the telescope.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
With the growing popularity of space tourism, Virgin Galactic introduces SpaceShipTwo, the world's first commercial spaceship.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The International Space Station becomes fully operational when its crew increases from three to six.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The U.S. spacecraft LCROSS crashes a Centaur rocket stage near the Moon's south pole. Analysis of the plume thrown up by the impact shows significant amounts of water.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Photos taken by the Mars Reconnaissance Orbiter of new impact craters reveal the presence of water ice underneath the Martian surface.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
After numerous failed attempts to free the Mars Exploration Rover Spirit from a sand pit, NASA announces that the robotic vehicle will become a stationary scientific platform.
</Question>
<Choice>2010</Choice>
</item>
</topics>