topics>
<item>
<Question>
A Babylonian temple in Nippur features rooms of clay tablets, suggesting an early form of library.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 3000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hieroglyphics begin to appear on Egyptian monuments. Combining art with writing, the characters are understood after the decipherment of the Rosetta Stone in the 19th century.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 2925 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ptahhotep becomes widely regarded for his wisdom literature, which includes proverbial sayings that stress humanity and loyalty.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 2400 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Composition begins on the collection of sacred Hindu hymns and verses known as the Vedas.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1500 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Homer, the father of Greek literature, composes (probably relying on oral traditions) his two masterpieces: the Iliad and the Odyssey.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 900 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the only known female poets of the ancient world, classical poet Sappho of Lesbos composes and performs (with a lyre) her sensual poetry.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 600 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Flourishing of the Greek poet Pindar, thought to be the greatest lyric poet of ancient Greece. Seventeen volumes of his poetry survive antiquity.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 475 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Beginning of Greek playwright Sophocles' 62-year career as a successful Athenian dramatist, during which he writes over 120 plays.
</Question>
<Choice>468 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek playwright Aeschylus' Oresteia trilogy (composed of Agamemnon, the Libation Bearers, and the Eumenides) is produced for the annual Athenian Dionysia festival.
</Question>
<Choice>458 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Medea, by Athenian playwright Euripides, is produced. It is the first work of its kind to focus on the artist's feelings of separation and isolation from his audience and the larger world.
</Question>
<Choice>431 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
First staging of Greek playwright Sophocles' most enduring play, Oedipus the King.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 430 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek playwright Aristophanes, the foremost (surviving) comic playwright in ancient Greece, produces his masterpiece Lysistrata.
</Question>
<Choice>411 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek philosopher Aristotle begins (but never completes) Poetics, a defense of poetry against criticism by Plato in The Republic. Poetics is often described as the first work of literary theory.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 320 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ramayana, an epic poem of India, is completed. The classical narrative of the Hindu deity Rama stresses love and harmony.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 300 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A library is established in Alexandria, Egypt, staffed by notable Greek writers and scholars. It becomes the greatest in antiquity, featuring copies of Aristotle's library.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 285 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Parchment is invented in Pergamum. Made from animal skins, it is processed so that both sides can be used.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 190 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Gaius Asinius Pollio uses war booty to build the first public library in Rome.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 39 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Latin poet Virgil leaves his epic poem, the Aeneid, the story of a Trojan prince destined by the gods to found the city of Rome, unfinished at his death.
</Question>
<Choice>19 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Metamorphoses, Roman poet Ovid's brilliant 15-book poetic retelling of many Greek and Roman myths and legends, is completed during Ovid's banishment from Rome.
</Question>
<Choice>8</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Dead Sea Scrolls, which include Jewish psalms, manuals, and commentaries, are composed.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 70</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ts'ai Lun uses tree bark, hemp waste, old rags, and fishnets to develop paper. His apprentice perfects the process, and paper soon spreads throughout the world.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 105</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman bishop of Hippo St. Augustine begins his Confessions, thought to be the first authentic autobiography.
</Question>
<Choice>397</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
European monasteries emerge as important book centres as monks copy manuscripts and later lend them to libraries and other monasteries.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 529</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An illiterate English shepherd named Caedmon composes (orally) his Hymn, which is commonly considered the earliest surviving Old English poem.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 658</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Beowulf, the oldest of the great heroic epics written in English, is believed to have been composed.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 700</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the first written records of Japan, the Kojiki ("Records of Ancient Matters"), offers discussions on the island's history, topography, and literature.
</Question>
<Choice>712</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English historian the Venerable Bede finishes his historical work the Ecclesiastical History of the English People, which contains the story of the poet Caedmon.
</Question>
<Choice>731</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Vercelli book, containing The Dream of the Rood, the finest example of an Old English religious poem, is produced in Italy. Discovered in 1822, the composition's author and date are unknown.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 900</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Exeter Book, containing the largest surviving collection of Old English poetry, including the elegiac lament The Wanderer, is copied and preserved.
</Question>
<Choice>975</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The only manuscript copy of the epic poem Beowulf (Cotton Vitellius A XV) is produced.
</Question>
<Choice>1000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese novelist Lady Shikibu Murasaki, a member of the Japanese court, begins her expansive and complex novel Genji monogatari (The Tale of Genji).
</Question>
<Choice>1001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Norman duke William conquers the British Isles, sparking a radical shift in the English language and fueling a revitalization of literature in England.
</Question>
<Choice>1066</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French poet Marie de France, the first female French poet, completes her lai (a narrative of a magical event) Eliduc (also titled Guildelüec and Guilliadun).
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1180</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Work begins on The Book of Leinster, one of the most important extant Middle Irish collections. It includes heroic tales, poems, and historical accounts.
</Question>
<Choice>1200</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Kamo Chomei, a leading figure in Japanese poetics, writes Hojo-ki ("The Ten Foot Square Hut"), an account of his life in seclusion.
</Question>
<Choice>1212</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Prose Edda, part of the Icelandic Edda, includes tales of Norse myth, told with humour and charm.
</Question>
<Choice>1222</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French poet Guillaume de Lorris writes the opening section of Roman de la Rose, a dream allegory thought to have greatly influenced English poet Geoffrey Chaucer, who translated the poem at the beginning of his career.
</Question>
<Choice>1230</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French bourgeois poet Jean de Meun writes the conclusion to the 21,000-line poem Roman de la Rose.
</Question>
<Choice>1280</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The most revered poem of the Middle Ages, La divina commedia (The Divine Comedy), is completed shortly before the death of Italian divino poeta (divine poet) Dante Alighieri.
</Question>
<Choice>1321</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian poet Petrarch writes his autobiography, Secretum meum ("Petrarch's Secret").
</Question>
<Choice>1342</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The monumental Decameron, consisting of 100 narratives recounting Italian life in medieval times, is completed in Florence by Italian poet Giovanni Boccaccio.
</Question>
<Choice>1353</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English poet Geoffrey Chaucer translates the first 1,705 lines of the popular French poem Roman de la Rose.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1360</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English poet Geoffrey Chaucer produces his first major work, the elegiac poem Book of the Duchess.
</Question>
<Choice>1369</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Having undertaken his first trip to Italy, Chaucer's poetic vision is transformed when he discovers the work of the Italian masters Petrarch, Dante, and Boccaccio.
</Question>
<Choice>1372</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The medieval romance Sir Gawayne and the Grene Knight is composed by an unknown English poet.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1375</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Vision of Piers Plowman, a 4,000-line poem that exists in three distinctly different versions, is written by a poet believed to be William Langland.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1385</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chaucer completes his epic love poem Troilus and Criseyde.
</Question>
<Choice>1385</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Canterbury Tales, Chaucer's most enduring literary work and the project he devotes himself to until his death, is begun in London.
</Question>
<Choice>1387</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English eccentric Julian of Norwich, whose revelations during her 30th year lead to a literary awakening, recounts her many visions of Christ in Revelations of Divine Love.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1390</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The best existing example of a medieval mystery play, the Second Shepherds' Play, is performed for the first time.
</Question>
<Choice>1425</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Considered the first autobiography in the vernacular, The Book of Margery Kempe documents the author's radical viewpoints and many heroic religious pilgrimages.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1434</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Everyman, considered the purest of the many morality plays performed during the Middle Ages, is written from a version of the Dutch play Elckerlyc.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1450</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English writer Sir Thomas Malory finishes Le Morte Darthur, the first English prose account of King Arthur and the fellowship of the Round Table, in prison.
</Question>
<Choice>1470</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Le Morte Darthur is edited and printed by William Caxton, the first English printer.
</Question>
<Choice>1485</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English poet and courtier Stephen Hawes writes The Passetyme of Pleasure.
</Question>
<Choice>1506</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nicolas de la Chesnaye composes the most famous of the French morality plays, Condemnation des banquets.
</Question>
<Choice>1507</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Renaissance Netherlandic scholar Desiderius Erasmus writes his most famous work, Moriae encomium (The Praise of Folly).
</Question>
<Choice>1511</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish Chaucerian William Dunbar ends his service in the court of King James IV. Composer of more than 100 satirical and religious poems, Dunbar's career spans the golden age of Scottish poetry.
</Question>
<Choice>1513</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian statesman and political theorist Niccolò Machiavelli writes his most enduring work, The Prince.
</Question>
<Choice>1513</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English Humanist poet Sir Thomas More publishes his masterpiece (written in Latin), Utopia.
</Question>
<Choice>1516</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sir Thomas More completes his major work in English, History of King Richard III, the first history in English that is also a significant work of literature.
</Question>
<Choice>1518</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English poet John Skelton writes Speke Parrot, the first of his political satires attacking Cardinal Thomas Wolsey. Collyn Clout and Why come ye nat to courte are written the following year.
</Question>
<Choice>1521</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian courtier Baldassare Castiglione publishes his idealization of the court of Urbino, Il libro del cortegiano (The Book of the Courtier).
</Question>
<Choice>1528</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
England achieves a 60% literacy rate owing in part to the introduction (by English printer William Caxton) of the German printing press late in the 15th century.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1530</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English poet Sir Thomas Wyat introduces the sonnet form (a form he modeled after Italian poets such as Petrarch) into English poetry.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1530</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French Renaissance humanist François Rabelais begins publication of his comic four-book series Gargantua and Pantagruel.
</Question>
<Choice>1532</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The bulk of the poetry written by English poet Henry Howard, who invented the "English" sonnet, is published posthumously in Tottel's Miscellany.
</Question>
<Choice>1557</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Queen Elizabeth I's ascension to the throne of England marks the beginning of the prolific literary period named in her honour.
</Question>
<Choice>1558</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English humanist Sir Thomas Hoby completes The Courtyer, his popular translation of Castiglione's Il libro del cortegiano.
</Question>
<Choice>1561</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John Foxe's monumental account of the persecutions of the Protestants, Actes and Monuments of These Latter and Perillous Dayes, is translated by the author from Latin into English.
</Question>
<Choice>1563</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
William Shakespeare, the greatest playwright in all of literature, is born in Stratford-upon-Avon.
</Question>
<Choice>1564</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A translation of Ovid's Metamorphoses into English is completed by prolific English translator Arthur Golding.
</Question>
<Choice>1567</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Queen Elizabeth pens one of her many witty and celebrated poems, "The Doubt of Future Foes."
</Question>
<Choice>1570</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English writer George Gascoigne completes what is considered by some to be the first novel in the English language, The Adventures of Master F.J.
</Question>
<Choice>1573</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English writer John Lyly finishes his wildly popular prose romance, Euphues.
</Question>
<Choice>1578</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English poet Edmund Spenser publishes The Shepheardes Calender, which marks the beginning of the English Renaissance in literature.
</Question>
<Choice>1579</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sir Philip Sidney undertakes a major revision of Arcadia, which is considered the most important original work of prose fiction written during the 16th century.
</Question>
<Choice>1584</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French essayist Michel de Montaigne, pioneer of the personal essay form, publishes all three books of his Essays in a single volume.
</Question>
<Choice>1588</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English lyric poet Samuel Daniel completes his sweet Elizabethan sonnet sequence, Delia.
</Question>
<Choice>1592</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pierce Penilesse, His Supplication to the Divell, a critical satire of many social issues, is published by English playwright, novelist, and poet Thomas Nashe.
</Question>
<Choice>1592</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English playwright Christopher Marlowe, whose Dr. Faustus and other plays introduce blank verse into English literature, is killed under mysterious circumstances.
</Question>
<Choice>1593</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
William Shakespeare publishes his erotic mythological poem dedicated to the earl of Southampton, Venus and Adonis.
</Question>
<Choice>1593</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
William Shakespeare writes Romeo and Juliet, one of his earliest and most enduring tragedies.
</Question>
<Choice>1594</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English poet Edmund Spenser publishes his complex wedding poem Epithalamion.
</Question>
<Choice>1595</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The major piece of criticism written by Sir Philip Sidney, The Defence of Poesie, is published posthumously.
</Question>
<Choice>1595</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The 6 books (of a proposed 12; the final 6 remained unfinished at his death) of Edmund Spenser's epic romance The Faerie Queene are published together in a single volume.
</Question>
<Choice>1596</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British philosopher Sir Francis Bacon, one of the great masters of English prose, publishes the first edition of his Essays.
</Question>
<Choice>1597</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first account of Shakespeare's work appears in Francis Meres' critical study comparing English and classical poets, Palladis Tamia: Wits Treasury.
</Question>
<Choice>1598</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English poet Mary Sidney Herbert writes To the Thrice-Sacred Queen Elizabeth, a dedication of the 150-psalm sequence her brother Sir Philip Sidney began translating into English and she completed.
</Question>
<Choice>1599</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
William Shakespeare completes Hamlet, one of his four greatest tragedies. The others, Othello, King Lear, and Macbeth, are written between 1600 and 1606.
</Question>
<Choice>1600</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The most famous of English poet Robert Southwell's lyric poems, The Burning Babe, is published.
</Question>
<Choice>1602</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English essayist Samuel Daniel completes his contribution to the Elizabethan critical debate about poetry, The Defence of Rhyme.
</Question>
<Choice>1603</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish novelist Miguel de Cervantes obtains official license for the publication of Part I of his adventure novel Don Quixote.
</Question>
<Choice>1604</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Volpone and The Alchemist, English playwright Ben Jonson's most successful satiric comedies, are written and performed between 1606 and 1610.
</Question>
<Choice>1606</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Shakespeare's cycle of 154 sonnets is published, bringing the English (later referred to as Shakespearean) sonnet to its maturest and most popular form.
</Question>
<Choice>1609</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Two of Shakespeare's most experimental and original plays, The Winter's Tale and The Tempest, are completed and staged in London during the 1610-11 season.
</Question>
<Choice>1610</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English mystic Aemilia Lanyer pioneers a pattern of feminist mythmaking in her work Salve Deus Rex Judaeorum, which includes a retelling of the biblical "fall" of man from Eve's perspective.
</Question>
<Choice>1611</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English poet Michael Drayton begins his most ambitious work, the 30,000-line geographical history poem Poly-Olbion. It is completed in 1622.
</Question>
<Choice>1612</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English playwright John Webster's dark tragedy, The Duchess of Malfi, is first performed.
</Question>
<Choice>1613</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English explorer Sir Walter Raleigh begins work on his History of the World while imprisoned in the Tower of London. It remains unfinished at his death.
</Question>
<Choice>1614</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English Jacobean dramatist and poet Ben Jonson publishes The Works of Benjamin Jonson, the first complete collection of an author's work published in English.
</Question>
<Choice>1616</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Persiles and Sigismunda, the last novel of Spanish writer Miguel de Cervantes, is published posthumously.
</Question>
<Choice>1617</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Countess of Montgomery's Urania, English writer Lady Mary Worth's controversial prose romance, is published to a storm of negative criticism.
</Question>
<Choice>1621</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English playwright Thomas Middleton writes (with William Rowley) one of his two tragic masterpieces, The Changeling.
</Question>
<Choice>1622</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John Heminge and Henry Condell, members of Shakespeare's company, compile and publish the First Folio, which contains "the most finished version" of each of Shakespeare's plays.
</Question>
<Choice>1623</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Three years after he is appointed dean of Saint Paul's Cathedral, British priest and metaphysical poet John Donne's private devotions are published.
</Question>
<Choice>1624</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The General History of Virginia, one of the first texts to be published in the New World, is completed by John Smith.
</Question>
<Choice>1624</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pioneer John Winthrop begins his extensive Journal of John Winthrop, documenting his life in New England.
</Question>
<Choice>1630</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Poems, the complete collection of John Donne's poetry, is published for the first time; it is revised by the author in 1635.
</Question>
<Choice>1633</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English poetic master John Milton contributes his famous elegy Lycidas to a collection memorializing one of his college classmates.
</Question>
<Choice>1637</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Life and Death of Dr. Donne is written by English biographer Izaak Walton to be published alongside a collection of Donne's sermons.
</Question>
<Choice>1640</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The only work by English lyric poet Robert Herrick, a 1,400-poem volume titled Hesperides, is published. It quickly vanishes into obscurity.
</Question>
<Choice>1648</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English Cavalier poet Richard Lovelace publishes his gently moralistic collection of poems, Lucasta.
</Question>
<Choice>1649</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first poetry collection written in the New World, Anne Bradstreet's The Tenth Muse Lately Sprung Up in America, is published in London.
</Question>
<Choice>1650</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Silex Scintillans, a large collection of sacred poems by Welshman Henry Vaughan, gives a final voice to the medieval doctrine of mystic correspondence.
</Question>
<Choice>1650</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British philosopher Thomas Hobbes, Francis Bacon's pupil and one of the greatest philosophers of the 17th century, publishes Leviathan, one of the great works of political philosophy.
</Question>
<Choice>1651</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of English poet Margaret Cavendish's many eclectic poetry collections, Poems and Fancies, is published.
</Question>
<Choice>1653</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English naval administrator Samuel Pepys begins his Diary, one of the most comprehensive and detailed portraits of English society during the Restoration.
</Question>
<Choice>1660</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American pastor Michael Wigglesworth publishes one of the most widely read poems in early New England, The Day of Doom.
</Question>
<Choice>1662</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John Milton publishes Paradise Lost, his masterpiece "justifying the ways of God to men."
</Question>
<Choice>1667</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The greatest writer of French comedy, Molière performs his comic masterpiece, Le Misanthrope.
</Question>
<Choice>1667</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British poet John Dryden is made poet laureate of England.
</Question>
<Choice>1668</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Forced Marriage, by English female writer (and former spy) Aphra Behn makes its debut on the London stage.
</Question>
<Choice>1671</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Pilgrim's greatest work and the most successful allegory in the English language, is written while Bunyan is in prison.
</Question>
<Choice>1678</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English poet Andrew Marvell's collected works, Miscellaneous Poems, is published three years after his death.
</Question>
<Choice>1681</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pioneer Mary Rowlandson records her experience as an Indian prisoner in A Narrative of the Captivity and Restoration of Mrs. Mary Rowlandson.
</Question>
<Choice>1682</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Preparatory Meditations, considered to be American poet Edward Taylor's strongest verse, is penned in New England.
</Question>
<Choice>1682</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English writer Aphra Behn, the first professional woman writer in the English language, finishes her most famous novel, Oroonoko, about an enslaved African prince.
</Question>
<Choice>1688</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese haiku poet Matsuo Basho, the greatest of the haiku masters, publishes his travel journal of northern Japan, Oku no hosomichi (The Narrow Road to the Deep North).
</Question>
<Choice>1694</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English writer Mary Astell writes her most famous work, A Serious Proposal to the Ladies.
</Question>
<Choice>1694</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Way of the World, considered by many to be the wittiest play ever written, is completed by British playwright William Congreve.
</Question>
<Choice>1700</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English Poet John Dryden publishes Fables Ancient and Modern, a collection of translations of works by Ovid, Boccaccio, and Chaucer containing one of his most astute critical essays.
</Question>
<Choice>1700</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American pastor Cotton Mather writes his famous series of sermon-essays, Magnalia Christi Americana ("A History of the Wonderful Works of Christ in America").
</Question>
<Choice>1702</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American writer Sarah Kemble Knight begins her Private Journal. Considered a classic of early American literature, it remains unpublished until 1825.
</Question>
<Choice>1704</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British writer and editor Sir Richard Steele founds the famous London newspaper, The Tatler. Joseph Addison later joins Steele in editing the newspaper.
</Question>
<Choice>1709</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Addison and Steele found The Spectator after The Tatler closes. Its contributors include Alexander Pope, Thomas Tickell, and Ambrose Philips.
</Question>
<Choice>1711</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English satirist Alexander Pope publishes the first version of his ingenious satirical poem, The Rape of the Lock.
</Question>
<Choice>1712</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British poet Anne Finch publishes her first collection of "country" poems, Miscellany Poems on Several Occasions, Written by a Lady.
</Question>
<Choice>1713</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English novelist Daniel Defoe publishes Robinson Crusoe, the first and most famous of his series of adventure tales.
</Question>
<Choice>1719</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English novelist Jonathan Swift's misanthropic masterpiece, the satirical novel Gulliver's Travels, is published to a wealth of critical success and controversy.
</Question>
<Choice>1726</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English poet-playwright John Gay publishes his famous ballad-opera The Beggar's Opera, considered the greatest theatrical success of the 18th century.
</Question>
<Choice>1728</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A masterpiece of mock-heroic verse, Alexander Pope's The Dunciad is published anonymously in three books.
</Question>
<Choice>1728</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jonathan Swift publishes A Modest Proposal, one of the most successful satires in the English language.
</Question>
<Choice>1729</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English poet James Thomson, the most popular nature poet of the 18th century, publishes the first collected edition of The Seasons.
</Question>
<Choice>1730</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American printer Benjamin Franklin begins his long, visionary career as the sole owner of a thriving print shop and the editor and publisher of the Pennsylvania Gazette.
</Question>
<Choice>1730</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The only complete manuscript version of the Old English poem Beowulf and the original manuscript of the epic poem The Battle of Maldon are damaged during a fire in the archives of Sir Robert Bruce Cotton.
</Question>
<Choice>1731</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English novelist Samuel Richardson publishes his epistolary novel Pamela: or, Virtue Rewarded.
</Question>
<Choice>1740</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Puritan minister Jonathan Edwards delivers his famous sermon Sinners in the Hands of an Angry God to a congregation in Enfield, Connecticut.
</Question>
<Choice>1741</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English novelist Henry Fielding publishes An Apology for the life of Mrs. Shamela Andrews, his parody of Samuel Richardson's prudish epistolary novel Pamela.
</Question>
<Choice>1741</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese haiku poet Yosa Buson, known for his ephemeral verse, eulogizes one of his former masters in Hokuju Rosen o itamu ("Mourning for Hokuju Rosen").
</Question>
<Choice>1745</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English lyric poet William Collins, a poet later much admired by the English Romantics, publishes his Odes on Several Descriptive and Allegorical Subjects.
</Question>
<Choice>1746</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Clarissa: or, The History of a Young Lady, English novelist Samuel Richardson's epistolary masterpiece, is revised and completed.
</Question>
<Choice>1747</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English essayist and poet Samuel Johnson begins compiling his monumental Dictionary of the English Language.
</Question>
<Choice>1747</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English poet Thomas Gray publishes Elegy Written in a Country Churchyard, his most enduring work.
</Question>
<Choice>1751</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French writer Voltaire publishes his best-known work, Candide, a satirical novel denouncing metaphysical optimism.
</Question>
<Choice>1759</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English novelist Laurence Sterne begins work on his multivolumed, humorous novel, Tristram Shandy.
</Question>
<Choice>1759</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American statesman, inventor, and writer Benjamin Franklin begins work on his famous Autobiography. Completed in 1788, it would remain unpublished until 1868.
</Question>
<Choice>1771</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish natural historian William Smellie completes publication of the first edition of the Encyclopædia Britannica in three volumes in Edinburgh.
</Question>
<Choice>1771</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Common Sense, the first pamphlet published in America that strongly supported independence from England, is published anonymously by American radical Thomas Paine.
</Question>
<Choice>1776</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Evelina, English novelist Fanny Burney's first and most influential novel, is published anonymously when she is 26.
</Question>
<Choice>1778</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first section of English poet Samuel Johnson's Lives of the Poets, is completed and published. The second is finished in 1781.
</Question>
<Choice>1779</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Letters From an American Farmer, a series of essays about life in America by Frenchman St. Jean de Crèvecoeur, is published in London.
</Question>
<Choice>1782</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English poet William Cowper, known for his placid poetry in the face of his sporadic bouts with insanity, undertakes his masterpiece, The Task.
</Question>
<Choice>1785</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Poems on Various Subjects is published in the United States by former slave and poet Phillis Wheatley.
</Question>
<Choice>1786</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American statesmen Alexander Hamilton, John Jay, and James Madison anonymously publish 85 essays advocating the new Constitution of the United States. They are later published as The Federalist.
</Question>
<Choice>1787</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The most famous biographer in the English language, British writer James Boswell, publishes The Life of Samuel Johnson, L.L.D.
</Question>
<Choice>1791</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English essayist Mary Wollstonecraft's most famous book of criticism, A Vindication of the Rights of Woman, breaks new ground with its feminist strength and passion.
</Question>
<Choice>1792</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English intellectual Thomas Paine publishes The Age of Reason, a series of essays written to give voice to Paine's overall philosophy of life. It is immediately attacked as anti-Christian.
</Question>
<Choice>1794</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Early Romantic British poet William Blake publishes his poetry collection Songs of Innocence and Experience.
</Question>
<Choice>1794</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The German encyclopaedia Konversationslexikon publishes its first volume. Friedrich Arnold Brockhaus buys the copyright in 1808, and the title is changed to Brockhaus Enzyklopädie.
</Question>
<Choice>1796</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English Romantic poets William Wordsworth and Samuel Taylor Coleridge publish the single most important collection of poems and essays in English literature, Lyrical Ballads.
</Question>
<Choice>1798</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The U.S. Library of Congress is founded. The largest national library, it houses extensive collections of books and manuscripts, as well as recordings and motion pictures.
</Question>
<Choice>1800</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
William Wordsworth publishes the majority of his groundbreaking Romantic verse in Poems in Two Volumes.
</Question>
<Choice>1807</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English novelist Jane Austen, author of the first modern novels in the English language, publishes Sense and Sensibility.
</Question>
<Choice>1811</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Samuel Taylor Coleridge publishes Biographia Literaria, which documents the philosophical influences that led to the Romantic awakening.
</Question>
<Choice>1817</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English novelist Mary Shelley, daughter of Mary Wollstonecraft and William Godwin and wife of Percy Bysshe Shelley, publishes her classic Frankenstein.
</Question>
<Choice>1818</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English Romantic poet George Gordon, Lord Byron, begins his masterpiece, the satire against modern civilization Don Juan.
</Question>
<Choice>1818</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese haiku poet Issa, known for the lyrical quality of his haiku, publishes one of his most enduring works, Oraga haru (The Year of My Life).
</Question>
<Choice>1819</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English Romantic poet Percy Bysshe Shelley completes his most famous work, Prometheus Unbound.
</Question>
<Choice>1819</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The growth of the middle classes, rising literacy rates, and increased leisure time in Europe and America contribute to the flourishing of the market in specialized magazines.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1820</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Shortly before his death, English Romantic poet John Keats publishes the volume that contains much of his most enduring work, Lamia, Isabella, The Eve of St. Agnes, and Other Poems.
</Question>
<Choice>1820</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Shelley writes Adonais, an elegy on the death of fellow Romantic poet John Keats.
</Question>
<Choice>1821</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Samuel Pepys publishes his Diary, an insightful and often humorous account of Restoration England. At more than 1,250,000 words, it fills six quarto volumes.
</Question>
<Choice>1825</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English poet Alfred, Lord Tennyson, publishes his youthful poetry collection Poems, Chiefly Lyrical, which contains much of his best early verse.
</Question>
<Choice>1831</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French novelist Victor Hugo gains fame with his historical novel Notre-Dame de Paris (The Hunchback of Notre Dame).
</Question>
<Choice>1831</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Tennyson's life changed drastically upon the death of his closest friend, Arthur Henry Hallam; his masterpiece, In Memoriam (1850), is a prolonged, poignant eulogy for Hallam.
</Question>
<Choice>1833</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Victoria is crowned Queen of England, marking the beginning of the Victorian period of English literature.
</Question>
<Choice>1837</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Innovations in printing technology and growth of large urban reading publics in Western Europe and America contribute to the rising popularity of the newspaper.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1840</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American surveyor William Byrd's History of the Dividing Line, written from a diary he kept during a survey of Virginia and North Carolina in 1728, is published after years in private circulation.
</Question>
<Choice>1841</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American poet and master of the macabre, Edgar Allan Poe, publishes the first detective story, The Murders in the Rue Morgue.
</Question>
<Choice>1841</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Victorian essayist and art critic John Ruskin publishes the first volume of his elaborate philosophical position on aesthetics, Modern Painters.
</Question>
<Choice>1843</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English historian and social critic Thomas Carlyle publishes his famous grouping of essays, Past and Present.
</Question>
<Choice>1843</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Edgar Allan Poe publishes his famous poetry collection The Raven and Other Poems.
</Question>
<Choice>1845</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American essayist Margaret Fuller writes her sermonlike treatise on the plight of women in early Victorian England, Woman in the Nineteenth Century.
</Question>
<Choice>1845</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English novelist, intellectual, and translator George Eliot completes her translation of David Friedrich Strauss's Das Leben Jesu kritisch bearbeitet (The Life of Jesus Critically Examined).
</Question>
<Choice>1846</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French novelist George Sand publishes her first rustic novel, La Mare au diable (The Devil's Pool).
</Question>
<Choice>1846</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English novelist Charlotte Brontë publishes the powerful narrative Jane Eyre.
</Question>
<Choice>1847</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English novelist Emily Brontë publishes her only novel, the gothic romance Wuthering Heights.
</Question>
<Choice>1847</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Vanity Fair, Indian-born English novelist William Makepeace Thackeray's intricate Victorian novel, is published to much critical acclaim.
</Question>
<Choice>1848</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Realism, an artistic movement begun in the arts by French painter Gustave Courbet, reaches French literature, influencing the work of Balzac, Flaubert, and the brothers Goncourt.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1850</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The most prolific and most talented of all the British Victorian novelists, Charles Dickens, publishes David Copperfield. He quickly follows with Bleak House (1853) and Hard Times (1854).
</Question>
<Choice>1850</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American novelist Nathaniel Hawthorne completes his moralistic masterpiece, The Scarlet Letter.
</Question>
<Choice>1850</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Alfred, Lord Tennyson, is appointed poet laureate for Britain.
</Question>
<Choice>1850</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American author Herman Melville publishes Moby Dick, his masterpiece and one of the most influential novels in American literature.
</Question>
<Choice>1851</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American novelist Harriet Beecher Stowe publishes Uncle Tom's Cabin; or, Life Among the Lowly. The novel helps turn American public opinion against slavery.
</Question>
<Choice>1852</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English novelist Elizabeth (Cleghorn) Gaskell writes her charmingly comic satirical novel Cranford.
</Question>
<Choice>1853</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English poet and scholar Matthew Arnold finishes the preface to and publishes a collection of his best early poetry, Poems.
</Question>
<Choice>1853</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Walt Whitman, arguably the most influential American poet and the "grandfather" of Modernism, publishes his revolutionary collection Leaves of Grass.
</Question>
<Choice>1855</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Men and Women, English poet Robert Browning's most memorable volume of poetry, is published while he is living in Italy.
</Question>
<Choice>1855</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English poet Elizabeth Barrett Browning (wife of Robert Browning) publishes her epic verse novel, Aurora Leigh.
</Question>
<Choice>1856</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French realist Gustave Flaubert publishes his racy, enduring novel, Madame Bovary.
</Question>
<Choice>1857</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Elizabeth Gaskell writes her reverent biography of Charlotte Brontë, Life of Charlotte Brontë.
</Question>
<Choice>1857</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French poet Charles Baudelaire is brought to trial for "offenses against religious morals" resulting from his recently published collection of verse, Les Fleurs du mal (The flowers of evil).
</Question>
<Choice>1857</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English naturalist Charles Darwin publishes his Origin of the Species. The book influences literature and criticism for the remainder of the 19th century.
</Question>
<Choice>1859</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British philosopher and social critic John Stuart Mill publishes his classic treatise attacking tyranny, On Liberty.
</Question>
<Choice>1859</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English translator Edward FitzGerald publishes his version of the 12th-century Persian poem The Rubáiyát of Omar Khayyám.
</Question>
<Choice>1859</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English Pre-Raphaelite painter and poet Dante Gabriel Rossetti (brother of Christina Rossetti) publishes his book of translations, The Early Italian Poets.
</Question>
<Choice>1861</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English poet Christina Rossetti publishes her first collection of verse, Goblin Market and Other Poems.
</Question>
<Choice>1862</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian novelist Leo Tolstoy publishes his epic historical novel, War and Peace.
</Question>
<Choice>1863</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British poet and playwright Algernon Charles Swinburne completes his earliest and most Greek-influenced play, Atalanta in Calydon.
</Question>
<Choice>1865</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British writer and mathematician Lewis Carroll completes his unique, multileveled novel, Alice in Wonderland.
</Question>
<Choice>1865</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian novelist Fyodor Mikhaylovich Dostoyevsky publishes his psychological thriller Crime and Punishment. It and his other works establish him as one of the century's most important novelists.
</Question>
<Choice>1866</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Robert Browning publishes his greatest single poem, The Ring and the Book, during the prolific period that follows the death of his wife, Elizabeth.
</Question>
<Choice>1868</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Little Women, American novelist Louisa May Alcott's high-spirited autobiographical novel, is published, bringing immediate fame to its author.
</Question>
<Choice>1869</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Charles Dickens leaves his last novel, The Mystery of Edwin Drood, unfinished at his death.
</Question>
<Choice>1870</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Norwegian poet, novelist, and playwright Bjørnstjerne Martinius Bjørnson publishes his epic poem, Arnljot Gelline.
</Question>
<Choice>1870</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
George Eliot begins publication of Middlemarch, considered by many to be the best novel written during the Victorian era.
</Question>
<Choice>1871</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American writer and critic Mark Twain finishes his enduring classic Tom Sawyer. He begins The Adventures of Huckleberry Finn the same year.
</Question>
<Choice>1876</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American novelist Henry James completes the first of his three writing periods with the distinctively international novel The Portrait of a Lady.
</Question>
<Choice>1881</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American educator F.J. Child publishes The English and Scottish Popular Ballads, the greatest collection of early ballads (anonymous narrative songs) ever compiled.
</Question>
<Choice>1882</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American writer Sarah Orne Jewett publishes one of her many delicate collections of short stories, A White Heron, and Other Stories.
</Question>
<Choice>1886</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish writer Arthur Conan Doyle publishes A Study in Scarlet, introducing the immortal detectives Sherlock Holmes and Dr. Watson.
</Question>
<Choice>1887</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first "little magazines," avant-garde journals of fiction, poetry, and criticism often associated with specific movements, are published in France.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1890</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Poems by Emily Dickinson, a posthumous collection edited by Mabel Loomis Todd and T.W. Higginson, is published. The enterprise of publishing Dickinson's 1,775 poems continues until 1955.
</Question>
<Choice>1890</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Norwegian playwright Henrik Ibsen produces his puzzling, uniquely satirical play Hedda Gabler.
</Question>
<Choice>1890</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American feminist writer Charlotte Perkins Gilman writes her infamous short story of postpartem "fog" and helplessness, "The Yellow Wall Paper."
</Question>
<Choice>1892</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian-born English writer Rudyard Kipling finishes his multileveled Jungle Books; he goes on to become the first English author to receive the Nobel Prize for Literature (1907).
</Question>
<Choice>1895</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British playwright Oscar Wilde writes his famous comedy The Importance of Being Earnest.
</Question>
<Choice>1895</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English rural novelist Thomas Hardy's period as a novelist ends with the publication of his greatest, darkest work, Jude the Obscure.
</Question>
<Choice>1896</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Thomas Hardy publishes his first collection of poetry, Wessex Poems.
</Question>
<Choice>1898</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American novelist Kate Chopin publishes The Awakening, a frankly feminist novella of a late-19th-century woman's emotional and sexual "awakening."
</Question>
<Choice>1899</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American novelist Theodore Dreiser completes his resonant first novel, Sister Carrie.
</Question>
<Choice>1900</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British writer Joseph Conrad publishes his complex and still-controversial novella Heart of Darkness, which recounts his experiences on the Congo River.
</Question>
<Choice>1902</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian playwright Anton Chekhov composes his last play, The Cherry Orchard, which is first performed the following year in Moscow.
</Question>
<Choice>1903</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American novelist, poet, and essayist Edith Wharton completes one of her earliest and most enduring novels, The House of Mirth.
</Question>
<Choice>1905</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American novelist and social critic Upton Sinclair publishes his proletarian masterpiece and exposé of the Chicago meatpacking industry, The Jungle.
</Question>
<Choice>1906</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Beginning of the Bloomsbury group, a circle of artists, writers, and critics whose members include Clive and Vanessa Bell, Virginia Woolf, E.M. Forster, Lytton Strachey, and John Maynard Keynes.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1907</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian-Hungarian lyric poet Rainer Maria Rilke begins publishing the fruits of his new style of lyric poetry, Ding-Gedicht ("object poem"), in his collection Neue Gedichte ("New Poems").
</Question>
<Choice>1907</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French writer and moralist André Gide cofounds La Nouvelle Revue Française, one of the most important literary magazines in pre-World War II France.
</Question>
<Choice>1908</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American expatriate poet Ezra Pound, often called the "poet's poet" because of his marked influence on 20th-century literature, publishes his first collection, A lume spento, in Venice.
</Question>
<Choice>1908</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Futurist Manifesto, by Italian poet and editor Filippo Tommaso Marinetti, is published in Italy. Futurism becomes an important movement in the arts and literature in Italy and Russia.
</Question>
<Choice>1909</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Chicago literary renaissance, a circle whose members include Carl Sandburg, Theodore Dreiser, Vachel Lindsay, and Sherwood Anderson, flourishes in poetry, fiction, and journalism.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1912</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French novelist Marcel Proust finishes the first draft of his seven-part autobiographical novel, À la recherche du temps perdu (Remembrance of Things Past).
</Question>
<Choice>1912</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American woman of letters Harriet Monroe begins editing Poetry magazine, which makes its reputation publishing avant-garde Modernist poets such as Ezra Pound, D.H. Lawrence, and Hilda Doolittle.
</Question>
<Choice>1912</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American poet Robert Frost's first poetry collection, A Boy's Will, is published in London with the support of such Modernist poets as Ezra Pound. North of Boston appears the following year.
</Question>
<Choice>1913</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Bengali poet and short-story writer Rabindranath Tagore wins the Nobel Prize for Literature.
</Question>
<Choice>1913</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Irish playwright and literary critic George Bernard Shaw produces his humane romantic comedy Pygmalion in German in Vienna.
</Question>
<Choice>1914</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Henry James completes the last of many collections of critical essays, Note on Novelists.
</Question>
<Choice>1914</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Prolific and gifted Irish writer James Joyce publishes his short-story collection Dubliners. His short novel A Portrait of the Artist as a Young Man is published in 1916.
</Question>
<Choice>1914</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English novelist D.H. Lawrence publishes his first Modernist novel, The Rainbow.
</Question>
<Choice>1915</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Czech novelist Franz Kafka publishes his novella The Metamorphosis, the story of Gregor Samsa, a man who wakes up one morning to find himself transformed into a beetle.
</Question>
<Choice>1915</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American frontier novelist Willa Cather finishes her first novel focusing on the plight of the artist, The Song of the Lark.
</Question>
<Choice>1915</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Eugene O'Neill makes his debut as a playwright with Bound East for Cardiff. O'Neill goes on to become one of the century's best-known playwrights, winning the Nobel Prize for literature in 1936.
</Question>
<Choice>1916</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Tendencies in Modern American Poetry, Imagist poet Amy Lowell's collection of critical essays, is published and widely circulated.
</Question>
<Choice>1917</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American dramatist and poet Edna St. Vincent Millay publishes her fresh, romantic first collection of poems, Renascence and Other Poems.
</Question>
<Choice>1917</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English poet Siegfried Sassoon publishes Counterattack, a collection of antiwar poems drawing on his experiences fighting in France.
</Question>
<Choice>1918</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English poet Wilfred Owen, author of some of the best poems detailing the experience of combat in World War I, is killed on November 4, a week before Armistice Day.
</Question>
<Choice>1918</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American novelist Sherwood Anderson publishes Winesburg, Ohio, an account of small-town life in the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1919</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Beginning of the Harlem Renaissance, a flourishing of African-American arts, letters, and music. Its members include James Weldon Johnson, Langston Hughes, Claude McKay, and Zora Neale Hurston.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1920</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sinclair Lewis' Main Street establishes his reputation as a leading American writer. He follows with Babbitt (1922) and Arrowsmith (1925) and wins the Nobel Prize for Literature in 1930.
</Question>
<Choice>1920</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Langston Hughes, African-American poet and a leading interpreter of the black experience in the United States, publishes his first poem, The Negro Speaks of Rivers.
</Question>
<Choice>1921</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Waste Land, American Modernist poet T.S. Eliot's most famous and most complex poem, is published to a wealth of praise.
</Question>
<Choice>1922</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American poet E.E. Cummings publishes his first work, a novel entitled The Enormous Room.
</Question>
<Choice>1922</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
James Joyce's definitive Modernist masterpiece Ulysses, which recounts one day (June 16, 1904) in the lives of Stephen Dedalus, Leopold Bloom, and Molly Bloom, is published in Paris.
</Question>
<Choice>1922</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Fugitives, a group of distinguished Southern writers under the leadership of John Crowe Ransom, forms at Vanderbilt University in Nashville, Tenn.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1922</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
African-American writer Jean Toomer publishes his only book of note, Cane, a unique collection of powerfully sexual poems, prose pieces, and short stories.
</Question>
<Choice>1923</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American lyric poet William Carlos Williams publishes his collection of fresh poems and prose statements, Spring and All.
</Question>
<Choice>1923</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British novelist and literary critic E.M. Forster publishes his masterpiece, A Passage to India.
</Question>
<Choice>1924</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chilean expatriate poet Pablo Neruda publishes his most widely read poetry collection,Veinte poemas de amor y una canción desesperada (Twenty Love Poems and a Song of Despair).
</Question>
<Choice>1924</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German novelist Thomas Mann publishes his great novel The Magic Mountain. He wins the Nobel Prize for Literature in 1929.
</Question>
<Choice>1924</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American novelist F. Scott Fitzgerald publishes his enduring story of East Egg and West Egg (modeled after Manhattan and Long Island), The Great Gatsby.
</Question>
<Choice>1925</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British author Virginia Woolf completes one of her most lyrical, brilliant novels, Mrs. Dalloway. To The Lighthouse and Orlando are published in 1927 and 1928.
</Question>
<Choice>1925</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British translator Arthur Waley begins his classic translation of Lady Shikibu Murasaki's novel, The Tale of Genji. The project is completed in 1933.
</Question>
<Choice>1925</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American New Critic and Fugitive poet Allen Tate writes his most famous poem, Ode to the Confederate Dead.
</Question>
<Choice>1926</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American radical writer Dorothy Parker publishes her first collection of verse, the smash success Enough Rope.
</Question>
<Choice>1926</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Publisher Hugo Gernsback founds science-fiction magazine Amazing Stories. During the 1930s the magazine helps establish the genre as a serious (albeit popular) form of literature.
</Question>
<Choice>1926</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German writer Hermann Hesse publishes his famous novel Steppenwolf, which, like his other novels, is strongly influenced by Eastern philosophy. He wins the Nobel Prize for Literature in 1946.
</Question>
<Choice>1927</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
African-American poet and editor Countee Cullen edits one of the most important early collections of verse by African-Americans, Caroling Dusk.
</Question>
<Choice>1927</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Virginia Woolf publishes her oft-quoted long essay on the hardships encountered by women writing in a man's world, A Room of One's Own.
</Question>
<Choice>1929</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first "hard-boiled" detective story, Dashiell Hammett's "Fly Paper," is published in Black Mask magazine.
</Question>
<Choice>1929</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German novelist Erich Maria Remarque publishes his classic World War I novel, All Quiet on the Western Front.
</Question>
<Choice>1929</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English war poet Siegfried Sassoon publishes his classic account of his experiences as a soldier during World War I in Memoirs of an Infantry Officer.
</Question>
<Choice>1930</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American novelist Dashiell Hammett publishes his masterpiece of "hard-boiled" fiction, The Maltese Falcon. The film version, starring Humphrey Bogart, becomes a cinema classic.
</Question>
<Choice>1930</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American poet Horace Gregory achieves his first critical success with the avant-garde collection Chelsea Rooming House.
</Question>
<Choice>1930</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American writer Pearl Buck publishes The Good Earth, the first of her several novels dealing with life in China. She wins the Nobel Prize for Literature in 1938.
</Question>
<Choice>1931</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Irish poet William Butler Yeats publishes some of his most seasoned and perceptive verse in one of his last collections, The Winding Stair.
</Question>
<Choice>1933</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Eccentric American writer Gertrude Stein--who completes most of her important works while in Paris--finishes her first commercial success, The Autobiography of Alice B. Toklas.
</Question>
<Choice>1933</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The U.S. Works Progress Administration starts the Federal Writers' Project, which produces an important series of travel guides and supports the work of such writers as Ralph Ellison and Saul Bellow.
</Question>
<Choice>1935</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese Neosensualist writer Kawabata Yasunari begins work on his novel Yukiguni (Snow Country), completing the book in 1948. He wins the Nobel Prize for Literature in 1968.
</Question>
<Choice>1935</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Absalom, Absalom!, Southern novelist William Faulkner's masterpiece, is completed but soon falls out of print. When rediscovered, it is hailed as the best American novel of the 20th century.
</Question>
<Choice>1936</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Danish writer Isak Dinesen publishes her autobiographical novel about her life in the African Ngong hills, Out of Africa.
</Question>
<Choice>1937</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
African-American author Zora Neale Hurston publishes her masterpiece, Their Eyes Were Watching God. The novel goes out of print and is not rediscovered until the 1970s.
</Question>
<Choice>1937</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American science-fiction writer John Campbell becomes editor of Astounding Stories, developing a reputation as the father of modern American science fiction.
</Question>
<Choice>1937</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Flourishing of the Negritude movement, a searching critique of European colonialism led by African writer Léopold Sédar Senghor and Caribbean writers Aimé Césaire and Léon Damas.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1939</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American novelist Raymond Chandler's The Big Sleep introduces detective Philip Marlowe and helps establish the "hard-boiled" detective novel as a serious literary form.
</Question>
<Choice>1939</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Martinique poet Aimé Césaire publishes his Cahier d'un retour au pays natal (Return to My Native Land), one of the most significant poetry works of the Negritude movement.
</Question>
<Choice>1939</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
African-American novelist Richard Wright completes his unique novel, Native Son.
</Question>
<Choice>1940</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American minimalist novelist Ernest Hemingway publishes his most popular novel, For Whom the Bell Tolls, loosely based on the author's experiences in Pamplona, Spain.
</Question>
<Choice>1940</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American poet John Crowe Ransom publishes his famous book of essays The New Criticism, which helps establish the New Criticism school of literary theory.
</Question>
<Choice>1941</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Brazilian novelist and social critic Jorge Amado publishes his classic Terras do sem fim (The Violent Land), a panoramic novel about plantation life in Bahia.
</Question>
<Choice>1942</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American correspondent Ernie Pyle publishes Here Is Your War, a collection of dispatches from the front. At his death in 1945, Pyle is the most famous of all World War II correspondents.
</Question>
<Choice>1943</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French author Albert Camus finishes his gruesomely dark play Caligula.
</Question>
<Choice>1944</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American Modernist poet H.D. begins work on her book-length poem, Trilogy.
</Question>
<Choice>1944</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American poet Robinson Jeffers completes his free adaptation of Euripides' classic play Medea; it opens the following year.
</Question>
<Choice>1946</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American metaphysical "poet of wit" Elizabeth Bishop publishes her first collection of verse, North & South.
</Question>
<Choice>1946</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American Fugitive poet and prominent Southern novelist Robert Penn Warren publishes his classic political novel All the King's Men.
</Question>
<Choice>1946</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American poet Robert Lowell's first major work, Lord Weary's Castle, is published; it wins the Pulitzer Prize the next year.
</Question>
<Choice>1946</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American poetry critic and poet Yvor Winters compiles his rational, traditionalist criticism in the collection In Defense of Reason.
</Question>
<Choice>1947</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Senegalese poet Léopold Sédar Senghor edits and publishes Anthology of the New Negro and Madagascan Poetry, a collection that includes some of the major works of the Negritude movement.
</Question>
<Choice>1948</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British novelist George Orwell publishes his apocalyptic novel Nineteen Eighty-four. It quickly becomes a classic of the genre.
</Question>
<Choice>1949</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Gwendolyn Brooks becomes the first African-American poet to win the Pulitzer Prize, for her collection of verse Annie Allen.
</Question>
<Choice>1949</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American poet and literary theorist Charles Olson publishes his influential essay Projective Verse.
</Question>
<Choice>1950</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mysterious, reclusive American writer J.D. Salinger publishes his famous coming-of-age novel, Catcher in the Rye.
</Question>
<Choice>1951</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American poet and pioneer of "poetic literalism" (an extension of imagism) Marianne Moore publishes her Collected Poems.
</Question>
<Choice>1951</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
African-American novelist Ralph Ellison writes his groundbreaking novel Invisible Man.
</Question>
<Choice>1952</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English playwright Samuel Beckett produces his postmodernist, experimental play Waiting for Godot, during which nothing happens.
</Question>
<Choice>1952</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Southern writer Flannery O'Connor publishes her comic masterpiece, Wise Blood.
</Question>
<Choice>1952</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American novelist John Steinbeck wins the Nobel Prize for Literature for his many outstanding novels set in Salinas Valley, Calif., including The Grapes of Wrath (1939) and East of Eden (1952).
</Question>
<Choice>1952</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British poet Dylan Thomas publishes his Collected Poems.
</Question>
<Choice>1952</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Angry Young Men, the English movement critical of both upper-class institutions and the drabness of working-class welfare state life begins to emerge as a force in English fiction.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1953</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American urban rationalist poet and critic Randall Jarrell publishes his influential collection of criticism Poetry and the Age.
</Question>
<Choice>1953</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Science-fiction writer Ray Bradbury completes his most famous novel, Fahrenheit 451.
</Question>
<Choice>1953</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American writer Saul Bellow publishes his acclaimed third novel, The Adventures of Augie March. He wins the Nobel Prize for Literature in 1976.
</Question>
<Choice>1953</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English novelist William Golding publishes his acclaimed Lord of the Flies. He wins the Nobel Prize for Literature in 1983.
</Question>
<Choice>1954</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American poet Wallace Stevens publishes The Collected Poems of Wallace Stevens shortly before his death.
</Question>
<Choice>1954</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Kingsley Amis starts his long and distinguished literary career with the publication of one of the best-known works of the Angry Young Men, Lucky Jim.
</Question>
<Choice>1954</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Beat poet Allen Ginsberg publishes Howl, his denunciation of American society and answer to Walt Whitman's Leaves of Grass.
</Question>
<Choice>1956</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American poet John Berryman publishes his most successful short poem, Homage to Mistress Bradstreet.
</Question>
<Choice>1956</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Egyptian writer Naguib Mahfouz completes his trilogy of historical novels, The Cairo Trilogy. In 1988 he becomes the first Arabic writer to win the Nobel Prize for Literature.
</Question>
<Choice>1956</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On the Road, one of the most influential novels of the 20th century, is published by Beat Generation founder and writer Jack Kerouac.
</Question>
<Choice>1957</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
West African author Chinua Achebe completes his perceptive novel Things Fall Apart.
</Question>
<Choice>1958</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Boris Pasternak wins the Nobel Prize for Literature but is forced to decline the award. His epic Doctor Zhivago, unpublished and criticized in the Soviet Union, is translated into 18 languages.
</Question>
<Choice>1958</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Beat poet Lawrence Ferlinghetti publishes his ingenious first book of poems, A Coney Island of the Mind. His City Lights bookstore becomes a centre of San Francisco literary life.
</Question>
<Choice>1958</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American poet Anne Sexton publishes her first poetry collection, To Bedlam and Part Way Back. Much of her work reflects on her mental breakdowns.
</Question>
<Choice>1960</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish novelist and literary critic Muriel Spark publishes her best-known novel, The Prime of Miss Jean Brodie.
</Question>
<Choice>1961</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian-born novelist and critic Vladimir Nabokov publishes his uniquely structured prose-poetry novel, Pale Fire.
</Question>
<Choice>1962</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
West Indian poet Derek Walcott completes his first collection of poetry, In a Green Night. He wins the Nobel Prize for Literature in 1992.
</Question>
<Choice>1962</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Unconventional Black Mountain poet Robert Creeley publishes his unique collection For Love, Poems 1950-1960.
</Question>
<Choice>1962</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American poet and novelist Sylvia Plath publishes her only novel, The Bell Jar, under a pseudonym.
</Question>
<Choice>1963</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian writer Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn's empassioned novel One Day in the Life of Ivan Denisovich is removed from candidacy for the Lenin prize because of his politics.
</Question>
<Choice>1963</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American poet Wendell Berry publishes November Twenty-six, Nineteen Hundred Sixty-three, a eulogy of John F. Kennedy.
</Question>
<Choice>1964</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese novelist Oe Kenzaburo publishes his autobiographical novel Kojinteki-na taiken (A Personal Matter), about a father and his brain-damaged son. He wins the Nobel Prize for Literature in 1994.
</Question>
<Choice>1964</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American Zen poet Gary Snyder publishes one of his most enduring collections of poetry, Six Sections from Mountains and Rivers Without End, Plus One.
</Question>
<Choice>1965</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American Southern novelist and playwright Truman Capote completes his journalistic "nonfiction novel," In Cold Blood.
</Question>
<Choice>1965</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American poet Adrienne Rich publishes her fourth collection of poetry, Necessities of Life, written almost entirely in free verse.
</Question>
<Choice>1966</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
West Indian-born novelist Jean Rhys publishes Wide Sargasso Sea, her famous retelling of Charlotte Brontë's Jane Eyre from the perspective of Bertha Rochester.
</Question>
<Choice>1966</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Latin-American author Gabriel García Márquez completes his epic novel One Hundred Years of Solitude.
</Question>
<Choice>1967</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
E.E. Cummings' Complete Poems, which assembles his entire body of eclectic poetry into two volumes, is published posthumously.
</Question>
<Choice>1968</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American "hippie" chronicler Tom Wolfe publishes The Electric Kool-Aid Acid Test, a novel about the psychedelic drug culture of the 1960s.
</Question>
<Choice>1968</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American novelist Kurt Vonnegut completes his comic and satirical war novel Slaughterhouse Five.
</Question>
<Choice>1969</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese novelist Mishima Yukio completes his magnificent Sea of Fertility series (Spring Snow, Runaway Horses, The Temple of Dawn, and The Decay of the Angel). He then commits ritual suicide.
</Question>
<Choice>1970</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American Poetry in the Twentieth Century, a literary history by American Beat poet and translator Kenneth Rexroth, is published in San Francisco.
</Question>
<Choice>1971</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American novelist Eudora Welty publishes her quiet novel The Optimist's Daughter, which wins the Pulitzer Prize.
</Question>
<Choice>1972</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American Black Mountain poet Denise Levertov revives her early sensual poetic style in one of her most popular collections, Footprints.
</Question>
<Choice>1972</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American postmodern novelist Thomas Pynchon publishes his lengthy, paranoid masterpiece, Gravity's Rainbow.
</Question>
<Choice>1973</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Canadian poet and fiction writer Margaret Atwood publishes one of her many mystical novels, Lady Oracle.
</Question>
<Choice>1976</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polish-born American novelist Isaac Bashevis Singer, chronicler of Jewish life in Poland and the U.S. and the century's most acclaimed Yiddish writer, wins the Nobel Prize for Literature.
</Question>
<Choice>1978</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Irish poet Seamus Heaney publishes a collection of essays honoring poets he admires, Preoccupations: Selected Prose, 1968-1978.
</Question>
<Choice>1980</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
South African writer Nadine Gordimer publishes her monumental short-story collection A Soldier's Embrace. She wins the Nobel Prize for Literature in 1991.
</Question>
<Choice>1980</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American short-story writer Tobias Wolff publishes his first collection of short stories, In the Garden of the North American Martyrs.
</Question>
<Choice>1981</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American writer Ann Beattie publishes her most perceptive collection of postmodernist short stories, The Burning House.
</Question>
<Choice>1982</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British poet Ted Hughes is appointed Britain's poet laureate for his years of prolific poetic genius.
</Question>
<Choice>1984</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
William Gibson's brilliant "cyberpunk" novel Neuromancer wins critical acclaim.
</Question>
<Choice>1984</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nigerian playwright and novelist Wole Soyinka wins the Nobel Prize for Literature.
</Question>
<Choice>1986</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pulitzer Prize-winning African-American author Toni Morrison publishes her most critically acclaimed novel, Beloved.
</Question>
<Choice>1987</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Anglo-Indian novelist Salman Rushdie publishes his controversial novel The Satanic Verses. After being condemned to death by Iranian Muslim clerics, he retreats into hiding.
</Question>
<Choice>1988</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese-born British novelist Kazuo Ishiguro publishes his quietly tempered masterpiece, The Remains of the Day.
</Question>
<Choice>1988</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American short-story writer Raymond Carver, known for his honest portrayals of working-class people, publishes his last collection, Where I'm Calling From.
</Question>
<Choice>1988</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A.S. Byatt's complex, multilayered academic novel Possession: A Romance wins the Booker Prize.
</Question>
<Choice>1990</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian poet and novelist Vikram Seth publishes his epic novel A Suitable Boy.
</Question>
<Choice>1993</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Irish writer Roddy Doyle, author of books set in working-class Dublin, wins the Booker Prize for his novel Paddy Clarke Ha Ha Ha.
</Question>
<Choice>1993</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Quirky American writer E. Annie Proulx publishes her first major critical success, The Shipping News.
</Question>
<Choice>1993</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Toni Morrison becomes the first African-American woman to win the Nobel Prize for Literature.
</Question>
<Choice>1993</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American novelist Cormac McCarthy publishes The Crossing, the second volume in his "Border Trilogy" about the American Southwest. The first volume, All the Pretty Horses, appeared in 1992.
</Question>
<Choice>1994</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Canadian short-story writer Alice Munro completes the often disturbing, often quiet short-story collection Open Secrets.
</Question>
<Choice>1994</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese novelist Kenzaburo Oe becomes the second Japanese author to win the Nobel Prize for Literature.
</Question>
<Choice>1994</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The year in literature culminates in the award of the Nobel Prize for Literature to Irish poet Seamus Heaney.
</Question>
<Choice>1995</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American novelist David Foster Wallace follows in Thomas Pynchon's footsteps with his groundbreaking 1,066-page novel Infinite Jest.
</Question>
<Choice>1996</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polish lyric poet Wislawa Szymborska wins the Nobel Prize for Literature.
</Question>
<Choice>1996</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. television host Oprah Winfrey adds a book-club segment to her popular show, creating a literary sensation as her selections become instant best-sellers.
</Question>
<Choice>1996</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Thomas Pynchon publishes Mason & Dixon, his first novel since Vineland.
</Question>
<Choice>1997</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A board of scholars and writers vote James Joyce's Ulysses the finest English-language novel of the 20th century.
</Question>
<Choice>1998</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian author Arundhati Roy wins the Booker Prize for her debut novel, The God of Small Things. The semiautobiographical work is noted for its lyrical prose and vivid narration.
</Question>
<Choice>1998</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Ted Hughes, Great Britain's poet laureate, dies.</Question>
<Choice>1998</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
José Saramago becomes the first Portuguese writer to win the Nobel Prize for Literature.
</Question>
<Choice>1998</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Michael Cunningham wins the Pulitzer Prize for fiction for his novel The Hours.
</Question>
<Choice>1999</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mark Strand wins the Pulitzer Prize for his poetry collection Blizzard of One, which is noted for its elegant minimalism.
</Question>
<Choice>1999</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Author Jorge Edwards becomes the first Chilean to win the Cervantes Prize. The lifetime achievement award recognizes his realistic work, which often focused on his country's politics.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Publishing books in electronic format, known as e-publishing, grows in popularity as several publishing houses announce plans to enter the field.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Gao Xingjian becomes the first Chinese-language writer to win the Nobel Prize for Literature.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Stanley Kunitz is named the 10th poet laureate of the U.S.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Amy Tan publishes The Bonesetter's Daughter. Her first book in more than five years, it explores the immigrant experience, a common theme in her works.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American author Philip Roth wins the PEN/Faulkner Award for Fiction for The Human Stain.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The 100th anniversary of the first publication of The Times Literary Supplement, considered one of the finest literary reviews in the English language, is celebrated in London.
</Question>
<Choice>2002</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ann Patchett wins the Orange Prize for Fiction and the PEN/Faulkner Award for Bel Canto, a novel that explores the unexpected bonds that develop between terrorists and hostages.
</Question>
<Choice>2002</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Da Vinci Code by Dan Brown is released and becomes one of the fastest-selling books of all time. The work of fiction generates real controversy over its theories concerning Christianity's origins.
</Question>
<Choice>2003</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Graphic novels represent one of the fastest-growing literary markets in the U.S.
</Question>
<Choice>2004</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English playwright Harold Pinter, author of ambivalent yet powerful dramas, receives the Nobel Prize for Literature.
</Question>
<Choice>2005</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Kiran Desai, daughter of British novelist Anita Desai, becomes the youngest woman to win the Man Booker Prize. She is honoured for The Inheritance of Loss, which examines the bitter pain of immigration and the lasting demoralization that colonialism inflicted upon India.
</Question>
<Choice>2006</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Orhan Pamuk wins the Nobel Prize for Literature, becoming the first Turk to receive a Nobel Prize.
</Question>
<Choice>2006</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American novelist Norman Mailer dies. His last novel, The Castle in the Forest, was published earlier in the year.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Doris Lessing becomes the first British woman to receive the Nobel Prize for Literature.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Internet retailer Amazon.com debuts the Kindle, a wireless electronic reading device. Hugely popular, it quickly sells out in the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Post-och Inrikes Tidningar, the oldest continuously published weekly newspaper, adopts an Internet-only format. The official Swedish gazette began operations in 1645.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
And the Hippos Were Boiled in Their Tanks, a novel written by William S. Burroughs and Jack Kerouac in 1945, is published for the first time.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Salman Rushdie's Midnight's Children (1981) wins the Best of the Booker prize, an honour determined by a public vote held in celebration of the Booker Prize's 40th anniversary.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Washington Post stops printing its stand-alone book section, leaving The New York Times as the only American newspaper to publish such a supplement.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American author John Updike--known for his realistic but subtle depiction of “American, Protestant, small-town, middle-class” life--dies.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An unfinished manuscript by Vladimir Nabokov, The Original of Laura, is published; the story revolves around an obese intellectual and his young wife, who is the seeming subject of a scandalous novel written by one of her former lovers.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Astrid Lindgren Memorial Award is presented to the Tamer Institute for Community Education, a Palestinian organization that encourages children to read.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American author J.D. Salinger--who wrote the classic novel Catcher in the Rye--dies.
</Question>
<Choice>2010</Choice>
</item>
</topics>