<topics>
<item>
<Question>
Neolithic skeletons show evidence of arthritis, tumours, and spina bifida. Trephined skulls may be associated with healing or ritual practices.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 10,000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sumerian physicians practice diagnosis of disease by astrology and divination of dreams and by parts of sacrificed animals, especially the liver.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 3000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
According to legend, emperor Huang-ti produces the Nei ching, the foundational text for Chinese medicine.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 3000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Legendary Chinese emperor Shen Nung invents acupuncture, a healing practice based on the insertion of needles to influence the balance of the ch’i, or life force.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 2700 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Egyptian King Djoser is attended by the physician Imhotep, later regarded as the god of medicine.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 2600 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Legendary Chinese emperor Fu Hsi creates dualistic cosmic theory of yin and yang.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 2300 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Code of Hammurabi includes laws regulating fees for medical practice and punishments for malpractice in the Babylonian Empire.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1790 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Edwin Smith papyrus gives a written account of Egyptian medical practices from diagnosis to therapeutic measures, including surgery.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1600 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Beginning of early Vedic period in medicine in India. Vedic practices include expulsion of demons believed to cause disease.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1500 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Ebers papyrus, an Egyptian medical text, includes discussion of internal diseases and diseases of the eye, skin, and extremities.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1500 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek philosopher Empedocles develops theory of correspondence between the four elements and the bodily humours. The theory is used in European and Islamic medical thought until the Renaissance.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 450 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Asclepius, a legendary physician, becomes the god of disease and healing in Greece. His staff entwined with holy snake becomes symbol of the medical profession.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 450 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek medical writings are assembled into the Hippocratic corpus, which establishes ethical standards of practice.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 431 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Brahmanic hospitals are established in Sri Lanka.</Question>
<Choice>c. 400 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The zoological writings of Greek philosopher Aristotle lay the foundations for physiological thought for the next 2,000 years. His work in human physiology emphasizes the primacy of the heart.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 350 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Alexandrian physician Herophilus of Chalcedon performs dissection on human cadavers and gives the first accurate anatomical descriptions of the eyes, brain, and body vessels.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 290 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Erasistratus of Ceos, sometimes called the father of physiology, studies the anatomy of the brain, veins, and arteries and describes the bicuspid and tricuspid valves of the heart.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 250 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The "rationalists," or "dogmatists," and the "empiricists" form rival medical traditions in Alexandria. The former favour theoretical approaches, the latter practical experience.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 200 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Romans establish institutions called valetudinaria for the care of sick and injured soldiers.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 100 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek physician Asclepiades of Bithynia helps popularize Greek medical practice in Rome. In his medical theory he rejected humoral theories for atomistic doctrines.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 90 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman nobleman Aulus Celsus writes De medicina. It describes Greek medical practices, including surgery, and is influential in the Renaissance.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 30</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek physician Pedanius Dioscorides begins work on his De materia medica, a study of the effects of 1,000 drugs and herbal remedies. The work is used into the Renaissance.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 77</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman school of physicians known as methodists develop theory that disease depends on relative tenseness and laxness of the body.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 100</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Aretaeus of Cappadocia founds the "pneumatist" school of medicine. Influenced by Stoic philosophy, he emphasizes the importance of the pneuma ("vital air") in understanding disease.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 140</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek gynecologist Soranus of Ephesus, a leader of the methodist school of medicine, composes his classic On Midwifery and the Diseases of Women.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 150</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Galen of Pergamum begins his synthesis of Greek and Roman practical and theoretical work on medicine and physiology. His doctrines dominate medical thinking for the next 13 centuries.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 160</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
St. Basil establishes a hospital outside Caesarea, with special housing for those suffering from leprosy. His work helps make the hospital a common institution throughout Byzantium and the Levant.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 370</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Rome noblewoman Fabiola, a student of St. Jerome, endows the first public hospital in Europe. Independent hospitals spread slowly after the fall of the Roman Empire.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 397</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The making of a Byzantine copy of Dioscorides’ De materia medica illustrates the great importance of practical medical works, such as herbals, in the ancient world.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 512</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Western Europe, abbeys and monasteries develop as centres of medical care, ministering to residents, pilgrims, and members of the local community.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 820</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Translation of Western medical writings reaches its peak in Baghdad under Hunayn ibn Ishaq (al-Ibadi), allowing a later assimilation of Western medical theory into Islamic medicine.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 840</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Flouishing of Persian physician and alchemist ar-Razi, whose treatises considered the medical traditions of Persia and Syrian, Greek, and Indian practitioners and writers.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 910</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The earliest known mental hospitals are established in Baghdad and Cairo.
</Question>
<Choice>918</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese physician Tamba Yasuyori completes his 30-volume Ishinho. The oldest extant Japanese medical work, it is based on Chinese medical works and adopts the Chinese theory of yin and yang.
</Question>
<Choice>982</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The city of Salerno in southern Italy becomes a famous centre for the study of the healing arts.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Iranian physician Avicenna (Ibn Sina) compiles Arab medical knowledge in Al-Qanun fi at-tibb (The Canon of Medicine), a classic text that influences both Islamic and medieval Western medicine.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1010</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Monks of the Order of Saint Lazarus open special houses for the care of patients afflicted with leprosy.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1100</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian scholar Gerard of Cremona translates important medical treatises by Galen, Rhazes, and Avicenna into Latin, bringing Greek, Roman, and Arabic medical knowledge to Europe.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1150</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Faculties of medicine and philosophy are formed at the University of Bologna.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1200</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English scholar Roger Bacon discusses a theory of lenses and vision. He is the first to describe eyeglasses, which are already in use in China and Europe.
</Question>
<Choice>1268</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Peter of Spain, author of works on medicine and psychology, is elected Pope John XXI.
</Question>
<Choice>1276</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Under the leadership of Jacob ben Machir ibn Tibbon, the University of Montpellier, in southern France, develops into the most important medical school in Europe.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1300</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian scholar Mondino de' Luzzi writes his Anatomy. It becomes a standard text for medical schools as practice in dissections is incorporated into the curriculum.
</Question>
<Choice>1316</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The "Black Death," or bubonic plague, arrives in Europe, killing at least one-third of the population over the next four years.
</Question>
<Choice>1347</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Simple single-lens microscopes are in use in Europe. The compound microscope will be invented in The Netherlands after 1590.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1450</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Severe epidemics of malaria occur in Europe.</Question>
<Choice>1493</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Syphilis appears among soldiers at the siege of Naples in Italy, then spreads rapidly throughout Europe. French and Italian writers blame each other’s armies for introducing the disease.
</Question>
<Choice>1494</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Relying on close observation and dissection, Italian artist Leonardo da Vinci undertakes detailed anatomical drawings.
</Question>
<Choice>1503</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physician Thomas Linacre, a late advocate of Galenic physiology, founds the Royal College of Physicians to regulate medical practice in England.
</Question>
<Choice>1518</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-Swiss alchemist and physician Paracelsus introduces alchemical theory into medicine and crusades for chemical treatments of disease rather than traditional materia medica.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1530</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The dissolution of the monasteries by King Henry VIII ends the building of hospitals in England for about 200 years.
</Question>
<Choice>1540</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Flemish anatomist Andreas Vesalius writes De humani corporis fabrica ("On the Fabric of the Human Body"), a revolutionary anatomy text that ends the dominance of Galen's doctrines.
</Question>
<Choice>1543</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian humanist and physician Girolamo Fracastoro proposes that contagious diseases are spread by invisible particles in air or through direct or indirect contact.
</Question>
<Choice>1546</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French surgeon Ambroise Paré, famous for his humanizing reforms of surgical practice, serves King Henry II of France.
</Question>
<Choice>1552</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian anatomist Gabriel Fallopius gives detailed descriptions of the female reproductive system, including the tubes that connect the ovaries to the uterus, in Observationes anatomicae.
</Question>
<Choice>1561</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian scholar Ulisse Aldrovandi publishes an official pharmacopeia describing the proper mixtures of plant remedies.
</Question>
<Choice>1574</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first documented case of a cesarean section performed on a living woman is published.
</Question>
<Choice>1610</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physician William Harvey publishes De motu cordis ("On the Movement of the Blood"). Based on detailed observations and experiments, it accurately describes the circulation of the blood.
</Question>
<Choice>1628</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jesuit missionaries bring cinchona bark from Peru to Europe. The bark, which contains trace amounts of naturally occurring quinine, is used to treat malaria.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1630</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French religious workers Vincent de Paul and Louise de Marillac establish the Daughters of Charity to provide nursing and medical care for the poor.
</Question>
<Choice>1633</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In his Discourse on Method, René Descartes proposes that mind and matter are distinct substances and that medicine, mechanics, and morals are all based on metaphysics and physics.
</Question>
<Choice>1637</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chemist and alchemist Jan Baptista van Helmont, known for applying chemical principles to physiology, describes digestion as a kind of fermentation in Ortus medicinae.
</Question>
<Choice>1648</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Through microscopic observations, Italian physician Marcello Malpighi identifies capillaries connecting the small arteries and veins in the lung.
</Question>
<Choice>1661</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Great Plague in London kills about 75,000 of the 460,000 residents.
</Question>
<Choice>1665</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physician Thomas Sydenham advocates careful observations and criticizes speculative theorizing in Observationes Medicae, a textbook that influences medical education for two centuries.
</Question>
<Choice>1676</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
After three years’ research, Dutch microscopist Antonie van Leeuwenhoek announces his observation of spermatozoa through a simple microscope. His work inaugurates the field of microbiology.
</Question>
<Choice>1677</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian physiologist Giovanni Borelli publishes De Motu Animalium, an account of iatromechanics, the application of mechanical principles to the study of locomotion and physiology.
</Question>
<Choice>1680</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch physician Hermann Boerhaave founds the influential tradition of medical education at the University of Leiden. His training emphasizes chemistry, physiology, and bedside observation of patients.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1700</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish surgeon Alexander Monro begins teaching anatomy at the University of Edinburgh, establishing a medical dynasty that helps turn Edinburgh into a leading centre of medical education.
</Question>
<Choice>1720</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In his Haemastaticks, English physiologist and chemist Stephen Hales describes the process for measuring blood pressure quantitatively.
</Question>
<Choice>1733</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British surgeon William Hunter begins his distinguished career teaching anatomy in London. A noted obstetrician, he writes The Anatomy of the Human Gravid Uterus, Exhibited in Figures in 1774.
</Question>
<Choice>1746</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first incorporated hospital in the American colonies is founded in Philadelphia.
</Question>
<Choice>1751</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In his book On the Most Effectual Means of Preserving the Health of Seamen, British doctor James Lind shows that citrus fruits prevent scurvy (at the time a leading cause of death in the Royal Navy).
</Question>
<Choice>1757</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first medical school in the American colonies opens at the College of Philadelphia (later the University of Pennsylvania).
</Question>
<Choice>1765</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American doctor Benjamin Rush begins practicing medicine in Philadelphia. An advocate of heroic intervention in treating disease, he is best known for his advocacy of humane treatment of the insane.
</Question>
<Choice>1769</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John Hunter, leading English surgeon and founder of pathological anatomy in England, is appointed physician extraordinary to King George III.
</Question>
<Choice>1776</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
William Cullen, professor of medicine at Edinburgh, publishes the first volume of his First Lines of the Practice of Physic, an attempt to classify all diseases.
</Question>
<Choice>1778</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss doctor J.A.Venel opens the first institution for crippled children and the first institute for orthopedics.
</Question>
<Choice>1780</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American statesman and inventor Benjamin Franklin invents bifocal lenses.
</Question>
<Choice>1784</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
After a decade of investigations, Italian scholar Luigi Galvani concludes that muscle contractions are stimulated by electricity, which he believes occurs naturally in animals.
</Question>
<Choice>1791</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physician Edward Jenner, a student of John Hunter, introduces the technique of vaccination against smallpox, one of the most feared diseases of the time.
</Question>
<Choice>1796</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In his Treatise on the Membranes, French physiologist Xavier Bichat argues that the body is composed of different tissues, whose functions and properties define the behaviour and treatment of disease.
</Question>
<Choice>1800</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
European countries begin enacting statutes to govern midwife training and licensing. By the end of the 20th century, midwives are delivering about three-fourths of infants born worldwide each year.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1800</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Phrenology, a technique for determining intellect and personality from the shape of the skull, is first proposed. Though discredited today, the practice is quite popular throughout the 19th century.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1802</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
William Worrall Mayo is born in England. He and subsequent generations of his family become pioneers in the practice of group medicine and found the highly influential Mayo Clinic in the U.S.
</Question>
<Choice>1819</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In his classic On Mediate Auscultation, French physician René-Théophile-Hyacinthe Laënnec describes the stethoscope and its use in examining the sounds of the heart and lungs and in diagnosing diseases.
</Question>
<Choice>1819</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French pharmacists Pierre Pelletier and Joseph Caventou isolate several physiologically active alkaloids from plants, including caffeine, strychnine, and quinine.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1820</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Philadelphia College of Pharmacy and Science, the first college of pharmacy in the United States, is established in Pennsylvania.
</Question>
<Choice>1821</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physiologist François Magendie shows that sensory and motor nerves have separate origins in the spine.
</Question>
<Choice>1822</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German embryologist Karl Ernst von Baer describes the mammalian ovum.
</Question>
<Choice>1827</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French educator Louis Braille first publishes his system of writing for the visually impaired. In it, letters are encoded as raised dots on embossed cardboard and read with the fingertips.
</Question>
<Choice>1829</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first of three major 19th-century cholera epidemics strikes Europe and the United States. The epidemics inspire sanitary reforms and contribute to the development of epidemiology.
</Question>
<Choice>1832</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first dental school in North America is founded in Baltimore, Maryland.
</Question>
<Choice>1840</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British public health reformer Edwin Chadwick prepares his Report on the Sanitary Conditions of the Labouring Population of Great Britain. The report helps spur urban sanitary reform.
</Question>
<Choice>1842</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Leukemia, a group of malignant diseases of the blood-forming tissues, is first described by English physician John H. Bennett and German pathologist Rudolph Virchow.
</Question>
<Choice>1845</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At Massachusetts General Hospital in Boston, American physician William Thomas Morton demonstrates the use of ether as a general anesthetic.
</Question>
<Choice>1846</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physiologist Carl Ludwig introduces the kymograph, which allows graphical recording of physiological functions like blood pressure and muscle contraction.
</Question>
<Choice>1847</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The American Medical Association is founded in Philadelphia "to promote the science and art of medicine and the betterment of public health."
</Question>
<Choice>1847</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German scientist Hermann von Helmholtz invents the ophthalmoscope, to study the structure and function of the eye and the condition of retinal blood vessels.
</Question>
<Choice>1851</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physiologist Claude Bernard discovers that the liver synthesizes glycogen and that vasomotor nerves control the dilation of blood vessels in response to temperature changes.
</Question>
<Choice>1856</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Die Cellular Pathologie, German physician Rudolf Virchow proposes that the cell is the locus of pathology. His work makes humoral and environmental theories of disease obsolete.
</Question>
<Choice>1858</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Florence Nightingale establishes the Nightingale School for Nurses, the world’s first school for nurses, at St. Thomas’s Hospital in London.
</Question>
<Choice>1860</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French surgeon and anthropologist Paul Broca announces that the seat of articulate speech is localized to the left frontal region of the brain.
</Question>
<Choice>1861</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French scientist Louis Pasteur invents "pasteurization."
</Question>
<Choice>1863</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The work of Swiss humanitarian Jean-Henri Dunant leads to the first Geneva Convention and establishment of the International Red Cross. He wins the first Nobel Prize for Peace in 1901.
</Question>
<Choice>1864</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In his classic Introduction to Experimental Medicine, French physiologist Claude Bernard argues that the body represents an "internal environment" comprehensible through experimental physiology.
</Question>
<Choice>1865</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish physician Joseph Lister begins developing techniques for antiseptic surgery, including sterilization of instruments. His innovations result in vastly lower surgical mortality rates.
</Question>
<Choice>1865</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physician Thomas Clifford Allbutt develops the clinical thermometer. His short, fast-reading thermometer replaces older models that were a foot long.
</Question>
<Choice>1866</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physician Jean Antoine Villemin demonstrates that tuberculosis is an infectious rather than a hereditary disease.
</Question>
<Choice>1867</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German doctor Karl August Wunderlich's Body Temperature and Disease popularizes the practice of using thermometers to determine the body temperature of patients.
</Question>
<Choice>1868</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At the University of Cambridge, physiologist Michael Foster establishes a laboratory of physiology. His "Cambridge School of Physiology" helps revolutionize the study of the subject in medical school.
</Question>
<Choice>1870</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Theodor Billroth, head of a surgical clinic in Vienna and the founder of modern abdominal surgery, performs the first successful operation to remove part of the stomach to treat cancer.
</Question>
<Choice>1881</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physician Robert Koch, known for advancing the germ theory of disease, isolates the tubercle bacillus, the cause of tuberculosis. He isolates the cholera bacillus the following year.
</Question>
<Choice>1882</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physician Jean-Martin Charcot opens a neurological clinic in Paris, attracting students from around the world. Austrian medical student Sigmund Freud comes to the clinic in 1885.
</Question>
<Choice>1882</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German bacteriologist Friedrich Loeffler codiscovers the diphtheria bacillus. Building on this work, he articulates the principles of disease causation later known as "Koch's Postulates."
</Question>
<Choice>1884</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian zoologist Élie Metchnikoff observes the process of phagocytosis, from which he develops the cellular theory of immunity.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1884</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Using newly developed vaccination procedures, French scientist Louis Pasteur saves the life of a boy stricken with rabies. Serum treatment of rabies is introduced in 1899.
</Question>
<Choice>1885</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British-trained physiologist H. Newell Martin and Americans S. Weir Mitchell and Henry P. Bowditch organize the American Physiological Society.
</Question>
<Choice>1887</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German medical researcher Emil von Behring and Japanese bacteriologist Kitasato Shibasaburo announce that blood serum from animals exposed to tetanus bacillus has anti-toxin properties.
</Question>
<Choice>1890</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The English physician George Redmayne Murray successfully treats myxedema (the common form of hypothyroidism) with an extract of the thyroid gland.
</Question>
<Choice>1891</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Johns Hopkins Medical School opens in Baltimore. Its rigorous curriculum and emphasis on research and clinical training raises standards for American medical education.
</Question>
<Choice>1893</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss bacteriologist Alexandre Yersin and Japanese bacteriologist Kitasato Shibasaburo independently discover the causative organism of the bubonic plague during an outbreak in China.
</Question>
<Choice>1894</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist Wilhelm Conrad Röntgen discovers X rays. His new discovery is applied to medicine almost immediately and soon becomes a major diagnostic tool.
</Question>
<Choice>1895</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British army surgeon Ronald Ross discovers the malarial parasite carried by the Anopheles mosquito. This work advances antimalarial campaigns and wins Ross the Nobel Prize for Medicine in 1902.
</Question>
<Choice>1897</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese bacteriologist Shiga Kiyoshi, a student of Kitasato Shibasaburo and Paul Ehrlich, discovers the dysentery bacillus.
</Question>
<Choice>1897</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian physiologist Ivan Pavlov begins research that will eventually lead him to develop the concept of conditioned reflex.
</Question>
<Choice>1898</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The American Nurses’ Association is founded. The association and the growth of formal training programs for nurses contribute to the professionalization of the field.
</Question>
<Choice>1898</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Viennese psychiatrist Sigmund Freud publishes The Interpretation of Dreams, a landmark in the history of psychoanalysis.
</Question>
<Choice>1899</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian immunologist and pathologist Karl Landsteiner identifies type A, B, and O blood groups on the basis of the antigens on the surface of the red blood cells.
</Question>
<Choice>1901</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John D. Rockefeller endows the General Education Board. The GEB and other philanthropies will play a major role in medical and scientific research in the United States until World War II.
</Question>
<Choice>1902</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish histologist Santiago Ramón y Cajal develops his first stain for identifying and studying nerve structures. His work establishes that the neuron is the building block of the nervous system.
</Question>
<Choice>1903</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
New York cook Mary Mallon, better known as "Typhoid Mary," is incarcerated by public health officials when an epidemic of typhoid fever is traced to the homes in which she worked.
</Question>
<Choice>1904</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English neurophysiologist Charles Scott Sherrington presents a holistic, integrative view of neurophysiology in his classic, The Integrative Action of the Nervous System.
</Question>
<Choice>1906</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German neuropathologist Alois Alzheimer describes physical abnormalities in the brain of a patient with severe dementia, establishing a physiological basis of such illnesses (Alzheimer’s disease).
</Question>
<Choice>1906</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German medical researchers August von Wassermann, Albert Neisser, and Carl Bruck develop the serum test for syphilis, one of the first major applications of immunology to medical diagnosis.
</Question>
<Choice>1906</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British biochemist F.G. Hopkins demonstrates the importance of certain amino acids (later called vitamins) to nutrition.
</Question>
<Choice>1906</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American educator Abraham Flexner publishes his Medical Education in the U.S. and Canada, a highly influential critique of American medical education.
</Question>
<Choice>1910</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German medical researcher Paul Ehrlich and his colleague Sahachiro Hata inaugurate chemotherapy by showing that the synthetic compound arsphenamine (Salvarsan) is effective against syphilis.
</Question>
<Choice>1910</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss psychiatrist Eugen Bleuler introduces the term "schizophrenia" to describe a group of related severe mental illnesses.
</Question>
<Choice>1911</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French-American surgeon Alexis Carrel wins the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for developing methods for joining blood vessels, a technique essential for transplant operations.
</Question>
<Choice>1912</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polish biochemist Casimir Funk coins the name "vitamine" (from vital amine) to describe essential growth substances that must be provided in the diet.
</Question>
<Choice>1912</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>American researchers discover Vitamin A.</Question>
<Choice>1913</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American reformer Margaret Sanger opens the first American birth control clinic in Brooklyn, N.Y.
</Question>
<Choice>1916</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The most destructive influenza epidemic in history kills approximately 20 million people worldwide.
</Question>
<Choice>1918</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Canadian physician Frederick Banting and colleagues Charles H. Best and J.J.R. Macleod discover insulin. Their discovery transforms the treatment of patients with diabetes.
</Question>
<Choice>1921</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The U.S. Food and Drug Administration is formed as a law enforcement agency to regulate the purity and safety of food, food additives, drugs, chemicals, cosmetics, and household and medical devices.
</Question>
<Choice>1927</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish bacteriologist Alexander Fleming discovers penicillin. The most powerful and versatile antibiotic discovered to date, it would transform medical treatment during and after World War II.
</Question>
<Choice>1928</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German researcher Gerhard Domagk announces the discovery of the antibacterial effects of the sulfonamide Prontosil, the first synthetic compound to cure general bacterial infections in humans.
</Question>
<Choice>1932</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist Ernest Lawrence and physician John Lawrence develop neutron therapy to destroy cancers. Their first patient is their mother, Gunda.
</Question>
<Choice>1937</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American microbiologist Selman Waksman isolates streptomycin, the first antibiotic effective against gram-negative bacteria (which cause such diseases as tuberculosis).
</Question>
<Choice>1943</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch physician Willem Kolff develops the artificial kidney used in dialysis.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1945</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British researchers Sir Alexander Fleming, Sir Howard Florey, and Ernst Chain are awarded the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for their work on the development of penicillin.
</Question>
<Choice>1945</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American chemist Karl Folkers isolates the antipernicious anemia factor cyanocobalamin, better known as Vitamin B12.
</Question>
<Choice>1948</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The United Nations founds the World Health Organization to further international cooperation in medicine and public health.
</Question>
<Choice>1948</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American researchers announce that cortisone, a substance produced by the adrenal gland, has anti-inflammatory properties and can relieve arthritis.
</Question>
<Choice>1948</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American chemist Linus Pauling and colleagues show that sickle-cell anemia is a "molecular disease" caused by a single amino acid change in the hemoglobin molecule.
</Question>
<Choice>1949</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American geneticist James D. Watson and British scientist Francis Crick discover that the structure of DNA is a double helix.
</Question>
<Choice>1953</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American surgeon John H. Gibbon, Jr., performs the first open-heart surgery with the aid of a heart-lung machine.
</Question>
<Choice>1953</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A vaccine against polio developed by American medical researcher Jonas Salk is released to the public.
</Question>
<Choice>1955</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American electrical engineer Earl Baaken develops an external electrical pulse-generator, or pacemaker, to correct irregular heartbeat.
</Question>
<Choice>1958</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Down's syndrome, caused by trisomy at chromosome 21, is the first chromosomal abnormality to be identified.
</Question>
<Choice>1959</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Thalidomide is prescribed as a sedative in Germany and Great Britain, leading to thousands of fetal deformities.
</Question>
<Choice>1959</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Food and Drug Administration (FDA) approves the female oral contraceptive, commonly known as "the pill," for use in the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1960</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An official report to the Surgeon General of the United States concludes that smoking tobacco is causally related to lung cancer.
</Question>
<Choice>1964</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The U.S. Congress enacts the Medicare and Medicaid programs, providing medical insurance for the elderly and the poor.
</Question>
<Choice>1965</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
South African surgeon Christiaan Barnard carries out the first human heart transplant.
</Question>
<Choice>1967</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British and American medical researchers develop the CAT scan, which integrates thousands of X-ray images into a detailed picture.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1970</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Major American tobacco companies agree to include warnings of the health dangers of smoking on cigarette packages and advertisements.
</Question>
<Choice>1971</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the landmark case, Roe v. Wade, The U.S. Supreme Court in effect legalizes abortion on demand for women in the first three months of pregnancy.
</Question>
<Choice>1973</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Argentine researcher Cesar Milstein and colleagues discover how to produce monoclonal antibodies by fusing specific lymphocytes with cultured myeloma cells that reproduce indefinitely.
</Question>
<Choice>1975</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first known outbreak of the Ebola virus, in Zaire, causes hundreds of death through severe hemorrhaging.
</Question>
<Choice>1976</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first birth of a human child conceived through in vitro fertilization, a technique pioneered by British doctors Patrick Steptoe and R.G. Edwards.
</Question>
<Choice>1978</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Researchers in the United Kingdom introduce magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), based on the discovery of nuclear magnetic resonance in 1946, into medical practice.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1980</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The World Health Organization declares that smallpox has been eradicated, three years after the last known case.
</Question>
<Choice>1980</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The C.D.C. (Centers for Disease Control) recognizes AIDS as a new disease.
</Question>
<Choice>1981</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The U.S. Food and Drug Administration approves genetically engineered insulin, the first product made from human genes through recombinant DNA techniques.
</Question>
<Choice>1982</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An artificial heart designed by Robert K. Jarvik is implanted into a patient, who dies several months later.
</Question>
<Choice>1982</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American researchers studying Duchenne's muscular dystrophy discover that it is caused by a defect on the 23rd chromosome. This is the first discovery of a specific marker for a genetic disease.
</Question>
<Choice>1983</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American researcher Robert Gallo and French researcher Luc Montagnier announce independent discoveries of the virus, later named HIV, that causes AIDS.
</Question>
<Choice>1984</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American surgeon Leonard Bailey transplants a baboon heart into a baby born with a fatal heart defect; she lives for 20 days.
</Question>
<Choice>1984</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first genetically engineered vaccine, which protects against hepatitis B infection, is approved for sale in the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1986</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Prozac is first prescribed in the United States, revolutionizing the treatment of depression.
</Question>
<Choice>1987</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The gene responsible for cystic fibrosis is isolated, leading to the development of a genetic test for the disease.
</Question>
<Choice>1989</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The NIH’s Recombinant DNA Advisory Committee approves the first gene therapy for humans, to treat adenosine deaminase deficiency and severe combined immunodeficiency.
</Question>
<Choice>1990</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Health-care reform emerges as a central issue in the United States as concerns grow over the cost and quality of medical treatment.
</Question>
<Choice>1993</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A team of American researchers headed by geneticist Mark H. Skolnick discovers the BRCA1 gene, believed to cause about 5-10% of breast cancers.
</Question>
<Choice>1994</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scientists discover the gene defect responsible for the progressive neurological disorder ataxia telangiectasia (AT).
</Question>
<Choice>1995</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Protease inhibitors provide a new treatment for AIDS, which dramatically improves rates of survival.
</Question>
<Choice>1996</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An outbreak of "mad cow" disease in England leads to a crisis in the beef industry when researchers conclude it can be transmitted to humans through eating meat.
</Question>
<Choice>1996</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
As nurses become the most widely available health-care providers, many countries are expanding their duties, allowing them to diagnose patients and prescribe medicine.
</Question>
<Choice>1996</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish researchers announce they have produced the first cloned mammal.
</Question>
<Choice>1997</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Bobbi McCaughey gives birth to septuplets, marking the first known case in the United States of seven live human births. She had been taking a fertility drug.
</Question>
<Choice>1997</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In an unprecedented move, the Liggett Group, a tobacco company in the United States, acknowledges the health risks of smoking when its CEO admits that cigarettes are addictive and can cause cancer.
</Question>
<Choice>1997</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The U.S. Food and Drug Administration approves Viagra (sildenafil), the first oral drug treatment for male impotence.
</Question>
<Choice>1998</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A research team led by Judah Folkman discovers a treatment that eliminates cancer in mice. Work is needed to test its effectivity in the treatment of humans.
</Question>
<Choice>1998</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The AIDS epidemic worsens in Africa as reports indicate that some 9,400 people on the continent are infected with the fatal virus every day.
</Question>
<Choice>1999</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
According to the World Health Organization, more than two-thirds of the world's nations do not maintain safe blood supplies.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
As head of the Human Genome Project, Francis Collins announces that the entire human genome has been sequenced. It is believed that the achievement will revolutionize medicine.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first-ever analysis of the world's health care systems is conducted, with France's being found the best in the world.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Health officials report a dramatic rise in deaths from cardiac arrest among U.S. adults under 35, particularly among women. Smoking, drug use, and obesity were blamed.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Authorities announce that diabetes could become an epidemic in the United States after the number of new cases rose more than 33 percent during the 1990s.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Anthrax-laced letters are mailed to U.S. media and political figures, resulting in several deaths. With growing fears of biological and chemical weapons, the U.S. government reassesses its vaccines against anthrax and smallpox.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Debates concerning the medicinal use of marijuana continue. The U.S. Supreme Court rules that under federal law there is no acceptable medical use for marijuana, but several months later Canada approves the drug in certain medical cases.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scientists decode the malaria genome. The discovery is expected to aid in the development of vaccines and drugs to combat the disease.
</Question>
<Choice>2002</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The foot-and-mouth epidemic that devastated England's cattle industry ends after the British government announces that the country is officially free of the highly contagious viral disease.
</Question>
<Choice>2002</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Experts predict a rise in diseases transmitted through insects, particularly mosquitoes. This comes in the wake of numerous deaths in the U.S. from the West Nile virus.
</Question>
<Choice>2003</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Vioxx is withdrawn from the market after it is revealed that the arthritis drug can increase the risk of heart attack and stroke. More than 80 million people worldwide have used the drug.
</Question>
<Choice>2004</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first human face transplant is performed in France on a woman who had been attacked by a dog. Doctors debate the ethical ramifications of the procedure.
</Question>
<Choice>2005</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The growing threat of avian flu leads numerous countries and organizations to pledge $1.9 billion to fight the disease.
</Question>
<Choice>2006</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The U.S. Supreme Court upholds an Oregon law that allows physician-assisted suicide for people who are terminally ill.
</Question>
<Choice>2006</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The FDA approves the first vaccine against cervical cancer. Designed for females between the ages of 9 and 26, Gardasil proves controversial as some believe it will encourage teenage sex.
</Question>
<Choice>2006</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A new strain of the deadly Ebola virus surfaces in Uganda, killing dozens of people.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Researchers announce that they have created a beating heart by injecting new heart cells into a dead rat heart. The landmark acheivement gives hope to the possibility of growing new human organs for medical use.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scientists use stem cells to bioengineer a section of trachea that was transplanted into a woman whose upper airway had been severely damaged by tuberculosis.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Doctors perform the world's first double arm transplant.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Zimbabwean government declares a state of emergency as a cholera epidemic sweeps through the country.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In one of the largest cases of food contamination in American history, hundreds of peanut products are recalled after a salmonella outbreak.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pres. Barack Obama reverses a government policy, adopted during the previous administration, that had prevented federal dollars from funding human embryonic stem cell research in the U.S.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In June the first influenza pandemic since 1968 is declared by Margaret Chan, director general of the World Health Organization, following an outbreak of an illness popularly known as swine flu.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Researchers announce that they have decoded the structure of a complete HIV genome.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
</topics>