<topics>
<item>
<Question>
An archaeological excavation in Moravia reveals a drum that dates from about 6000 BC. Drums are apparently among the oldest musical instruments and are played around the world.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 6000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sumerian and Egyptian archaeological records indicate use of the arched harp, a vertical harp whose neck stretches away from the musician. The harp is still played in Africa and Central Asia.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 3000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sumerian musicians play the lyre, an instrument that would diffuse throughout the Old World.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 3000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The earliest trumpets, sounding one or two notes and used in martial events, appear in Egypt. The instrument would later be adopted by Greek and Roman armies; it is still used in military ceremonies.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 2000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Vedic chant, a three-tone system for reciting the Hindu Vedas, is developed. It is the world's oldest continuous vocal tradition.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1200 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Israelite king Solomon the Great builds the Temple of Jerusalem, which supports a large musical establishment.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 957 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Poets reciting Homer's Iliad and Odyssey are accompanied by musicians. Greek music is primarily vocal and is used in theatre and religious ceremonies as well as poetry recitation.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 900 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Terpander, lyric poet of Lesbos, flourishes. The kithara, a seven-stringed instrument that he invents, becomes one of the most popular instruments in ancient Greek music.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 647 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Alcaeus, poet of Greek island of Lesbos, changes the character of Greek lyric poetry with intense personal content, working with Sappho and the musicians of the island.
</Question>
<Choice>580 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek philosopher and mathematician Pythagoras recognizes intervals in music as consonant and invariant.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 525 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pindar, the great lyric poet from Thebes, composes some of the most famous odes in Greek music. The oldest of his surviving epinicia, choral celebrations of athletic victories, dates from 498.
</Question>
<Choice>498 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In his dialogue The Republic, Plato discusses the place of music in society and suggests that certain kinds of music are detrimental to the state because of their effects on listeners.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 378 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In his Politics, Aristotle divides music into two categories: ritual music (the music of ecstasy) and music of diversion (for relaxation and daily life).
</Question>
<Choice>c. 335 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek astronomer Eratosthenes settles in Alexandria. There, in addition to his astronomical work, he writes about the tuning of the tetrachord, the Greek four-note musical scale.
</Question>
<Choice>255 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The expansion of Roman power in the Mediterranean leads to the diffusion of Roman musical forms, such as the seven-note diatonic scale, and the mixing of instruments and styles from different regions.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 250 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The transverse flute, which is held sideways to the player's right, is used in Greece. The exact date of its invention is unknown.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 200 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek Epicurean philosopher Philodemus writes his treatise On Music, of which extensive fragments remain.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 65 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Second Temple of Jerusalem is destroyed, ending Jewish use of musical instruments in worship.
</Question>
<Choice>70</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman geographer, astronomer, and mathematician Ptolemy writes a three-volume treatise on Harmonics.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 150</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Neoplatonist Porphyry writes a commentary on Ptolemy's Harmonics. His and other philosophers' musical interests reflect the prominent place of music in Greek culture and thought.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 280</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Roman emperor Constantine legalizes Christianity. The new faith's legitimacy spurs a flourishing of musical composition in the West, particularly in hymns.
</Question>
<Choice>313</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The establishment of the Byzantine Empire, and separation of western and eastern churches, gives rise to Byzantine chant, which draws on Hellenistic and Middle Eastern sources.
</Question>
<Choice>330</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Syriac Christian writer St. Ephraem Syrus composes hymns on a variety of religious and theological subjects. This work earns him the title "Harp of the Holy Spirit" among his contemporaries.
</Question>
<Choice>364</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
St. Ambrose, Bishop of Milan, is credited with bringing the practice of alternation in hymnody from the East to the West and with writing some of the best-known Latin hymns.
</Question>
<Choice>379</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
St. Augustine of Hippo begins his De musica, an influential work on musical aesthetics. He advocates simple compositions that do not distract the listener from the religious content of songs.
</Question>
<Choice>387</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Boethius writes his De consolatione philosophiae. Following Plato, it suggests that music is divided into three parts: musica mundana, musica humana, and musica instrumentalis.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 520</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Rule of St. Benedict establishes a framework for monastic life. It includes a choral daily prayer, a form that plays an important part in the development of Western music.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 529</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
St. Gregory the Great is elected Pope. His reform of the mass, intended to make liturgy more widely accessible, leads to the development of the Gregorian chant, which is named in his honour.
</Question>
<Choice>590</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Widsith, an Old English story about the travels of a scop (itinerant musician) in Germanic lands, is preserved in the Exeter Book. It provides a rare view of the life of early medieval musicians.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 600</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The kettledrum, which consists of a skin stretched over a hemispheric shell, is depicted in a Persian relief. The expansion of Islamic civilization introduces the drum into Asia and Africa.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 600</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The place of vocal music in Islam is established when Muhammad institutes the daily adhan ("call to prayer"), which is chanted at mosques by the mu` addin (muezzin).
</Question>
<Choice>c. 622</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
St. Benedict Biscop founds the monastery of Jarrow in Northumbria, bringing Roman chant to his part of England.
</Question>
<Choice>682</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The monastery of St. Gall in Switzerland is founded. It becomes a centre of musical activity in the Middle Ages.
</Question>
<Choice>720</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
St. John of Damascus organizes the hymnody of the Byzantine Church, creating the Octoechos (“Book of Eight Tones”).
</Question>
<Choice>c. 740</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Charlemagne imports the Gregorian chant into the Frankish kingdom. There it comes into contact with the Gallican chant, resulting in a modified Gregorian chant that spreads through the Holy Roman Empire.
</Question>
<Choice>768</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Muslim philosopher al-Kindi writes the earliest known Arabic treatise on music. Like the ancient Greeks he studied, al-Kindi's musical studies were part of a larger set of philosophical interests.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 850</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Notker the Stammerer creates his Liber Hymnorum, the introduction of which contains his explanation of the origin of the plainsong sequence.
</Question>
<Choice>860</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The system of te'amim, which provides guidance for the cantillation (intoned recitation) of the Torah, is created at Tiberias in Palestine. The system is influenced by early Byzantine chant.
</Question>
<Choice>900</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Iraqi scholar Abu al-Faraj al-Isbahani writes the Kitab al-aghani ("The Book of Songs"), an encyclopedic study that reveals the diverse geographical and cultural sources of medieval Islamic music.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 950</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
St. Volodymyr (Vladimir) of Kiev converts to Christianity and imports Greek musicians into Kievan Rus.
</Question>
<Choice>988</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Cathedral schools begin to grow in western Europe, their curricula defined by the seven liberal arts. Music is classified as part of the quadrivium, along with geometry, mathematics, and astronomy.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The monastery of Grottaferrata, 19 kilometres from Rome, is founded by St. Nilus of Rossano. It maintains the Greek/Byzantine liturgy in the West.
</Question>
<Choice>1004</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian music theorist Guido of Arezzo devises the syllablic names for the notes of the scale (ut--later replaced with do--re, mi, fa, sol, la), and the use of letters for notes (e.g., A, B, C, etc.).
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1030</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Emergence of the term "minstrel" to identify traveling musicians who perform secular and popular songs. The minstrel is one of several types of itinerant musicians in medieval European culture.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1100</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Cistercian monk St. Bernard establishes the abbey of Clairvaux. One of the most important figures in medieval monasticism, he is a major reformer of monastic liturgy and its musical accompaniment.
</Question>
<Choice>1115</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German abbess and visionary mystic St. Hildegard collects her music and verse in Symphonia harmoniae.
</Question>
<Choice>1152</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Cathedral of Notre-Dame in Paris is dedicated. The cathedral would become a major centre of musical innovation, bringing the organum, clausula, conductus, and motet into late medieval music.
</Question>
<Choice>1182</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
European appearance of the lute, a stringed instrument developed in Muslim Spain and based on the Arab 'ud. The Arab 'ud, in turn, came from 7th-century Persia and probably had Asian antecedents.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1200</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pérotin, a composer associated with the Cathedral of Notre-Dame in Paris, introduces four-part polyphony into Western music.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1200</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dominican friar Vincent of Lielc, the earliest known Polish composer, writes an office in honour of St. Stanislaus, the patron saint of Poland.
</Question>
<Choice>1255</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Cantigas de Santa Maria, a set of Galician folk hymns, are collected under the direction of King Alfonso the Wise of Castile.
</Question>
<Choice>1280</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Development of the madrigal, which combines lyric poetry and polyphonic arrangement. The madrigal's fortunes wax and wane until the 16th century, when it is established throughout Europe.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1300</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Philippe de Vitry writes Ars nova, a treatise outlining changes in French music caused by the adoption of new notational techniques, such as mensural notation and coloured notes.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1320</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Flemish composer Gilles Binchois enters the service of Philip III the Good of Burgundy, where he composes some of the finest religious and secular music of the period.
</Question>
<Choice>1430</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jean d' Ockeghem becomes court musician to Charles I, Duke de Bourbon, writing his Missa cuiusvis toni, a canon that exemplifies the Franco-Flemish style of early Renaissance music.
</Question>
<Choice>1446</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Accademia Platonica in Florence is established under the leadership of Marsilio Ficino. Devoted mainly to philosophy at first, its interests soon expand to include musical studies.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1450</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Two decades after the invention of the printing press by Johannes Gutenberg, the first mechanically printed music, the Constance Gradual, is published in southern Germany.
</Question>
<Choice>1473</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Invention of the double bass, the largest and lowest-voiced member of the violin family.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1480</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jakob Obrecht is made magister capellae at St. Donatian, Brugge, where he writes the Missa 'Salve diva parens, a masterpiece of contrapuntal Franco-Flemish music.
</Question>
<Choice>1489</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chamber music, a form of performance characterized by small ensembles playing without the aid of a conductor and performing for small audiences, develops in the 16th century.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1500</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
After 1700 years' development, the pipe organ reaches its mature form in northern Germany, leading to the growth of a body of music tailored to exploit its grand and complex capabilities.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1500</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Invention of the viol (or viola da gamba), a six-stringed bowed instrument used mainly in chamber music. The instrument's popularity waned greatly in the 17th century.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1500</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Protestant Reformation begins in Wittenberg, Ger., sparking a revolution in Christian theology and liturgy and parallel changes in religious music.
</Question>
<Choice>1517</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German humanist scholar Johannes Reuchlin, best known for his influential studies of Hebrew language and literature, transcribes into Western notation the biblical cantillation of his day.
</Question>
<Choice>1518</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish instrument-makers invent the guitar, a six-stringed instrument based on the vihuela.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1520</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Josquin des Prez, famed throughout western Europe for his choral music, dies in Conde, Burgundy.
</Question>
<Choice>1521</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first major volume of chorales for use in Protestant liturgy is published. Chorales' univocal arrangement and vernacular lyrics reflect the carefully planned accessibility of Protestant worship.
</Question>
<Choice>1524</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John Calvin orders the removal of organs from churches in the city of Geneva.
</Question>
<Choice>1536</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Huguenot composer Loys Bourgeois begins work on a series of psalm settings that are published in the Genevan Psalter, one of the most popular musical compilations of early Protestantism.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1545</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John Marbeck publishes The Booke of Common Praier Noted, which provides the first music in English for the Anglican liturgy.
</Question>
<Choice>1550</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jacobus Clemens enters the service of the Marian Brotherhood in 's-Hertogenbosch, Holland. Among many other works, he published the Souter Liedekens, a series of Flemish metrical psalms.
</Question>
<Choice>1550</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Gioseffo Zarlino publishes his definitive work on 16th-century counterpoint, Istitutioni harmoniche. Despite its fame the book is attacked by Vincenzo Galilei, father of Galileo Galilei.
</Question>
<Choice>1558</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Council of Trent concludes after 18 years' work. Among its achievements is a reform of Roman Catholic church music.
</Question>
<Choice>1563</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Orlando di Lasso publishes three complete cycles of the Magnificat in eight tones, showing remarkable compositional dexterity and variety.
</Question>
<Choice>1567</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
E.N. Ammerbach publishes the Orgel oder Instrument Tabulatur, which outlines a new system of tabulature, with letter names for notes and rhythmic signs above them.
</Question>
<Choice>1571</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Giovanni Pierluigi da Palestrina returns to the Capella Gulia in St. Peter's in Rome, where he remains until his death in 1594.
</Question>
<Choice>1571</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman Catholic composer William Byrd is sworn in as gentleman of the (Anglican) English Chapel Royal.
</Question>
<Choice>1572</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
After 24 years of being assistant, Francisco Guerrero becomes maestro de capilla of the Cathedral of Seville.
</Question>
<Choice>1574</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Marc' Antonio Ingegneri, maestro di cappella at the Cathedral in Cremona, publishes his Motets for Five Voices.
</Question>
<Choice>1576</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian instrument-makers create the violin, based on the medieval fiddle.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1580</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Invention of the cello. The earliest versions of the instrument are built with five strings, rather than the modern four.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1580</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Flemish instrument-maker Hans Ruckers establishes Europe's leading workshop for harpsichord manufacture. The Ruckers house operates through the 16th and 17th centuries.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1580</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Luca Marenzio publishes the first madrigals in what is called the "ornamented style."
</Question>
<Choice>1580</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Giovanni Gabrieli becomes organist at St. Mark's Basilica in Venice.
</Question>
<Choice>1585</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hans Leo Hassler is appointed court organist to Octavian II Fugger in Augsburg, Ger.
</Question>
<Choice>1585</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Tomás Luis de Victoria becomes chaplain of the Monastery of Sta. Clara in Madrid, where he composes and assembles his Missae Liber secundus.
</Question>
<Choice>1587</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Seth Calvisius' Melopoeia, an influential music theory text organized in 21 chapters, is published in Leipzig, Ger.
</Question>
<Choice>1592</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John Dowland publishes his First Book of Songes or Ayres, which greatly influences English songs, especially lute music.
</Question>
<Choice>1597</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Worshipful Company of Musicians is chartered in London by King James I.
</Question>
<Choice>1604</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mikolaj Zielenski publishes his Offertoria in Gniezno, Poland, bringing the Polish Renaissance to its height.
</Question>
<Choice>1611</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Kievan Academy in Ukraine is founded by Peter Mogila, with a strong emphasis on ecclesiastical music.
</Question>
<Choice>1615</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Heinrich Schütz, the most important German composer before J.S. Bach, is appointed Kapellmeister to the court of Saxony. He brings Italian musical style to Germany and writes the first German opera.
</Question>
<Choice>1617</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Michael Praetorius' Syntagma musicum, an encyclopedic three-volume work on the theory and practice of music, is published in Germany.
</Question>
<Choice>1620</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English composer Thomas Tomkins becomes organist of Chapel Royal, London.
</Question>
<Choice>1621</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Ancient Society of College Youths is formed in England to promote "change ringing" of church bells.
</Question>
<Choice>1637</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Publication of the Bay Psalm Book, the first book to be printed in the North American British colonies.
</Question>
<Choice>1640</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian composer Giacomo Carissimi, one of the best-known composers of the 17th century, writes his oratorio Jephtha. Carissimi wrote a number of oratorios, including several with religious subjects.
</Question>
<Choice>1650</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Paris Opéra, one of the most revered musical institutions in Europe, is founded as the Royal Academy of Music (Académie Royale de Musique).
</Question>
<Choice>1669</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mykola Dyletsky introduces Western musical concepts, soprano singers, and a more expressive style to Russian choral singing, to the horror of traditionalists.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1675</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian violin-maker Antonio Stradivari begins to experiment with varnishes, wood thicknesses, and designs for his violins, producing some of the finest instruments ever made.
</Question>
<Choice>1684</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
After having been interrupted by Oliver Cromwell, the singing of the choral offices is restored to St. Paul's Cathedral, London, with John Blow as organist and master of the choristers.
</Question>
<Choice>1687</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Danish composer Dietrich Buxtehude begins his twenty-year tenure as organist of St. Mary's Church in Lübeck. He helps turn the city into a musical centre, and is visited by both Handel and Bach.
</Question>
<Choice>1688</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English Baroque composer Henry Purcell's opera Dido and Aeneas debuts in Chelsea, Eng. It establishes his reputation and popularity as a composer.
</Question>
<Choice>1689</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Marc-Antoine Charpentier, a leading French composer of oratorios and occasional collaborator with Molière, is named music master at the Sainte-Chapelle, Paris.
</Question>
<Choice>1698</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The bass drum is borrowed by European musicians from Turkish Janissary bands.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1700</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Invention of the balalaika, a Russian version of the lute. The balalaika would become an important instrument in popular and folk music.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1700</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian instrument-maker Bartolomeo Cristofori invents the piano. He continues refining his instrument until 1726, when he produces the instrument on which the modern piano is modeled.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1709</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Approximate birthdate of Italian harpsichordist Domenico Alberti, who introduces left-handed broken chords (since called "Alberti bass").
</Question>
<Choice>1710</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The "Three Choirs Festival," combining the cathedral choirs of Gloucester, Worcester, and Hereford, is founded in England.
</Question>
<Choice>1715</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German late Baroque composer Georg Philipp Telemann becomes the musical director of Hamburg's five main churches.
</Question>
<Choice>1721</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German composer and musician Johann Sebastian Bach is appointed director of church music in Leipzig, after Telemann turns down the position.
</Question>
<Choice>1723</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
First performances of Bach's St. Matthew Passion in Leipzig, Ger.
</Question>
<Choice>1727</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John Gay's Beggar's Opera is first performed in London.
</Question>
<Choice>1728</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first secular concert in Boston, Mass., is given in "Mr. Pelham's Great Room" on December 30.
</Question>
<Choice>1731</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The French composer and musical theorist Jean-Philippe Rameau's greatest opera, Hippolyte et Aricie, is first performed. His collaborators include Voltaire and Rousseau.
</Question>
<Choice>1733</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
George Frideric Handel's Messiah: A Sacred Oratorio is performed for the first time in Dublin, Ireland.
</Question>
<Choice>1742</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
William Boyce publishes his wildly successful Twelve Sonatas for Two Violins with a Bass for Violoncello or Harpsichord.
</Question>
<Choice>1747</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The harp songs of famed Irish bard Turlough O'Carolan are published in Dublin by his son.
</Question>
<Choice>1748</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The string quartet, consisting of two violins, viola, and cello, emerges as the most popular type of group in chamber music.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1750</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian composer Franz Joseph Haydn enters the service of Prince Pál Antal Esterházy. One of the most important figures in Classical music, Haydn helps establish both the string quartet and symphony.
</Question>
<Choice>1761</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
St. Cecilia Society, the oldest musical society in America, is founded in Charleston, South Carolina.
</Question>
<Choice>1762</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first missions are established in California by Franciscan friars led by Junipero Sérra. The missions teach plainsong and polyphony to Native Americans.
</Question>
<Choice>1769</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
William Billings publishes The New-England Psalm-Singer, the first collection of music composed entirely in America.
</Question>
<Choice>1770</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
La Scala, one of the world's major operatic venues, is built in Milan.
</Question>
<Choice>1776</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart moves to Vienna, a centre for German music and the stage for the most important and popular work of his career.
</Question>
<Choice>1781</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Philadelphia instrument-maker John Isaac Hawkins invents the upright piano. Smaller and cheaper than the grand piano, it becomes a fixture of middle-class European homes in the 19th century.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1800</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first performance of Ludwig van Beethoven's Symphony #1 in C Major is given in Vienna.
</Question>
<Choice>1801</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
E.T.A. Hoffmann proposes the notion of "the artist as spiritual hero," which becomes an important theme of the Romantic movement.
</Question>
<Choice>1813</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first Southern "shape-note" tune book, Kentucky Harmony, is published for use in song-schools.
</Question>
<Choice>1816</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Stille Nacht ("Silent Night") is written for midnight mass in the village of Oberndorf, Austria, by Franz Gruber.
</Question>
<Choice>1818</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>German Friedrich Buschmann invents the harmonica.</Question>
<Choice>1821</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German instrument-maker Carl Almenräder begins to change the design of the French bassoon, introducing new elements that eventually yield a distinctively German bassoon.
</Question>
<Choice>1825</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German composer Felix Mendelssohn, one of the best-known Romantic composers, conducts the first modern performance of J.S. Bach's St. Matthew Passion, reviving interest in Bach's work.
</Question>
<Choice>1829</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The cancan becomes popular in the music halls of Paris.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1830</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French Romantic composer Hector Berlioz completes his Symphonie fantastique, one of his most famous works.
</Question>
<Choice>1830</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The opera Norma by Italian composer Vincenzo Bellini is first performed at La Scala in Milan.
</Question>
<Choice>1831</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polish composer and piano virtuoso Frédéric Chopin performs the Piano Concerto in F Minor and the Variations, opus 2, in his first Paris concert.
</Question>
<Choice>1832</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The monastery of St. Pierre de Solesmes is refounded by Abbot Proper Geurenger. It is largely responsible for the resurrection of Gregorian chant in the modern Catholic Church.
</Question>
<Choice>1837</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first music is published in Braille notation in Scotland.
</Question>
<Choice>1838</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The clarinet, invented in the early 18th century by German flute-maker Johann Christoph Denner, reaches its mature form with the addition of modern ring keys, needle springs, and mounted keywork.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1840</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Salomon Sulzer, chief Reform cantor of Vienna and the leading figure in 19th-century synagogue music, begins publishing Shir Zion, which outlines the musical principles of Reform Judaism.
</Question>
<Choice>1840</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Felix Mendelssohn becomes the first director of the newly established Leipzig Conservatory.
</Question>
<Choice>1841</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The New York Philharmonic Orchestra, the oldest concert orchestra in continuous existence in the United States, is founded.
</Question>
<Choice>1842</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American composer Stephen Collins Foster publishes his first song, "Open Thy Lattice, Love." He becomes famous for his minstrel songs and sentimental ballads, particularly "Swanee River" (1851).
</Question>
<Choice>1842</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The British Theatre Regulations Act of 1843, which legalized smoking and drinking in music halls, and the rapid growth of the urban working class contribute to the popularity of the music hall.
</Question>
<Choice>1843</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Antoine-Joseph Sax patents the first saxophone.</Question>
<Choice>1846</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian composer Giuseppe Verdi writes his classic La traviata (The Fallen Woman). He is the leading figure in 19th-century opera, writing such great works as Aida (1871) and Otello (1887).
</Question>
<Choice>1853</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-born instrument-maker Henry Engelhard Steinway produces the first Steinway grand piano, in his shop in New York. The Steinway becomes one of the most famous grand pianos.
</Question>
<Choice>1856</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first opera house opens in New Orleans, Louisiana.
</Question>
<Choice>1859</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The American Civil War inspires a number of new patriotic songs. Most famous among them is Julia Ward Howe's "Battle Hymn of the Republic."
</Question>
<Choice>1862</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Charles Gounod's Faust, his most famous opera, is first performed in Paris.
</Question>
<Choice>1869</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nationalist composer Aleksandr Borodin, whose music drew on Russian folk melodies, begins work on his opera Prince Igor.
</Question>
<Choice>1869</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Portuguese visitors introduce the machada to Hawaii. It is adapted by the Hawaiians and renamed the ukulele, Hawaiian for "flea."
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1870</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Brighton Festival is established as a series of "oratorio concerts by subscription only."
</Question>
<Choice>1870</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German musicologist Philipp Spitta publishes the first volume of his monumental two-volume study of J.S. Bach. In 1885 he cofounds the first scholarly journal of musicology.
</Question>
<Choice>1873</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Georges Bizet's great opera Carmen is first performed in Paris.
</Question>
<Choice>1875</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Trial By Jury establishes the popularity of W.S. Gilbert and Arthur Sullivan. Their collaboration later yields such "Savoy Operas" as H.M.S. Pinafore (1878) and Pirates of Penzance (1880).
</Question>
<Choice>1875</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Edvard Grieg, a founder of the Norwegian nationalist school of music, writes the incidental music for Ibsen's Peer Gynt, first performed in Christiana (later Oslo).
</Question>
<Choice>1876</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Gabriel Fauré's Requiem is written and first performed in Paris. It is later revised to include orchestration.
</Question>
<Choice>1877</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Thomas Edison patents the phonograph. By making it possible to record musical performances, it transforms the music industry by helping to revolutionize the way people listen to music.
</Question>
<Choice>1877</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Peter Ilich Tchaikovsky's Swan Lake is first performed in Moscow. Tchaikovsky is regarded as the leading Russian composer of the late 19th century, particularly for his classical ballets.
</Question>
<Choice>1877</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Academic Festival Overture of Johannes Brahms is first performed at the University of Breslau, Ger.
</Question>
<Choice>1881</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German musicologist Hugo Riemann publishes his classic Musiklexikon. Riemann's work on musical harmony would lay the foundations for modern music theory.
</Question>
<Choice>1882</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German composer Richard Wagner, one of the most influential and controversial figures in 19th-century music, completes his last work, Parsifal.
</Question>
<Choice>1882</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Metropolitan Opera Association opens in New York City with a performance of Charles Gounod's Faust.
</Question>
<Choice>1883</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Guido Adler becomes professor of music at the German University of Prague. His method, which emphasizes style criticism in music research, shaped the modern discipline of musicology.
</Question>
<Choice>1885</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian composer Anton Bruckner's Te Deum is first performed in Vienna.
</Question>
<Choice>1886</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Zigeunerlieder of Johannes Brahms are first sung in Frankfurt, Ger.
</Question>
<Choice>1887</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Moulin Rouge, one of the earliest and most famous cabarets, opens in Paris. The cabaret would later be transplanted to Germany and the U.S., where it became a venue for popular music.
</Question>
<Choice>1889</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jean Sibelius, the leading composer of Scandinavia, writes his tone poem "Finlandia."
</Question>
<Choice>1899</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The blues develops in the American Deep South. While its origins are obscure, the genre has had an immense impact on popular music in the 20th century, particularly in the United States and England.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1890</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Carnegie Hall, one of the most famous concert halls in the United States, opens in New York City.
</Question>
<Choice>1891</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Tin Pan Alley's popular music produces the song "And the Band Played On."
</Question>
<Choice>1895</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Gustav Mahler becomes artistic director of the Vienna Art Opera.
</Question>
<Choice>1897</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
African-American composer Scott Joplin publishes his Maple Leaf Rag, which quickly sells one million copies.
</Question>
<Choice>1899</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Giacomo Puccini's opera Tosca premieres in Rome. His other compositions, including La Bohème (1896) and Madame Butterfly (1904), are among the greatest works in the history of operas.
</Question>
<Choice>1900</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Enrico Caruso makes a successful debut in Covent Garden, London, singing in Rigoletto.
</Question>
<Choice>1902</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pope Pius X promulgates his Motu Proprio, which restores Gregorian chant and Renaissance polyphony to prominence in Roman Catholic worship.
</Question>
<Choice>1903</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Bela Bartók and Zoltán Kodály publish their first volume of Hungarian Folk Songs, sparking a new interest in the ethnomusicology of Central Europe.
</Question>
<Choice>1906</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Arnold Schoenberg begins one of the great experiments in modern music when he composes his first atonal works, the piano piece Opus 11, No. 1, and Five Orchestral Pieces, Opus 16.
</Question>
<Choice>1909</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The opening-night performance of Igor Stravinsky's modern ballet The Rite of Spring, at the Théâtre des Champs Élysées, causes a riot. Stravinsky's music is part of the core of 20th-century modernism.
</Question>
<Choice>1913</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Irish-born composer Victor Herbert helps found the American Society of Composers, Arrangers, and Producers (ASCAP), to enforce musical copyright.
</Question>
<Choice>1914</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sergey Rachmaninoff's All-Night Service is sung in Moscow for the first time.
</Question>
<Choice>1915</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>The Latvian National Opera founded in Riga.</Question>
<Choice>1918</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Serialism, a method of composition in which a melodic line is repeated over and over, is developed by Arnold Schoenberg. It is elaborated by later modern composers like Pierre Boulez.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1919</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Arthur Honegger's Le Roi David is staged for the first time in Paris.
</Question>
<Choice>1921</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Arnold Schoenberg composes his first 12-tone work, the Piano Suite, Opus 25.
</Question>
<Choice>1921</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The British Broadcasting Corporation is founded. The government-owned broadcaster becomes an important patron of the arts in Britain, as well as a vehicle for widely diffusing classical music.
</Question>
<Choice>1922</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
George Gershwin's Rhapsody in Blue is first performed.
</Question>
<Choice>1924</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The atonal opera Wozzeck by Alban Berg, a student of Arnold Schoenberg, has its premiere in Berlin.
</Question>
<Choice>1925</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The "Grand Ole Opry" is founded in Nashville, Tennessee. One of the most important centres for country music performance in the United States, it establishes Nashville as the capital of country music.
</Question>
<Choice>1925</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Clarinetist Benny Goodman records his first solo album, He's the Last Word, showing strong New Orleans jazz influence.
</Question>
<Choice>1926</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Broadway theatre season has a record 280 productions. Broadway strongly influences the course of American music in the 20th century.
</Question>
<Choice>1927</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Die Dreigroschenoper (The Three Penny Opera), a collaboration between Bertolt Brecht and Kurt Weill, opens in Berlin.
</Question>
<Choice>1928</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Maurice Ravel's orchestral piece Boléro nearly starts a riot during its debut in Paris.
</Question>
<Choice>1928</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Gospel music, which has its origins in the African-American Pentecostal church movement of the late 1800s, finds its mature voice in the work of Thomas Dorsey, who blends sacred music and blues.
</Question>
<Choice>1929</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Billie Holiday begins singing in Harlem nightclubs, displaying a vivid vocal style that establishes her as the premier jazz singer from the 1930s to the '50s.
</Question>
<Choice>1931</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American composer Hoagy Carmichael records his hit song "Stardust" with Isham Jones. The song had been popular since its publication in 1927 and remains a classic.
</Question>
<Choice>1931</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Berkshire Music Festival begins in Lenox, Massachusetts.
</Question>
<Choice>1934</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Cole Porter's Anything Goes opens in New York.</Question>
<Choice>1934</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American singer Ella Fitzgerald begins her career with the Chick Webb orchestra. In the 1940s and 1950s she becomes one of the best-known female jazz singers.
</Question>
<Choice>1935</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American composer Irving Berlin, famous for such songs as "White Christmas" and "God Bless America," composes his first film musical score, Top Hat.
</Question>
<Choice>1935</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Samuel Barber's Adagio for Strings is first performed.
</Question>
<Choice>1938</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nathaniel Cole forms the Nat King Cole Trio, marking the transition from jazz to big band sound.
</Question>
<Choice>1939</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Alto saxophonist Charles Parker moves to New York, where he plays with Dizzy Gillespie and other jazz notables; he establishes a reputation as the genre's best improvisational player.
</Question>
<Choice>1939</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American composer Randall Thompson conducts the first performance of his Alleluia in Lenox, Mass.
</Question>
<Choice>1940</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Frank Sinatra, a veteran of the Tommy Dorsey Orchestra, first reaches national prominence as a soloist on the radio program "Your Hit Parade."
</Question>
<Choice>1940</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A Ceremony of Carols, written for treble voices and harp by Benjamin Britten, is first performed at Norwich Castle.
</Question>
<Choice>1942</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Bing Crosby's recording of Irving Berlin's "White Christmas" becomes one of the most popular songs in American history.
</Question>
<Choice>1942</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Appalachian Spring, a ballet by Aaron Copland, is danced for the first time by Martha Graham’s company. Copland's work is notable for its use of folk music melodies.
</Question>
<Choice>1944</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Dizzy Gillespie founds the first "bop" orchestra.</Question>
<Choice>1944</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Benjamin Britten's opera Peter Grimes is performed for the first time in Sadler's Wells, United Kingdom.
</Question>
<Choice>1945</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Virgil Thomson and Gertrude Stein collaborate to create Louisiana Story, an opera about the women's suffrage movement.
</Question>
<Choice>1946</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jazz trumpeter and singer Louis Armstrong, the most famous and popular jazz musician in the U.S. since the 1930s, forms his All Stars jazz ensemble.
</Question>
<Choice>1947</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Rodgers and Hammerstein's Oklahoma! opens on Broadway.
</Question>
<Choice>1947</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jazz performers, most notably alto saxophonist Charlie Parker, experiment with "bebop," a fluid, improvisational style employing chromatic scales and complex rhythms.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1948</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Bluegrass is invented by mandolin player Bill Monroe, leader of the Blue Grass Boys, and banjo player Earl Scruggs.
</Question>
<Choice>1948</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mahalia Jackson's Gospel-blues record Let the Power of the Holy Ghost Fall on Me wins the French Academy's Grand Prix du Disc.
</Question>
<Choice>1949</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jazz trumpeter Miles Davis releases Birth of the Cool, which defines the West Coast "cool" style of jazz. His later albums are milestones in modal jazz, jazz rock, and electronic jazz.
</Question>
<Choice>1949</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Elliot Carter's String Quartet #1, characterized by complex metrical modulation and intricate harmonies, is first performed.
</Question>
<Choice>1951</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian-born American composer Gian Carlo Menotti is commissioned by NBC to write the first opera for television, Amahl and the Night Visitors.
</Question>
<Choice>1951</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John Cage creates his first "taped" work, Landscape No. 5, for a dance by Jean Erdman. Cage becomes one of the most famous postwar American composers.
</Question>
<Choice>1952</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Karlheinz Stockhausen's Elektronische Studie I ("Electronic Study") is the first composition consisting of sine wave sounds. Stockhausen's work is influential in avant-garde musical circles.
</Question>
<Choice>1953</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Francis Poulenc's Dialogue of the Carmelites, using an almost entirely female cast, opens in Paris.
</Question>
<Choice>1953</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ralph Vaughan Williams' Hodie: A Christmas Cantata debuts in London.
</Question>
<Choice>1954</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Rock music is born in the United States.</Question>
<Choice>c. 1955</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
RCA engineers invent the first electronic synthesizer. Improved by Robert Moog and others in the 1960s and 1970s, electronic instruments would revolutionize modern composition and performance.
</Question>
<Choice>1955</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Elvis Presley releases his first single, "Heartbreak Hotel." Elvis would help shape the public image, and wide popularity, of rock music in the late 1950s and 1960s.
</Question>
<Choice>1956</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
James Brown releases his first single, "Please, Please, Please." His popular success and wide influence earn him the nickname "the godfather of soul."
</Question>
<Choice>1956</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Leonard Bernstein's musical West Side Story, based on William Shakespeare's Romeo and Juliet, makes its debut in New York.
</Question>
<Choice>1957</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Johnny Cash establishes his position as a leading country music artist with songs like "Folsom Prison Blues," and "I Walk the Line."
</Question>
<Choice>1957</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English violinist and teacher Neville Marriner founds the Academy of St. Martin-in-the-Fields, in London. The chamber ensemble becomes one of the best-known and most popular in the world.
</Question>
<Choice>1959</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Songwriter Berry Gordy, Jr., founds the Motown Recording Corporation. The label's performers would include some of the most popular musicians of the 1960s, including Marvin Gaye and Stevie Wonder.
</Question>
<Choice>1959</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Milton Babbitt writes the first completely synthesized work, Composition for Synthesizer.
</Question>
<Choice>1961</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Second Vatican Council is convened in Rome. Its reforms, announced in 1965, will result in sweeping changes in liturgical music.
</Question>
<Choice>1962</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first album by the Beatles, Please Please Me, is released in the United Kingdom. Led by John Lennon and Paul McCartney, the Beatles become one of the most important rock groups of all time.
</Question>
<Choice>1962</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Barbra Streisand releases her first solo album, which wins two Grammy Awards.
</Question>
<Choice>1963</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John Coltrane records his masterpiece A Love Supreme, marking the high point of his innovations in jazz.
</Question>
<Choice>1964</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Beatles tour the United States for the first time. Their appearance on “The Ed Sullivan Show" draws 73 million viewers.
</Question>
<Choice>1965</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The National Endowment for the Arts is established in Washington, D.C., to support the fine arts.
</Question>
<Choice>1965</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Folk musician Bob Dylan scandalizes musical purists by playing electric guitar on his album Highway 61 Revisited.
</Question>
<Choice>1965</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Aretha Franklin establishes herself as the "Queen of Soul" with the release of "Respect."
</Question>
<Choice>1967</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jimi Hendrix releases his debut album, Are You Experienced? Between 1967 and his death in 1970, Hendrix establishes a reputation as the most innovative and skilled guitarist in rock music.
</Question>
<Choice>1967</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Tammy Wynette, considered the "first lady of country music," releases her anthem, "Stand by Your Man."
</Question>
<Choice>1968</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Stanley Kubrick's 2001: A Space Odyssey brings to popular attention the radical work of Hungarian composer György Ligeti, whose work consists of shifting tone colours devoid of melodies and rhythms.
</Question>
<Choice>1968</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Plácido Domingo makes his debut at La Scala in Milan. The Spanish-born tenor is noted for his resonant and powerful voice.
</Question>
<Choice>1969</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
African-American soprano Jessye Norman makes her operatic debut as Elisabeth in Richard Wagner's Tannhäuser.
</Question>
<Choice>1969</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The three-day Woodstock Art and Music Fair, one of the high points of the counterculture of the 1960s, takes place near Woodstock, N.Y.
</Question>
<Choice>1969</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Arthur Fiedler retires after forty years as conductor of the Boston Pops.
</Question>
<Choice>1970</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American minimalist composer Steve Reich composes Four Organs, a work for four electric organs and maracas.
</Question>
<Choice>1970</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
New Zealand soprano Kiri Te Kanawa rises to international prominence as the Countess in Mozart's Marriage of Figaro.
</Question>
<Choice>1971</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Duke Ellington becomes first jazz musician elected to the Royal Music Academy of Stockholm.
</Question>
<Choice>1971</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Rolling Stones record their dark classic, Exile on Main Street.
</Question>
<Choice>1972</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jamaican musician Bob Marley's album Catch a Fire establishes his international popularity and brings reggae music to the attention of audiences in Europe and America.
</Question>
<Choice>1973</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jean Langlais' Five Meditations on the Apocalypse is performed for the first time in Paris.
</Question>
<Choice>1974</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Playing the role of Pamira in "Le Siège de Corinthe," Beverly Sills makes her debut at the Metropolitan Opera in New York City.
</Question>
<Choice>1975</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American composer Philip Glass's opera Einstein on the Beach makes its debut, winning the cerebral, minimalist Glass a wide following.
</Question>
<Choice>1976</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
After an absence of many years, conductor Herbert von Karajan returns to the Wiener Stadtsoper (Vienna State Opera).
</Question>
<Choice>1977</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The compact disc begins to appear in record stores. Within a decade the small, digital discs would all but replace phonograph records and radically improve the quality of music recording.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1980</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Michael Jackson releases "Thriller," one of the most successful albums in the world. Its sales are helped by Jackson's music videos for MTV cable television.
</Question>
<Choice>1982</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Seattle-based rock band Pearl Jam releases its debut CD, Ten. The band's success marks the growing popularity of grunge rock, developed in Seattle in the 1980s.
</Question>
<Choice>1991</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Whitney Houston's soulful rendition of "I Will Always Love You" tops the pop charts for 14 weeks, a record in the music industry.
</Question>
<Choice>1992</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Henryk Gorecki's Symphony No. 3: Symphony of Sorrowful Songs becomes a surprise best-seller in Europe and the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1993</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The death of guitarist Jerry Garcia marks the end of the Grateful Dead, one of the most long-lived and iconoclastic groups in rock music.
</Question>
<Choice>1995</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A number of musical events commemorate the 50th anniversary of the end of World War II, most notably the Requiem of Reconciliation.
</Question>
<Choice>1995</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Rock and Roll Hall of Fame opens in Cleveland, Ohio.
</Question>
<Choice>1995</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Displaying "Girl Power," the Spice Girls make history in England as their first four singles hit number one on the British charts.
</Question>
<Choice>1997</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Singer Sarah McLachlan founds Lilith Fair, a traveling summer concert tour of female performers. Its phenomenal success proves the marketability of female artists.
</Question>
<Choice>1997</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
World Music is firmly established as a niche in popular music, spurred by marketing developments, technological advances, and collaboration among musicians in the West, Africa, and Asia.
</Question>
<Choice>1997</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The San Francisco Opera produces the world premiere of the opera version of Tennessee Williams's play A Streetcar Named Desire.
</Question>
<Choice>1998</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Lauryn Hill wins five Grammy Awards for her groundbreaking solo album, The Miseducation of Lauryn Hill, credited with establishing rap music firmly in the mainstream.
</Question>
<Choice>1999</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ricky Martin and Jennifer Lopez lead the explosion of Latin pop music.
</Question>
<Choice>1999</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian opera tenor Andrea Bocelli becomes the first classical artist to top the U.S. pop charts with his album "Sogno."
</Question>
<Choice>1999</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Teen music, led by 'N Sync, Britney Spears, Christina Aguilera, and the Backstreet Boys, dominates the airwaves and record sales.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Carlos Santana wins a record-tying eight Grammy Awards for his album Supernatural.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Experience Music Project, a rock and roll museum, opens in Seattle, Washington, to much fanfare.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Steely Dan earns three Grammy Awards, including best album, for Two Against Nature (2000), their first studio album in 20 years.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
La Scala, Milan's opera house, closes for renovations, which take some three years to complete.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Former Beatle George Harrison dies. Earlier in the year, the Beatles returned to the top of the charts with 1, a collection of their greatest hits.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The lawsuit between record labels and Napster, an Internet site where users swap music files, raises issues of copyright infringement and misuse.
</Question>
<Choice>2002</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hip-hop artist Eminem tops the music charts with The Eminem Show, which sells more than 7.5 million copies. He also makes his motion-picture debut in 8 Mile, a semiautobiographical movie that earns commercial and critical success.
</Question>
<Choice>2002</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jazz singer Norah Jones wins 5 Grammy Awards, including best new artist and album (Come Away with Me).
</Question>
<Choice>2003</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
World-renowned Italian tenor Luciano Pavarotti gives his final performance on the operatic stage in a production of Giacomo Puccini's Tosca at New York City's Metropolitan Opera.
</Question>
<Choice>2004</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The London Symphony Orchestra celebrates its 100th season.
</Question>
<Choice>2004</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In an attempt to call attention to poverty in Africa, a series of concerts, known as Live 8, are held around the world on the eve of the Group of Eight (G-8) summit.
</Question>
<Choice>2005</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the mountains of Swabia in southwestern Germany, archaeologists unearth what is believed to be the world's oldest musical instruments, a 35,000-year-old flute fashioned out of a wooly mammoth tusk and two smaller flutes made of swan bones.
</Question>
<Choice>2005</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The seminal punk band Sex Pistols--which released only one album, Never Mind the Bollocks, Here's the Sex Pistols--is inducted into the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame but refuses to attend the ceremony.
</Question>
<Choice>2006</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Apple announces that more than two billion songs have been purchased from iTunes. The world's most popular online music store, iTunes allows users to download songs to their computers and MP3 players.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British rock band Led Zeppelin stages its first full-blown concert in more than 25 years.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In an attempt to reach a wider audience, the Metropolitan Opera Company broadcasts live, in high-definition digital format, several productions to movie theatres around the world.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British art-rock band Radiohead releases its seventh album, In Rainbows, via Internet download and allows fans to pay any price they wish. The album is sold as a standard CD the following year.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American pop star Madonna is inducted into the Rock and Roll Hall of Fame.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The British band Coldplay continues to enjoy great popularity as Viva la Vida tops the charts in the United Kingdom and the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Seattle band Fleet Foxes are at the forefront of a hippie folk rock revival.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Widely regarded as one of the best rap artists of his generation, Lil Wayne receives eight Grammy nominations for Tha Carter III.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Continuing his mid-career resurgence, Bruce Springsteen wins a Golden Globe for "The Wrestler," a song featured in the movie of the same name; headlines the halftime show at the Super Bowl; and releases the album Working on a Dream.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Michael Jackson, known as the "King of Pop" for his best-selling music, dies shortly before the start of a comeback tour; the cause of death was a lethal combination of sedatives and propofol, an anesthetic.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Green Day produces a punk opera largely based on its best-selling album American Idiot (2004).
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Taylor Swift, at age 19, becomes the youngest-ever artist to be named entertainer of the year by the Country Music Association
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Noted rhythm-and-blues singer Teddy Pendergrass dies.
</Question>
<Choice>2010</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Beyoncé wins six Grammy Awards, including song of the year for "Single Ladies (Put a Ring on It)"; it was the most trophies awarded to a female performer at one Grammy ceremony.
</Question>
<Choice>2010</Choice>
</item>
</topics>