<topics>
<item>
<Question>
Various religions have creation myths describing the origins of the universe and, through them, the meaning of life, the underlying order of nature, and destiny of humans and the cosmos.
</Question>
<Choice>In the Beginning</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Some Neanderthal peoples bury their dead with food, artifacts, and red ochre, suggesting possible belief in an afterlife.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 70,000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Paleolithic people create wall engravings, some of which may have had religious significance.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 30,000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Development of Desert cultures in southwestern North America, in which religion is associated with food plant gathering and some shamanism.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 8000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Agricultural village culture begins in China. Members of these villages practice bone divination and cult of the dead.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 6000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Development of agriculture in Central America leads to established settlements and ritual centres that involve sacred rulers and plant spirits.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 5000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
King Menes unifies Upper and Lower Egypt, founding the first Egyptian dynasty. He celebrates with the construction of a new temple to Ptah.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 3110 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Arrival of maize culture in North America leads to village settlements and religious change, including the use of earthen mounds in religious constructions.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 3000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Step Pyramid at Saqqarah is built. The oldest example of Egyptian pyramidal royal tombs, it is constructed to ensure the dead's successful voyage to the next world.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 2650 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Development of the Indus River civilization in modern-day India and Pakistan. It practices indigenous religion with public and domestic goddess worship.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 2500 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Egyptian gods, mythologies, and cults are connected through the myth of divine kingship. Among the most important of the gods is Osiris, god of fertility and the underworld.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 2475 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mesopotamian king Naram-Sin declares himself divine. He refocuses the state's religious ideology from one deity associated with a particular city to a universal divine king.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 2254 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
According to traditional sources, Abraham (the first Hebrew patriarch) leads his people out of Mesopotamia into Canaan, between modern-day Syria and Egypt.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 2000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Redaction of traditions regarding Gilgamesh, a 3rd-millennium Sumerian king. His epic journey weaves together themes of immortality, the Flood, and divine retribution.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1800 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Olmec civilization arises in much of Mesoamerica. Urban culture grows, along with the importance of sacred rulers, powerful deities, and shamanic practices.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1500 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese Shang dynasty kings and priests practice rituals to deified ancestors and nature gods, and they continue bone divination.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1400 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
King Akhenaton of Egypt's 18th dynasty promotes a monotheistic belief in the sun god Aton, countering ancient Egypt's traditional polytheism.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1350 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Under the leadership of Moses, Hebrew slaves escape from Egyptian captivity and travel to Canaan. At Mount Sinai they receive the Ten Commandments, sealing a covenant with God.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1290 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Following its arrival in South Asia, Indo-Aryan writers compose the Sanskrit Vedas, a collection of hymns to the gods. Foremost among them is the Rigveda.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1200 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Babylonian king Nebuchadrezzar I focuses Babylonian state religion on Marduk, changing the god's role from city patron to henotheistic manifestation of all divinities.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1125 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese emperor claims authority as "Decree of Heaven" during Zhou (Chou) dynasty. Ancestors are worshiped in attempts to influence natural deities.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1040 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Israelite dynastic monarchy under David is established, with Jerusalem as the capital.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1013 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Eastern Woodland cultures in North America develop burial mounds and create Mother Earth images.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Vedic priests in South Asia compile Brahmana texts as ritual manuals, which contain discussions and narratives relating to sacrifice.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Probable period of Zoroaster, an eastern Iranian thinker who breaks from Indo-Iranian religious traditions in advocating monotheism and ethical dualism.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The First Jewish Temple in Jerusalem is built by King Solomon, son of David, to house the Ark of the Covenant.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 950 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Olmec religion develops cult devotion to gods associated with natural forces.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 900 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Earliest estimated date of the composition of the Chinese Tao-te ching ("Classic of the Way of Power"), by an unknown author.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 800 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Beginnings of classical Jewish prophecy with Amos, who decries the corruption and injustice in Israelite society.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 750 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Assyrians conquer Samaria, marking the decline of the 10 northern Jewish tribes.
</Question>
<Choice>721 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hesiod composes his Theogony, which outlines the lineage of the ancient Greek gods and describes their rise to and preservation of power.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 700 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The I-ching ("Classic of Change") is composed in Chou dynasty China as wisdom literature intended to give practitioners divine guidance for their lives.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 680 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Creative peak of Upanisad writers, who compiled esoteric teachings that explain the nature of the universe and humanity through the notions of “Brahman” and “atman.”
</Question>
<Choice>c. 600 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Rise of prominence of the temple of Delphi, one of the most important Greek temples and the oracle of Apollo. The temple would operate until Christianity displaced pagan religion in Greece.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 590 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Babylonians conquer southern kingdom of Judea, destroy the first Jewish Temple in Jerusalem, and initiate the Babylonian exile.
</Question>
<Choice>586 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
According to tradition, the First Buddhist Council at Rajagrha fashions monastic discipline and composes instructive sutras.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 543 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the dates—which vary according to tradition—for the enlightenment of Siddhartha Gautama and his attainment of the title "Buddha" ("Awakened One").
</Question>
<Choice>528 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Traditional date for the death of Mahavira, practitioner of extreme nonviolence, 24th and last Tirthankara ("ford-maker") of Jainism.
</Question>
<Choice>527 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Construction of the second Temple of Jerusalem is finished.
</Question>
<Choice>515 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
K'ung-fu-tzu (Confucius) attempts ethical reforms in China to restore the social balance according to the Tao ("Way") as willed by Heaven.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 500 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Second Buddhist Council at Vaishali tightens monastic discipline and ends in a sectarian split between Mahasanghikas and Theravadins.
</Question>
<Choice>483 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Earliest version of the Mahabharata ("Great Epic of the Bharata Dynasty") is composed. One of the great epic poems of world literature, it will be revised and expanded until c. 400 AD.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 400 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Composition of early versions of the Dharmasutra and Dharmashastra texts, which define Hindu behaviour in ritual, society, politics, and law.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 400 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Meng-tzu (Mencius) in China composes the book, known as the Mencius, that helps spread Confucian ideas about the centrality of filial piety and the contingency of the Mandate of Heaven.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 320 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Ramayana ("Romance of Rama") is completed by the Indian sage Valmiki. Along with the Mahabharata, it is one of the two great Sanskrit epic poems.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 310 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Development of Maya civilization in south-central Mesoamerica. Prominent in religious life are ceremonial centres, which later develop into cities.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 300 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Renouncing violence after his violent victory at Kalinga, Mauryan emperor Ashoka adopts Buddhism personally and patronizes it institutionally.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 261 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Third Buddhist Council is called by emperor Ashoka at Pataliputra. By now divided into various schools, this council may have included only members of the Theravada school of Buddhism.
</Question>
<Choice>247 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese emperor Wudi (Wu-ti) declares Confucianism the imperial ideology and state cult. Confucianism flourishes and eventually spreads to Korea, Japan, and Vietnam.
</Question>
<Choice>136 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Religious ceremonial buildings are built in the Andes.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 100 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jains split into Digambara ("Sky-clad") and Shvetambaras ("White-robed") sects, finalizing a rift over monastic rules. According to the Shvetambaras, the rift occurred in 83.
</Question>
<Choice>80 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman senate confers divinity upon Julius Caesar, beginning an imperial cult in which his successor, Augustus, would fashion himself as mediator between the gods and humanity.
</Question>
<Choice>44 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman poet Virgil composes the Aeneid, which depicts the origins of Roman religion in both the Greek mythology and local ritual.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 25 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the 6th century, Dionysius Exiguus centres the Western Christian calendar on this, the supposed year of Christ's birth, dividing time into AD and BC.
</Question>
<Choice>1</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Following a three-year ministry in Judea, Samaria, and Galilee, Jesus is crucified by Jewish and Roman leaders and, according to tradition, resurrected.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 32</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Paul (previously Saul of Tarsus) converts to Christianity and becomes one of its most important missionaries and interpreters.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 35</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The second Jewish Temple in Jerusalem is destroyed, prompting a shift of focus of Judaism toward rabbinical leadership and development of the Talmud.
</Question>
<Choice>70</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Four Gospels ("good news") are written between 70 and 120 AD by the evangelists Matthew, Mark, Luke, and John.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 70</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Emergence of Gnosticism. A syncretic faith drawing on Iranian religion, Platonic philosophy, and Jewish mysticism, it has a strong impact on early Christianity.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 120</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Canonization of the 27 books of the New Testament begins. Previously a more fluid body of writings, the Scriptures are defined more precisely in part to counter emergent heretical writings.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 150</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian Buddhist monk Nagarjuna founds the Madhyamika ("Middle Path") school of Mahayana thought, which focuses on the notion of "emptiness."
</Question>
<Choice>c. 200</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Mishna is edited by Rabbi Judah ha-Nasi. It brings into written form a collection of centuries-old oral laws that supplement the Pentateuch.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 200</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the most significant texts in Mahayana Buddhism, the Lotus Sutra places a deified Buddha as the goal of both devotion and personal attainment.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 270</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Persecutions of Christians by the Roman Empire culminate under the emperor Diocletian.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 300</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Through the patronage of Emperor Constantine I, the Roman Empire recognizes Christianity as a legal religion in the Edict of Milan.
</Question>
<Choice>313</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Christian monasticism begins with the ascetic activities and written rule of the hermit St. Anthony of Egypt.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 320</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Council of Nicaea addresses the Arian heresy, which challenges the dogma of the Trinity, with an affirmation that God and the Son of God are of the same essence.
</Question>
<Choice>325</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Development of Christian cenobitic (communal) monasticism in Egypt, under the guidance of Pachomius of the Thebaid and other Desert Fathers.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 330</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Constantinople, established on the site of Byzantium by the emperor Constantine as a "Christian city" in 324, replaces Rome as the capital of the Roman Empire.
</Question>
<Choice>330</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Constantine the Great abolishes crucifixion, a method of execution practiced in the Roman world since the 6th century BC.
</Question>
<Choice>337</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Under Theodosius I, who becomes emperor in 392, the Roman Empire adopts Christianity as its state religion.
</Question>
<Choice>392</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Composition of the earlier Puranas, Sanskrit collections of narratives regarding cosmogony, the gods, humanity, and kings. The Puranas would be expanded until roughly 1000.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 400</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Yogacara school of Mahayana Buddhism in South Asia reaches its peak, under the leadership of the monk Asanga and his younger brother Vasubandhu.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 400</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Palestinian Talmud ("study"), a commentary on the Mishna, is completed after nearly 300 years’ work. The Babylonian Talmud is completed 100 years later.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 400</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese Buddhist monk Fa-hsien begins a long pilgrimage through Buddhist centres in India and Ceylon, returning with a large body of sacred texts unknown to the Chinese.
</Question>
<Choice>402</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Augustine of Hippo, the greatest early Christian thinker, outlines a theology of history in his City of God. His other great work is his Confessions, the first autobiography written in the West.
</Question>
<Choice>426</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Compilation continues of the Avesta, a collection of Zoroastrian texts, some attributed to Zoroaster and of ancient origin, which outline themes of ethical dualism and monotheism.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 450</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Council of Chalcedon, convened by Pope Leo I in response to Monophysite doctrine controversy, affirms that two natures are in the one person of Christ.
</Question>
<Choice>451</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Development of Hindu Tantrism. It separates into exoteric "right-handed" and esoteric "left-handed" practices, which involve a range of ritual and meditative practices.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 480</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Buddhism is introduced to Japan from Korea in the 6th century. It spurs the labeling as "Shinto" previously unsystematic preexisting local worship of kami (supernatural beings).
</Question>
<Choice>c. 500</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Vajrayana ("Vehicle of the Diamond") Buddhism, combining Yogacara discipline and Madhyamika philosophy with Tantric practice, flourishes from the 6th to the 11th century.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 510</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Benedictine Rule is established by Saint Benedict, and construction begins on the monastery at Monte Cassino. The rule establishes the pattern and daily rhythm for medieval monasticism.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 529</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Celtic Christian missionary Brendan founds the monastery at Clonfert, Ireland. A leader of early medieval Celtic mission activity, Brendan is also remembered in legend as a traveler.
</Question>
<Choice>561</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Augustine, a Roman Benedictine, travels to England. There he founds the church at Canterbury, the primary seat of English Christianity.
</Question>
<Choice>597</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Bhakti, a form of Hindu devotionalism, develops in South India.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 600</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In his hometown of Mecca, Muhammad reports the first of the revelations that compose the Qur'an.
</Question>
<Choice>610</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Persecuted, Muhammad escapes to Medina to establish the Muslim community (umma). The first year of the Muslim lunar calendar dates from this hijrah (emigration).
</Question>
<Choice>622</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The greatly outnumbered Muslims interpret their success against their Meccan rivals at the Battle of Badr as a sign of Allah's favour.
</Question>
<Choice>624</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Muhammad successfully returns with the umma to Mecca and rededicates the Ka'bah for monotheistic devotion.
</Question>
<Choice>630</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Following the death of Muhammad, the reign of the "Rightly Guided Caliphs" brings a vast expansion of Islam. By the early 700s, the faith stretches from North Africa to the Near East.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 632</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ch'an Buddhism develops in China as a form of Mahayana that, avoiding scholasticism and ritual, uses logic to awaken the Buddha-nature present in all people.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 640</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Caliph 'Uthman ibn 'Affan oversees the redaction of a standard version of the Qur'an.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 650</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
'Ali, cousin and son-in-law of Muhammad and fourth caliph, is assassinated at Kufah, Iraq, contributing to the split between Sunni and Shi'ah Muslims.
</Question>
<Choice>661</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Husayn, son of 'Ali, is massacred with Shi'ite followers at Karbala, Iraq, thus establishing a Shi'ite paradigm of suffering and pessimism.
</Question>
<Choice>680</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Completion of the Dome of the Rock, Jerusalem. The mosque is situated on the spot where Muhammad ascended into Heaven and where Abraham prepared the sacrifice of Isaac.
</Question>
<Choice>691</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In South Asia in the 8th century, Hindu philosopher Shankara composes commentaries on the Upanisads, which promote the nondualism of Advaita Vedanta.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 700</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Earliest approximate date of Zoroastrian migration from Iran to Diu and Gujarat, in India, in an attempt to escape Muslim domination. In India, they become known as Parsis ("Persians").
</Question>
<Choice>c. 700</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Influenced by Mesoamerican contact in the 8th century, members of the North American Mississippian culture practice fertility religion and venerate sacred kings.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 710</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Sailendra dynasty begins construction of the Borobudur monument in central Java, merging the Buddhist art forms of stupa and mandala.
</Question>
<Choice>778</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Charlemagne is crowned as first emperor of the Holy Roman Empire, as the result of an alliance between the papacy and the Franks.
</Question>
<Choice>800</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first of several large, sophisticated Hindu temples are built at Bhubaneswar, a dynastic capital and religious centre in eastern India.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 800</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Khmer rulers begin construction of Hindu temples at Angkor. The most famous of these, the Angkor Wat temple complex (completed c. 1150), is the world's largest religious structure.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 890</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Toltec empire develops in Mesoamerica. Its iconography suggests it is a militaristic culture, whose members are followers of warrior cults.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 900</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Burgundian Abbey of Cluny is established, marking the beginning of the Cluniac reforms.
</Question>
<Choice>910</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The grand prince of Kiev, Vladimir I, initiates the spread of Orthodox Christianity in Rus when he is baptized into the faith.
</Question>
<Choice>988</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In China, Neo-Confucianism contributes to a revival of Confucian thought that lasts 800 years.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spread of Mississippian culture into eastern plains of North America mixes local religion with cosmological ritual and symbol system.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Avicenna (Ibn Sina) dies after a controversial life in which he merged Islamic mysticism with Platonic philosophy.
</Question>
<Choice>1037</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Schism of 1054 over theological and political differences and the mutual excommunication of the pope and the patriarch, mark the definite break between Greek and Latin churches.
</Question>
<Choice>1054</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hindu theologian Ramanuja, a major figure in devotional Hinduism, argues (against the views of Shankara) that the perceived world is real and not an obstruction to moksa ("liberation").
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1060</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Rashi (Rabbi Shlomo Yitzhaqi) of Troyes, the first great northern European Jewish scholar, begins one of the most influential commentaries on the Bible and the Talmud.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1065</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pope Gregory VII, a major figure in church reform, and Holy Roman Emperor Henry IV struggle over lay investiture, leading to Henry's excommunication and later absolution.
</Question>
<Choice>1075</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Muslim theologian al-Ghazali abandons his successful theological career for the life of a mystic. His voluminous writings help integrate Sufism into the mainstream of Islam.
</Question>
<Choice>1095</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
First of several European Crusades attempts to liberate Jerusalem and the "Holy Land" from Muslim rule and expand the power and wealth of European rulers into the Middle East.
</Question>
<Choice>1095</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Establishment of the Cistercian monastic order, led by St. Robert of Molesme. The Cistercians observed strict rules requiring manual labour and poverty.
</Question>
<Choice>1098</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Tamil author Kampan composes the Iramavataram, a Tamil-language version of the Ramayana.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1150</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Establishment of the Carmelite order on Mt. Carmel, in Palestine. The order's early members consisted of pilgrims and soliders from the Crusades. It migrated to Europe in the 1240s.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1155</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Japanese school of Pure Land (Jodo) Buddhism is founded by Honen in Japan.
</Question>
<Choice>1175</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Muslim Sultan Salah ad-Din (Saladin) recaptures Jerusalem after 88 years of Frankish rule. He goes on to drive the Crusaders out of all but three cities in the Holy Land.
</Question>
<Choice>1187</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Buddhist priest Ensai introduces the Chinese Ch'an sect Lin-chi into Japan. Though Zen Buddhism first appeared in Japan in the 6th century, Ensai's effort are responsible for its full flowering.
</Question>
<Choice>1191</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Spain, Moses Maimonides completes his Arabic-language The Guide for the Perplexed. It establishes him as the preeminent Jewish philosopher of the Middle Ages.
</Question>
<Choice>1191</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish Muslim Averroës (Ibn Rushd) dies. His work challenged the antiphilosophical arguments of al-Ghazali and established him as the foremost commentator on Aristotle.
</Question>
<Choice>1198</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Inca rule expands from the Andes and will reach from Argentina to Ecuador, using an imperial religion of the Sun to unify the state.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1200</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Mesoamerica, Aztec civilization slowly displaces Toltec. In their cities, most notably Tenochtitlán, they build large religious ceremonial centres and practice human sacrifice.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1200</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Francis of Assisi and a group of friars found the Franciscan order with the approval of Pope Innocent III.
</Question>
<Choice>1209</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Dominican order is founded by St. Dominic. One of four mendicant orders in the Catholic church, it eschews property and is supported by charitable contributions.
</Question>
<Choice>1215</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pope Gregory IX initiates the Catholic Inquisition in an effort to discover and try heretics. At first using only verbal interrogation, from 1252 it was authorized to use physical torture.
</Question>
<Choice>1231</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Thomas Aquinas, the leading Catholic intellectual of the late Middle Ages, writes his Summa theologiae to systematize Christian theology and incorporate Aristotelian philosophy.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1265</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish Kabbalist Moses de León writes the Sefer ha-Zohar ("Book of Splendor"). Long ascribed to an ancient author, it is Judaism's most important mystical work.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1280</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The papacy abandons Rome for Avingon, France, for safety.
</Question>
<Choice>1309</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The return of the papacy from Avignon to Rome leads to the Great, or Western, Schism, which divides the papacy between two and then three rival popes. The schism ends in 1417.
</Question>
<Choice>1377</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English theologian John Wycliffe begins his systematic and scholarly criticism of the Catholic church. His work criticizes the doctrine of transubstantiation and advocates predestination.
</Question>
<Choice>1378</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Czech reformer Jan Hus, an opponent of the practice of selling indulgences and one of many pre-Reformation critics of the Catholic church, is burned at the stake for heresy.
</Question>
<Choice>1415</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ottoman Turks capture Constantinople, destroy the Byzantine Empire, and establish the city (renamed "Istanbul") as the capital of the Ottoman Empire.
</Question>
<Choice>1453</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Gutenberg Bible is published on the newly invented printing press. It foreshadows the mass production and distribution of texts, which contribute to the Protestant Reformation.
</Question>
<Choice>1453</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pope Sixtus IV authorizes the Spanish Inquisition to combat Muslims, Jews, and heretics in the newly reconquered territories of Spain. It is directed by Tomás de Torquemada.
</Question>
<Choice>1478</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian mystic Kabir of Varanasi seeks to unify Hindu and Muslim religious traditions, preaching a faith that combined Hindu notions of karma and predestination with Muslim monotheism.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1490</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish Christians conquer Granada, ending the Muslim Nasrid dynasty, which ruled southern Spain from 1238. They expel those Jews and Moors (Muslims) who refuse to convert to Catholicism.
</Question>
<Choice>1492</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Renaissance scholar Desiderius Erasmus publishes his Handbook of a Christian Knight in 1503 and 1504, which advocates humanist learning and ecclesiastical reform.
</Question>
<Choice>1503</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Rajput princess Mira Bai refuses to consummate her marriage, claiming to having already married the god Krishna, and begins her life as a model of Hindu loving-devotion.
</Question>
<Choice>1516</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
To the door of Wittenberg Chapel, Martin Luther nails his "95 Theses," which challenge a variety of practices in the Catholic church. His actions spark the Protestant Reformation.
</Question>
<Choice>1517</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The overthrow of the Aztec Empire, by Spanish conquistadores led by Hernán Cortés and indigenous allies, marks the decline of native religions in Mexico and the institution of Catholicism.
</Question>
<Choice>1521</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
First baptisms of the Anabaptists, who, inspired by Swiss Reformer Huldrych Zwingli, practice adult baptism following public confession.
</Question>
<Choice>1525</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ottoman forces lay siege to Vienna, provoking European fears of the political and doctrinal challenge of Islam for Western Christianity.
</Question>
<Choice>1529</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Two apparitions of the Virgin of Guadalupe (later patroness of Mexico) appear before Indian convert Juan Diego. The Basilica of Guadalupe is the main religious centre of Mexico.
</Question>
<Choice>1531</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A Spanish expedition led by Francisco Pizarro overthrows the Inca empire. In the following years, Inca religious traditions are suppressed, and Catholicism becomes the official religion.
</Question>
<Choice>1532</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Act of Supremacy finalizes the Church of England's break with the Catholic church. King Henry VIII is declared head of the church, and monasteries are suppressed.
</Question>
<Choice>1534</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Geneva, French Protestant John Calvin writes Institutes of the Christian Religion. His vision of Christianity propels him into leadership in the Protestant movement.
</Question>
<Choice>1536</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The death of Indian guru (“religious teacher”) Nanak is followed by a lineage of nine other gurus, each of whom helps further establish the Sikh tradition.
</Question>
<Choice>1539</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ignatius Loyola founds the Society of Jesus. In contrast to medieval orders, the Jesuits combine hierarchy and strict obedience with considerable organizational flexibility.
</Question>
<Choice>1540</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Council of Trent is convened. Running until 1563, it begins the Counter-Reformation, reaffirming and detailing certain Catholic tenets while reforming others.
</Question>
<Choice>1545</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The slave trade introduces indigenous African and Islamic religious traditions to the Americas, resulting in new faiths such as Santería, which blends elements of Yoruba religion and Christianity.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1550</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Unitarianism develops in central Europe. A non-Trinitarian Christian movement, it is roundly attacked by both Catholics and Calvinists in its early years.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1550</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the Saint Bartholomew's Day Massacre, French Catholics murder some 3,000 Huguenots (Protestants) in Paris. The massacre was plotted by Catherine de Médicis.
</Question>
<Choice>1572</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Tulsidas composes Ramcaritmanas ("Sacred Lake of the Acts of Rama"), a Hindi vernacular Ramayana and the greatest work of medieval Hindi literature.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1574</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ram Das, fourth Guru of Sikhism, founds the sacred centre of Amritsar in Punjab, India.
</Question>
<Choice>1577</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian Jesuit missionary Matteo Ricci becomes the first Christian missionary to enter China. He lives in China for 30 years.
</Question>
<Choice>1582</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The metropolitan of Moscow is elevated to the position of patriarch in the Eastern Orthodox church, thus granting the Russian Orthodox church self-governance.
</Question>
<Choice>1589</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The adoption of horses by North American Plain dwellers increases their capacity for big-game hunting and begins a long synthesis of agricultural and hunter religious practices.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1600</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sikh guru Arjun compiles the hymns of Sikh, Hindu, and Muslim saints to create the Adi Granth, the central object of Sikh veneration and ritual.
</Question>
<Choice>1604</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Thomas Helwys founds the General Baptist church, the first Baptist church in England. He argues that Christ's atonement applied to all persons, not a body of the elect.
</Question>
<Choice>1612</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English separatists, or Pilgrims, lead the founding of Plymouth Colony.
</Question>
<Choice>1620</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John Winthrop sets forth his vision of the colony of Massachusetts as "a Citty upon a Hill" in his sermon "A Modell of Christian Charity."
</Question>
<Choice>1630</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Congregation for the Propagation of the Faith condemns Confucian rites as incompatible with Catholicism. Jesuits had urged tolerance of the rites.
</Question>
<Choice>1645</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English preacher George Fox establishes the Society of Friends, or Quakers. Its services favour internal guidance by the Holy Spirit, rather than external ritual and scriptural authority.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1660</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
William Penn, founder of the Commonwealth of Pennsylvania, publishes his defense of religious toleration, The Great Case of Liberty of Conscience Once More Debated & Defended.
</Question>
<Choice>1670</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
With the passage of the Toleration Act, the English Parliament grants freedom of religion to Nonconformists (i.e., members of churches other than the Church of England).
</Question>
<Choice>1689</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A schism among Mennonites leads to the rise of the Amish, a conservative Christian group headed by Jakob Ammann.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1697</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Start of the First Great Awakening, a religious revival that sweeps the American colonies. Its leading figures were Anglican George Whitefield and Congregationalist Jonathan Edwards.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1720</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Peter the Great, influenced by Protestant examples of church administration, replaces the patriarchate of the Russian Orthodox church with a synod.
</Question>
<Choice>1721</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Ephrata Community, a Protestant monastic settlement, is founded in Pennsylvania, U.S., by Johann Conrad Beissel.
</Question>
<Choice>1732</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John Wesley, founder of Methodism, has his "Aldersgate Street Experience" and dedicates his life to preaching salvation by faith. He and his brother Charles found the Methodist church.
</Question>
<Choice>1738</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Muslim reformer Muhammad 'Abd al-Wahhab meets political leader Muhammad ibn Sa'ud, with whom he will form an alliance promoting Wahhabism in Arabia.
</Question>
<Choice>1745</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jonathan Edwards publishes A Treatise Concerning Religious Affections, defending the Great Awakening.
</Question>
<Choice>1746</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ba'al Shem Tov (Israel ben Eliezer) begins Hasidism, a pietistic revival of Judaism that stresses knowledge of the immanence of God in the world.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1750</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ann Lee joins the Shakers. She rises to leadership of the church, establishing its doctrines and transplanting the church to the United States. It flourishes in New England.
</Question>
<Choice>1758</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish Franciscan priest Junípero Serra founds Mission San Diego. He founds eight more missions in California between 1770 and 1782.
</Question>
<Choice>1769</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Beginning of Haskala ("Jewish Enlightenment"), during which reformers seek to introduce central and eastern European Jews to European secular education and culture.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1770</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jewish Enlightenment figure Moses Mendelssohn completes a German translation of the Hebrew Bible in an effort to integrate Jewish tradition into German culture.
</Question>
<Choice>1783</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The United States Constitution is drafted in Philadelphia. It embodies the ideal of secular government with deliberate separation of "church and state."
</Question>
<Choice>1787</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Revolutionary French National Assembly passes the Civil Constitution of the Clergy, which seeks to nationalize the Catholic church in France. It is bitterly opposed by French Catholics.
</Question>
<Choice>1790</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Second Great Awakening begins in America. An important example of a revivalist movement, it continues until the 1830s.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1795</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Methodist church separates from the Church of England despite the late founder John Wesley's wish to maintain it as an included "society."
</Question>
<Choice>1795</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The expansion of European empires brings Western systems of knowledge into contact with indigenous cultural and religious traditions, often to the detriment of the latter.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1800</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The African Methodist Episcopal church is established. One of the most important African-American churches, it expands after the Civil War through missionary work in the South.
</Question>
<Choice>1816</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Thomas Chalmers becomes minister at St. John's in Glasgow. In addition to his missionary work, he writes a number of books that apply Christian doctrine to economics and economic policy.
</Question>
<Choice>1819</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jean-François Champollion deciphers the inscription on the Rosetta Stone, allowing the interpretation of ancient Egyptian religion through hieroglyphics.
</Question>
<Choice>1822</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ram Mohun Roy founds Brahmo Samaj, a monotheist movement that rejects some Hindu practices and draws on Islam and Christianity. It begins a trend toward "Reform Hinduism."
</Question>
<Choice>1828</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Joseph Smith relates his revelation in the Book of Mormon and founds the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints (Mormons) in New York state.
</Question>
<Choice>1830</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Karl Marx writes a critique of religion in which he casts it as the product of society and the state and as "the opium of the people."
</Question>
<Choice>1843</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Free Church of Scotland is formed by evangelical dissenters of the Church of Scotland.
</Question>
<Choice>1843</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mirza 'Ali Mohammad claims to be the Bab (gateway) to the hidden imam (the perfect embodiment of Islamic faith). He founds the Babi religion, which breaks with Islam in 1848.
</Question>
<Choice>1844</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Antoinette Brown is the first female ordained by a recognized denomination in the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1853</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Charles Darwin's Origin of Species presents the argument for evolution by natural selection. While less radical than other evolutionary theories, it conflicts with biblical accounts of Creation.
</Question>
<Choice>1859</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Seventh Day Adventist church is founded in the United States. It stresses the imminent Second Coming of Christ.
</Question>
<Choice>1863</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mirza Hoseyn 'Ali Nuri (Baha' Ullah) diverges from the Babism of the Azalis and founds the Baha'i religion in Iran.
</Question>
<Choice>1863</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
F. Max Müller, known for his application of philology and other modern scholarly tools to the study of religion, begins work on his monumental Sacred Books of the East.
</Question>
<Choice>1875</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dayanand Sarasvati founds Arya Samaj, a monotheistic Hindu movement based on his reading of the Rigveda, which rejected all else as unauthentic.
</Question>
<Choice>1875</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sir Sayyid Ahmad Khan founds the Anglo-Mohammedan Oriental College at Aligarh to bring together Muslim and British culture. He is also a leading figure in the revival of Indian Islam.
</Question>
<Choice>1875</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English Evangelist William Booth and his wife, Catherine Mumford Booth, found the Salvation Army, a religious and charitable organization modeled after the military.
</Question>
<Choice>1878</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Christian Science Church is established in Boston, Mass., by Mary Baker Eddy.
</Question>
<Choice>1879</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American Henry Steel Olcott, a cofounder of the Theosophical Society, immigrates to India. His educational work in Sri Lanka had a strong impact on Buddhism on the island.
</Question>
<Choice>1879</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Emergence of Ethiopianism in sub-Saharan Africa. The movement advocates the Africanization of Christianity, formation of independent churches, and political independence.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1880</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The resurgence of Zionism (Jewish nationalism) leads to the first European Jewish immigration to Israel and the revival of Hebrew as a vernacular language.
</Question>
<Choice>1882</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Paiute Native American prophet Wovoka promotes the Ghost Dance to provoke the world's renewal, European-American annihilation, and the reestablishment of native traditions.
</Question>
<Choice>1889</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sioux Native Americans begin to practice the Ghost Dance. Overreaction by an alarmed American government leads to the Wounded Knee massacre.
</Question>
<Choice>1890</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The World Parliament of Religions meets in Chicago. It includes a speech by Swami Vivekananda, which spurs the spread of Vedanta in the West.
</Question>
<Choice>1893</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hindu reformer Mohandas Karamchand (Mahatma) Gandhi begins a nonviolent campaign against racism in South Africa. He later campaigns against British hegemony in South Asia.
</Question>
<Choice>1893</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The conviction of French Army officer Alfred Dreyfus sparks the 12-year Dreyfus Affair, which exposes the depth of French anti-Semitism and leads to anticlerical reforms.
</Question>
<Choice>1894</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hungarian-born Zionist Theodor Herzl organizes the World Zionist Organization in an effort to create an internationally recognized Jewish political state in Israel.
</Question>
<Choice>1897</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In India, Swami Vivekananda establishes the Ramakrishna Movement, named after the Bengali tantric mystic who was his teacher.
</Question>
<Choice>1897</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An alliance of secret religious societies and Ch'ing dynasty officials initiate the Boxer Rebellion, which spreads antiforeign sentiment throughout North China.
</Question>
<Choice>1900</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American philosopher and psychologist William James applies psychology to the analysis of religion in The Varieties of Religious Experience.
</Question>
<Choice>1902</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Inspired in part by African-American missionary activity, new religious movements develop in Africa, such as the Zionist churches in southern Africa and (from 1918) the Aladura in Nigeria.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1910</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French sociologist Émile Durkheim writes Elementary Forms of the Religious Life, in which he argues that religion is a projection and function of society.
</Question>
<Choice>1912</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Russian Orthodox Church reestablishes the patriarchate during the All-Russian Church Council.
</Question>
<Choice>1917</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Native American Church is founded to institutionalize Native American peyote religion in the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1918</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Rastafarian movement develops in rural Jamaica, which identifies Ethiopian emperor Haile Selassie I as the Messiah.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1920</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Scopes "Monkey Trial" in Tennessee highlights the debate between Christian creationism and Darwin's evolutionism in American secular education.
</Question>
<Choice>1925</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hasan al-Banna' founds the Muslim Brotherhood in Egypt to oppose secular government in Muslim states.
</Question>
<Choice>1929</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Wali Farad Muhammad, declaring himself to be a prophet of Allah to African-Americans, establishes the Nation of Islam in Detroit.
</Question>
<Choice>1930</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Cargo cults flourish in Melanesia. Its leaders prophesy the return of ancestors and divinities aboard ships carrying European goods.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1930</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The International Bible Students Association, under the leadership of Joseph Franklin Rutherford, is renamed the Jehovah's Witnesses.
</Question>
<Choice>1931</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nazis harness European anti-Jewish sentiment in the Holocaust (Shoah). By the end of World War II, six million Jews and many others considered socially or religiously deviant have been annihilated.
</Question>
<Choice>1938</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Theologian and New Testament scholar Rudolf Bultmann analyzes the Bible, using historical criticism, and seeks to "demythologize" it.
</Question>
<Choice>1941</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Following its World War II defeat, Japan creates a constitution that guarantees religious freedom, ends Shinto as the state religion, and allows new religions to flourish.
</Question>
<Choice>1945</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first of the Dead Sea Scrolls are discovered in a cave near the Dead Sea. The scrolls provide detailed insights into the history of Palestine, Judaism, and early Christianity.
</Question>
<Choice>1947</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mahatma Gandhi is assassinated by Hindu nationalist Nathuram Godse.
</Question>
<Choice>1948</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The nation of Israel is established as a Jewish homeland. The region of Palestine is divided between Jews and Arabs.
</Question>
<Choice>1948</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Communist takeover of China under the leadership of Mao Zedong leads to oppression of religious groups.
</Question>
<Choice>1949</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Rev. Martin Luther King, Jr., leads the Montgomery, Ala., bus boycott to protest racial inequality. His movement uses tactics of nonviolent resistance inspired by Mahatma Gandhi.
</Question>
<Choice>1955</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian lawyer and government official Bhimrao Ramji Ambedkar leads 200,000 fellow "untouchable" Hindus into conversion to Buddhism to escape oppression of the Hindu caste system.
</Question>
<Choice>1956</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pope John XXIII initiates the Second Vatican Council. After three years' work, the council implements a variety of reforms to Catholic liturgical practice.
</Question>
<Choice>1962</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Malcolm X signals his split from the Nation of Islam and entry into mainstream Islam when he changes his name to El-Hajj Malik el-Shabazz.
</Question>
<Choice>1964</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A.C. Bhaktivedanta Swami founds the International Society for Krishna Consciousness in Los Angeles.
</Question>
<Choice>1966</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Following the Six-Day War, Israel occupies the West Bank and East Jerusalem, allowing Jewish devotions at the Western Wall of the Second Temple of Jerusalem.
</Question>
<Choice>1967</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Peruvian priest Gustavo Gutiérrez publishes one of the major statements of liberation theology, Teologia de la liberación.
</Question>
<Choice>1971</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Aboriginal Land Rights Act recognizes Australian Aborigine land rights, especially over territory with particular religious significance.
</Question>
<Choice>1976</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Polish cardinal Karol Wojtyla is elected pope.</Question>
<Choice>1978</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Islamic revolutionary forces under Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini overthrow the Pahlavi Shah and establish the Islamic Republic of Iran.
</Question>
<Choice>1979</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Many Muslims respond with a call for jihad ("sacred struggle") against the military forces of the Soviet Union invading Afghanistan.
</Question>
<Choice>1979</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Black South African Anglican archbishop Desmond Tutu is awarded the Nobel Prize for Peace for his work in opposition to apartheid.
</Question>
<Choice>1984</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Indian army attacks Sikh separatists in the Harimandir (Golden Temple) at Amritsar, one of the holiest sites in the Sikh religion.
</Question>
<Choice>1984</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The 14th Dalai Lama is awarded the Nobel Prize for Peace for his nonviolent efforts to liberate Tibet from Chinese occupation.
</Question>
<Choice>1989</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hindu nationalists attack a Muslim mosque in Ayodhya, India, sparking Hindu-Muslim riots throughout much of India, Pakistan, and Bangladesh.
</Question>
<Choice>1992</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Debates over church policies regarding homosexuality highlight the complicated role sexuality plays in contemporary religious thought and the place of churches in modern society.
</Question>
<Choice>1993</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Karen Armstrong, one of Britain's leading commentators on religion, publishes A History of God, which spends more than a year on the best-seller list.
</Question>
<Choice>1993</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The white Pentecostal Fellowship of North America reverses segregationist policies and unites with black churches to form the Pentecostal/Charismatic Churches of North America.
</Question>
<Choice>1994</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Church of England ordains 32 women priests. The controversial step highlights the international debate over the place of women in church hierarchies.
</Question>
<Choice>1994</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pope John Paul II leads programs aimed at easing doctrinal or theological divisions between the Roman Catholic Church and the Eastern Orthodox Church.
</Question>
<Choice>1995</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The 1990s witness the growth of both radical Islamic movements among the poor in the Middle East and the broader expansion of Islam in Europe and the Americas.
</Question>
<Choice>1995</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Conflicts between religious groups in South Asia pose a challenge to secularism in the region.
</Question>
<Choice>1995</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman Catholic bishop and East Timorese activist Carlos Filipe Ximenes Belo is awarded the 1996 Nobel Peace Prize. Belo is one of many Third World religious figures who campaign for human rights.
</Question>
<Choice>1996</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Noted U.S. theologian Martin E. Marty publishes the third book in his series Modern American Religion, a proposed four-volume study of religious tradition over the past century.
</Question>
<Choice>1996</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The suicide of 39 members of the Heaven's Gate group in southern California raises concerns about millenarian apocalyptic groups.
</Question>
<Choice>1997</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Millions of Hindus make pilgrimages to the holy city of Haridwar, India, to bathe in the Ganges River in celebration of the 20th century's last Kumbh Mela ("Festival of the Pot").
</Question>
<Choice>1998</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Vatican issues a statement apologizing for the Roman Catholic Church's failure to act during the Holocaust.
</Question>
<Choice>1998</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pope John Paul II makes his first trip to Cuba, where he criticizes the country's long suppression of religion.
</Question>
<Choice>1998</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Plans to build a mosque near the Basilica of the Annunciation in Nazareth, Israel, lead to riots.
</Question>
<Choice>1999</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The number of Roman Catholics in the world passes the one billion mark.
</Question>
<Choice>1999</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ian Barbour receives the Templeton Prize for Progress in Religion for his integration of science and religion.
</Question>
<Choice>1999</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Cormac Murphy-O'Connor is installed as the archbishop of Westminster.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At the Millennium World Peace Summit religious leaders agree to build peace through interfaith cooperation.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Officials of the Roman Catholic Church announce that salvation is available "fully and only through the Catholic Church."
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Vatican reveals that the third prophecy of the Virgin Mary (revealed in 1917 to peasant children in Fatima) was the 1981 assassination attempt on Pope John Paul II.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Afghanistan troops begin destroying all of the country's statues, including two 5th-century Buddhas, after the ruling Taliban claims they are offensive to Islam.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Islam is the focus of international attention after extremists of the religion call for a holy war and stage terrorist attacks against the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Rev. Arthur Peacocke wins the Templeton Prize for Progress in Religion for his encouragement of cooperation between science and religion.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A Moscow judge rules that Jehovah's Witnesses have not violated a law banning religious sects that incite violence and thus can practice their religion in Russia. The case was seen as a test of religious freedom in the country.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Controversy surrounds the Roman Catholic church after accusations of sexual abuse by clergy and cover-ups by church hierarchy. Criminal and civil cases ensue, and the church adopts new policies to end the problem.
</Question>
<Choice>2002</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Rowan Williams is enthroned as the 104th archbishop of Canterbury. His support of homosexuals in the church and the appointment of female bishops has aroused controversy.
</Question>
<Choice>2003</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
V. Gene Robinson becomes the first openly gay man to be consecrated as an Anglican bishop when he is appointed bishop of New Hampshire in the Episcopal Church, U.S.A.
</Question>
<Choice>2003</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Religious symbols, including Muslim head scarves, are banned in French public schools. The country is noted for its strict secularism.
</Question>
<Choice>2004</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Millions mourn the death of John Paul II, one of the most popular popes. Soon after Joseph Ratzinger is enthroned as Pope Benedict XVI.
</Question>
<Choice>2005</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Controversy erupts after a Danish newspaper prints cartoons depicting the Prophet Muhammad, including some that link him to terrorism. Muslims stage violent protests and boycotts, especially after the cartoons are reprinted in other European newspapers.
</Question>
<Choice>2006</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Katharine Jefferts Schori becomes the first woman to serve as presiding bishop of the Episcopal Church.
</Question>
<Choice>2006</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A 1,700-year-old codex containing a Gospel of Judas that portrays Jesus's betrayer as a friend who acted out of loyalty was made public by the National Geographic Society in Washington, D.C.
</Question>
<Choice>2006</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Roman Catholic church declares that the traditional view of limbo offered an "unduly restrictive view of salvation" and that there was hope that infants who died unbaptized would be saved.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Buddhist monks in Myanmar (Burma) stage demonstrations calling for democratic reforms.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Gordon B. Hinckley--president of the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, the largest denomination of the Mormon religion--dies at age 97.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Vatican hosts the first seminar of the Catholic-Muslim Forum in an attempt to improve relations between the two religions.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Kirill I becomes the Russian Orthodox Patriarch of Moscow and All Russia.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Anglican Church in North America (ACNA) is officially launched in Bedford, Texas, by traditionalists, many of whom previously seceded from the theologically liberal Episcopal Church in the United States of America (ECUSA).
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Codex Sinaiticus, the earliest-known manuscript of the Christian Bible, is made available online.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mehmet Ali Agca, who attempted to kill Pope John Paul II in 1981, is released from prison; after being pardoned in 2000, he was returned to his home country of Turkey, where he was jailed for unrelated crimes.
</Question>
<Choice>2010</Choice>
</item>
</topics>