<topics>
<item>
<Question>
Ionian school of philosophy seeks to explain phenomena in terms of matter and physical forces rather than the actions of gods.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 600 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek philosopher Thales of Miletus asserts that all things originate from water.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 600 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek philosopher Anaximander proposes an origin of the cosmos without reference to supernatural forces, a novelty that helps establish natural philosophy as an enterprise distinct from religion.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 570 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek philosopher Pythagoras establishes a school at Croton. He is best remembered for the Pythagorean theorem for right triangles, which he may not have formulated.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 532 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Flourishing of Pythagoreanism, a school of philosophy that believes that reality has a mathematical nature and ascribes a mystical power to certain numbers.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 525 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek philosopher Parmenides argues that all change is illusory and that understanding of nature must come from reason rather than experience.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 490 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek philosopher Anaxagoras brings Ionian philosophy to Athens. He discovers the true cause of solar eclipses and argues that there are an infinite number of elements.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 480 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek philosopher Zeno advances his famous paradoxes intended to show that motion is illusory. He is described by Aristotle as the inventor of dialectic.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 460 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek philosopher Empedocles asserts that all matter in the universe is composed of different proportions of earth, air, fire, and water.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 450 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Aristotle begins his studies at Plato's Academy. His vast corpus of work in astronomy, biology, and other fields virtually defines Western and Islamic science until the 17th century.
</Question>
<Choice>367 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Astronomer and mathematician Eudoxus of Cnidus expounds a system of geocentric, homocentric spheres to explain irregularities in the motion of the planets.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 360 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Theophrastus succeeds Aristotle as head of the Lyceum. Theophrastus' works in biology and botany strongly influence the life sciences until the Renaissance.
</Question>
<Choice>323 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek mathematician Euclid of Alexandria produces his Elements, a work that dominates elementary mathematics for over 2,000 years.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 300 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek astronomer Aristarchus of Samos formulates a geometric method for determining the relative distances of the Sun and the Moon. He advances the first known theory of a heliocentric solar system.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 270 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek mathematician and astronomer Eratosthenes, director of the great library at Alexandria, calculates the circumference of the Earth.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 250 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek astronomer Hipparchus of Rhodes (2nd century BC) makes relatively accurate predictions of the precession of the equinoxes and a very accurate determination of the tropical year.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 130 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Alexandrian astronomer and geographer Ptolemy produces the Almagest. His geocentric model of the universe dominates astronomical thought for the next 1,400 years.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 130</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine philosopher Themistius writes first Eastern commentaries on works of Aristotle.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 360</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Alexandrian philosopher John Philoponus writes commentaries on Aristotle.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 550</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Isidore of Seville, author of the Etymologies, an influential medieval encyclopedia and source of information on ancient geography, becomes archbishop of Seville.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 600</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Flourishing of Jabir ibn Hayyan, the most influential early Arab alchemist, who based his system on Greek theories of the elements.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 760</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Arab scholars begin to translate Greek and Roman scientific works into Arabic and Syriac, preserving them against loss in the West during the Middle Ages.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 800</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Arab astrologer Albumazar produces a synthesis of Persian and Indian astrological practice with Greek philosophy that legitimizes astrology in the Islamic world and, later, in Western circles.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 820</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Arab philosopher Al-Kindi produces works on astronomy, astrology, Indian arithmetic, and medicine.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 830</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hunayn ibn Ishaq (al-Ibadi) directs translation of Western scientific and medical writing in Baghdad; he produces an important translation of Galen's medical works.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 840</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John Scotus Erigena begins career as translator of ancient scientific works, with a particular concern to reconcile Christian and Neoplatonic accounts of nature.
</Question>
<Choice>845</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Arab mathematician Thabit ibn Qurrah becomes court astronomer in Baghdad and translates a number of Greek mathematical texts.
</Question>
<Choice>860</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Gerbert of Aurillac begins study of mathematical sciences. As Pope Sylvester II (999-1003), he helps revive the study of mathematics in cathedral schools.
</Question>
<Choice>967</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Arab mathematician and physicist Alhazen produces works on optical theory and planetary motion. His theories, translated into Latin in 1270, strongly influence European thinkers.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Iranian physician and philosopher Avicenna moves to court of Esfahan. His 200 works on philosophy and medicine have an immense impact on late medieval Western thought.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1022</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Adelard of Bath produces an important translation of Euclid's Elements. Elsewhere he advocates philosophical naturalism, arguing against the importance of supernatural forces in everyday life.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1125</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French philosopher William of Conches argues that God operates through natural forces rather than miracles; he writes important commentaries on the natural philosophy of Plato.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1130</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hugh of Saint Victor, whose Didascalicon is an important medieval encyclopedia, becomes rector of the school at St. Victor.
</Question>
<Choice>1133</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French theologian and philosopher Thierry de Chartres becomes chancellor of Chartres. He promotes Arabic scientific learning and attempts to reconcile Greek and Christian accounts of creation.
</Question>
<Choice>1141</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The University of Paris, a leading centre of late medieval learning and especially scientific thought, is separated from the cathedral school of Notre Dame.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1160</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Arab philosopher Averroës begins work on his Aristotelian commentaries, which strongly influence Scholastic philosopers from the 1230s.
</Question>
<Choice>1169</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The University of Oxford is founded after English students are barred from the University of Paris.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1170</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At the end of a long career in which he translated 80 ancient and Arabic scientific works into Latin, Gerard of Cremona completes his edition of Ptolemy's Almagest.
</Question>
<Choice>1175</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The University of Cambridge is founded by faculty and students escaping the riotous atmosphere of Oxford.
</Question>
<Choice>1209</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Robert Grosseteste begins career in which he promotes philosophical rationalism and introduces Latin translations of Greek and Arabic scientific writings to the West.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1229</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English Franciscan Roger Bacon begins his scholarly career. His argument that good science is a handmaid to religion, not a challenge to it, helps define the place of science in medieval thought.
</Question>
<Choice>1247</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
William of Moerbeke translates Aristotle's On the Heavens, beginning a career as an influential translator of and commentator on the works of Aristotle and Plato.
</Question>
<Choice>1260</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Siger de Brabant and colleagues at the University of Paris begin controversial lectures on Aristotelian philosophy that conservatives see as contradicting Christian theology.
</Question>
<Choice>1260</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Étienne Tempier, bishop of Paris, issues condemnations of philosophical doctrine that reinforce subordinating science to theology. A second round of condemnations is promulgated in 1277.
</Question>
<Choice>1270</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John Duns Scotus, influential realist philosopher, begins his teaching career at the University of Paris.
</Question>
<Choice>1302</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An unknown author writing under the name of Geber produces several treatises on alchemy that define and legitimize the practice in the West.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1310</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English cleric Thomas Bradwardine publishes his De proportionibus velocitatum in motibus, in which he attempts to describe motion mathematically.
</Question>
<Choice>1328</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jean Buridan, famous for his work in logic, optics, and mechanics, becomes rector of the University of Paris. His theory of "impetus" becomes important in late medieval physics.
</Question>
<Choice>1328</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nicholas Oresme presents arguments for the possibility of a heliocentric universe. His advocacy of geometrical analysis of motion advanced kinematics.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1370</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Regiomontanus completes his translation of Ptolemy's Almagest. His translation, published in 1496 as the Epitome, would be a major source for Renaissance astronomers.
</Question>
<Choice>1463</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-Swiss physician Paracelsus begins lecturing at the University of Basel. His wide-ranging and influential works include studies of alchemy, chemistry, medicine, and fossils.
</Question>
<Choice>1524</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Flemish physician and anatomist Andreas Vesalius publishes De humani corporis fabrica, the first modern, accurate study of human anatomy based on dissections of cadavers.
</Question>
<Choice>1543</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polish astronomer Nicolaus Copernicus' De revolutionibus orbium coelestium advances a heliocentric model of the solar system.
</Question>
<Choice>1543</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian physician and mathematician Gerolamo Cardano publishes his Ars magna ("Great Art"), a landmark in the history of algebra.
</Question>
<Choice>1545</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physician and chemist Georgius Agricola's De re metallica, published posthumously, lays the foundation for the study of metallurgy.
</Question>
<Choice>1556</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian physician and anatomist Matteo Realdo Colombo's De re anatomica describes the pulmonary circuit.
</Question>
<Choice>1559</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian physician Gabriel Fallopius' Observationes anatomicae describe the inner organs of the ear and the female reproductive system (including the Fallopian tubes named in his honour).
</Question>
<Choice>1561</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Danish astronomer Tycho Brahe founds his observatory, Uraniborg. His observations of stellar motion possess unprecedented accuracy and contribute to the rejection of Aristotelian cosmology.
</Question>
<Choice>1576</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian philosopher Giordarno Bruno is burned at the stake, ending a long career that included work in cosmology, physics, and memory systems.
</Question>
<Choice>1600</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physician William Gilbert's De magnete, the first broad discussion of magnetism since the 13th century, postulates that the Earth is a giant lodestone and has magnetic properties.
</Question>
<Choice>1600</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German astronomer Johann Bayer, in his Uranometria, establishes the modern nomenclature of stars by assigning each star in a constellation a letter of the Greek alphabet.
</Question>
<Choice>1603</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch lens-grinder Hans Lippershey applies for a patent on a telescope. He is traditionally credited with having invented the telescope, though the matter was disputed at the time.
</Question>
<Choice>1608</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German astronomer Johannes Kepler, in his Astronomia nova, states what would become known as his first two laws of planetary motion.
</Question>
<Choice>1609</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
With his new telescope, Italian physicist Galileo Galilei discovers four moons of Jupiter, the individual stars of the Milky Way, mountains on the Moon, and the phases of Venus.
</Question>
<Choice>1610</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish mathematician John Napier's Mirifici logarithmorum canonis descriptio, based on work begun about 1590, describes the nature and use of logarithms.
</Question>
<Choice>1614</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German astronomer Johannes Kepler, in his Harmonice mundi, presents his third, or harmonic, law of planetary motion.
</Question>
<Choice>1619</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch mathematician Willebrord van Roijen Snell formulates the law of refraction named after him (Snell's Law).
</Question>
<Choice>1621</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German astronomer Johannes Kepler's Tabulae rudolphinae gives far more accurate planetary positions than those of earlier methods.
</Question>
<Choice>1627</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physician William Harvey's Exercitatio anatomica de motu cordis et sanguinis in animalibus announces his discovery of the circulation of blood in animals.
</Question>
<Choice>1628</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian physicist Galileo Galilei's Dialogo sopra i due massimi sistemi del mondo (Dialogue Concerning the Two Chief World Systems) presents arguments for the Copernican system.
</Question>
<Choice>1632</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English mathematician William Oughtred invents the rectilinear slide rule.
</Question>
<Choice>1633</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian physicist Galileo Galilei is brought before the Inquisition and forced to recant his belief in Copernicanism. He spends the remainder of his life under house arrest.
</Question>
<Choice>1633</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French philosopher René Descartes's Discourse on Method is published, a highly influential attempt to reduce all of nature to mathematical law.
</Question>
<Choice>1637</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian physicist Galileo Galilei publishes his Dialogues Concerning the Two New Sciences.
</Question>
<Choice>1638</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English astronomer Jeremiah Horrocks predicts and is the first person to observe a transit of the planet Venus across the Sun.
</Question>
<Choice>1639</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian physicist and mathematician Evangelista Torricelli invents the mercury barometer.
</Question>
<Choice>1643</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French philosopher René Descartes proposes his theory of vortices, in which the planets are carried around the Sun by a celestial whirlpool (solar vortex).
</Question>
<Choice>1644</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch mathematician, astronomer, and physicist Christiaan Huygens discovers Saturn's largest satellite (later named Titan) and correctly interprets the "arms" of the planet as rings.
</Question>
<Choice>1655</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch mathematician, astronomer, and physicist Christiaan Huygens invents the pendulum clock.
</Question>
<Choice>1656</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Anglo-Irish natural philosopher Robert Boyle begins his pioneering experiments with the air pump, which result in a variety of discoveries and the establishment of the experimental method.
</Question>
<Choice>1656</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch biologist Jan Swammerdam first observes red blood cells under a microscope. This and his later work establish him as one of the century's most talented microscopists.
</Question>
<Choice>1658</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Royal Society of London for the Promotion of Natural Knowledge, the first scientific society in Great Britain, is founded.
</Question>
<Choice>1660</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Anglo-Irish natural philosopher Robert Boyle asserts that in an ideal gas under constant temperature, volume and pressure will vary inversely (Boyle's law).
</Question>
<Choice>1662</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physicist and instrument-maker Robert Hooke publishes his Micrographia ("Small Drawings"), the first great work devoted to microscopic observations.
</Question>
<Choice>1665</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physicist and mathematician Isaac Newton begins a remarkable creative period in which he invents the calculus and makes fundamental discoveries in optics and physics.
</Question>
<Choice>1665</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jean-Baptiste Colbert founds the Academy of Sciences in Paris. Its observatory is established a year later.
</Question>
<Choice>1666</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian physician and physiologist Marcello Malpighi's Dissertatio epistolica de bombyce establishes the field of microscopic anatomy, or histology.
</Question>
<Choice>1669</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch microscopist and biologist Antonie van Leeuwenhoek concludes that the moving objects he sees through his microscope are little animals, or microorganisms.
</Question>
<Choice>1674</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German mathematician Gottfried Wilhelm Leibniz develops integral and differential calculus. His supporters and Isaac Newton's argue for years over priority for the discovery.
</Question>
<Choice>1675</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Royal Greenwich Observatory founded by King Charles II, with John Flamsteed appointed first Astronomer Royal.
</Question>
<Choice>1675</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Danish astronomer Ole Christensen Rømer determines, on the basis of observations of eclipses of Jupiter's satellites, that the speed of light is finite.
</Question>
<Choice>1676</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch mathematician, astronomer, and physicist Christiaan Huygens begins advancing the wave, or pulse, theory of light.
</Question>
<Choice>1677</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Lucasian professor at Cambridge since 1669, Isaac Newton publishes his Philosophiae naturalis principia mathematica, which announces the three laws of universal motion.
</Question>
<Choice>1687</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Georg Stahl advances the theory of phlogiston, a substance thought to be involved in corrosion and combustion. The theory dominates chemistry for a century.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1700</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Isaac Newton's last major work, the Opticks, is published. Increasingly Newton's interests turn from mechanics and mathematics to alchemy and biblical prophesy and chronology.
</Question>
<Choice>1704</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In his Synopsis of the Astronomy of Comets, Oxford astronomer Edmond Halley argues that comets seen in 1531, 1607, and 1682 are actually the same comet with a period of 75 or 76 years.
</Question>
<Choice>1705</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physiologist Stephen Hales's Vegetable Staticks, a pioneering work applying quantitative methods to plant and animal physiology, is published.
</Question>
<Choice>1727</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English astronomer James Bradley announces discovery of the aberration of starlight.
</Question>
<Choice>1728</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish naturalist Carolus Linnaeus publishes his Systema naturae, the first of his works on botanical classification.
</Question>
<Choice>1735</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physiocrats argue for the existence of "natural laws" in economics, an early expression of the view that economics can be studied using scientific principles.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1750</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
After over a decade of research on electricity, American printer Benjamin Franklin--by attaching a key to kite string--proves that lightning is an electrical discharge.
</Question>
<Choice>1752</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish naturalist Carolus Linnaeus introduces the binomial system (genus/species) of nomenclature into botany.
</Question>
<Choice>1753</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British chemist Joseph Black rediscovers and studies "fixed air" (carbon dioxide). He develops the concept of latent heat in 1761.
</Question>
<Choice>1756</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Reappearance of Comet Halley verifies English astronomer Edmond Halley's prediction that the comet has a period of 75 or 76 years.
</Question>
<Choice>1758</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English geologist John Michell publishes his pioneering work on earthquakes, arguing that earthquakes are caused by high-pressure underground steam.
</Question>
<Choice>1760</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British chemist Henry Cavendish demonstrates the existence of inflammable air (hydrogen) as a distinct substance. He performs a number of other experiments; most remain unpublished.
</Question>
<Choice>1766</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English explorer James Cook begins the first of three voyages to the South Pacific, which yield a treasure trove of information about the geography, biology, and anthropology of the Pacific.
</Question>
<Choice>1768</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French astronomer Charles Messier issues his first catalog of 45 nebulous objects. By 1784 the list includes 103 objects.
</Question>
<Choice>1771</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish chemist Carl Wilhelm Scheele discovers oxygen, but Joseph Priestley wins credit for his independent discovery of the element after beating Scheele into print.
</Question>
<Choice>1772</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English chemist Joseph Priestley discovers "dephlogisticated air," later recognized as the element oxygen.
</Question>
<Choice>1774</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Adam Smith publishes his Inquiry into the Nature and Causes of the Wealth of Nations. Its discussion of market behaviour and the "invisible hand" make it a founding document of modern economics.
</Question>
<Choice>1776</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French chemist Antoine-Laurent Lavoisier announces his oxygen theory of combustion. The theory eventually overturns the phlogiston theory, which had been problematic for years.
</Question>
<Choice>1777</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English naturalist Joseph Banks, a veteran of Cook's first voyage and tireless advocate of science, becomes head of the Royal Society of London, dominating British science until 1820.
</Question>
<Choice>1778</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-born British astronomer William Herschel discovers Uranus, the first planet to be discovered since antiquity. This begins his long and prominent career as an astronomer and cosmologist.
</Question>
<Choice>1781</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British astronomer John Goodricke is first to explain periodic changes in the magnitude of a variable star (Algol).
</Question>
<Choice>1782</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French chemist Antoine-Laurent Lavoisier announces that water is not an element but rather a compound of oxygen and hydrogen.
</Question>
<Choice>1783</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Caroline Herschel, sister of William Herschel, begins her own astronomical research. She discovers 3 nebulae and 8 comets and produces a catalog of star clusters and nebulae.
</Question>
<Choice>1783</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physicist Charles-Augustin de Coulomb uses his torsion balance to demonstrate the inverse square law of force for electrostatic charges.
</Question>
<Choice>1785</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish geologist James Hutton proposes his theory of uniformitarianism, which argues that natural forces of erosion, volcanism, etc., are responsible for the formation of the Earth.
</Question>
<Choice>1785</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Applying Newtonian mechanics to his analysis of planetary motion, French mathematician Pierre-Simon Laplace demonstrates the inherent stability of the solar system.
</Question>
<Choice>1786</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French chemists Antoine-Laurent Lavoisier, Claude Berthollet, Antoine de Fourcroy, and Guyton de Morveau present a reformed nomenclature for chemistry.
</Question>
<Choice>1787</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English naturalist Gilbert White publishes The Natural History and Antiquities of Selborne, a modest classic of natural history.
</Question>
<Choice>1789</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British geologist William Smith begins research showing that lithologically similar beds can be distinguished by the fossils found in them, founding the field of stratigraphy.
</Question>
<Choice>1793</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In his Zoonomia or the Laws of Organic Life, English naturalist Erasmus Darwin (grandfather of Charles Darwin) advances an evolutionary theory in which organisms adapt to their environment.
</Question>
<Choice>1794</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Thomas Malthus' Essay on the Principle of Population introduces the idea that population growth will always outrun food production. The book influences economists and biologists alike.
</Question>
<Choice>1798</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physicist Henry Cavendish determines the density of the Earth, using geologist John Michell's torsion balance.
</Question>
<Choice>1798</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German geographer Alexander von Humboldt begins an expedition to South America. His work contributes to the creation of physical geography and biogeography.
</Question>
<Choice>1799</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French zoologist Georges Cuvier begins publication of his Lessons on Comparative Anatomy, which helps establish the discipline of comparative anatomy.
</Question>
<Choice>1800</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian physicist Alessandro Volta invents the voltaic pile, the first battery.
</Question>
<Choice>1800</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian astronomer Giuseppe Piazzi discovers the first asteroid (Ceres).
</Question>
<Choice>1801</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physicist Thomas Young shows that interference can exist between light waves. This indicates that light travels as waves, rather than corpuscles, as Isaac Newton argued.
</Question>
<Choice>1802</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British chemist John Dalton argues that chemical elements are composed of identical, indivisible particles of matter (atoms) that maintain their individuality in chemical reactions.
</Question>
<Choice>1803</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British chemist Humphry Davy is the first person to isolate potassium and sodium electrolytically.
</Question>
<Choice>1807</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish chemist Jöns Jacob Berzelius begins research that yields precise determination of atomic weights, modern chemical symbols, electrochemical theory, and new analytical techniques.
</Question>
<Choice>1807</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French chemist Joseph-Louis Gay-Lussac proposes the law of combining volumes of gases (Gay-Lussac's law).
</Question>
<Choice>1808</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In his Zoological Philosophy, French biologist Jean-Baptiste Lamarck advances the argument for evolution through inherited characteristics.
</Question>
<Choice>1809</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish botanist Robert Brown publishes Prodromus Florae Novae Hollandiae, the first extensive study of the botany of Australia, based on his travels to the continent (1801-1803).
</Question>
<Choice>1810</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian physicist Amedeo Avogadro proposes that equal volumes of all gases at the same temperature and pressure contain equal numbers of molecules.
</Question>
<Choice>1811</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German optician Joseph von Fraunhofer finds that the solar spectrum is crossed with many dark lines, some corresponding to the bright doublet of lines in many flame spectra.
</Question>
<Choice>1814</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Danish physicist Hans Christian Ørsted discovers the relationship between electricity and magnetism. His discovery becomes one of the foundations of electromagnetic theory.
</Question>
<Choice>1820</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Justus von Liebig establishes a chemistry laboratory at the University of Giessen, the first facility designed to support student research under the guidance of an established scientist.
</Question>
<Choice>1826</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish botanist Robert Brown observes Brownian motion.
</Question>
<Choice>1827</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German chemist Friedrich Wöhler is the first to synthesize an organic material (urea) from inorganic substances.
</Question>
<Choice>1828</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish geologist Charles Lyell begins publication of his 3-volume Principles of Geology. Its powerful arguments for the principle of uniformitarianism are highly influential.
</Question>
<Choice>1830</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English naturalist Charles Darwin begins a five-year cruise aboard the HMS Beagle. His observations and articles from the trip establish him as one of the foremost naturalists in England.
</Question>
<Choice>1831</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British chemist and physicist Michael Faraday conducts research that leads to his discovery of electromagnetic induction.
</Question>
<Choice>1831</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Shortly before his death in a duel, French mathematician Évariste Galois writes a paper introducing the concept of group theory into algebra.
</Question>
<Choice>1832</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American surgeon William Beaumont's Experiments and Observations on the Gastric Juice and the Physiology of Digestion is the first comprehensive study of human digestion.
</Question>
<Choice>1833</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German astronomer Friedrich Wilhelm Bessel publishes the first accurate determination of the distance of a fixed star (61 Cygni), obtained by measuring its stellar parallax.
</Question>
<Choice>1838</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German botanist Matthias Jakob Schleiden advances the cell theory for plants, arguing that cells are the basic units of plant structures.
</Question>
<Choice>1838</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British naturalist Charles Darwin publishes his Journal of Researches, recounting his five-year voyage (1831-1836) on the HMS Beagle.
</Question>
<Choice>1839</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British geologist Roderick Murchison describes the Silurian system of strata. He later names several other strata, including the Devonian, Early Paleozoic, and Permian.
</Question>
<Choice>1839</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physiologist Theodor Schwann applies Schleiden's cell theory to animals, arguing that cells are fundamental units of animal structure.
</Question>
<Choice>1839</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English botanist Joseph Dalton Hooker begins his scientific career as naturalist aboard the HMS Erebus. He later becomes director of Kew Gardens and a supporter of Darwinian evolution.
</Question>
<Choice>1839</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Royal Botanic Gardens at Kew (now Kew Gardens) become a scientific research facility and a major clearinghouse for international botanical research and exchange.
</Question>
<Choice>1841</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian physicist Christian Doppler proposes the Doppler principle, which relates the observed frequency of a wave to the motion of the source or the observer.
</Question>
<Choice>1842</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Cambridge astronomer John Couch Adams circulates among colleagues his predicted position of a planet beyond Uranus.
</Question>
<Choice>1845</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Urbain-Jean-Joseph Le Verrier independently calculates the position of a planet beyond Uranus.
</Question>
<Choice>1845</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German astronomers Johann Gottfried Galle and Heinrich Louis d'Arrest observe the planet Neptune, confirming the predictions of Adams and Le Verrier.
</Question>
<Choice>1846</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist Hermann von Helmholtz presents cogent proof of the principle of conservation of energy and introduces the concept of potential energy.
</Question>
<Choice>1847</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist Rudolf Clausius formulates the second law of thermodynamics, which states that entropy increases at the expense of available energy.
</Question>
<Choice>1850</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physicist Jean-Bernard-Léon Foucault’s pendulum demonstrations illustrate the diurnal rotation of the Earth.
</Question>
<Choice>1851</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British naturalist Alfred Russel Wallace begins an eight-year expedition to the Malay Archipelago. He collects specimens and conducts research in biogeography.
</Question>
<Choice>1854</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British naturalists Charles Darwin and Alfred Russel Wallace present papers outlining their theories of evolution by natural selection.
</Question>
<Choice>1858</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German chemist August Kekulé lays the foundation of structural organic chemistry. In 1865 he discovers the structure of six-carbon benzene.
</Question>
<Choice>1858</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British naturalist Charles Darwin publishes his Origin of Species. The work advances the theory of evolution by natural selection; it has an influence far outside the biological sciences.
</Question>
<Choice>1859</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist Gustav Robert Kirchhoff and chemist Robert Bunsen discover the principles of spectrum analysis.
</Question>
<Choice>1859</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physicist James Clerk Maxwell discovers that electromagnetic waves travel through a medium at a speed determined by the electric and magnetic properties of the medium.
</Question>
<Choice>1861</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British astronomer William Huggins determines spectroscopically that some nebulae are gaseous. His work provides one of the foundations of the new discipline of astrophysics.
</Question>
<Choice>1864</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Norwegian chemists Peter Waage and Cato Guldberg formulate the law of mass action (the rate of a reaction depends upon the concentration of reactants).
</Question>
<Choice>1864</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian biologist Gregor Mendel announces his laws of heredity based on experiments with hybrids of plants. His work is ignored until 1900, when it is rediscovered by geneticists.
</Question>
<Choice>1865</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian chemist Dmitry Ivanovich Mendeleyev pronounces the periodic law of elements, one of the basic laws of modern chemistry.
</Question>
<Choice>1869</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian astronomer Pietro Angelo Secchi initiates spectral classification of stars.
</Question>
<Choice>1869</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physicist John William Strutt (later Lord Rayleigh) argues that the scattering of blue light out of the direct beam of sunlight as it passes through the atmosphere causes the sky to appear blue.
</Question>
<Choice>1871</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physicist James Clerk Maxwell, in his Electricity and Magnetism, shows that all electric and magnetic phenomena can be interpreted in terms of stresses and motions of a material medium.
</Question>
<Choice>1873</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist Josiah Willard Gibbs begins publishing his work on thermodynamics and statistical mechanics that eventually helps establish the field of physical chemistry.
</Question>
<Choice>1873</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chemists Jacobus Henricus van't Hoff and Joseph-Achille Le Bel independently pioneer the field of stereochemistry.
</Question>
<Choice>1874</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronomer Asaph Hall discovers two moons of Mars: Phobos (“Fear”) and Deimos (“Terror”).
</Question>
<Choice>1877</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish physical chemist Svante Arrhenius argues that electrolytes are dissolved in solution. He is awarded the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1903.
</Question>
<Choice>1884</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist Heinrich Rudolph Hertz begins generating and propagating artificial electromagnetic waves. This work is the start of research on radio broadcasting.
</Question>
<Choice>1885</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist Henry Rowland invents a machine for making precise diffraction gratings, bringing a new precision to spectroscopic research.
</Question>
<Choice>1885</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicists Albert Michelson and Edward Morley disprove the existence of a luminiferous ether and establish that the speed of light is a constant.
</Question>
<Choice>1887</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Marine Biological Laboratory at Woods Hole, Mass., a major centre for biological and oceanographic research, is founded.
</Question>
<Choice>1888</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronomer George Ellery Hale invents the spectroheliograph, a device for photographing the Sun at precise wavelengths. He later founds both the Yerkes and Mount Wilson observatories.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1889</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist Wilhelm Conrad Röntgen discovers X rays. The discovery soon revolutionizes physics, medical diagnosis, and engineering.
</Question>
<Choice>1895</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Inspired in part by the work of Wilhelm Röntgen the previous year, French physicist Henri Becquerel discovers radioactivity.
</Question>
<Choice>1896</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German chemist Eduard Buchner discovers that enzymes extracted from living yeast cells promote alcoholic fermentation, indicating the importance of enzymes in metabolic processes.
</Question>
<Choice>1897</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physicist J.J. Thomson establishes the existence of electrons.
</Question>
<Choice>1897</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physicists Pierre and Marie Curie discover polonium and radium.
</Question>
<Choice>1898</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sigmund Freud publishes The Interpretation of Dreams, which brings popular attention to the new field of psychoanalysis.
</Question>
<Choice>1899</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist Max Planck formulates quantum theory, sparking a revolution in modern physics continued by Albert Einstein and other physicists.
</Question>
<Choice>1900</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first Nobel Prizes are awarded. They rapidly become the most prestigious and well-known awards in science.
</Question>
<Choice>1901</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Marie Curie isolates pure radium. Later that year she shares the 1903 Nobel Prize for Physics with her husband and Henri Becquerel. She wins the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1911.
</Question>
<Choice>1903</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
George Ellery Hale founds the Mount Wilson Observatory in southern California. Originally devoted mainly to solar physics, it later adds two large reflecting telescopes.
</Question>
<Choice>1904</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist Albert Einstein's "annus mirabilis"; he publishes four papers that announce, among other findings, the special theory of relativity.
</Question>
<Choice>1905</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physical chemist Walther Hermann Nernst formulates the third law of thermodynamics.
</Question>
<Choice>1906</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American geneticist Thomas Hunt Morgan begins work on genetic mutation in Drosophila melanogaster (fruit flies). Drosophila soon becomes popular with geneticists and biology teachers.
</Question>
<Choice>1908</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronomer George Ellery Hale shows that magnetic fields are present in sunspots.
</Question>
<Choice>1908</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist Robert Andrews Millikan's oil-drop experiment yields the first accurate value of the charge of the electron. He wins the Nobel Prize for Physics for his work in 1923.
</Question>
<Choice>1909</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
After several years' experimental research, physicist Ernest Rutherford proposes the modern theory of atomic structure, consisting of a massive nucleus surrounded by orbiting electrons.
</Question>
<Choice>1911</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Danish astronomer Ejnar Hertzsprung discovers a relationship between spectral class and luminosity; the discovery is represented most famously in the Hertzsprung-Russell (H-R) diagram.
</Question>
<Choice>1911</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronomer Vesto Melvin Slipher begins obtaining spectrograms of spiral nebulae. Their high radial velocities provide evidence favouring the theory that the universe is expanding.
</Question>
<Choice>1912</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German meteorologist and geophysicist Alfred Lothar Wegener proposes his theory of continental drift.
</Question>
<Choice>1912</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physical chemist Frederick Soddy introduces the term isotope to distinguish atoms that are chemically identical but have different atomic weights.
</Question>
<Choice>1912</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Danish physicist Niels Bohr completes his theory of the quantized structure of the atom, the first application of quantum theory to molecular structure.
</Question>
<Choice>1913</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronomer Henry Norris Russell, co-creator with Ejnar Hertzsprung of the Hertzsprung-Russell (H-R) diagram, presents his influential theory of stellar evolution.
</Question>
<Choice>1913</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polish-born British anthropologist Bronislaw Malinowski begins fieldwork in the Trobriand Islands of New Guinea. His experiences and writings help create the field of social anthropology.
</Question>
<Choice>1915</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
After several years' work, German physicist Albert Einstein publishes his general theory of relativity.
</Question>
<Choice>1916</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Harlow Shapley's study of the distribution of globular stellar clusters shows that the centre of the Milky Way is in the constellation of Sagittarius.
</Question>
<Choice>1917</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physicist Ernest Rutherford achieves the transmutation of elements by causing swiftly moving alpha particles and light elements to interact.
</Question>
<Choice>1919</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British astronomer Arthur Stanley Eddington's observations of stars during a total solar eclipse support Einstein's prediction that light will be deflected in a gravitation field.
</Question>
<Choice>1919</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Norwegian meteorologist Vilhelm Bjerknes develops the idea of warm and cold fronts, a key idea in modern meteorology and weather forecasting.
</Question>
<Choice>1921</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physical chemist Gilbert N. Lewis formulates his electron theory of chemical bonding.
</Question>
<Choice>1923</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronomer Edwin Powell Hubble, using Cepheid variables that he discovered in the Andromeda galaxy, proves that the latter lies far outside the Milky Way galaxy.
</Question>
<Choice>1924</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
South African physical anthropologist and paleontologist Raymond Dart discovers the first Australopithecus fossil in a limestone quarry near Taung, South Africa.
</Question>
<Choice>1924</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist Werner Heisenberg proposes that elementary particles be treated either as waves or as particles, depending on the nature of the investigation.
</Question>
<Choice>1925</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian physicist Erwin Schrödinger proposes his theory of wave mechanics.
</Question>
<Choice>1926</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist Werner Heisenberg announces his uncertainty principle, which holds that it is impossible to know simultaneously both the position and momentum of an elementary particle.
</Question>
<Choice>1927</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian-born physicist George Gamow begins work on his "liquid drop" model of atomic nuclei, the basis for the modern theories of nuclear fission and fusion.
</Question>
<Choice>1928</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronomer Edwin Powell Hubble finds that most galaxies are receding and that their radial velocity is proportional to their distance.
</Question>
<Choice>1929</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist Ernest Lawrence designs his first cyclotron, an instrument for accelerating elementary particles to very high energies.
</Question>
<Choice>1929</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronomer Clyde Tombaugh discovers the planet Pluto.
</Question>
<Choice>1930</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French astronomer Bernard Lyot invents the coronagraph, which allows astronomers to observe the solar corona when the Sun is not in eclipse.
</Question>
<Choice>1930</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian logician Kurt Gödel announces his incompleteness proof, showing that some truths of elementary number theory will remain unprovable.
</Question>
<Choice>1931</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist Robert Van de Graaff builds his first electrostatic generator at MIT. The Van de Graaff generator becomes one of the most widely used particle accelerators.
</Question>
<Choice>1931</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American engineer Karl Jansky's discovery that a disturbing variety of radio static originated from the centre of the Milky Way galaxy initiates the field of radio astronomy.
</Question>
<Choice>1931</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Kenyan anthropologist Louis Leakey begins work at Olduvai Gorge, Tanzania. His discoveries there contribute to the theory that humans originated in Africa some 2.5 million years ago.
</Question>
<Choice>1931</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physicists John Douglas Cockcroft and Ernest Walton are the first to split the nucleus of an atom, by bombarding lithium and boron nuclei with protons.
</Question>
<Choice>1932</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physicist James Chadwick discovers the neutron.
</Question>
<Choice>1932</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physicists Frédéric and Irène Joliot-Curie win the Nobel Prize for Chemistry for producing artificial radioactive elements by bombarding lighter elements with X rays.
</Question>
<Choice>1935</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German chemists Otto Hahn and Fritz Strassmann produce barium from the much heavier element uranium by bombarding it with neutrons.
</Question>
<Choice>1938</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian physicists Lise Meitner and Otto Frisch coin the term fission to describe the process observed by Hahn and Strassmann in 1938.
</Question>
<Choice>1939</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicists Edwin M. McMillan and Philip H. Abelson, bombarding uranium with neutrons, artificially create the first sample of a transuranium element (neptunium).
</Question>
<Choice>1940</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Team led by Italian-born American physicist Enrico Fermi achieves first self-sustaining nuclear reaction at Stagg Field at the University of Chicago.
</Question>
<Choice>1942</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Atomic bombs are detonated, first at Alamogordo, N.M., and then over Hiroshima and Nagasaki, Japan.
</Question>
<Choice>1945</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
George Gamow and Ralph Alpher elaborate the modern version of the "big-bang" model of the origins of the universe.
</Question>
<Choice>1948</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
200-inch Hale reflector telescope, then the world's largest, is dedicated at Palomar Mountain Observatory in California.
</Question>
<Choice>1948</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Theoretical physicist Richard Feynman introduces Feynman diagrams, which provide a vastly simplified method of calculating elementary particle reactions.
</Question>
<Choice>1949</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The National Science Foundation is created, establishing the importance and continuing presence of federal funding in basic scientific research.
</Question>
<Choice>1950</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
CERN, a physics research facility located near Geneva, Switz., is founded. It grows to become one of the largest and most productive basic research centres in the world.
</Question>
<Choice>1952</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British biophysicist Francis Crick and American biologist James Watson announce the double-helix structure of DNA.
</Question>
<Choice>1953</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American chemist Linus Pauling wins the Nobel Prize for Chemistry for his application of quantum theory to molecular bonding. He wins a second Nobel (for Peace) in 1962.
</Question>
<Choice>1954</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist James Van Allen announces discovery of the Van Allen radiation belts surrounding the Earth.
</Question>
<Choice>1958</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Two Cultures and the Scientific Revolution, British scientist C.P. Snow argues that the worlds of science and literature are diverging, to the detriment of each.
</Question>
<Choice>1959</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American geophysicists Harry Hess and Robert Dietz suggest that mid-ocean ridges are spreading apart and producing valleys into which hot lava from the Earth's interior is rising.
</Question>
<Choice>1961</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Thomas Kuhn's The Structure of Scientific Revolutions sets forth the notion of "paradigms" and sets the agenda for future scholarly studies of scientific change.
</Question>
<Choice>1962</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch-born American astronomer Maarten Schmidt discovers that certain distant celestial objects (quasars) are moving away from the Earth at speeds enormously faster than any known star.
</Question>
<Choice>1963</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist Murray Gell-Mann introduces the concept of the "quark," a particle that is the building block of electrons, protons, neutrons, and other elementary particles.
</Question>
<Choice>1964</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicists Arno Penzias and Robert Wilson detect cosmic microwave background radiation. Their discovery lends support to the big-bang theory of the origins of the universe.
</Question>
<Choice>1965</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Richard Feynman, Julian Schwinger, and Tomonaga Shinichiro share the Nobel Prize for Physics for their work on quantum electrodynamics.
</Question>
<Choice>1965</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British radio astronomers Jocelyn Bell and Antony Hewish detect the first pulsar.
</Question>
<Choice>1967</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The X-ray source Cygnus X-1 emerges as a strong candidate for being a black hole.
</Question>
<Choice>1974</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Benoit Mandelbrot discovers fractals.</Question>
<Choice>1975</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spaceships Voyager 1 and 2 begin their travels. Before leaving the solar system, the two probes collect a wealth of information about the outer planets and make a variety of discoveries.
</Question>
<Choice>1977</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British anthropologist Mary Leakey discovers footprints at Olduvai Gorge, Tanzania, made by early hominids 3.5 million years ago.
</Question>
<Choice>1978</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American economist Lawrence Klein wins the Nobel Prize for Economics for his pioneering work in econometrics and the mathematical modeling of national economies.
</Question>
<Choice>1980</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Internet, an electronic computer and information-exchange network created to support communication between scientists, opens.
</Question>
<Choice>1983</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biologist Barbara McClintock wins the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for her work on mobile genetic elements in hybrid corn.
</Question>
<Choice>1983</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American chemist Kary Mullis and colleagues begin development of PCR (polymerase chain reaction), a widely used technique for replicating samples of DNA.
</Question>
<Choice>1983</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American chemists Richard Smalley and Robert Curl and British chemist Harold Kroto discover spherical carbon structures they call fullerenes, or "buckyballs."
</Question>
<Choice>1985</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist Norman Ramsey shares the Nobel Prize for Physics for his development of the atomic clock, the most precise timepiece in the world.
</Question>
<Choice>1989</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scientists at CERN, a physics research facility in Switzerland, begin work on the World Wide Web, a network to speed the circulation of scientific preprints and research reports.
</Question>
<Choice>1989</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Human Genome Project, a project to map the location of all the genes on every chromosome in human beings, begins.
</Question>
<Choice>1990</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mathematician Andrew Wiles announces a proof of Fermat's last theorem, one of the oldest puzzles in mathematics. Two years later, Wiles publishes a stronger, definitive version of the proof.
</Question>
<Choice>1993</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
After being repaired in late 1993, the Hubble Space Telescope resumes work as a major astronomical instrument.
</Question>
<Choice>1994</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scientists at Fermilab report experimental evidence of the "top" quark, confirming the Standard Model of elementary particle theory.
</Question>
<Choice>1995</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American scientists succeed in producing the Bose-Einstein condensate, a form of matter predicted by Albert Einstein and the Indian physicist Satyendra Bose.
</Question>
<Choice>1995</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Geologists announce that they have discovered evidence of organic matter in a 4.5 billion-year-old Martian meteorite, suggesting that life existed on Mars. The finding is controversial.
</Question>
<Choice>1996</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Paleontologists working in Morocco discover a new dinosaur, Carcharodontosaurus saharicus, possibly larger than Tyrannosaurus rex.
</Question>
<Choice>1996</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the quest to discover increasingly heavy chemical elements, Peter Armbruster and a team of scientists successfully synthesize element 112.
</Question>
<Choice>1996</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Anthropologists using DNA manipulation techniques succeed in analyzing the genetic makeup of Homo neanderthalensis and find evidence that humans crossed the Bering Strait some 30,000 years ago.
</Question>
<Choice>1997</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Researchers report a planet orbiting the star Gliese 876, a close neighbour of our solar system at 15 light-years away. Calculations suggest that water might exist beneath the planet's surface.
</Question>
<Choice>1998</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A team of U.S. scientists announce that they had genetically altered human cells to defeat the cells' programmed self-destruction due to aging.
</Question>
<Choice>1998</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A team of researchers in Hawaii, U.S., led by Ryuzo Yanagimachi, produce the world's first cloned mouse, from which several clones are created.
</Question>
<Choice>1998</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The discovery of the skeleton of a four-year-old in Portugal that features both modern and Neanderthal skeletal traits challenges the commonly held theory of hominid evolution.
</Question>
<Choice>1999</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
New evidence is reported that supports the existence of the postulated nuclear island of stability.
</Question>
<Choice>1999</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mathematicians extend Andrew Wiles's proof of Fermat's last theorem to prove the full Taniyama-Shimura conjecture.
</Question>
<Choice>1999</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chemists from the University of Chicago announce the creation of octanitrocubane, a compound that could be the most powerful nonnuclear explosive.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Professor J.L. Kirschvink of the California Institute of Technology publishes a report concerning his Snowball Earth theory, which postulates that the Earth was once completely glaciated.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The rise of genetically modified plants draws heated debates over possible dangers.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In May the Field Museum of Natural History in Chicago unveils Sue, a Tyrannosaurus rex skeleton that is the most complete and best-preserved ever discovered.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scientists report findings that suggest the Earth was struck by an asteroid some 250 million years ago, triggering volcanic eruptions that caused the worst mass extinction in the planet's history.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first complete skull of a Tenontosaurus dinosaur is uncovered in Oklahoma.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
X rays reveal that the Iceman, the oldest mummified body ever found, has an arrowhead in his shoulder. The discovery suggests that the Iceman may have bled to death.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scientists in Texas clone a domestic cat. Other cloned animals include sheep, pigs, mice, and goats.
</Question>
<Choice>2002</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Stem cell research is at the centre of an international debate. While scientists support stem cell use for its possible health advances, the use of human fetal cells has some opposed to the research.
</Question>
<Choice>2002</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Using a satellite that measures microwave radiation, scientists are able to create a map of the universe just after its creation. The detailed picture confirms the big-bang model.
</Question>
<Choice>2003</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An undersea earthquake in the Indian Ocean triggers the most destructive tsunami ever recorded. At least 225,000 people are killed and numerous countries, including Indonesia, Sri Lanka, Maldives, India, and Thailand, sustain massive damage.
</Question>
<Choice>2004</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The complete genetic code of a chimpanzee is sequenced and is found to be more than 96% identical to that of a human. This adds to the growing debate over evolution and intelligent design.
</Question>
<Choice>2005</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scientists create element 118 by bombarding californium with calcium ions. Seven years earlier researchers had announced the discovery of the element but were later forced to retract their findings after it was revealed that a member of their team had fabricated data.
</Question>
<Choice>2006</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The field of epigenetics--the study of the epigenome (the way the genome is modified chemically and packaged) and its functional significance--continues to grow in prominence.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A magnitude-7.9 earthquake strikes China’s Sichuan province, killing nearly 90,000 and leaving millions homeless.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Large Hadron Collider, the world's most powerful particle accelerator, runs its first test operation.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The journal Science publishes the first full reconstruction of a skeleton of Ardipithecus ramidus, the oldest-known hominin. It was found in rocks dated to 4.4 million years ago and thus is older than Australopithecus.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A report is published in which the colour of a dinosaur is scientifically identified for the first time; using fossils, researchers determine that the dinosaur Sinosauropteryx had feathers that were white and chestnut in colour.
</Question>
<Choice>2010</Choice>
</item>
</topics>