<topics>
<item>
<Question>
The tomb of an Egyptian child contains nine stone pins, which were probably used in an ancient variation of bowling.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 5200 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hieroglyphic evidence indicates the spread of boxing from Ethiopia to Egypt.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 4000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Archaeological evidence shows that the ancients played a board game nearly identical to backgammon.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 3000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Some Egyptian graves contain wooden dolls, geometrically painted and with hair of wood beads or clay.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 2500 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Archaeological evidence indicates that swimming is practiced in Egypt for recreation.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 2500 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A rock carving in Norway near the Arctic Circle shows two men on skis.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 2000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The children’s game of swings is played on the island of Crete.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1600 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Multiple references to the sport of hurling appear in old Irish manuscripts.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1250 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
According to Sophocles, Palamedes invents dice during the siege of Troy. Later archaeological finds prove that dice had existed much earlier.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1200 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A fencing match is pictured in a temple built by Ramses III near Luxor in Egypt.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1190 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the epic poem the Iliad, Homer describes chariot races during Patroclus’s funeral.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 800 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The ancient Olympic Games are held for the first time, in Olympia, Greece. The games are outlawed by Emperor Theodosius I in AD 393.
</Question>
<Choice>776 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Remains of tlachtli, courts for the game of ollama, suggest that the game developed among the Olmecs during the La Venta culture period. Ollama eventually spreads throughout Mesoamerica.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 600 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Victorious in six Olympic Games, the Greek wrestler Milon of Croton is one of the most celebrated athletes in antiquity.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 510 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Cockfighting makes its way from China and other Eastern countries into Greece.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 500 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Flourishing of Greek Pythagorean Archytas of Tarentum, who is the first documented kite flier.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 400 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In his treatise Peri hippikes, Greek historian Xenophon describes techniques for training horses, many of which remain useful to this day.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 400 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Celtiberians engage in an early form of bullfighting as they hunt bulls for sport.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 270 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Chinese play a kickball game called tsu-chu, the ancestor of modern soccer.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 206 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Venationes, or animal hunts, are staged in Rome for the amusement of nobles and the general public. The events are more slaughters than hunts.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 150 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Rome's Circus Maximus, one of the largest sporting arenas in the world, is expanded under Julius Caesar's direction. The facility can hold about 150,000 spectators.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 60 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Young Octavian (later Caesar Augustus), as well as other Roman children, plays marble games with nuts serving as the marbles.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 55 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Jacks is played in ancient Greece.</Question>
<Choice>c. 40 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Nihon shoki describes the first sumo (then sumai) fight, during which Nomi no Sukune kills Taima no Kehaya.
</Question>
<Choice>23 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Construction begins on the Colosseum in Rome. One of the most remarkable architectural achievements of the Roman era, it seats about 50,000 and can even be flooded for mock naval combats.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 70</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek writer Julius Pollux describes the game apodidraskinda, later commonly known as hide-and-seek.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 150</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In his Cynegeticus, Greek historian Arrian describes coursing, a hounds chasing game by sight instead of scent.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 150</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Circle-and-cross board games resembling the ancient nyout, are played throughout Korea.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 200</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The world's largest hippodrome, a stadium designed for horse and chariot racing, is completed in Constantinople. Work on the facility had begun over a century earlier.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 330</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Christianity gains in prominence in Greece, putting an end to the Isthmian Games, an ancient athletic and musical festival in honour of Poseidon.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 350</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Circus Maximus hippodrome is enlarged to a seating capacity of about 250,000.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 350</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The modern version of chess is invented in northwest India.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 570</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A game very much like modern handball is developed in Ireland.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 980</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The modern board game of draughts, or checkers, is invented in the south of France.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1100</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dominoes is played in China. The numbers probably represent the throws of two dice, as there are no blank faces.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1150</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Horse racing takes place in Siena, Italy. Much later this evolves into the full festival known as the Palio.
</Question>
<Choice>1232</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The game of paille-maille, croquet’s precursor, is regularly played in France.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1250</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In China, Chang San-Feng incorporates gentler elements of more aggressive martial arts into kung fu. He is probably the founder of the discipline of Taijiquan.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1300</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The dice game of hazard is frequently played in England. A gambling game, it serves as the basis for the modern game of craps.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1350</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The board game Nine Men’s Morris reaches its peak of popularity across Europe.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1360</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Tarot cards begin appearing in Italy and France. Tarot are variously thought to have originated outside Europe, in Egypt, India, or China.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1380</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Violent, large-scale games of lacrosse, with as many as a thousand players per side, are played by the Iroquois nation. The game is also popular among the Cherokee and other Native Americans.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1390</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first English book about hunting, The Master of the Game, is penned by Edward of Norwich, 2nd duke of York. Despite its popularity at the time, the book is not published until 1904.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1400</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Fox hunting develops in England. It is still popular among the upper classes and is considered by contemporary supporters to be an integral part of country life.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1420</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Individual jousts tend to replace group mock battles as a favoured form of public entertainment in western Europe.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1430</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Scottish parliament warns that golf is distracting the populace from the more essential military skill of archery.
</Question>
<Choice>1457</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Italian card game Baccarat is introduced into French circles. The game would later become popular in European casinos in the 19th century.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1480</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jeu de paume, also known as court tennis or real tennis, enjoys widespread popularity in France.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1500</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Henry VIII of England is presented a gift of jewel-encrusted darts by Anne Boleyn. Darts become a popular diversion for Tudor monarchs.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1525</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Florence, La Lotto di Firenze is believed to be the first lottery to award cash prizes. Lotteries are used by Renaissance cities and states to raise money for public welfare, works, and defense.
</Question>
<Choice>1530</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Spanish Riding School of Vienna is founded. The school is famous for its Lipizzaner horses, which receive an extraordinary classical training.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1580</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The original version of the card game whist, from which bridge is derived, is played in England.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1600</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
As Sir Thomas Dale lands at Jamestown, Va., he angrily observes starving colonists competing at a game of bowling. It is the first recorded sporting event among colonists.
</Question>
<Choice>1611</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Akashi Shiganosuke becomes the first sumo wrestler to achieve the formal rank of Yokozuna, or grand champion.
</Question>
<Choice>1632</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The ball-and-stick game of shinty is played in Scotland by Highland clans.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1650</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English author Izaak Walton publishes his book The Compleat Angler. Over 300 editions of the classic fishing treatise are published over the next 300 years.
</Question>
<Choice>1653</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
According to legend, French mathematician Blaise Pascal invents the game of Roulette.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1660</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Horse racing becomes the first organized sport in North America. Governor Richard Nicolls of the colony of New York creates a course on Long Island and offers prizes to the winners.
</Question>
<Choice>1665</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The manufacture of weapons, including even ceremonial swords, is outlawed on the island of Okinawa, Japan. This leads to the development of karate.
</Question>
<Choice>1669</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English children play the nursery-rhyme game of London Bridge.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1670</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first documented 11-a-side cricket match is played in Sussex, Eng.
</Question>
<Choice>1697</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English pugilist James Figg wins the first world heavyweight boxing championship. The bare-knuckle fighter is also known for his skills at fencing and wrestling.
</Question>
<Choice>1719</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish matador Francisco Romero is the first bullfighter to use the muleta, or red cape, as well as the sword.
</Question>
<Choice>1726</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first fishing club in the American colonies is formed in Philadelphia. It is named the Schuylkill Fishing Company, after one of the rivers that forms the city's boundaries.
</Question>
<Choice>1732</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
London author Edmond Hoyle publishes A Short Treatise on the Game of Whist. He becomes the first recognized authority on card and board games and the inspiration for the phrase “according to Hoyle.”
</Question>
<Choice>1742</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Jockey Club, which regulates horse racing and breeding, is formed in Newmarket, Suffolk.
</Question>
<Choice>1750</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jigsaw puzzles are used in England to teach geography.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1750</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English impresario and equestrian Philip Astley opens Astley's Amphitheatre. The Amphitheatre eventually becomes a franchise across Europe and the first modern circus.
</Question>
<Choice>1770</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Captain Robert Jones’s A Treatise of Skating provides the first account of figure skating.
</Question>
<Choice>1772</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
During his third expedition to the South Pacific, English explorer James Cook and his crew observe Tahitians surfing.
</Question>
<Choice>1777</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The earliest form of bingo, a children’s game called lotto, is played in Europe.
</Question>
<Choice>1778</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first running of the Derby is held at Epsom Downs, Surrey, Eng.
</Question>
<Choice>1780</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The table game of Roulette gains prominence throughout the casinos of Europe.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1780</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French brothers Joseph-Michel and Jacques-Étienne Montgolfier complete the first hot-air balloon flight.
</Question>
<Choice>1783</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The bat-and-ball game pelota vasca is played in Spain. A century later it is imported to Cuba and renamed jai alai.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1783</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Marylebone Cricket Club is founded and headquartered at Lord’s Cricket Ground. The club serves as the governing body of the sport.
</Question>
<Choice>1787</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Trapshooting contests and exhibitions are regularly held in England for the first time.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1790</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Duddingston Curling Society is founded in Edinburgh, Scot. The club frames the first set of curling rules.
</Question>
<Choice>1795</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
André-Jacques Garnerin becomes the first skydiver when he parachutes from a balloon at an altitude of 3,200 feet.
</Question>
<Choice>1797</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Friedrich Jahn opens a turnplatz, an open-air gymnasium in Berlin, beginning the modern renaissance of gymnastics.
</Question>
<Choice>1811</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
During the course of his research on light, Scottish natural philosopher David Brewster invents the kaleidoscope.
</Question>
<Choice>1816</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At the Rugby School in Rugby, Warwickshire, Eng., a player carries the ball instead of kicking it, thus paving the way for the sport of rugby.
</Question>
<Choice>1823</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The United Bowmen of Philadelphia form the first archery club in the United States. Healthful exercise is the goal, and nothing but water is drunk at its meetings.
</Question>
<Choice>1828</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The game of Poker is altered to be played with a standard 52-card deck, creating the modern form of the game.
</Question>
<Choice>1834</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first modern Highland Games are held in Scotland, at Braemar and Strathdon.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1835</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Numismatic Society of London is founded, becoming the first coin collecting association.
</Question>
<Choice>1836</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Henley Regatta (later the Henley Royal Regatta) is contested for the first time, at Henley-on-Thames, Oxfordshire, Eng. It is one of the best-known events in the sport of rowing.
</Question>
<Choice>1839</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The parlour game of pantomimed charades is described by William Makepeace Thackeray in his novel Vanity Fair.
</Question>
<Choice>1848</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English chess master Howard Staunton endorses a chess set designed by Nathaniel Cook. The Staunton pattern, as it becomes known, is still the most popular chess set design.
</Question>
<Choice>1849</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>The game of mah-jongg originates in China.</Question>
<Choice>c. 1850</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jump rope, or skip rope, becomes popular with school children, especially in England and Germany.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1850</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Under Commodore John C. Stevens, the America wins a yachting competition against 14 British vessels. The victor’s prize cup is for all subsequent contests known as "The America’s Cup."
</Question>
<Choice>1851</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mountaineering grows in popularity among European and British gentlemen. Among other things, the sport is lauded for its intellectual value, as many of its leaders are scientists or artists.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1853</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The racket sport of squash is developed at the English public school Harrow.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1855</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Paul C. Morphy wins the American chess championship at the first American Chess Congress. The American Chess Association is formed during the competition.
</Question>
<Choice>1857</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The growing popularity of Thomas Hughes's Tom Brown's School Days, published in 1857, helps make the ideal of "muscular Christianity" part of Victorian culture.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1860</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Taking advantage of the increased popularity of gambling, the casino at Monte-Carlo opens. Casinos become popular destinations for wealthy tourists in the mid-19th century.
</Question>
<Choice>1861</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Football Association is established in England, and a uniform set of soccer rules is set down.
</Question>
<Choice>1863</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
James L. Plimpton of Medford, Mass., designs the first modern four-wheel roller skate, leading to an explosion in the popularity of roller-skating.
</Question>
<Choice>1863</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
William Gilbert Grace of England plays his first match of first-class cricket. He becomes the greatest cricketer of the Victorian era, with 54,896 runs and 2,876 wickets in a 44-year career.
</Question>
<Choice>1865</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The game of shinty is played by British soldiers stationed in Canada. Not long after, it evolves into the modern game of ice hockey.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1865</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Wilhelm Steinitz of Prague defeats Adolf Anderssen for the first world chess championship. Steinitz remains champion for nearly 30 years.
</Question>
<Choice>1866</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sondre Nordheim of Norway wins the first known ski-jumping competition. The contest is held in his hometown.
</Question>
<Choice>1866</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British journalist John Graham Chambers introduces the Marquess of Queensberry rules for boxing.
</Question>
<Choice>1867</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At New Brunswick, N.J., the College of New Jersey (later renamed Princeton University) and Rutgers College play the first intercollegiate football game.
</Question>
<Choice>1869</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The gymkhana, an athletics and equestrian exhibition, spreads from India to England. It is one of several sports or sporting events that migrate between England and its imperial possessions.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1870</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The pari-mutuel system of wagering on horse races is introduced in France by businessman Pierre Oller.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1870</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The National Rifle Association of America is founded under the leadership of former Union general Ambrose Burnside.
</Question>
<Choice>1871</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Professional bookmaking makes its first appearance at American horse tracks.
</Question>
<Choice>1873</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Indian court game of poona is introduced to England at the country estate of Badminton. The game’s name is soon changed to that of the estate.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1873</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
H.J. Lawson of England designs the first chain-driven bicycle.
</Question>
<Choice>1874</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Westminster Kennel Club is formed in New York City. Its first annual dog show is held two years later.
</Question>
<Choice>1875</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At Churchill Downs in Louisville, Ky., Aristides wins the inaugural Kentucky Derby. The derby eventually becomes the most prestigious horse race in the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1875</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The National League of Professional Baseball Clubs is established. The rival American League is founded in 1900.
</Question>
<Choice>1876</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first uniform rules of water polo are formulated in Scotland.
</Question>
<Choice>1877</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spencer W. Gore wins the first tennis championship to be held at the All-England Croquet Club at Wimbledon.
</Question>
<Choice>1877</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
European racehorse Kincsem is retired with a record of 54 victories in 54 races. Over a century later it still stands as the best unbeaten record in Thoroughbred racing history.
</Question>
<Choice>1879</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Greek board game of Halma is invented. In a slightly altered form, it is marketed in the United States as Chinese checkers in the 1930s.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1880</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Coney Island amusement park, with its 3.5-mile boardwalk, becomes a popular New York City tourist attraction. The area also includes sideshows, museums, and orchestra halls.
</Question>
<Choice>1881</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Tokyo, Kano Jigoro establishes the first school of judo, which comes to be known as the Kodokan School.
</Question>
<Choice>1882</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The United States National Horse Show is held for the first time.
</Question>
<Choice>1883</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hamburg, Ger., hosts the first international speed skating competition.
</Question>
<Choice>1885</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Great Bend, Kan., hosts the first major greyhound races in the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1886</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
England and the United States play the first international polo match.
</Question>
<Choice>1886</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Denver, Colo., plays host to the first rodeo competition. Like many sports, rodeo is a formalized version of practical activities: riding and roping are essential skills for ranchers.
</Question>
<Choice>1887</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Amateur Athletic Union of the United States is founded for the purpose of preserving "sport for sport’s sake."
</Question>
<Choice>1888</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Euchre becomes popular as a family card game in the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1890</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Yale University football coach Walter Camp writes the first book about the sport, introducing rule changes and clarifying the differences between rugby and American football.
</Question>
<Choice>1891</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At the International Young Men’s Christian Association Training School in Springfield, Mass., physical education teacher James Naismith invents the game of basketball.
</Question>
<Choice>1891</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the first championship fight with padded gloves and the Marquess of Queensberry rules, Jim Corbett defeats champion John L. Sullivan for the heavyweight crown.
</Question>
<Choice>1892</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The International Olympic Committee is formed in Paris.
</Question>
<Choice>1894</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American William G. Morgan invents volleyball for the benefit of those who find the new game of basketball too taxing. Morgan initially calls the game "mintonette."
</Question>
<Choice>1895</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first automobile race in the United States takes place on Thanksgiving Day. The course runs from Chicago, Ill., to Evanston, and is won by a car driving an average of 7.5 miles per hour.
</Question>
<Choice>1895</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Due largely to the efforts of Pierre, baron de Coubertin, the first modern Olympic Games are held, in Athens.
</Question>
<Choice>1896</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John J. McDermott of New York City wins the first Boston Marathon with a time of 2 h 55 min 10 s.
</Question>
<Choice>1897</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Matthias Zdarsky publishes the first ski instruction manual, Die alpine Lilienfelder Skifahrtechnik. The book helps define and popularize the sport of Alpine skiing.
</Question>
<Choice>1897</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first world championship birling (logrolling) competition is held in Omaha, Neb.
</Question>
<Choice>1898</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Joshua Slocum of Nova Scotia completes the first solo sail around the world in his fishing boat, Spray.
</Question>
<Choice>1898</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first Davis Cup tennis competition is won by the American team.
</Question>
<Choice>1900</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At the Summer Olympics in Paris, American Ray C. Ewry takes the gold medal in all three standing jumps. Ewry enters eight Olympic jumping events and wins them all during his career.
</Question>
<Choice>1900</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Amsterdam schoolmaster Nico Broekhuysen invents korfball.
</Question>
<Choice>1901</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first Harmsworth Cup of motorboat racing is won by Englishman S.F. Edge.
</Question>
<Choice>1903</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In baseball’s first World Series, the Boston Red Sox of the American League beats the Pittsburgh Pirates of the National League.
</Question>
<Choice>1903</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Platform and springboard diving are recognized as championship events by the Amateur Swimming Federation.
</Question>
<Choice>1904</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first Vanderbilt Cup automobile race is run. Races are an important means of advertising the still-new form of transportation and encourage technological innovation in auto design.
</Question>
<Choice>1904</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Fédération Internationale de Football Association is organized as the global governing body of amateur soccer.
</Question>
<Choice>1904</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Cy Young pitches the first perfect game in major league baseball history by not allowing an opposing player to reach base. Young goes on to win a record 511 games in his career.
</Question>
<Choice>1904</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Kansas State College hosts the first major horseshoe pitching tournament.
</Question>
<Choice>1905</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Intercollegiate Athletic Association is formed and draws up competition rules for football and other intercollegiate sports. Later it becomes the National Collegiate Athletic Association.
</Question>
<Choice>1906</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Tourist Trophy motorcycle races are run for the first time, on the Isle of Man, just off the northwestern coast of England.
</Question>
<Choice>1907</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American Jack Johnson defeats Tommy Burns to become the first African-American man to win the world heavyweight boxing championship.
</Question>
<Choice>1908</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Imperial Cricket Conference is formed by England, South Africa, and Australia. Cricket is one of the enduring legacies of the British Empire and is played in Africa, India, and the Caribbean.
</Question>
<Choice>1909</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first Indianapolis 500 auto race is won by Ray Harroun driving a Marmon Wasp.
</Question>
<Choice>1911</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The International Amateur Athletic Federation is founded in Stockholm for the purpose of uniting over 160 national track-and-field associations.
</Question>
<Choice>1912</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At the Summer Olympics in Stockholm, Native American Jim Thorpe wins the pentathlon and decathlon. He goes on to play professional football and baseball.
</Question>
<Choice>1912</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first modern crossword puzzle is published in the New York World’s Sunday supplement.
</Question>
<Choice>1913</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Shuffleboard is introduced into Florida by Daytona Beach hoteliers Mr. and Mrs. Robert Ball.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1913</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Andalusian matador Juan Belmonte revolutionizes bullfighting by emphasizing graceful capework and exposure to danger over the act of killing.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1914</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Golfer Harry Vardon of England wins his sixth British Open. The Vardon Trophy—awarded annually to the professional with the best scoring average—is named for him.
</Question>
<Choice>1914</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Babe Ruth wins the first of his dozen American League home run crowns. The baseball slugger’s exploits are so renowned that the term “Ruthian” is coined to describe remarkable feats of batting.
</Question>
<Choice>1918</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the United States, the popularity of dog racing explodes after the mechanical rabbit is invented by O.P. Smith.
</Question>
<Choice>1919</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The heavily favoured Chicago White Sox lose the World Series to Cincinnati and then are accused of taking bribes from gamblers, leading to the Black Sox scandal.
</Question>
<Choice>1919</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Big Bill Tilden wins the first of six consecutive U.S. tennis championships. He goes on to win a total of 70 American and international titles.
</Question>
<Choice>1920</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Negro league baseball begins in the United States, with the formation of the Negro National League. Negro league play is rendered obsolete in the 1940s, when the major leagues are integrated.
</Question>
<Choice>1920</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chess champion Emanuel Lasker of Prussia is defeated by José Raúl Capablanca, ending Lasker’s 27-year-reign as world chess champion.
</Question>
<Choice>1921</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Thomas Hitchcock, Jr., leads the American polo team that defeats Great Britain in the Westchester Cup. In his storied career, he receives the highest possible rating in 18 of 19 seasons.
</Question>
<Choice>1921</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Arnold Lunn of England introduces slalom gates to downhill skiing, thus creating the modern Alpine slalom race.
</Question>
<Choice>1922</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Bobsledding gains international recognition as a sport. A year later it is included in the program of the first Winter Olympic Games, held in Chamonix, France.
</Question>
<Choice>1923</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At the Summer Olympics in Paris, American swimmer Johnny Weissmuller wins the first three of his five Olympic gold medals. He later becomes Tarzan in a series of motion pictures.
</Question>
<Choice>1924</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Harold Abrahams wins a gold medal in the 100-metre run in the Summer Olympics in Paris.
</Question>
<Choice>1924</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Against a University of Michigan football team that hasn’t been beaten in three years, Red Grange of Illinois scores on long touchdown runs the first four times he touches the ball.
</Question>
<Choice>1924</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first patent on a design for water skis is awarded to Fred Waller of Long Island, N.Y.
</Question>
<Choice>1925</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Stanley Cup becomes the property of the National Hockey League, to be presented annually to the league champion.
</Question>
<Choice>1926</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Gertrude Ederle of New York City becomes the first woman to swim the English Channel.
</Question>
<Choice>1926</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Hambletonian Stake is held for the first time. The leading horse race for trotters, it is named after the foundation sire of nearly all modern U.S. trotters.
</Question>
<Choice>1926</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American conjurer Harry Houdini describes his craft in an article in the 13th edition of the Encyclopædia Britannica.
</Question>
<Choice>1926</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Ryder Cup match play golf tournament is held for the first time.
</Question>
<Choice>1927</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first world championships of table tennis are held in London.
</Question>
<Choice>1927</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Finland’s Paavo Nurmi wins the 10,000-metre run at the Summer Olympics in Amsterdam, the last of his six individual gold-medal performances over three Olympic Games.
</Question>
<Choice>1928</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At the Winter Olympics in St. Moritz, Switz., 15-year-old Norwegian Sonja Henie wins the gold medal in figure skating. She repeats the feat in 1932 and 1936.
</Question>
<Choice>1928</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American Avery Brundage begins his 24-year presidency of the U.S. Olympic Association and Committee. He also heads the International Olympic Committee from 1952 to 1972.
</Question>
<Choice>1929</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Uruguay wins the first World Cup of soccer. Held every four years, the World Cup is one of the most popular and closely followed sporting events on Earth.
</Question>
<Choice>1930</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>The first modern pinball machines begin to appear.</Question>
<Choice>1930</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Irish Sweepstakes is authorized by the Irish government, with profits to aid Irish hospitals. The Sweepstakes is replaced in 1987 by a state lottery.
</Question>
<Choice>1930</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Architect Alfred M. Butts develops Criss Cross, which is later modified to the board game Scrabble by James Brunot.
</Question>
<Choice>1931</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At the Summer Olympics in Los Angeles, versatile American athlete Babe Didrikson wins medals in the hurdles, javelin competitions, and high jump. She goes on to a spectacular career in golf.
</Question>
<Choice>1932</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The board game Monopoly is developed. It quickly becomes one of the most popular games of all time.
</Question>
<Choice>1933</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Amateur Softball Association of America is founded. Five years later, it has the largest membership of any amateur sports organization in the world.
</Question>
<Choice>1933</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
League founder George Halas coaches the Chicago Bears over the New York Giants 23-21 in the first National Football League championship game.
</Question>
<Choice>1933</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Golf legend Bobby Jones helps to initiate the annual Masters Tournament at the Augusta (Ga.) National Golf Club.
</Question>
<Choice>1934</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jay Berwanger of the University of Chicago is the first winner of the Heisman Trophy, an annual award that recognizes the finest college football player in the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1935</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Baseball Hall of Fame is founded at Cooperstown, N.Y. The first five inductees are Ty Cobb, Walter Johnson, Christy Mathewson, Babe Ruth, and Honus Wagner.
</Question>
<Choice>1936</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the Summer Olympics at Berlin, African-American athlete Jesse Owens silences Adolf Hitler’s claims of Aryan supremacy when he wins four gold medals in track and field.
</Question>
<Choice>1936</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italy wins its second World Cup, defeating Hungary 3-2.
</Question>
<Choice>1938</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Heavyweight champion Joe Louis of the United States avenges what had been his only defeat by knocking out German Max Schmeling in the first round.
</Question>
<Choice>1938</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Don Budge becomes the first amateur lawn player to win tennis's grand slam (Wimbledon, plus the Australian, French, and U.S. opens) in one year.
</Question>
<Choice>1938</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Carl E. Stotz organizes Little League, the international baseball association for young boys. Girls are admitted in 1974.
</Question>
<Choice>1939</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
New York Yankee Lou Gehrig, stricken with amyotrophic lateral sclerosis, retires from baseball having played in 2,130 consecutive games, a record that would stand until 1995.
</Question>
<Choice>1939</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Willie Mosconi wins the first of 15 pocket billiards championships. Known for his accuracy and fancy shots, he elevates the game to respectability in the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1941</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One major league baseball season sees two magnificent feats: Ted Williams bats .406 for the year, and Joe DiMaggio sets a record by hitting safely in 56 consecutive games.
</Question>
<Choice>1941</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byron Nelson wins 18 golf tournaments in one year, including a streak of 11 in a row.
</Question>
<Choice>1945</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Baseball owners choose Happy Chandler as commissioner, but later regret it when he overrides their opposition to integrating the major leagues. In 1951 Chandler fails to win reelection.
</Question>
<Choice>1945</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jackie Robinson, second baseman of the Brooklyn Dodgers, becomes the first African-American baseball player in the modern major leagues.
</Question>
<Choice>1947</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
For the first time, both disciplines of Alpine skiing (downhill and slalom) are Winter Olympic medal events in the games at St. Moritz, Switz.
</Question>
<Choice>1948</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The design for the Frisbee flying disc is patented by Fred Morrison.
</Question>
<Choice>1948</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At the Summer Olympics in London, American Bob Mathias becomes the youngest track-and-field champion ever, winning the decathlon at age 17. He also triumphs four years later in Helsinki, Fin.
</Question>
<Choice>1948</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The National Basketball League and Basketball Association of America merge to form the National Basketball Association.
</Question>
<Choice>1949</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Boxer Rocky Marciano becomes heavyweight world champion, unseating Jersey Joe Walcott. Marciano is undefeated until his retirement in 1956; 43 of his 49 professional victories are knockouts.
</Question>
<Choice>1952</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At the Summer Olympics in Helsinki, Fin., Emil Zátopek of Czechoslovakia performs the superhuman feat of winning the 5,000- and 10,000-metre races and the marathon.
</Question>
<Choice>1952</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sir Edmund Hillary of New Zealand and fellow mountaineer Tenzing Norgay of Nepal become the first men to reach the top of Mount Everest, the highest summit in the world.
</Question>
<Choice>1953</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
New York Yankee Mickey Mantle leads the American League in home runs, RBIs, and batting average (.353), and wins the first of three AL Most Valuable Player awards.
</Question>
<Choice>1956</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
England’s Roger Bannister is the first person to run the mile in under four minutes.
</Question>
<Choice>1954</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
West Germany defeats Hungary 3-2 to win its first World Cup.
</Question>
<Choice>1954</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Quiz shows become popular on American television. In 1958 the industry is rocked by the Twenty-One scandal, but the genre recovers in the 1960s.
</Question>
<Choice>1955</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the Winter Olympics at Cortina d’Ampezzo, Italy, Austria’s Anton Sailer wins all three Alpine skiing events.
</Question>
<Choice>1956</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Windsurfing originates in the United States.</Question>
<Choice>c. 1957</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Seventeen-year-old soccer sensation Pelé leads Brazil to a 5-2 victory over Sweden in the World Cup final. Pelé becomes a Brazilian national hero and one of the world's best-known athletes.
</Question>
<Choice>1958</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American Bobby Fischer becomes the youngest player in the world to earn the rank of chess grand master. He later becomes the first American world chess champion.
</Question>
<Choice>1958</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Winnipeg Blue Bombers win the first modern Grey Cup of Canadian football.
</Question>
<Choice>1959</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Centre Bill Russell leads the Boston Celtics to the first of their eight straight National Basketball Association championships.
</Question>
<Choice>1959</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jacques Plante is the first National Hockey League goaltender to wear a protective face mask. Other goalies soon follow suit.
</Question>
<Choice>1959</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At the Summer Olympics in Rome, Ethiopian Abebe Bikila, running in his bare feet, wins the first of his two gold medals in the marathon.
</Question>
<Choice>1960</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Philadelphia Warriors player Wilt Chamberlain scores 100 points in a single game, a National Basketball Association record.
</Question>
<Choice>1962</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japan’s Watanabe Osamu wins his second world wrestling championship in the freestyle featherweight division. After an Olympic victory the following year, he retires undefeated with over 300 wins.
</Question>
<Choice>1963</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russia’s Lidiya Skoblikova becomes the first athlete to win four gold medals at one Winter Olympic Games when she sweeps the women’s speed skating events at Innsbruck, Austria.
</Question>
<Choice>1964</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French cyclist Jacques Anquetil is the first man to win the Tour de France five times. Established in 1904, the Tour is one of the most prestigious and demanding events in all of athletics.
</Question>
<Choice>1964</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the Summer Olympics at Tokyo, Soviet gymnast Larisa Latynina wins 6 medals, raising her final career total to a record 18 Olympic medals.
</Question>
<Choice>1964</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Yomiuri Giants win the first of nine consecutive Japan Series titles.
</Question>
<Choice>1965</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jim Brown of the Cleveland Browns retires from professional football, having gained 12,312 yards in nine seasons.
</Question>
<Choice>1965</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Led by team captain Bobby Moore, England defeats West Germany 4-2 (in extra time) in Wembley Stadium in London to win the World Cup of soccer.
</Question>
<Choice>1966</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Green Bay of the National Football League defeats Kansas City of the American Football League in the inaugural Super Bowl. Three years later the leagues merge into simply the National Football League.
</Question>
<Choice>1967</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Heavyweight champion Muhammad Ali refuses induction into the armed forces on religious grounds. He is subsequently convicted of violating the Selective Service Act and barred from the boxing ring.
</Question>
<Choice>1967</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In perhaps the greatest single feat in track and field history, American Bob Beamon smashes the world long jump record by nearly two feet at the Summer Olympics in Mexico City.
</Question>
<Choice>1968</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Special Olympics take place for the first time. The competition is held at Soldier Field in Chicago.
</Question>
<Choice>1968</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American tennis player Arthur Ashe wins both the amateur and open U.S. singles championships, becoming the first African-American winner of a major men’s singles championship.
</Question>
<Choice>1968</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pelé leads Brazil in its third World Cup victory, defeating Italy 4-1. One of the best-known and best-loved athletes in the world in the 1960s and 1970s, he is named Athlete of the Century in 1980.
</Question>
<Choice>1970</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Baseball player Curt Flood refuses to report to training camp and initiates court proceedings against baseball’s reserve clause. Flood loses, but several years later free agency is established.
</Question>
<Choice>1970</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Pakistan wins the first World Cup of field hockey.</Question>
<Choice>1971</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Atari Inc. introduces Pong, a video game, into arcades. The game's commercial success marks the beginning of an era of mass popularity for electronic games.
</Question>
<Choice>1972</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At the Summer Olympics in Munich, W.Ger., American swimmer Mark Spitz becomes the first athlete to win seven gold medals in one Olympics, setting world records in all seven races.
</Question>
<Choice>1972</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Coach John Wooden guides University of California at Los Angeles to its seventh consecutive collegiate basketball championship.
</Question>
<Choice>1973</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Iditarod Trail Sled Dog Race is contested for the first time at its traditional distance of 1,100 miles.
</Question>
<Choice>1973</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Secretariat becomes the first horse to win the American Triple Crown since Citation had won it in 1948.
</Question>
<Choice>1973</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Eddy Merckx of Belgium wins his fifth Tour de France, tying the record of Frenchman Jacques Anquetil.
</Question>
<Choice>1974</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hank Aaron of the Atlanta Braves breaks Babe Ruth's major league home run record. Aaron finishes his career with 755 home runs.
</Question>
<Choice>1974</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Cricketer Garfield Sobers of the West Indies is knighted. In his career, he has set Test match records in runs (8,032) and centuries (26) and has come to be regarded as one of his sport's greatest performers.
</Question>
<Choice>1975</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The development of the faster and more maneuverable polyurethane wheel causes a renewed enthusiasm for skateboarding.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1975</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At the Summer Olympics in Montreal, Romanian gymnast Nadia Comaneci is the first to achieve a perfect score of 10 in an Olympic gymnastic event. She receives seven such scores during the competition.
</Question>
<Choice>1976</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Walter Payton of the Chicago Bears rushes for an NFL record 275 yards in one game. He ends his career with a record total of 16,726 yards rushing.
</Question>
<Choice>1977</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the greatest hitting feat of baseball’s World Series, Reggie Jackson hits three home runs in one game—in three consecutive at-bats, on three consecutive pitches.
</Question>
<Choice>1977</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Vasily Alekseyev sets the last of his 79 world records in weightlifting.
</Question>
<Choice>1978</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Irina (Konstantinovna) Rodnina of the Soviet Union wins her 10th consecutive world championship in pairs figure skating.
</Question>
<Choice>1978</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Entertainment and Sports Programming Network is founded in Bristol, Conn. By 1996, it is the country’s largest cable network, carried to nearly 70 million homes.
</Question>
<Choice>1978</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American cowboy Tom R. Ferguson becomes the first man to win the Professional Rodeo Cowboys Association’s all-around title six times consecutively.
</Question>
<Choice>1979</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Stock-car driver Richard Petty wins his seventh and final Winston Cup racing championship. Known as “The King,” Petty is the first driver to win more than three such titles.
</Question>
<Choice>1979</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American Eric Heiden wins all five speed skating gold medals in the Winter Olympics at Lake Placid, N.Y.
</Question>
<Choice>1980</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
West German glider pilot Hans Werner Grosse sets a world record of 812 miles for distance around a triangular course.
</Question>
<Choice>1981</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In winning the Nordic World Cup competition, American Bill Koch popularizes a new “skating” style of cross-country skiing.
</Question>
<Choice>1982</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italy wins its first World Cup in 44 years. Its third victory comes in a 3-1 match against fellow national powerhouse and regular World Cup finalist West Germany.
</Question>
<Choice>1982</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At the World Aquatic Championships, American diver Greg Louganis becomes the first in his sport to earn a perfect score of 10 from all the judges.
</Question>
<Choice>1982</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Czech-born American tennis player Martina Navratilova defeats longtime rival Chris Evert (6-1, 6-3) at the U.S. Open. It is Navratilova's third Grand Slam title of the year.
</Question>
<Choice>1983</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ice dancing couple Jayne Torvill and Christopher Dean of Great Britain skate flawlessly to Maurice Ravel's Boléro and win the gold medal at the Winter Olympics in Sarajevo, Yugos.
</Question>
<Choice>1984</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At the Summer Olympics in Los Angeles, American Carl Lewis repeats the feat of Jesse Owens, winning gold medals in the same four events that Owens won at the 1936 Berlin Games.
</Question>
<Choice>1984</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Bernard Hinault becomes the third cyclist to win the Tour de France five times.
</Question>
<Choice>1985</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pete Rose of the Cincinnati Reds surpasses Ty Cobb's record of hits in a career (4,191) to become baseball's all-time hits leader.
</Question>
<Choice>1985</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American golfer Jack Nicklaus wins a record sixth Masters Tournament. In his career, Nicklaus is named Professional Golfers’ Association player of the year five times.
</Question>
<Choice>1986</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At Seoul, South Korea, swimmer Kristin Otto of East Germany becomes the first woman to win six gold medals in one Olympic Games.
</Question>
<Choice>1988</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Steffi Graf of West Germany wins the Grand Slam of tennis tournaments (Wimbledon, plus the Australian, French, and U.S. Opens).
</Question>
<Choice>1988</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Florence Griffith Joyner becomes the fastest woman with her record-setting times in the 100-metre sprint (10.49 sec) and the 200-metre sprint (21.34).
</Question>
<Choice>1988</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Wayne Gretzky breaks Gordie Howe's National Hockey League all-time scoring record (1,850 points). He finishes his career in 1999 with 2,857 points.
</Question>
<Choice>1989</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
West Germany, coached by Franz Beckenbauer, blanks Argentina 1-0 to earn its third World Cup of soccer. Beckenbauer becomes the only man to both play for and coach a World Cup championship team.
</Question>
<Choice>1990</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Led by star forward Mia Hamm, the United States wins the first women’s World Cup of soccer.
</Question>
<Choice>1991</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Freestyle skiing is added as an Olympic medal event, in the Winter Games at Albertville, France.
</Question>
<Choice>1992</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At the Olympics in Barcelona, Spain, Jackie Joyner-Kersee of the United States becomes the first woman to win consecutive gold medals in the heptathlon.
</Question>
<Choice>1992</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Boat racer Chip Hanauer wins the Gold Cup, tying the record in Unlimited hydroplanes with seven national championships.
</Question>
<Choice>1993</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A baseball strike in the United States causes the cancellation of the World Series for the first time in 90 years.
</Question>
<Choice>1994</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Brazil wins its fourth World Cup. It is Brazil's second World Cup trophy: the nation took permanent possession of the Jules Rimet Trophy after its 1970 victory.
</Question>
<Choice>1994</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At the Winter Olympics in Lillehammer, Nor., Bonnie Blair of the United States becomes the first speed skating competitor to win at the same distance (500 metres) in three straight Olympics.
</Question>
<Choice>1994</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Miguel Indurain of Spain becomes the first to win the Tour de France five consecutive times.
</Question>
<Choice>1995</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Race-car driver Jacques Villeneuve becomes the first Canadian to win the Indianapolis 500.
</Question>
<Choice>1995</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Sri Lanka wins the sixth World Cup in cricket.</Question>
<Choice>1996</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British oarsman Steven Redgrave wins the coxless pairs gold medal in the Summer Olympics at Atlanta, Ga., and becomes the first endurance-event champion in four different Olympics.
</Question>
<Choice>1996</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first Olympic beach volleyball competition is won by Kent Steffes and Karch Kiraly of the United States. For Kiraly, arguably volleyball's greatest player, it is his third Olympic gold medal.
</Question>
<Choice>1996</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Tiger Woods shoots a 270 over 72 holes at the Masters Tournament to become the first person of African descent, as well as the first person of Asian descent, to win a major professional golf title.
</Question>
<Choice>1997</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. gambling revenues hit $47.6 billion. The 1980s and ’90s have seen a vast growth in the number of casinos in the United States and in the popularity and social acceptability of gambling.
</Question>
<Choice>1997</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Extreme sports, such as street luge and wakeboarding, begin to enter the mainstream.
</Question>
<Choice>1997</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jeff Gordon wins his second NASCAR Winston Cup points title, as he helps make race-car driving one of the fastest growing sports in the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1997</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Fifteen-year-old figure skater Tara Lipinski becomes the youngest female athlete to win a gold medal in an individual event at the Winter Olympic Games in Nagano, Japan.
</Question>
<Choice>1998</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Olympics are hit by a scandal after it is revealed that prospective host cities offered gifts to voters.
</Question>
<Choice>1998</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Cal Ripken, Jr., sits out a Major League Baseball game, ending his record of most consecutive games played at 2,632.
</Question>
<Choice>1998</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Snowboarding and curling are contested for the first time in Olympic history, in the Winter Games at Nagano, Japan.
</Question>
<Choice>1998</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mark McGwire, first baseman of the St. Louis Cardinals, hits his 62nd home run of the season, breaking Roger Maris’s record; by season’s end McGwire will have hit 70 home runs.
</Question>
<Choice>1998</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Michael Jordan, the greatest player in basketball history, announces his retirement. He had won two Olympic gold medals, 10 league scoring titles, and led the Chicago Bulls to six national titles.
</Question>
<Choice>1999</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English ballooning instructor Brian Jones and Swiss psychiatrist Bertrand Piccard are the first to circumnavigate the Earth nonstop in a hot-air balloon. The trip is made in just under 20 days.
</Question>
<Choice>1999</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Lennox Lewis defeats Evander Holyfield to become the only British boxer in the 20th century to hold the undisputed world heavyweight title.
</Question>
<Choice>1999</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Tony Lockett retires from the Australian Football League (AFL) with a record-breaking 1,357 goals.
</Question>
<Choice>1999</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Inge De Bruijn of The Netherlands is one of the stars at the Sydney Olympics, capturing 4 medals and setting three world records in swimming events.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
With his win at the British Open, American golfer Tiger Woods becomes the youngest player to win the sport's four major championships.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Shaquille O'Neal of the Los Angeles Lakers captures his first NBA championship and is named the most valuable player of the playoffs.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At Wimbledon Pete Sampras wins his record-setting 13th Grand Slam single's title for men.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jamaican cricket player Courtney Walsh becomes the highest wicket taker (435) in Test history.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
NASCAR driver Dale Earnhardt, Sr., dies after crashing during the final lap of the Daytona 500. Known as "The Intimidator," he helped popularize the sport.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Baseball outfielder Barry Bonds of the San Francisco Giants hits 73 home runs to break Mark McGwire's single-season home run record.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Penn State football coach Joe Paterno wins his 324th game to break Bear Bryant's career record; Paterno finishes the season with 327 victories.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Winter Olympics are held in Salt Lake City, Utah. Charges of impropriety in figure-skating events leads to a review of the judging system.
</Question>
<Choice>2002</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The New England Patriots of the NFL defeat the heavily favoured St. Louis Rams to win the franchise's first Super Bowl.
</Question>
<Choice>2002</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Led by the play of Ronaldo, Brazil defeats Germany to win its fifth World Cup.
</Question>
<Choice>2002</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Emmitt Smith of the Dallas Cowboys breaks the NFL's career rushing record (16,726 yards) that had been held by Walter Payton.
</Question>
<Choice>2002</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Switzerland wins its first America's Cup, sailing's premier prize.
</Question>
<Choice>2003</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
England becomes the first team from the Northern Hemisphere to win the Rugby World Cup.
</Question>
<Choice>2003</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian women dominate professional tennis. At the French Open Anastasiya Myskina becomes the first Russian female to win a Grand Slam title. She is soon followed by Mariya Sharapova (Wimbledon) and Svetlana Kuznetsova (U.S. Open).
</Question>
<Choice>2004</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Due to an owners' lockout, the entire 2004-05 NHL season is cancelled. It is the first time a North American professional sports league has called off an entire season.
</Question>
<Choice>2004</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Despite concerns about construction delays and terrorist threats, the Olympic Games in Athens are a huge success. Standout athletes include American Michael Phelps, who wins a record 8 swimming medals.
</Question>
<Choice>2004</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American cyclist Lance Armstrong, who overcame testicular cancer in the late 1990s, wins a record seventh Tour de France and subsequently retires from racing.
</Question>
<Choice>2005</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Fernando Alonso of Spain captures the Formula 1 world championship at age 24, becoming the youngest driver to win the honour.
</Question>
<Choice>2005</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japan wins the first World Baseball Classic. The 16-team tournament had been in jeopardy until the U.S. allowed Cuba to participate.
</Question>
<Choice>2006</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italy defeats France to claim its fourth World Cup. The match is marred by controversy when, after persistent verbal abuse from Italian defender Marco Materazzi, French captain Zinedine Zidane head-butts his opponent and is given a red card.
</Question>
<Choice>2006</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Bobby Knight records his 880th career win to become the most successful coach in men's college basketball, surpassing Dean Smith.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Tony Dungy becomes the first African American coach to win a Super Bowl in the NFL, as his Indianapolis Colts defeat the Chicago Bears.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Barry Bonds of the San Francisco Giants becomes the all-time home run champion in major league baseball, surpassing Hank Aaron (755); Bonds ends the season with 762 home runs.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The New England Patriots become the first 16-0 team in NFL history but lose to the New York Giants in the Super Bowl XLII.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The use of performance-enhancing drugs continues to dominate sports, especially baseball. MLB releases the Mitchell report, which alleges that some 85 players, including Barry Bonds and Roger Clemens, have possessed or used steroids or human growth hormone (HGH) in the previous decade.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
With his victory at the Australian Open, Novak Djokovic becomes the first Serbian man to win a Grand Slam singles title.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American swimmer Michael Phelps wins a record eight gold medals at the 2008 Olympics in Beijing.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Usain Bolt of Jamaica sets world records in both the 100- and 200-m sprints at the 2008 Olympics, the first person to accomplish the feat.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Pittsburgh Steelers defeat the Arizona Cardinals in Super Bowl XLIII to win a record sixth NFL championship.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Rafael Nadal becomes the first Spaniard to win the Australian Open.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Martin Brodeur of the New Jersey Devils registers his 552nd career victory to become the winningest goalie in NHL history.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
With his victory at Wimbledon, tennis player Roger Federer wins his record 15th grand slam title.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Rio de Janeiro is awarded the 2016 Summer Olympics; it is the first time a South American city has been selected to host the Games.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Tiger Woods takes an indefinite leave of absence from golf following the revelation that he had a series of extramarital afffairs.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
South Africa hosts the World Cup; it is the first time the association football (soccer) tournament has been held in Africa.
</Question>
<Choice>2010</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Li Na becomes the first Chinese tennis player to be ranked in the Women's Tennis Association top 10.
</Question>
<Choice>2010</Choice>
</item>
</topics>