<topics>
<item>
<Question>
First appearance of deliberately shaped tools produced by ancestors of human beings.
</Question>
<Choice>2.6 million BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Homo erectus produces a simple tool of chipped flint; the precise use of the Acheulean hand ax is unknown.
</Question>
<Choice>1.5 million BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Members of the Aurignacian culture in Western Europe begin to produce cave art and a variety of specialized tools.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 40,000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Cro-Magnon man begins to produce rope, sewing needles, blades with attached handles, and other relatively complex technologies.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 35,000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Evidence of chopping-tool manufacture in China, India, and Southeast Asia. The pebble chopper was the most important tool produced by these groups.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 10,000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pottery production, agriculture, and domestication of animals appear, first in the region of Iraq and Syria, then through the valleys of the Indus and Nile rivers.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 9000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Beer is brewed in Sumeria and Babylonia. Beers become popular in the Middle East, Africa, and other areas where the climate does not support grape and wine production.
</Question>
<Choice>6500 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The loom, a machine used for weaving cloth, comes into use.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 4500 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Egyptians begin to fashion copper and develop alloys, marking the birth of metallurgy and metalworking.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 4000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Digging sticks, crude plows and sickles, grinding stones, and irrigation systems appear in Mesopotamia.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 4000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>The wheel comes into use in Mesopotamia.</Question>
<Choice>c. 3500 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>The Bronze Age begins in China and Greece.</Question>
<Choice>c. 3100 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first pyramids are erected in Egypt, using human labour and sleds to move hewn stones weighing several tons each.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 2700 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Silkworm cultivation begins in China. China dominates production of the fabric for millennia; international demand for silk leads to creation of the "Silk Road."
</Question>
<Choice>c. 2500 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Improvements to wheel include independent axles and spokes, which allow more efficient transport of heavier loads.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 2000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Babylonians under King Hammurabi (1792-1750 BC) embark on canal-building and artificial irrigation, improving water-diversion and irrigation techniques dating to 5000 BC.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1750 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Minoan civilization reaches its technological and cultural peak. Amenities at the palace at Knossos include bathrooms and running water.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1600 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Water clocks are in use in Egypt. Simple water clocks, or clepsydras, are used throughout the ancient world and take a variety of forms.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1500 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Iron Age begins in Europe and spreads to China by 600 BC.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1200 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Paved roads in use in Near Eastern cities.</Question>
<Choice>1200 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Phoenician dominance of Mediterranean seas begins, continuing until about 800 BC. Phoenician ships, which are far more efficient, replace traditional paddles with oars.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1100 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek engineers invent the catapult, exploiting gravity and expanding their arsenal of battering rams and wheeled vehicles.
</Question>
<Choice>400 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Pharos of Alexandria is built and becomes an archetype for all later lighthouses.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 280 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Great Wall of China is completed when existing defensive structures are united and extended. It reaches a height of 30 feet (9 m) and extends 4,000 miles (6,400 km).
</Question>
<Choice>c. 214 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Archimedes, best known of ancient engineers, is killed during the siege of Syracuse.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 211 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Alexander the Great sponsors the development of iron armour, a more durable alternative to bronze. Leather and other kinds of armour have been in use since 1100 BC.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 200 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman use of nailed horseshoes gives horses' hooves protection against hard ground.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 110 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Work begins on the Tower of the Winds, Athens. A marble structure 42 feet (12.8 metres) high, it is built by Andronicus of Cyrrhus to tell time.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 100 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Glassblowing develops in Syria.</Question>
<Choice>100 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Vertical undershot waterwheels appear in eastern Mediterranean. Waterwheels will be an important source of mechanical power in the West until the 19th century.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 85 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Vitruvius writes De architectura. Its studies of city planning, architecture, hydraulics, timekeeping, and fortifications are central to Western architecture and engineering for 1,500 years.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 30 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese sources describe horizontal waterwheels being used to operate bellows of iron-smelting furnaces. Horizontal waterwheels are popular in Asia, India, and the Near East.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 30</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Work begins on the Segovia aqueduct, which carries water for 10 miles (16 km).
</Question>
<Choice>c. 98</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Records indicate paper is produced in China. Paper spreads to the Islamic world in the 700s and Europe in the 1300s, transforming writing, book production, and the cultures that adopt it.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 105</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Teutonic tribes bring heavy iron plowshares into Western Europe, inaugurating extensive agriculture-based settlement in this region.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 500</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Soap production develops in Europe, though it is used primarily for laundry rather than personal hygiene.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 500</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese develop block book printing, a printing method in which entire pages are carved in relief on a single block of wood.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 510</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The astrolabe is developed. Among the most important and versatile medieval instruments, it is used widely in astronomy and navigation. It reaches Europe from the Islamic world.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 550</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The stirrup is adopted by European horsemen, stabilizing the rider and eventually transforming mounted warfare by giving attacking riders greater stability in combat.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 700</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese blend charcoal, sulfur, and saltpetre to create incendiary mixtures, leading to the development of gunpowder. Gunpowder reaches Europe in the 14th century.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 800</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The gearless "Norse" or "Greek" mill emerges in Europe, employing waterpower to drive a pair of grindstones.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The vertically mounted undershot waterwheel appears in England, providing an efficient power source for processing grains, oils, and textiles and for sawing wood.
</Question>
<Choice>1086</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An elaborate waterpowered mechanical clock is constructed in China under the supervision of Su Sung.
</Question>
<Choice>1088</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Padded horse collars improve use of horses for agricultural and other transportation purposes in Europe.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1100</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Windmills, first invented in Persia in the 7th century, come into use in Europe, bringing mechanical power to areas lacking in reliable sources of flowing water.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1120</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Magnetic compass is in use in China and the Mediterranean. Francis Bacon later declares it one of the three great inventions of all time; printing and gunpowder are the other two.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1190</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
First recorded reference to eyeglasses made by Roger Bacon. Eyeglasses are already in use in both China and Europe.
</Question>
<Choice>1268</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
First recorded use of navigational charts; with the astrolabe, the charts bring extensive global exploration and the expansion of European powers.
</Question>
<Choice>1270</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spinning wheel, known earlier in India, appears in Europe. It is probably the first machine with a belt transmission and parts that move at different rates.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1275</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Use of waterpower to drive systems of hammers (operated by cams attached to a drive shaft) encourages establishment of textile and paper industries in England.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1280</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Marco Polo returns from China, carrying information about Chinese technologies to the West, which are enthusiastically embraced for commercial and scientific purposes.
</Question>
<Choice>1295</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>First European use of treadle, applied in weaving.</Question>
<Choice>c. 1300</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The portolan chart, an improved maritime navigational chart, comes into use in Europe. Its invention marks the beginnings of professional cartography.
</Question>
<Choice>1300</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Earliest record of a cannon in Europe. Until the development of iron shot in the 1500s, cannons shoot arrows, stones, and other objects.
</Question>
<Choice>1326</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first public mechanical clock to strike the hours is erected in Milan, Italy. Weight-driven clocks offer reliable means of timekeeping in sunless climates.
</Question>
<Choice>1335</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Blast furnaces are used in iron-ore smelting, encouraging large-scale production of cast-iron building and machine components.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1350</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The carpenter's brace, the first complete crank, is used by Flemish carpenters. It leads to the use of connecting rods and flywheels and, ultimately, to machine designs using rotary motion.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1400</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian architect Filippo Brunelleschi begins construction of the octagonal ribbed dome of the Florence Cathedral.
</Question>
<Choice>1420</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Refining hand-block printing techniques of earlier eras, Johannes Gutenberg develops a hand-operated printing press employing ink rollers and raised, hand-set letters.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1450</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Metal plates are used for printing in the German Rhine valley and northern Italy. These plates extend the size of print runs and support more detailed illustration than woodcuts.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1455</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Prince Henry the Navigator sponsors voyages of exploration to the Madeiras and western Africa. These lay the groundwork for later European maritime travel to eastern Africa, Asia, and the Americas.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1460</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French manufacturers begin to make silk, in part on the basis of knowledge of Asian techniques.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1480</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Leonardo da Vinci designs submarines, airplanes, bicycles, and screw-cutting machines. His work illustrates the close links between science, art, and engineering in the Renaissance.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1490</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Railroads first appear in European mines.</Question>
<Choice>c. 1550</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German engineer Georgius Agricola's widely influential De re metallica is published posthumously. The treatise describes mining and engineering techniques, including shaft and pump design.
</Question>
<Choice>1556</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-Swiss naturalist Conrad Gesner provides the first description of the lead pencil. Pencils gain popularity in Europe from the late 1500s.
</Question>
<Choice>1565</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Englishman Rev. William Lee invents the stocking frame, the first practical knitting machine.
</Question>
<Choice>1589</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Coal mining is established in Germany's Ruhr valley, laying an early foundation for extensive industrial development in the region.
</Question>
<Choice>1590</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
William Gilbert writes De Magnete, an influential summary of contemporary knowledge of magnetism and electricity.
</Question>
<Choice>1600</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch opticians develop the refracting telescope. It is soon copied elsewhere in Europe, most famously by Galileo, who uses it to discover the moons of Jupiter.
</Question>
<Choice>1608</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Cotton manufacturing begins in Manchester, Eng., establishing a foundation for the industrial economy of the region.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1620</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
England's Statute of Monopolies, the first modern patent law, is passed by Parliament.
</Question>
<Choice>1623</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch mathematician and physicist Christiaan Huygens develops experimental piston engine, based on the design of cannons and using explosive powder as fuel.
</Question>
<Choice>1673</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The pressure cooker is invented by French-born British engineer and physicist Denis Papin.
</Question>
<Choice>1679</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The 150-mile- (240-km-) long Midi Canal is completed. It connects the Mediterranean and the Bay of Biscay, employing locks, aqueducts, and a tunnel.
</Question>
<Choice>1692</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English engineer Thomas Savery patents a rudimentary atmospheric steam engine, based on steam condensation.
</Question>
<Choice>1698</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Agriculture in England begins to employ technological improvements, including crop rotation and Jethro Tull's mechanical sower.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1700</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Abraham Darby of England adapts the blast furnace to use coke as fuel, greatly improving the production of cast iron.
</Question>
<Choice>1708</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Precision lathes are developed in Europe for the production of clocks and scientific instruments. They also provide an important foundation for industrial machine tools.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1710</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Thomas Newcomen produces the first commercially viable atmospheric steam engine, connecting a piston to a rocking beam that can in turn operate a pump.
</Question>
<Choice>1712</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English inventor John Kay patents the flying shuttle loom, mechanizing a cumbersome feature of loom operation.
</Question>
<Choice>1733</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The sextant replaces the octant as European mariners' favourite instrument for making celestial measurements on land and water.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1750</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English clockmaker John Harrison's chronometer is officially recognized as reliable enough to be used in calculating longitude at sea. He eventually wins £20,000 for his invention.
</Question>
<Choice>1763</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English inventor Richard Arkwright patents a steam-powered rotary engine spinning machine, which, by the 1790s, leads to the extensive employment of steam power in cotton mills.
</Question>
<Choice>1769</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
James Watt patents a steam engine based on a separate chamber for the condensation of steam and a "double acting" piston moved in both directions by the steam.
</Question>
<Choice>1769</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Industrialist Matthew Boulton works with James Watt between 1775 and 1800 to apply the steam engine to mining and other industrial operations.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1775</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Samuel Crompton invents the spinning mule, which mechanically mimics the movements of hand spinning, allowing the large-scale production of thread and yarn.
</Question>
<Choice>1779</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Construction is finished on a 100-foot- (30-m-) span cast-iron bridge at Coalbrookdale, Eng. The "Ironbridge" is the first major structural application of the material.
</Question>
<Choice>1779</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French brothers Joseph-Michel and Jacques-Étienne Montgolfier stage the first manned untethered balloon flight, using a large linen bag inflated with hot air.
</Question>
<Choice>1783</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English manufacturer Henry Cort invents a method for producing rolled steel bars. The next year he patents a puddling process for converting pig iron into wrought iron.
</Question>
<Choice>1783</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first patent laws are enacted in the United States. Thomas Jefferson plays a major role in their creation.
</Question>
<Choice>1790</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American engineer Oliver Evans invents the first successful high-pressure steam engine.
</Question>
<Choice>1790</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American inventor Eli Whitney designs a cotton gin to mechanically separate the fibres and seeds of short-staple cotton.
</Question>
<Choice>1793</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The École Polytechnique is founded in Paris. The first technical university, it sets the precedent for providing university education in technical, rather than liberal, subjects.
</Question>
<Choice>1794</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Frenchman Claude Chappe invents the semaphore, a signaling system employing a set of arms that pivot on a post.
</Question>
<Choice>1794</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
France adopts the metric system. A product of post-French Revolution reforms, the system is later adopted by most of the world.
</Question>
<Choice>1795</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian physicist Alessandro Volta creates the first electric battery, using zinc and copper disks.
</Question>
<Choice>1800</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
After several years' work with steam engines, English mechanical engineer Richard Trevithick builds the first steam-powered locomotive.
</Question>
<Choice>1803</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French engineer Joseph-Marie Jacquard begins work on a loom that uses punched cards to produce elaborate patterns in woven fabrics. The invention, later called the Jacquard loom, is finished in 1805.
</Question>
<Choice>1804</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Bands of English labourers known as "Luddites" riot to protest unemployment and low wages. They attribute their troubles to the spread of mechanized textile production.
</Question>
<Choice>1811</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Times of London begins printing newspapers on a steam-powered flatbed press.
</Question>
<Choice>1814</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sir Marc Isambard Brunel patents his tunneling shield, a machine that makes possible, for the first time, underwater tunneling.
</Question>
<Choice>1818</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Charles Babbage, an English mathematician, develops plans for a mechanical "analytical engine," predecessor to computers of later eras.
</Question>
<Choice>1820</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English inventor Joseph Aspdin patents portland cement, a burned mixture of limestone and clay that is cheaper than naturally occurring cements.
</Question>
<Choice>1824</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, one of the first colleges in the United States devoted to teaching engineering and science, is founded in Troy, N.Y.
</Question>
<Choice>1824</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Erie Canal, linking Albany, N.Y., and Buffalo, N.Y., opens after seven years' embrace of large-scale civil engineering projects.
</Question>
<Choice>1825</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first rail line for passengers, the Stockton and Darlington Railway, begins operation in England.
</Question>
<Choice>1825</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
First steam-powered railroads are built in the United States to transport coal from mines to market.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1830</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English scientist Michael Faraday and American physicist Joseph Henry independently reveal relationship of electricity and magnetism, laying the groundwork for electrical engineering.
</Question>
<Choice>1831</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American inventor Cyrus McCormick designs a mechanized reaper.
</Question>
<Choice>1831</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Balloon-frame housing, an inexpensive construction method employing simple framing and lumber cut to standard lengths, is developed in Chicago.
</Question>
<Choice>1832</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
First electromagnetic telegraph is developed by German physicists Carl Friedrich Gauss and Wilhelm Weber.
</Question>
<Choice>1833</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English inventor William Henry Fox Talbot successfully refines techniques of negative photography, leading to numerous patents of negative and printing methods.
</Question>
<Choice>1835</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British inventors William Cooke and Charles Wheatstone patent workable technologies for electric telegraph.
</Question>
<Choice>1837</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American inventor John Deere begins to sell plows with steel moldboards, greatly increasing their efficiency and durability and making possible the cultivation of the Great Plains.
</Question>
<Choice>1837</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German inventor M.H. von Jacobi develops electrotyping, a process for duplicating relief printing plates.
</Question>
<Choice>1838</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American Samuel F.B. Morse devises Morse Code, a signal system for telegraphy.
</Question>
<Choice>1838</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first self-propelled bicycle is built by Scottish inventor Kirkpatrick Macmillan.
</Question>
<Choice>1839</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The daguerreotype, the first successful form of photography, is publicly unveiled. It was developed by Louis-Jacques-Mandé Daguerre and Joseph-Nicéphore Niepce in the 1830s.
</Question>
<Choice>1839</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American Charles Goodyear invents vulcanization, vastly expanding uses of rubber for industry and transportation.
</Question>
<Choice>1839</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The United States Patent Office occupies its new building in Washington, D.C., designed by architect Robert Mills.
</Question>
<Choice>1840</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English mechanical engineer Joseph Whitworth develops standardized screw threads, streamlining machine operation and inspiring related efforts in the United States and elsewhere.
</Question>
<Choice>1841</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Thames Tunnel, the first underwater tunnel, opens in London. It is the capstone of the career of French-born British engineer Marc Isambard Brunel.
</Question>
<Choice>1842</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The U.S. Congress awards American inventor Samuel F.B. Morse a contract to build the first telegraph line, between Baltimore, Md., and Washington. The line opens the next year.
</Question>
<Choice>1843</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American inventor Erastus Bigelow begins work on a powered loom for the manufacture of carpets. His device is completed in 1851.
</Question>
<Choice>1845</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American inventor Elias Howe patents the first practical sewing machine.
</Question>
<Choice>1846</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American engineer James Bogardus builds the first cast-iron frame buildings. His book Cast Iron Buildings: Their Construction and Advantages (1858) helps popularize the new building type.
</Question>
<Choice>1848</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first undersea cable is laid beneath the English Channel, bringing almost instantaneous telegraphic communication between Europe and Britain.
</Question>
<Choice>1850</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Steamboats dominate American river transport, particularly on the Mississippi River.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1850</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American manufacturers begin to adopt system of interchangeable parts (using gauges, jigs, and fixtures), laying the foundation for mass production.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1850</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American Isaac Singer founds I.M. Singer & Company, which by 1860 is the world's largest sewing machine manufacturer. It also pioneers the installment credit plan.
</Question>
<Choice>1851</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English photographer Frederick Scott Archer invents the wet collodion photographic process. Unlike daguerreotypes, the images on collodion plates can be reproduced on paper.
</Question>
<Choice>1851</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Crystal Palace exhibition in London focuses wide public attention on industrial technologies and manufactures.
</Question>
<Choice>1851</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John Roebling erects the first wire-rope suspension bridge over Niagara Falls. It serves as a model for later suspension bridges, including Roebling's Brooklyn Bridge (opened 1883).
</Question>
<Choice>1852</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Elisha Otis invents an automobile safety device for elevators, which prevents their uncontrolled falling. Otis' device makes elevators safer and contributes to the growth of tall buildings.
</Question>
<Choice>1852</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian telegraph system opens, facilitating British administrative and military control of the colony.
</Question>
<Choice>1853</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English inventor Henry Bessemer patents a converter that introduces cold air into molten iron to produce steel in larger quantities at lower cost than previously.
</Question>
<Choice>1856</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Belgian inventor Jean-Joseph-Étienne Lenoir designs the first internal-combustion engine, based on the horizontal steam engine and using gas as fuel.
</Question>
<Choice>1859</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
World's first successful oil well is drilled in Titusville, Pa.
</Question>
<Choice>1859</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Prolific German-born English engineer and inventor William Siemens patents the open-hearth furnace process for steelmaking.
</Question>
<Choice>1861</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Richard J. Gatling invents the Gatling gun, the first practical machine gun.
</Question>
<Choice>1862</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Congress passes the Morrill Act, which provides federal funds for public colleges devoted to "agriculture and the mechanical arts." Many state engineering colleges are founded in its wake.
</Question>
<Choice>1862</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Metropolitan Railway, the world's first subway, opens in London.
</Question>
<Choice>1863</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Open-hearth process for steelmaking, invented by William Siemens, is first used. The Siemens-Martin process eventually dominates the industry.
</Question>
<Choice>1864</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Massachusetts Institute of Technology, chartered in 1861, holds its first classes in Boston. MIT moves to Cambridge in 1916.
</Question>
<Choice>1865</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
After several years' effort, the first permanent transatlantic telegraph cable is laid, linking America and Europe.
</Question>
<Choice>1866</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Alfred Nobel, Swedish chemist and engineer, is awarded a patent for dynamite. Nobel later endows the Nobel Prizes, among the world's most prestigious awards for notable achievements.
</Question>
<Choice>1867</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American inventor Christopher Latham Sholes, building on the work of earlier engineers, patents the first modern typewriter. It is sold in 1873 as the Remington Typewriter.
</Question>
<Choice>1868</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American inventor George Westinghouse patents the railroad air brake. Westinghouse later becomes the leading advocate of alternating current for power systems in the U.S.
</Question>
<Choice>1869</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
R.L. Maddox introduces dry-plate process in photography. Maddox's dry collodion process is more convenient than the wet collodion process invented in 1851.
</Question>
<Choice>1871</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English-born American photographer Eadweard Muybridge begins his photographic studies of human and animal motion.
</Question>
<Choice>1872</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Thomas Edison devises the quadruplex telegraph, which allows four messages to be sent over a single telegraph wire.
</Question>
<Choice>1874</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American inventor Alexander Graham Bell patents the telephone.
</Question>
<Choice>1876</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Thomas Edison patents the phonograph.</Question>
<Choice>1877</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Thomas Edison, rediscovering work done earlier by English inventor Joseph Swan, devises the carbon-filament electric lamp.
</Question>
<Choice>1879</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Cities in North and South America and Europe begin to establish electric railways and subways.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1880</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Thomas Edison and Joseph Swan both display practical incandescent light bulbs.
</Question>
<Choice>1880</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physician Étienne-Jules Marey develops a process for making motion pictures with a single camera.
</Question>
<Choice>1882</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chicago's new 10- and 12-story buildings attract the term "skyscraper," formerly used for large horses, tall hats, and fly balls in baseball.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1882</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Brooklyn Bridge, designed by John and Washington Roebling, opens after 14 years of construction. The bridge is hailed as one of the masterworks of 19th-century engineering.
</Question>
<Choice>1883</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English engineer Charles Algernon Parsons invents the steam turbine engine, passing steam through rotors to achieve high-speed rotary motion.
</Question>
<Choice>1884</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German designer Karl Benz produces the first automobile powered by an internal-combustion engine.
</Question>
<Choice>1885</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English scientist Francis Galton establishes that human fingerprints are unique and proposes the first system for classifying fingerprints.
</Question>
<Choice>1885</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Serbian-American engineer Nikola Tesla sells the patent rights to his alternating-current technology to George Westinghouse.
</Question>
<Choice>1885</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American photographer and inventor George Eastman introduces the Kodak, an easy-to-use camera that helps turn photography into a popular hobby.
</Question>
<Choice>1888</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The 984-foot (300-m), iron-framed Eiffel Tower (named in honour of its designer, bridge engineer Gustave Eiffel) is erected in Paris.
</Question>
<Choice>1889</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
William Stewart Halsted introduces the use of rubber gloves in surgery, at Johns Hopkins Hospital, Baltimore, Md.
</Question>
<Choice>1890</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Iowa blacksmith John Froehlich builds the first tractor.
</Question>
<Choice>1892</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Rudolf Diesel of Germany receives patent for an efficient heavy-oil engine. The Diesel engine is eventually used extensively in trucks and locomotives.
</Question>
<Choice>1892</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist Wilhelm Conrad Röntgen discovers X rays, short-wave rays that rapidly find applications in diagnostic medicine and the study of materials.
</Question>
<Choice>1895</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
King C. Gillette, American inventor and entrepreneur, develops the safety razor, replacing conventional straight razors.
</Question>
<Choice>1895</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian engineer Guglielmo Marconi files the first of his patents for a wireless radio system. Transatlantic transmission of a radio signal is achieved in 1901.
</Question>
<Choice>1896</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Argonaut, designed by Simon Lake, is the first submarine to operate extensively in open water.
</Question>
<Choice>1897</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Danish engineer Valdemar Poulsen invents the arc generator, a device for generating continuous radio waves. He receives a patent for the generator in 1903.
</Question>
<Choice>1901</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Photographs are transmitted by telegraph for the first time by German inventor Arthur Korn.
</Question>
<Choice>1902</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch physiologist Willem Einthoven invents the electrocardiograph to measure electrical impulses of the heart.
</Question>
<Choice>1903</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
After several years' experimentation and careful study of the work of predecessors, Orville and Wilbur Wright fly in a heavier-than-air vehicle at Kitty Hawk, N.C.
</Question>
<Choice>1903</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>J.P.L. Elster invents the photoelectric cell.</Question>
<Choice>1904</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English engineer John Fleming, the first professor of electrical engineering in Britain, invents the vacuum diode, a key radio technology.
</Question>
<Choice>1904</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American inventor Lee De Forest develops the audion, greatly facilitating transcontinental telephony and the development of radio.
</Question>
<Choice>1906</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Canadian-American engineer Reginald Fessenden broadcasts the first radio program featuring voice and music.
</Question>
<Choice>1906</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Simplon Tunnel, one of the world's longest railroad tunnels, opens, connecting Iselle, Italy, and Brig, Switzerland.
</Question>
<Choice>1906</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American entrepreneur and inventor Henry Ford begins production of the Model T, the first affordable automobile.
</Question>
<Choice>1908</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Belgian-born American engineer Leo Baekeland invents Bakelite, a promising forerunner of modern plastics.
</Question>
<Choice>1909</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American inventor Elmer Sperry founds the Sperry Gyroscope Company, a major producer of navigational and control systems.
</Question>
<Choice>1910</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American engineer Frederick Winslow Taylor publishes The Principles of Scientific Management. His methods of routinizing factory work help shape 20th-century industrial labour.
</Question>
<Choice>1911</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The British luxury liner Titanic sinks in the North Atlantic; about 1,515 drown.
</Question>
<Choice>1912</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Cellophane is first manufactured in a process developed by Edwin Pradenberger.
</Question>
<Choice>1912</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Henry Ford introduces the assembly line at his Dearborn, Mich., factory. Mass production is born.
</Question>
<Choice>1913</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The 60-story Woolworth Building, designed by architect Cass Gilbert, is completed in New York. It is the world's tallest building to date.
</Question>
<Choice>1913</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The 50-mile (80-km) Panama Canal opens after work began by the French in 1879.
</Question>
<Choice>1914</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
World War I introduces automatic weapons, trench warfare, and chemical weapons to warfare, marking the beginning of "total war" in the 20th century.
</Question>
<Choice>1914</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German scientists develop processes for the large-scale production of nitrogen for munitions, based on the research of chemists Fritz Haber and Carl Bosch.
</Question>
<Choice>1915</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ford Motor Company builds its one millionth automobile and expands production to include tractors, widely used in the United States and the Soviet Union.
</Question>
<Choice>1915</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John T. Thompson, retired American army officer, patents the Thompson submachine, or "Tommy," gun.
</Question>
<Choice>1920</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
First American radio station, KDKA, begins broadcasting from Pittsburgh, Pa. The station is owned by the Westinghouse Electric Corporation.
</Question>
<Choice>1920</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American engineer Lee De Forest unveils a working system of sound motion pictures.
</Question>
<Choice>1923</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian-born U.S. engineer Vladimir Zworykin patents the "iconoscope," an electronic picture tube that is a key technology for the first television.
</Question>
<Choice>1923</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first self-winding wristwatch is patented by English inventor John Harwood.
</Question>
<Choice>1924</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German pilot Hugo Eckener flies the zeppelin ZR-3 in the first Atlantic airship crossing. He flies the Graf Zeppelin around the world in 1929.
</Question>
<Choice>1924</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Bell Laboratories, a research branch of American Telephone and Telegraph (AT&T), opens. It will become one of the best-known scientific and engineering research laboratories of the 20th century.
</Question>
<Choice>1925</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German industrial chemist Carl Bosch adapts processes for the production of hydrogen to industrial scale.
</Question>
<Choice>1925</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Kodak begins to manufacture 16mm movie film, increasing the portability of movie cameras.
</Question>
<Choice>1926</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist Robert Goddard supervises flight of the first liquid-fuel rocket, in Auburn, Mass. He is later recognized as one of the founders of modern rocketry.
</Question>
<Choice>1926</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American aviator Charles Lindbergh flies a monoplane from New York to Paris nonstop in 33 1/2 hours, inspiring huge public interest in air travel.
</Question>
<Choice>1927</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicists H. Geiger and W. Müller invent the radiation-detecting Geiger counter. The device facilitates laboratory study--and later industrial use--of radioactive materials.
</Question>
<Choice>1927</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Alexander Fleming discovers penicillin. It revolutionizes the treatment of infectious diseases when produced in commercial quantities from 1941.
</Question>
<Choice>1928</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American businessman and inventor Clarence Birdseye begins selling frozen foods. His methods of quick freezing transform American food consumption.
</Question>
<Choice>1929</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American pilot Jimmy Doolittle completes flight using only instruments.
</Question>
<Choice>1929</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Soviet government begins construction on the steel-producing city of Magnitogorsk, in the southern Urals.
</Question>
<Choice>1929</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
DuPont Company chemist Wallace H. Carothers directs research that results in the discovery, in 1931, of neoprene, the first wholly synthetic fiber.
</Question>
<Choice>1930</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Electric refrigerators begin to replace iceboxes in American kitchens.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1930</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Empire State Building is erected in New York City. At a height of 1,250 feet (381 m), it remains the tallest structure in the world until 1954.
</Question>
<Choice>1931</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Aldous Huxley publishes Brave New World, a dystopian novel set in the 25th century that foreshadows the development of in vitro fertilization and cloning.
</Question>
<Choice>1932</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American aviator Amelia Earhart becomes the first woman to fly alone across the Atlantic.
</Question>
<Choice>1932</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Massachusetts Institute of Technology engineer Vannevar Bush and students construct the differential analyzer, a powerful analog computer.
</Question>
<Choice>1933</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American intellectual Lewis Mumford publishes Technics and Civilization, drawing scholarly and popular attention to the role of technology in world civilization.
</Question>
<Choice>1934</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Robert Watson-Watt designs first radar (radio detection and ranging) equipment, which detects distant objects through the reflection of radio waves.
</Question>
<Choice>1935</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Boulder Dam, harnessing the Colorado River for electricity production, is completed after six years' work. It is renamed the Hoover Dam in 1947.
</Question>
<Choice>1936</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
DuPont begins production of nylon, developed in 1934 by DuPont chemist Wallace H. Carothers.
</Question>
<Choice>1938</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
World War II brings expanded military development and use of airplanes, generally metal-framed and powered with gas turbines.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1939</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Vannevar Bush becomes first head of the American National Defense Research Committee (NDRC), which directs wartime research in radar, medicine, and atomic weapons.
</Question>
<Choice>1940</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American research on nuclear fission is organized into the Manhattan Project. The project develops and builds the atomic bombs dropped on Hiroshima and Nagasaki in 1945.
</Question>
<Choice>1942</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first jet-powered aircraft are developed in the United States, Britain, and Germany, leading to adoption of jet power in aircraft of many types in succeeding decades.
</Question>
<Choice>1944</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The V-2 rocket, designed by German aeronautical engineer Werner von Braun, enters service, attacking cities in England. Von Braun and his group defect to the United States in 1945.
</Question>
<Choice>1944</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scientists at the University of Pennsylvania complete ENIAC, a room-sized computer consisting of 18,000 high-speed vacuum tubes.
</Question>
<Choice>1946</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Bell Telephone Laboratories physicists invent the transistor. The electronic device is rapidly incorporated into many industrial inventions, including the computer.
</Question>
<Choice>1947</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
MIT mathematician Norbert Wiener publishes Cybernetics, a pioneering study of control and communications systems that draws on his research in fire control and neurology.
</Question>
<Choice>1948</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American researchers led by Hungarian-born physicist Edward Teller detonate the first hydrogen bomb.
</Question>
<Choice>1952</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Transatlantic telephone service begins.</Question>
<Choice>1956</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The U.S. government invests billions of dollars in construction of the interstate highway system, one of history's largest public works and engineering projects.
</Question>
<Choice>1956</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The U.S.S.R. launches the first artificial satellite, Sputnik I, inaugurating a space race between the Soviet Union and the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1957</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA) is established by the U.S. government, indicating the nation's commitment to participating fully in the space race with the Soviet Union.
</Question>
<Choice>1958</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Computers, previously used almost exclusively on government projects, begin to find applications in oil refining, electricity generation, and other production venues.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1959</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Soviet cosmonaut Yury Gagarin orbits the Earth in the first manned spaceflight. The first manned flight by an American (Alan Shepard) is staged the same year.
</Question>
<Choice>1961</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American naturalist Rachel Carson publishes Silent Spring, alerting the public to the environmental risks of industrial pollutants and pesticides.
</Question>
<Choice>1962</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Telstar, the first communications satellite, is put into orbit for use by American companies.
</Question>
<Choice>1962</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American engineer Stephanie Kwolek discovers a polyamide solvent that leads to the production of Kevlar, the primary material of bulletproof vests.
</Question>
<Choice>1966</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronaut Neil Armstrong, commander of the Apollo 11 mission, becomes the first man to walk on the Moon.
</Question>
<Choice>1969</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The U.S. establishes the Environmental Protection Agency (EPA) to monitor and regulate pollution.
</Question>
<Choice>1970</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Intel Corporation introduces the first microprocessor, which combines on a single chip functions once performed by thousands of transistors.
</Question>
<Choice>1971</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Vikings 1 and 2 land on Mars. The unmanned American spacecraft transmit information about the Martian atmosphere and soil and conduct experiments to search for life on the planet.
</Question>
<Choice>1976</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Steven Jobs and Steve Wozniak found Apple Computer Inc., the first company devoted to selling personal computers. The Apple II goes on sale in 1977.
</Question>
<Choice>1976</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English researchers Patrick Steptoe and Robert Edwards develop techniques for human in vitro fertilization, resulting in the birth of the first "test-tube" baby in 1978.
</Question>
<Choice>1976</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The U.S. Supreme Court agrees that an oil-eating bacterium, developed through genetic engineering, can be patented. Seven years later the court extends patentability to mammals.
</Question>
<Choice>1980</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The space shuttle, the first reusable space vehicle, begins operation.
</Question>
<Choice>1981</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
DNA fingerprinting, based on scientific analysis of individuals' genetic makeup, is developed by British geneticist Alec Jeffreys.
</Question>
<Choice>1984</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Explosions at the nuclear power plant at Chernobyl, Ukraine, bring about the worst nuclear reactor accident in history.
</Question>
<Choice>1986</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
United States space shuttle Challenger explodes after liftoff, killing its crew of seven astronauts.
</Question>
<Choice>1986</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Hubble Space Telescope is launched; mechanical flaws in its primary optical system are soon discovered.
</Question>
<Choice>1990</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Continued globalization of the automobile industry leads to opening of Japanese manufacturing plants in the U.K. and the United States and restructuring among European firms.
</Question>
<Choice>1992</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese authorities announce plans for the construction of Three Gorges Dam, the largest hydroelectric project in history.
</Question>
<Choice>1993</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A successful mission to repair the Hubble Space Telescope is the highlight of the year in space exploration.
</Question>
<Choice>1993</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Work begins on the Petronas Towers in Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia. At 450 m, they are among the world's tallest buildings, officially beating Chicago's Sears Tower (443 m).
</Question>
<Choice>1994</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Microsoft Corporation unveils Windows 95, a graphical operating system that succeeds its popular Windows 3.1.
</Question>
<Choice>1995</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Internet and World Wide Web grow steeply in both size and popularity, helping to bring the concept of "cyberspace" closer to reality.
</Question>
<Choice>1995</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The chess-playing computer Deep Blue raises new questions about artificial intelligence after defeating Garry Kasparov, the game's best human player.
</Question>
<Choice>1996</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Digital video (or versatile) disc (DVD) is introduced to U.S. consumers as a viewing alternative to VCRs.
</Question>
<Choice>1997</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first U.S. television station begins broadcasting in digital high-definition television (HDTV). Enabling sharper and brighter pictures, HDTV is scheduled to replace nondigital signals.
</Question>
<Choice>1998</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A study estimates that online Internet sales will reach $12 billion for the year.
</Question>
<Choice>1999</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On May 1 the world's longest cable-stayed bridge, the Tatara Ohashi, opens, connecting Honshu and Shikoku in Japan.
</Question>
<Choice>1999</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A U.S. House committee releases a report alleging that the People's Republic of China stole classified information about strategic nuclear weapon systems from U.S. facilities over a 20-year period.
</Question>
<Choice>1999</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Dow Jones industrial average stock index tops the 10,000 mark, partially on the strength of internet stocks.
</Question>
<Choice>1999</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first expeditionary crew is scheduled to take up residence on the International Space Station.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American computer scientist Raymond Kurzweil wins the National Medal of Technology. Noted for his predictions about technology's future, he believes the distinction between man and machine is fading.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The fall of technology stocks in the U.S. sends shockwaves through dot-com companies.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An e-mail virus, known as the Love Bug, sweeps through much of the world, causing many businesses to shut down their e-mail systems.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Southern Cross II, a U.S. Global Hawk spy plane, becomes the first unmanned aircraft to fly across the Pacific Ocean.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Leaning Tower of Pisa opens for the first time since 1990 after engineers reduce its tilt.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
With more than one billion worldwide, cell phones are at the forefront of a wireless revolution. No longer just used for making calls, the new mobile phones can take photographs and record home movies.
</Question>
<Choice>2002</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spam (unsolicited e-mail) is a growing problem; some experts predict it will soon overtake the volume of legitimate e-mail.
</Question>
<Choice>2003</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British computer scientist Tim Berners-Lee, considered the inventor of the World Wide Web, is knighted.
</Question>
<Choice>2004</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nanotechnology, which enables the manufacture of materials and devices at an extremely small scale, moves to the forefront as researchers look to develop new products with the technology, including implants that will identify cancer cells in the human body.
</Question>
<Choice>2004</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Apple unveils its newest iPod, a version that also plays video. Introduced in 2001, the pocket-sized portable music player has become a phenomenon, with more than 42 million sold.
</Question>
<Choice>2005</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Faced with competition from the telephone, fax, and e-mail, Western Union ends its telegram operations; the company began sending telegrams in the 1850s.
</Question>
<Choice>2006</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The online search engine Google acquires YouTube--a popular Web site where users can post, watch, and comment on personal and commercial videos--for $1.65 billion in stock.
</Question>
<Choice>2006</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Microsoft introduces its new operating system, Vista, the successor to Windows.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Researchers announce that they have used silicon nanowires to create a rechargeable battery that generates 10 times the electricity of existing lithium-ion batteries.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Apple introduces its second version of the iPhone, a multipurpose handheld device combining mobile telephone, digital camera, music player, and personal computing technologies. The latest model was updated to use third-generation (3G) wireless technology.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Toshiba demonstrates a computer interface that uses an infrared sensor to respond to users' hand gestures.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Tata Motors of India begins delivery of the world's cheapest automobile, the Tato Nano; the least-expensive model is priced at about $2,500.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Iranians protesting their country's disputed election use the social networking Web site Twitter to organize protests and distribute information following a crackdown on news agencies within Iran.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Apple iPad, a touch-screen tablet computer, is unveiled; it can run all applications that are available for the iPhone as well as its own e-book application, iBooks.
</Question>
<Choice>2010</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
To assist earthquake-ravaged Haiti, cell-phone users donate millions of dollars through text messages; the Red Cross alone receives more than $20 million, which it declares "an unprecedented amount for a text campaign."
</Question>
<Choice>2010</Choice>
</item>
</topics>