<topics>
<item>
<Question>The solar system is formed.</Question>
<Choice>about 4,600,000,000,000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dinosaurs appear on Earth. They survived for about 160 million years.
</Question>
<Choice>about 225,000,000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mesopotamia, one of the world's first civilizations, develops in what is now Iraq.
</Question>
<Choice>about 5000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Construction of a structure known as Stonehenge begins in what is now southeastern England.
</Question>
<Choice>about 3100 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The island of Crete is home to one of the earliest Greek civilizations.
</Question>
<Choice>about 3000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>The first calendar is developed.</Question>
<Choice>about 3000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Construction begins on the pyramids in ancient Egypt. They were built to protect the tombs of important rulers.
</Question>
<Choice>about 2550 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Middle Kingdom in Egypt begins. The kingdom lasted from 2050 to 1800 BC.
</Question>
<Choice>2050 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>The first Chinese dynasty, the Shang, takes power.</Question>
<Choice>1766 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Rise of the Hittite empire in the Middle East. The Hittites were warriors, and probably the first people to use iron.
</Question>
<Choice>about 1600 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Mycenaean civilization develops in ancient Greece.</Question>
<Choice>1600 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>The Maya settle in Central America and Mexico.</Question>
<Choice>about 1500 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Zhou Dynasty takes power in China. They ruled for nearly 900 years.
</Question>
<Choice>1122 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Dorians gain control over Greece. They greatly influenced architecture.
</Question>
<Choice>1100 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
King Solomon builds the first Jewish Temple in Jerusalem. It was destroyed by the Babylonians in 586 BC.
</Question>
<Choice>950 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The ancient city of Carthage is founded by the Phoenicians on the north coast of Africa.
</Question>
<Choice>814 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first recorded event of the Olympic Games takes place in Olympia, Greece.
</Question>
<Choice>776 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Birth of Confucius. His philosophy and teachings greatly influenced the people of China and east Asian civilization.
</Question>
<Choice>551 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Construction of the second Temple of Jerusalem is finished.
</Question>
<Choice>515 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>The Roman Republic is formed.</Question>
<Choice>509 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Etruscans create one of the first cities to be laid out in a grid plan.
</Question>
<Choice>about 500 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The abacus is invented, most likely by ancient Sumerians in Mesopotamia.
</Question>
<Choice>about 500 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Construction begins on the Parthenon in Athens, Greece.
</Question>
<Choice>447 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Peloponnesian War between Athens and Sparta begins. The war ended in 404 BC. It was one of the major conflicts of ancient Greece.
</Question>
<Choice>431 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Birth of Alexander the Great.</Question>
<Choice>356 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first dynasty to unify China and create an empire, the Qin, takes power. It lasts until 206 BC.
</Question>
<Choice>221 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Work begins to connect the separate walls of the Great Wall of China into a single structure.
</Question>
<Choice>214 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Rise of the Han Dynasty in China. They established the importance of culture and the arts.
</Question>
<Choice>206 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Cleopatra becomes queen of Egypt. She rules until her death in 30 BC.
</Question>
<Choice>51 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Roman ruler Julius Caesar is assassinated.</Question>
<Choice>44 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Augustus becomes the first emperor of Rome.</Question>
<Choice>27 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Jesus Christ is born in Bethlehem.</Question>
<Choice>about 6 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Construction begins on the Colosseum in Rome, Italy.
</Question>
<Choice>70</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mount Vesuvius erupts and destroys the towns of Pompeii and Herculaneum near what is now Naples, Italy.
</Question>
<Choice>79</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Greek astronomer Ptolemy publishes The Almagest, which catalogs the existence of more than 1,022 stars.
</Question>
<Choice>about 150</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Goths begin to conquer parts of the Roman Empire.
</Question>
<Choice>about 200</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Gupta Dynasty takes control of the northern half of India. They are removed in 540.
</Question>
<Choice>320</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The city of Constantinople, now Istanbul, is founded by Constantine the Great.
</Question>
<Choice>330</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Huns invade Europe. A later leader, Attila, assumes full power in 445.
</Question>
<Choice>370</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Roman Empire is divided, and the eastern part becomes known as the Byzantine Empire.
</Question>
<Choice>395</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Christianity spreads to Ireland.</Question>
<Choice>about 450</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Fall of the Roman Empire in the West. Rome is captured by a group of invaders called the Visigoths.
</Question>
<Choice>476</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Middle Ages begins in Europe. The Middle Ages lasted until about 1500.
</Question>
<Choice>about 500</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Muhammad receives the first of a series of messages and visions. These were eventually compiled into the Koran, the holy book of Islam.
</Question>
<Choice>610</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The religion of Islam is founded by Muhammad in what is now Saudi Arabia.
</Question>
<Choice>622</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Construction begins on the Muslim shrine known as the Dome of the Rock in Jerusalem. It was completed in 691.
</Question>
<Choice>685</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Charlemagne is crowned emperor of Western Europe by Pope Leo III. The coronation was the foundation of the Holy Roman Empire.
</Question>
<Choice>800</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Vikings engage in the first of many fierce raids on England.
</Question>
<Choice>865</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
England's King Alfred the Great begins his reign. He ruled until his death in 899.
</Question>
<Choice>871</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first permanent settlers of Iceland arrive from Norway.
</Question>
<Choice>874</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Song Dynasty takes power in China. It is later overthrown by the Mongols in 1279.
</Question>
<Choice>960</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>The city of Al Qahirah, or Cairo, is founded.</Question>
<Choice>969</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
William, duke of Normandy, invades England in what is known as the Norman Conquest. He defeats England's king, Harold, at Hastings. William is later crowned king in Westminster Abbey on Christmas Day.
</Question>
<Choice>1066</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Work begins on Angkor Wat in what is now Cambodia. This temple complex is the world's largest religious structure.
</Question>
<Choice>about 1113</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first of Japan's shoguns, or military leaders, takes power. The shoguns dominated the Japanese government until 1867.
</Question>
<Choice>1192</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Genghis Khan rises to power and rules the Mongol Empire. The Mongols begin to conquer parts of China, Russia, and the Middle East.
</Question>
<Choice>1206</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Magna Carta, or the Great Charter, is signed by King John of England.
</Question>
<Choice>1215</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Inquisition, a court of the Roman Catholic church, is established. The church used the Inquisition to deal with people accused of heresy, or revolting against religious authority.
</Question>
<Choice>1231</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Venetian adventurer Marco Polo embarks on his expedition to China.
</Question>
<Choice>1271</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Aztec establish the city of Tenochtitlan in what is now Mexico. The Spanish conquest of Tenochtitlan in 1521 marks the fall of the Aztec Empire.
</Question>
<Choice>about 1325</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Hundred Years' War between England and France begins. It was the longest war in recorded history.
</Question>
<Choice>about 1337</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Black Death, also called the bubonic plague, spreads throughout Europe. The disease killed more than one third of the population.
</Question>
<Choice>about 1347</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Beginning of the Renaissance. This rebirth of Western culture and the arts flourishes throughout Europe through the 1500s.
</Question>
<Choice>about 1350</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Joan of Arc leads French forces to victory over an English army at the battle of Orleans.
</Question>
<Choice>1429</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ottoman Turks led by Muhammad II capture the city of Constantinople and destroy the Byzantine Empire. The city, renamed Istanbul, becomes the capital of the Ottoman Empire.
</Question>
<Choice>1453</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Birth of Michelangelo. His statue of David, completed in 1504, and his paintings on the ceiling of the Sistine Chapel in Rome (now in Vatican City) are considered some of the greatest works of art ever created.
</Question>
<Choice>1475</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Spanish Inquisition begins under Pope Sixtus IV. It finally ended in 1834.
</Question>
<Choice>1478</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The marriage of Ferdinand and Isabella creates a unified Spain.
</Question>
<Choice>1479</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ivan III, also known as Ivan the Great, frees Russia from Mongol rule.
</Question>
<Choice>1480</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Christopher Columbus sets sail from Spain on an expedition to discover a western sea route to Asia. He is considered the first European to visit and explore the Americas.
</Question>
<Choice>1492</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Portuguese navigator Vasco da Gama leads the first of three sea voyages to India. He was the first explorer to round the southern tip of Africa, at the Cape of Good Hope.
</Question>
<Choice>1497</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The African slave trade begins. The Portuguese first introduce African slaves into Europe.
</Question>
<Choice>about 1500</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Leonardo da Vinci begins painting the Mona Lisa. It is one of his most famous works of art.
</Question>
<Choice>about 1503</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish explorer Vasco Nunez de Balboa is the first European to reach the Pacific Ocean.
</Question>
<Choice>1513</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In his search for the legendary Fountain of Youth, the Spanish explorer Juan Ponce de Leon lands on the shores of what is now Florida.
</Question>
<Choice>1513</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Martin Luther begins the Protestant Reformation in Germany. His influence on religious thought reshaped all of Europe.
</Question>
<Choice>1517</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ferdinand Magellan begins the voyage that makes him famous. He is the first European to sail across the Pacific Ocean and to discover a route by which ships could sail a complete circle around the world.
</Question>
<Choice>1519</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hernan Cortes leads Spanish forces to conquer the Aztec Empire.
</Question>
<Choice>1521</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish explorer Francisco Pizarro overthrows the Inca Empire of Peru.
</Question>
<Choice>1532</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ivan IV, also known as Ivan the Terrible, inherits the throne of Russia. He rules until his death in 1584.
</Question>
<Choice>1533</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish explorer Francisco Coronado leads a large expedition into what is now the southwestern United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1540</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish explorer Hernando de Soto discovers the Mississippi River.
</Question>
<Choice>1541</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polish astronomer Nicolaus Copernicus changes the way people view the solar system when he proposes that all the planets revolve around the sun. His theory led to a scientific approach to astronomy.
</Question>
<Choice>1543</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Akbar, the greatest ruler of the Mughal Empire, assumes the throne in India.
</Question>
<Choice>1556</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
England defeats the Spanish Armada in one of the most significant battles at sea. It was the first time ships were armed with guns.
</Question>
<Choice>1588</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sir Frances Drake becomes the first Englishman to successfully sail around the world.
</Question>
<Choice>1580</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An elaborate style of art known as baroque begins to flourish throughout Europe.
</Question>
<Choice>about 1600</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jamestown, the first permanent English settlement in North America, is founded.
</Question>
<Choice>1607</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French explorer Samuel de Champlain founds the city of Quebec. The city becomes France's first permanent Canadian colony.
</Question>
<Choice>1608</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian astronomer and physicist Galileo Galilei greatly improves the design of the telescope. His work allows him to make many discoveries about the solar system.
</Question>
<Choice>1609</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English poet and playwright William Shakespeare dies in his hometown of Stratford-upon-Avon.
</Question>
<Choice>1616</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Mayflower arrives in North America. A group of Puritan Separatists, or Pilgrims, establish the first permanent European settlement in New England at Plymouth Colony, in what is now Massachusetts.
</Question>
<Choice>1620</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch colonists purchase Manhattan Island from the Algonquian Indians with goods said to value 24 dollars.
</Question>
<Choice>1626</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British minister Roger Williams and his followers found the settlement of Providence in Rhode Island.
</Question>
<Choice>1636</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Harvard College is founded in New Towne (now Cambridge), Massachusetts. It is the oldest university in the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1636</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Louis XIV becomes king of France.</Question>
<Choice>1643</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The last of the Chinese dynasties, the Qing, takes power. They ruled for more than 250 years.
</Question>
<Choice>1644</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch settlers establish a permanent European colony at Table Bay (now Cape Town) near the southern tip of Africa.
</Question>
<Choice>1652</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Great Fire of London destroys most of the city.
</Question>
<Choice>1666</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Father Jacques Marquette and Louis Jolliet, a trader, explore and chart the course of the Mississippi River.
</Question>
<Choice>1673</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English Quaker William Penn founds the colony of Pennsylvania.
</Question>
<Choice>1681</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French explorer Sieur de La Salle claims the Mississippi River valley for France.
</Question>
<Choice>1682</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physicist and mathematician Isaac Newton publishes his theory of gravity and the laws of motion.
</Question>
<Choice>1687</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Salem witch trials take place as fear of the practice of witchcraft spreads throughout the Massachusetts Bay Colony.
</Question>
<Choice>1692</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An early English-language version of Aesop's fables are published by Roger L'Estrange.
</Question>
<Choice>1692</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Peter I, or Peter the Great, founds the Russian Empire.
</Question>
<Choice>1721</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first edition of Benjamin Franklin's Poor Richard's Almanac is published.
</Question>
<Choice>1732</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Industrial Revolution begins. The revolution promotes the growth of cities, the factory system, and many other changes to everyday life in Europe.
</Question>
<Choice>about 1750</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Cumberland Gap is discovered by Thomas Walker. Many American settlers move west through the mountain pass in the following years.
</Question>
<Choice>1750</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German composer Johann Sebastian Bach dies in Leipzig, Germany.
</Question>
<Choice>1750</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The French and Indian War begins. The war, fought in North America, ended in 1763.
</Question>
<Choice>1754</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian composer Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart is born. He is considered one of the greatest musical geniuses of all time.
</Question>
<Choice>1756</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first edition of Mother Goose rhymes is published by John Newbery in London, England.
</Question>
<Choice>about 1760</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Catherine II, or Catherine the Great, becomes empress of Russia. She ruled until 1796.
</Question>
<Choice>1762</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English explorer James Cook begins the first of three voyages to the South Pacific. He was the first European to cross the Antarctic Circle.
</Question>
<Choice>1768</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Thomas Jefferson begins work on Monticello, his estate in Virginia.
</Question>
<Choice>1768</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish priest Junipero Serra founds the first California mission at the Spanish settlement of San Diego.
</Question>
<Choice>1769</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British troops fire into a crowd of unarmed colonists, killing ex-slave Crispus Attucks. He is the first casualty in the cause of American independence from British rule. The attack is known as the Boston Massacre.
</Question>
<Choice>1770</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In an incident later known as the Boston Tea Party, American patriots dump shiploads of tea into the Boston Harbor to protest British treatment of American colonists.
</Question>
<Choice>1773</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The First Continental Congress meets in Philadelphia. It was the first successful effort of the colonists working together.
</Question>
<Choice>1774</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Paul Revere rides through the countryside near Boston, Massachusetts, warning the colonists that the British troops are approaching to invade the area.
</Question>
<Choice>1775</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The American Revolution begins. The war for the 13 colonies' independence from the British Empire begins in Massachusetts with the battle of Lexington and Concord.
</Question>
<Choice>1775</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Green Mountain Boys, under the leadership of Ethan Allen, defeat the British at Fort Ticonderoga, in what is now New York. This was an important early victory in the American Revolution.
</Question>
<Choice>1775</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American frontiersman Daniel Boone blazes a trail through the Cumberland Gap to the Kentucky River.
</Question>
<Choice>1775</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Thomas Paine publishes the pamphlet Common Sense. It argues for the independence of America's 13 colonies from Britain and for the establishment of a free republic.
</Question>
<Choice>1776</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>The Declaration of Independence is adopted.</Question>
<Choice>1776</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Articles of Confederation, the first constitution of the United States, are passed by the Second Continental Congress.
</Question>
<Choice>1777</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The planet Uranus is discovered by astronomer William Herschel. It is the first planet discovered since the invention of the telescope.
</Question>
<Choice>1781</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The United States Constitution is drafted in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. It is adopted one year later.
</Question>
<Choice>1787</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first settlement in Australia is established in New South Wales. The majority of the early colonists were convicted criminals sent over from Britain.
</Question>
<Choice>1788</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The storming of the Bastille, a famous Paris prison, marks the beginning of the French Revolution.
</Question>
<Choice>1789</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
George Washington becomes the first president of the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1789</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Supreme Court of the United States is established.
</Question>
<Choice>1789</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Bill of Rights is added to the United States Constitution.
</Question>
<Choice>1791</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French queen Marie Antoinette is found guilty of treason and beheaded. She was a symbol of the people's hatred for the old regime during the French Revolution.
</Question>
<Choice>1793</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>U.S. inventor Eli Whitney invents the cotton gin.</Question>
<Choice>1793</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John Adams is elected the second president of the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1796</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Thomas Jefferson is elected the third president of the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1800</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland is formed.
</Question>
<Choice>1801</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The United States purchases the Louisiana Territory from France.
</Question>
<Choice>1803</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
President Thomas Jefferson sends Captain Meriwether Lewis and Lieutenant William Clark on the first U.S. overland expedition from St. Louis, Missouri, to the Pacific Ocean.
</Question>
<Choice>1804</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Haiti becomes an independent country and is no longer under French rule.
</Question>
<Choice>1804</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts is founded in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania. It was the first art school established in the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1805</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first steamboat makes a trial run from New York City to Albany, New York. The steamboat was invented by Robert Fulton.
</Question>
<Choice>1807</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
James Madison is elected the fourth president of the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1808</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mexico revolts against Spanish rule. Spain later grants Mexico its independence in 1821.
</Question>
<Choice>1810</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The War of 1812 begins between the United States and England.
</Question>
<Choice>1812</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Grimm brothers publish their collection of fairy tales based on traditional folk tales.
</Question>
<Choice>1812</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
James Monroe is elected the fifth president of the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1816</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Simon Bolivar helps Colombia win independence from Spain. He is named president and military leader of the new South American country.
</Question>
<Choice>1819</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The U.S. Congress passes the Missouri Compromise. It marked the beginning of the conflict over slavery between the North and the South that ultimately led to the American Civil War.
</Question>
<Choice>1820</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French scholar Jean-Francois Champollion discovers the meaning of the ancient scripts on the Rosetta Stone.
</Question>
<Choice>1822</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German composer Ludwig van Beethoven completes work on one of his greatest compositions, the Ninth Symphony.
</Question>
<Choice>1824</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John Quincy Adams is elected the sixth president of the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1825</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>The Erie Canal opens in upstate New York.</Question>
<Choice>1825</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Andrew Jackson is elected the seventh president of the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1828</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greece declares its independence from the Ottoman Turks.
</Question>
<Choice>1829</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Joseph Smith founds Mormonism, or the Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, in New York.
</Question>
<Choice>1830</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. farmer and inventor Cyrus McCormick invents the mechanical reaper.
</Question>
<Choice>1831</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In a conflict now known as the Black Hawk War, Native American chief Black Hawk leads a revolt against the United States Army to defend his Illinois homeland.
</Question>
<Choice>1832</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The American Anti-Slavery Society is founded by William Lloyd Garrison.
</Question>
<Choice>1833</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch author Hans Christian Andersen publishes the first volume of his stories for children.
</Question>
<Choice>1835</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Martin Van Buren is elected the eighth president of the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1836</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Texas wins its independence from Mexico. The battle at the Alamo was one of the most significant events in its war for independence.
</Question>
<Choice>1836</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
William Henry Harrison is elected the ninth president of the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1840</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John Tyler becomes the tenth president of the United States. He is the first vice president to replace a president who has died in office.
</Question>
<Choice>1841</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The New York Philharmonic Orchestra, the oldest concert orchestra in continuous existence in the United States, is founded.
</Question>
<Choice>1842</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
James K. Polk is elected the 11th president of the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1844</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. author Edgar Allan Poe writes his most famous poem, The Raven.
</Question>
<Choice>1845</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>The great potato famine begins in Ireland.</Question>
<Choice>1845</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. civil rights leader Frederick Douglass publishes his autobiography, The Narrative of the Life of Frederick Douglass, an American Slave.
</Question>
<Choice>1845</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German astronomer Johann Gottfried Galle officially discovers the planet Neptune.
</Question>
<Choice>1846</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The African country of Liberia proclaims itself a republic. It was founded by freed U.S. slaves in the 1820s.
</Question>
<Choice>1847</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A group of Mormons establishes the first settlement in the Great Salt Lake region of Utah.
</Question>
<Choice>1847</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Mexican War ends with the signing of the Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo. Mexico gives up ownership of most of the southwestern territories of the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1848</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German missionaries Johannes Rebmann and Johann Ludwig Krapf become the first Europeans to see the African mountain Kilimanjaro.
</Question>
<Choice>1848</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. reformers Lucretia Mott and Elizabeth Cady Stanton lead the first women's rights convention in Seneca Falls, New York.
</Question>
<Choice>1848</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Karl Marx and Friedrich Engels publish The Communist Manifesto.
</Question>
<Choice>1848</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Zachary Taylor is elected the 12th president of the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1848</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first great gold rush in North America begins in northern California.
</Question>
<Choice>1849</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Harriet Tubman escapes from slavery in Maryland. Her involvement in the Underground Railroad leads many other slaves to freedom.
</Question>
<Choice>1849</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Vice President Millard Fillmore becomes the 13th president of the United States after the sudden death of President Taylor.
</Question>
<Choice>1850</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Uncle Tom's Cabin, a novel by Harriet Beecher Stowe about the cruelty of slavery in America, is published.
</Question>
<Choice>1852</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Franklin Pierce is elected the 14th president of the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1852</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Kansas-Nebraska Act is passed by the U.S. Congress. This made slavery possible again in states where it had been previously outlawed since the Missouri Compromise of 1820.
</Question>
<Choice>1854</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
James Buchanan is elected the 15th president of the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1856</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John Brown and other abolitionists raid a federal arms warehouse at Harpers Ferry, Virginia. They hoped to use the weapons to help the antislavery movement in the United States, but the raid was unsuccessful.
</Question>
<Choice>1859</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Construction begins on the Suez Canal in Egypt.</Question>
<Choice>1859</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English scientist and naturalist Charles Darwin publishes his theories on evolution in the book On the Origin of Species by Means of Natural Selection.
</Question>
<Choice>1859</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Abraham Lincoln is elected the 16th president of the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1860</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
South Carolina withdraws from the United States. Within a year, many other southern states follow, and the Confederate States of America, or Confederacy, is formed.
</Question>
<Choice>1860</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Pony Express, a system of delivering mail on horseback across the country, begins. It is in operation for barely two years.
</Question>
<Choice>1860</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jefferson Davis becomes president of the Confederate States of America.
</Question>
<Choice>1861</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The American Civil War begins. The war ends four years later with the surrender of the southern troops.
</Question>
<Choice>1861</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. President Abraham Lincoln issues the Emancipation Proclamation.
</Question>
<Choice>1863</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The 13th Amendment is added to the U.S. Constitution. The amendment abolishes slavery throughout the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1865</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. President Abraham Lincoln is assassinated by John Wilkes Booth in Ford's Theatre in Washington, D.C.
</Question>
<Choice>1865</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Andrew Johnson becomes the 17th president of the United States after the assassination of Abraham Lincoln.
</Question>
<Choice>1865</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British writer Lewis Carroll publishes Alice's Adventures in Wonderland.
</Question>
<Choice>1865</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>The United States purchases Alaska from Russia.</Question>
<Choice>1867</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The British North America Act is passed, uniting all the provinces of Canada. This act served as Canada's constitution for more than 100 years.
</Question>
<Choice>1867</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The 250-year-old Tokugawa shogunate is overthrown in Japan. A new government is established, and Japan opens its border to international trade.
</Question>
<Choice>1868</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The 14th Amendment, which grants blacks the right to citizenship, is added to the U.S. Constitution.
</Question>
<Choice>1868</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ulysses S. Grant is elected the 18th president of the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1868</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Susan B. Anthony and Elizabeth Cady Stanton found the National Woman Suffrage Association (NWSA).
</Question>
<Choice>1869</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>The Franco-Prussian War begins.</Question>
<Choice>1870</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italy is unified into a single republic. It had been divided into many individual states after the fall of the Roman Empire.
</Question>
<Choice>1870</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The 15th Amendment, granting blacks the right to vote, is added to the U.S. Constitution.
</Question>
<Choice>1870</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A great fire erupts in Chicago, Illinois, and destroys nearly one third of the city.
</Question>
<Choice>1871</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first Kentucky Derby horse race takes place at Churchill Downs in Louisville, Kentucky.
</Question>
<Choice>1875</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Englishman Matthew Webb becomes the first person to swim the English Channel from Dover, England, to Calais, France.
</Question>
<Choice>1875</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. inventor Alexander Graham Bell receives a patent for the telephone.
</Question>
<Choice>1876</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Porfirio Diaz becomes dictator of Mexico. He remained in power until he was forced into exile in 1911.
</Question>
<Choice>1876</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Rutherford B. Hayes is elected the 19th president of the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1876</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the famous battle of the Little Bighorn, Sioux Indians Crazy Horse and Sitting Bull lead members of their tribe to successfully defend their land against U.S. Lieutenant Colonel George A. Custer and his troops.
</Question>
<Choice>1876</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Thomas Alva Edison invents the phonograph. He is considered one of the greatest inventors of all time.
</Question>
<Choice>1877</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first major ski-jumping event takes place at Kristiania (now Oslo), Norway.
</Question>
<Choice>1879</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
James A. Garfield is elected the 20th president of the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1880</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Vice President Chester A. Arthur becomes the 21st president of the United States after the assassination of President Garfield.
</Question>
<Choice>1881</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. folk hero William Frederick Cody, or Buffalo Bill, starts his famous Wild West outdoor exhibition. It is later known as Buffalo Bill's Wild West and Congress of Rough Riders of the World.
</Question>
<Choice>1883</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Grover Cleveland is elected the 22nd president of the United States. He was re-elected again in 1894, making him the 24th president as well.
</Question>
<Choice>1884</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. writer Mark Twain publishes The Adventures of Huckleberry Finn.
</Question>
<Choice>1884</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Indian National Congress is formed. India gains full independence from Britain in 1947.
</Question>
<Choice>1885</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Gold is discovered in the Transvaal area of South Africa near what is now Johannesburg.
</Question>
<Choice>1886</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Statue of Liberty is erected in New York Harbor.
</Question>
<Choice>1886</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Benjamin Harrison is elected the 23rd president of the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1888</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Brazil gains its independence from Portugal and becomes a republic.
</Question>
<Choice>1889</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The game of basketball is invented by James A. Naismith in the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>about 1890</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
New Zealand is the first nation to grant women the right to vote.
</Question>
<Choice>1893</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. architect Frank Lloyd Wright opens his own architectural office.
</Question>
<Choice>1893</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist Wilhelm Roentgen discovers X rays. He is later awarded the Nobel prize for physics for his work.
</Question>
<Choice>1895</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Henry Ford introduces the first automobile to the American public. He is later credited with developing the assembly line method for the mass production of vehicles.
</Question>
<Choice>1896</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
William McKinley is elected the 25th president of the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1896</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first of the modern Summer Olympic Games takes place in Athens, Greece.
</Question>
<Choice>1896</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. scientist George Washington Carver heads the new department of agriculture at the Tuskegee Normal and Industrial Institute in Alabama. His work greatly improved the farming practices of the South during the early 1900s.
</Question>
<Choice>1896</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hawaii is officially annexed by the United States. It does not become a state until 1959.
</Question>
<Choice>1898</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The U.S. battleship Maine explodes in the harbor in Havana, Cuba. This incident triggers the start of the Spanish-American War.
</Question>
<Choice>1898</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Boer War begins between Dutch and English settlers for control of the region that is now South Africa.
</Question>
<Choice>1899</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The musical form known as the blues develops in the American South. The first recordings were made in the 1920s.
</Question>
<Choice>about 1900</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French impressionist painter Claude Monet begins work on one of his most famous works of art, Water Lilies.
</Question>
<Choice>1900</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>The first Nobel prizes are awarded.</Question>
<Choice>1901</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Vice President Theodore Roosevelt becomes president of the United States after the assassination of President McKinley.
</Question>
<Choice>1901</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English explorers Robert F. Scott and Ernest Henry Shackleton lead the first of their three expeditions to Antarctica.
</Question>
<Choice>1901</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>The Commonwealth of Australia is formed.</Question>
<Choice>1901</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first great Texas oil well is discovered at Spindletop Hill near Beaumont.
</Question>
<Choice>1901</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>The Republic of Cuba is established.</Question>
<Choice>1902</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Theodore Roosevelt is elected the 26th president of the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1904</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Helen Keller is the first blind and deaf woman to graduate from Radcliffe College in Cambridge, Massachusetts.
</Question>
<Choice>1904</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Norway declares its independence from Sweden.</Question>
<Choice>1905</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A massive earthquake hits San Francisco, California. Fire spreads and destroys much of the city.
</Question>
<Choice>1906</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
New Zealand becomes a self-governing state within the British Empire. It gains full independence from Britain in 1947.
</Question>
<Choice>1907</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Ford Motor Company introduces the Model T, the first affordable automobile.
</Question>
<Choice>1908</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
William Howard Taft is elected the 27th president of the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1908</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
W.E.B. Du Bois and others found the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP).
</Question>
<Choice>1909</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. explorer Robert E. Peary is credited as the first person to reach the North Pole.
</Question>
<Choice>1909</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>The Union of South Africa is formed.</Question>
<Choice>1910</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The tales of Paul Bunyan, the legendary giant lumberjack, first appear in print in the Detroit News-Tribune.
</Question>
<Choice>1910</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Norwegian explorer Roald Amundsen becomes the first person to reach the South Pole.
</Question>
<Choice>1911</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German meteorologist Alfred Wegener publishes the first detailed theory of continental drift.
</Question>
<Choice>1912</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Woodrow Wilson is elected the 28th president of the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1912</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The British luxury liner Titanic strikes an iceberg in the North Atlantic Ocean and sinks, killing more than 1,500 people.
</Question>
<Choice>1912</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. athlete Jim Thorpe wins gold medals in the decathlon and the pentathlon at the Olympic Games in Stockholm, Sweden. He was considered one of the greatest athletes of all time.
</Question>
<Choice>1912</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The assassination of Archduke Francis Ferdinand of Austria triggers the start of World War I. Fighting between the Central Powers and the Allies formally ended with an armistice, or truce, signed by Germany in 1918.
</Question>
<Choice>1914</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>The Panama Canal opens.</Question>
<Choice>1914</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>The United States enters World War I.</Question>
<Choice>1917</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Russian Revolution begins. Fighting and unrest continues as Bolshevik leader Vladimir Lenin rises to power and establishes a Communist government in Russia.
</Question>
<Choice>1917</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Finland declares itself an independent country.</Question>
<Choice>1917</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. President Woodrow Wilson proposes his Fourteen Points as a basis for a peace plan at the end of World War I.
</Question>
<Choice>1918</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The dual monarchy of Austria-Hungary ends, and both countries become independent republics.
</Question>
<Choice>1918</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
After a series of wars lasting nearly 100 years, Afghanistan finally gains its independence from Great Britain.
</Question>
<Choice>1919</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An international assembly meets in Paris to arrange a settlement of Europe's affairs after World War I. The Treaty of Versailles came out of this conference, greatly limiting Germany's military capacity and forcing them to pay for their role in starting the war.
</Question>
<Choice>1919</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
African American creativity in music, literature, and the visual arts flourishes in a period known as the Harlem Renaissance.
</Question>
<Choice>about 1920</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first assembly of the League of Nations takes place in Geneva, Switzerland.
</Question>
<Choice>1920</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mahatma Gandhi becomes a leader of the Indian National Congress. He urges nonviolent protest against the British rule.
</Question>
<Choice>1920</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Great Britain divides Ireland into northern and southern provinces. The Irish Free State is established in 1921 in the southern part of the island. The Irish Free State ultimately cuts ties with Great Britain and becomes an independent republic in 1949.
</Question>
<Choice>1920</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Warren G. Harding is elected the 29th president of the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1920</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The 19th Amendment is added to the U.S. Constitution granting women the right to vote.
</Question>
<Choice>1920</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Adolf Hitler becomes head of the National Socialist German Workers' Party, or Nazi Party.
</Question>
<Choice>1920</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese soldier and political leader Mao Zedong helps to create the Chinese Communist Party (CCP). He later became chairman of the People's Republic of China in 1949.
</Question>
<Choice>1921</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Benito Mussolini and his Fascist party rise to power in Italy. He rules as prime minister until 1943.
</Question>
<Choice>1922</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Egypt gains independence from Great Britain.</Question>
<Choice>1922</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Turkey is proclaimed a republic. The Ottoman Empire finally comes to an end after more than 600 years in power.
</Question>
<Choice>1923</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Vice President Calvin Coolidge becomes president of the United States after the death of President Harding.
</Question>
<Choice>1923</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mexican artist Diego Rivera completes work on his first mural.
</Question>
<Choice>1923</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Calvin Coolidge is elected the 30th president of the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1924</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Joseph Stalin becomes the leader of the Soviet Union after the death of Vladimir Lenin. He ruled until 1953 and was considered one of the most merciless and cruel dictators of the 20th century.
</Question>
<Choice>1925</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. athlete Lou Gehrig joins the New York Yankees. He is elected to the Baseball Hall of Fame in Cooperstown, New York, in 1939.
</Question>
<Choice>1925</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. aviator Charles Lindbergh is the first person to fly across the Atlantic Ocean without making any stops.
</Question>
<Choice>1927</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Herbert Hoover is elected the 31st president of the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1928</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
General Chiang Kai-shek becomes head of the Nationalist government in China.
</Question>
<Choice>1928</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The United States stock market collapses and triggers a severe economic crisis in the industrialized world. This was known as the Great Depression.
</Question>
<Choice>1929</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. astronomer Clyde Tombaugh discovers the planet Pluto.
</Question>
<Choice>1930</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. social work pioneer Jane Addams wins the Nobel peace prize for her efforts to end war.
</Question>
<Choice>1931</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish artist Salvador Dali paints The Persistence of Memory. It is one of the most famous surrealist paintings in the world.
</Question>
<Choice>1931</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Franklin D. Roosevelt is elected the 32nd president of the United States. He is the only United States president elected to the office four times.
</Question>
<Choice>1932</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. aviator Amelia Earhart is the first woman to fly solo across the Atlantic Ocean.
</Question>
<Choice>1932</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Adolf Hitler becomes chancellor of Germany.</Question>
<Choice>1933</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Tennessee Valley Authority (TVA) is created by the U.S. Congress to help develop the resources of the Tennessee River valley.
</Question>
<Choice>1933</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
President Roosevelt introduces the first of his New Deal programs to help improve economic conditions in the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1933</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Adolf Hitler's campaign of anti-Semitism known as the Holocaust begins with the passing of the Nuremberg Laws in Germany. The laws strip Jews of their citizenship.
</Question>
<Choice>1935</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Babe Ruth is elected to the National Baseball Hall of Fame in Cooperstown, New York.
</Question>
<Choice>1936</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Spanish Civil War begins. Under the leadership of General Francisco Franco, the Nationalists defeat the Republicans in 1939 and take control of Spain. Franco rules as dictator until his death in 1975.
</Question>
<Choice>1936</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
African-American athlete Jesse Owens wins four gold medals at the Olympic Games in Berlin, Germany.
</Question>
<Choice>1936</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. First Lady Eleanor Roosevelt begins publishing her daily column, My Day. It appears in newspapers across the country.
</Question>
<Choice>1936</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. major league baseball player Ty Cobb is the first player to be elected into the National Baseball Hall of Fame.
</Question>
<Choice>1936</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Oil is first discovered in Saudi Arabia. The country becomes the world's leading producer of oil.
</Question>
<Choice>1938</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Germany, under the leadership of Adolf Hitler, invades Poland. This marks the beginning of World War II.
</Question>
<Choice>1939</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. photographer Ansel Adams helps establish the world's first museum collection of photographs at the Museum of Modern Art in New York City.
</Question>
<Choice>1940</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. jazz musician Louis Armstrong forms his famous Dixieland band called the All-Stars.
</Question>
<Choice>1940</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Winston Churchill becomes prime minister of Great Britain.
</Question>
<Choice>1940</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The United States enters World War II after Japan's surprise attack on the U.S. naval base at Pearl Harbor, Hawaii.
</Question>
<Choice>1941</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. President Franklin D. Roosevelt and British Prime Minister Winston Churchill sign the Atlantic Charter.
</Question>
<Choice>1941</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Lebanon gains its independence from France and becomes a separate state.
</Question>
<Choice>1943</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. General Dwight D. Eisenhower leads Allied troops in the invasion of Normandy, France, on what was known later as D-Day.
</Question>
<Choice>1944</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Vice President Harry S. Truman becomes president of the United States after President Roosevelt dies.
</Question>
<Choice>1945</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The United States drops atom bombs on two Japanese cities, Hiroshima and Nagasaki. The cities were largely destroyed.
</Question>
<Choice>1945</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
World War II ends with the surrender of Germany and Japan to Allied forces.
</Question>
<Choice>1945</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Nuremberg Trials against Nazi leaders charged with war crimes takes place in Nuremberg, Germany.
</Question>
<Choice>1945</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Germany and the city of Berlin are divided after the end of World War II into zones of occupation. Based on this division, Germany remained divided into East and West Germany until 1989.
</Question>
<Choice>1945</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The United Nations is formed to maintain international peace and security.
</Question>
<Choice>1945</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Ho Chi Minh becomes president of North Vietnam.</Question>
<Choice>1945</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Arab states of the Middle East form the Arab League, also called the League of Arab States, in Cairo, Egypt.
</Question>
<Choice>1945</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Juan Peron is elected president of Argentina.</Question>
<Choice>1946</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
George Balanchine founds what is later known as the New York City Ballet, one of the most prestigious ballet companies in the world.
</Question>
<Choice>1946</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sri Lanka, once known as Ceylon, becomes an independent country after nearly 150 years under British rule.
</Question>
<Choice>1947</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jawaharlal Nehru becomes the first prime minister of the newly independent nation of India.
</Question>
<Choice>1947</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first of the ancient religious documents known as the Dead Sea Scrolls are discovered in a cave in Jordan.
</Question>
<Choice>1947</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Marshall Plan is proposed to help rebuild the economies of Europe after the end of World War II and to prevent the spread of Communism.
</Question>
<Choice>1947</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The diary of a young Jewish girl named Anne Frank is published. Later known simply as The Diary of Anne Frank, it tells the story of her life during two years spent in hiding from the Nazis during World War II.
</Question>
<Choice>1947</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The nation of Israel is established as a Jewish homeland.
</Question>
<Choice>1948</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Harry S. Truman is elected the 33rd president of the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1948</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Myanmar gains its independence after nearly 60 years under British rule.
</Question>
<Choice>1948</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The National Party rises to power in South Africa and establishes a policy of racial segregation called apartheid.
</Question>
<Choice>1948</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The United States and its European allies form the North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO).
</Question>
<Choice>1949</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The National Basketball League (NBL) and the Basketball Association of America (BAA) merge to form the National Basketball Association (NBA).
</Question>
<Choice>1949</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Communist forces in North Korea stage a surprise attack on the Republic of Korea. This incident sets off the Korean War. The conflict between North and South Korea finally ends in 1953.
</Question>
<Choice>1950</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Gwendolyn Brooks becomes the first African American to win a Pulitzer prize for poetry.
</Question>
<Choice>1950</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dwight D. Eisenhower is elected the 34th president of the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1952</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The United States performs the first successful test of a hydrogen, or thermonuclear, bomb on the Bikini Islands in the Pacific Ocean.
</Question>
<Choice>1952</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A militant group known as the Mau Mau stage a rebellion against the British colonial government in Kenya. This uprising, which ended in 1960, led to Kenya's independence from British rule in 1963.
</Question>
<Choice>1952</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
New Zealand adventurer Edmund Hillary and Nepalese mountaineer and guide Tenzing Norgay are the first people to reach the top of Mount Everest, the highest point on Earth.
</Question>
<Choice>1953</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nikita Khrushchev becomes premier of the Soviet Union.
</Question>
<Choice>1953</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The U.S. Supreme Court case of Brown vs. Board of Education of Topeka rules that segregation in the nation's school systems is unconstitutional.
</Question>
<Choice>1954</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Construction begins on the St. Lawrence Seaway. The project, which finished in 1959, connected the Great Lakes with the Atlantic Ocean.
</Question>
<Choice>1954</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Rosa Parks refuses to give up her bus seat to a white man in Montgomery, Alabama. This leads to a bus boycott that sets off the beginning of the U.S. Civil Rights Movement.
</Question>
<Choice>1955</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Marian Anderson becomes the first African American singer to perform as a member of the Metropolitan Opera in New York City.
</Question>
<Choice>1955</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Soviet Union launches Sputnik I, the first artificial satellite ever to orbit the Earth.
</Question>
<Choice>1957</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ghana gains independence from Britain. Over the next several years many more African countries gain independence from European powers.
</Question>
<Choice>1957</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Charles de Gaulle becomes president of France under a new government which he helps to create.
</Question>
<Choice>1959</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Fidel Castro rises to power and becomes dictator of Cuba. He soon cuts ties with the United States and establishes alliances with the major Communist powers.
</Question>
<Choice>1959</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John F. Kennedy is elected the 35th president of the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1960</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first weather satellite, the Television and Infra Red Observation Satellite (Tiros), is developed.
</Question>
<Choice>1960</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British scientist Jane Goodall begins her groundbreaking work in the study of chimpanzees and their behavior on the shores of Lake Tanganyika in Tanzania.
</Question>
<Choice>1960</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The United States and exiled Cubans attempt the Bay of Pigs invasion. This effort to overthrow Fidel Castro and his Communist government in Cuba fails.
</Question>
<Choice>1961</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Construction begins on the Berlin Wall, the most striking symbol of the Cold War. It is built by the East German Communist government to prevent East Germans from fleeing to West Germany.
</Question>
<Choice>1961</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Angola begins its fight for independence against Portugal. After years of conflict, Angola becomes an independent nation in 1975.
</Question>
<Choice>1961</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Cuban Missile Crisis erupts when the United States discovers that the Soviet Union has placed nuclear arms in Cuba. The Soviet Union eventually agrees to remove the weapons.
</Question>
<Choice>1962</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. civil rights leader Martin Luther King, Jr., leads a march on Washington, D.C. He delivers his famous I Have a Dream speech.
</Question>
<Choice>1963</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. President Kennedy is assassinated while campaigning for reelection in Dallas, Texas.
</Question>
<Choice>1963</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Vice President Lyndon B. Johnson becomes president of the United States after the assassination of President Kennedy.
</Question>
<Choice>1963</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Lyndon B. Johnson is elected the 36th president of the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1964</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The United Republic of Tanzania is formed by the union of the two states of Tanganyika and Zanzibar.
</Question>
<Choice>1964</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Civil Rights Act is passed by the U.S. Congress. The act prohibits discrimination on the basis of race, creed, national origin, or sex.
</Question>
<Choice>1964</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. boxer Muhammad Ali (then Cassius Clay) defeats Sonny Liston to become the heavyweight champion of the world.
</Question>
<Choice>1964</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British author Roald Dahl publishes the popular book Charlie and the Chocolate Factory.
</Question>
<Choice>1964</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Malcolm X, a champion for African American rights and racial unity, is assassinated in New York City.
</Question>
<Choice>1965</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>The U.S. Congress passes the Voting Rights Act.</Question>
<Choice>1965</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mao Zedong launches the Cultural Revolution in China in an effort to renew the spirit of the Communist revolution.
</Question>
<Choice>1966</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Six-Day War erupts between Israel and neighboring Arab countries.
</Question>
<Choice>1967</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Thurgood Marshall becomes the first African American justice of the U.S. Supreme Court.
</Question>
<Choice>1967</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Martin Luther King, Jr., is assassinated in Memphis, Tennessee.
</Question>
<Choice>1968</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Richard M. Nixon is elected the 37th president of the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1968</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. astronauts Neil Armstrong and Edwin E. Aldrin, Jr., become the first people to set foot on the moon.
</Question>
<Choice>1969</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Golda Meir becomes the first female prime minister of Israel.
</Question>
<Choice>1969</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Work is completed on the Aswan High Dam on the Nile River in Egypt. It is considered one of the great engineering feats of the 20th century.
</Question>
<Choice>1970</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Salvador Allende is elected president of Chile.</Question>
<Choice>1970</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
East Pakistan declares its independence and takes the name Bangladesh.
</Question>
<Choice>1971</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Vietnam War nears an end as the United States, North and South Vietnam, and the Viet Cong sign a cease-fire agreement. The country is united under Communist rule in 1976.
</Question>
<Choice>1973</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Yom Kippur war begins with a surprise attack against Israel by forces from Egypt and Syria.
</Question>
<Choice>1973</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. major league baseball star Hank Aaron hits his 715th home run, setting a new lifetime home run record.
</Question>
<Choice>1974</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>U.S. President Nixon resigns from office.</Question>
<Choice>1974</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Vice President Gerald Ford becomes the 38th president of the United States after President Nixon's resignation. He is the only president who was not elected to office.
</Question>
<Choice>1974</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Under the leadership of Pol Pot, a brutal Communist group known as the Khmer Rouge seize control of Cambodia.
</Question>
<Choice>1975</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jimmy Carter is elected the 39th president of the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1976</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Canadian ice-hockey player Wayne Gretzky joins the World Hockey Association (WHA) and becomes the youngest player ever in professional ice hockey.
</Question>
<Choice>1978</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Egyptian president Anwar el-Sadat and Israeli prime minister Menachem Begin sign a peace treaty at Camp David, in the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1979</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Islamic revolutionaries seize the U.S. embassy in Tehran, Iran, and take more than 50 Americans hostage.
</Question>
<Choice>1979</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Idi Amin's eight-year reign of terror on the people of Uganda finally ends when troops from Tanzania invade and force him into exile.
</Question>
<Choice>1979</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>The Soviet Union invades Afghanistan.</Question>
<Choice>1979</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Saddam Hussein becomes president of Iraq.</Question>
<Choice>1979</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Vigdis Finnbogadottir is elected president of Iceland. She is the world's first elected woman president.
</Question>
<Choice>1980</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Zimbabwe (then Rhodesia) holds its first multiracial elections. Robert Mugabe is elected the country's first prime minister under majority rule.
</Question>
<Choice>1980</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ronald Reagan is elected the 40th president of the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1980</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sandra Day O'Connor becomes the first female justice of the U.S. Supreme Court.
</Question>
<Choice>1981</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. President Ronald Reagan is shot in an assassination attempt by John Hinckley, Jr.
</Question>
<Choice>1981</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Egyptian president Anwar el-Sadat is assassinated.</Question>
<Choice>1981</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Falkland Islands War takes place between Argentina and Great Britain over control of the islands.
</Question>
<Choice>1982</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The United States invades the tiny Caribbean island of Grenada to prevent it from becoming another Cuban-style dictatorship.
</Question>
<Choice>1983</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Pioneer 10 spacecraft becomes the first artificial object to leave the solar system. It was launched in 1972 and flew by the planet Jupiter the following year. Its mission formally ended in 1997, but it continued to travel through the galaxy.
</Question>
<Choice>1983</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian Prime Minister Indira Gandhi is assassinated.
</Question>
<Choice>1984</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sandinista leader Daniel Ortega Saavedra is elected president of Nicaragua. He establishes a Socialist state. The United States was opposed to the Sandinistas and later supported the anti-Sandinista rebels known as contras.
</Question>
<Choice>1984</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The U.S. space shuttle Challenger explodes 73 seconds after launch, killing all seven crew members aboard.
</Question>
<Choice>1986</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Corazon Aquino is elected president of the Philippines.
</Question>
<Choice>1986</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The worst accident in the history of the nuclear power industry takes place at the Chernobyl plant near Kiev, Ukraine.
</Question>
<Choice>1986</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Soviet Premier Mikhail Gorbachev and U.S. President Ronald Reagan sign the Strategic Arms Limitation Agreement, a treaty to reduce nuclear weapons.
</Question>
<Choice>1987</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
George Bush is elected the 41st president of the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1988</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A war between Iran and Iraq ends after eight years of brutal conflict.
</Question>
<Choice>1988</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Berlin Wall is opened, allowing passage between East and West Berlin. The event leads to the end of the Cold War. The following year the wall is destroyed and Germany is formally reunited.
</Question>
<Choice>1989</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
United States troops invade Panama and overthrow the country's dictator, Manuel Noriega.
</Question>
<Choice>1989</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese troops kill hundreds of students in Beijing's Tiananmen Square. The students had been protesting for democracy and free speech.
</Question>
<Choice>1989</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Exxon Valdez supertanker spills millions of gallons of oil into Prince William Sound, Alaska.
</Question>
<Choice>1989</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
South African civil rights leader Nelson Mandela is released from prison. He spent nearly 30 years in jail for his protests against apartheid.
</Question>
<Choice>1990</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Lech Walesa wins the first open presidential elections held in post-Communist Poland.
</Question>
<Choice>1990</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jean-Bertrand Aristide becomes the first democratically elected president of Haiti.
</Question>
<Choice>1990</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Namibia gains its independence from South Africa.</Question>
<Choice>1990</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Civil war breaks out in Rwanda between the Hutu and Tutsi ethnic groups.
</Question>
<Choice>1990</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Iraqi President Saddam Hussein orders troops to invade Kuwait. This incident leads to the Persian Gulf War in 1991.
</Question>
<Choice>1990</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Maastricht Treaty establishes the European Union, which brings together the countries of Europe for trade and other foreign policy issues.
</Question>
<Choice>1991</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Soviet Union officially collapses. Russia and 14 other independent nations are created from the former Soviet state.
</Question>
<Choice>1991</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Boris Yeltsin is elected the first president of the newly independent Russia.
</Question>
<Choice>1991</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Croatia, Slovenia, and Macedonia declare their independence from Yugoslavia. The following year Bosnia and Herzegovina does the same. Civil war rages in these regions for several years.
</Question>
<Choice>1991</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Bill Clinton is elected the 42nd president of the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1992</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Czechoslovakia is divided into two new and independent countries, the Czech Republic and Slovakia.
</Question>
<Choice>1993</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Leaders of Israel and the Palestine Liberation Organization (PLO) sign a peace accord in Washington, D.C.
</Question>
<Choice>1993</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The U.S. Congress passed the North American Free Trade Agreement (NAFTA), allowing free trade between the United States, Canada, and Mexico.
</Question>
<Choice>1993</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Labor leader Cesar Chavez dies. He improved the lives of farmworkers in the United States by organizing them into a successful union.
</Question>
<Choice>1993</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nelson Mandela is elected president of South Africa in the first elections open to candidates of all races.
</Question>
<Choice>1994</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Channel Tunnel (Eurotunnel), a railway tunnel that runs under the English Channel and connects England and France, officially opens.
</Question>
<Choice>1994</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A terrorist bomb destroys the Alfred P. Murrah Federal Building in Oklahoma City, Oklahoma.
</Question>
<Choice>1995</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The warring republics of the former Yugoslavia sign a peace treaty.
</Question>
<Choice>1995</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
South African president Nelson Mandela signs a new constitution into law.
</Question>
<Choice>1996</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The government of Guatemala and rebel leaders sign a peace treaty, ending nearly 40 years of civil war.
</Question>
<Choice>1996</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
China regains control of Hong Kong from Great Britain.
</Question>
<Choice>1997</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the United States, two new professional women's basketball leagues are established.
</Question>
<Choice>1997</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Pathfinder probe lands on Mars to collect information on the planet's geology.
</Question>
<Choice>1997</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Warring parties in Northern Ireland sign a peace agreement after decades of conflict.
</Question>
<Choice>1998</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
President Clinton becomes the second president in U.S. history to be impeached. He was found not guilty in 1999.
</Question>
<Choice>1998</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Vladimir Putin becomes Russia's new prime minister.
</Question>
<Choice>1999</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. professional baseball player Joe DiMaggio dies. He is considered one of the game's greatest all-round players.
</Question>
<Choice>1999</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Brian Jones and Bertrand Piccard become the first people to travel nonstop around the world in a balloon. The trip took 19 days.
</Question>
<Choice>1999</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The euro is introduced as the standard currency for countries in the European Union.
</Question>
<Choice>1999</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Field Museum of Natural History in Chicago unveils Sue, a Tyrannosaurus rex skeleton that is the most complete and best-preserved ever discovered.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
George W. Bush is elected the 43rd president of the United States in one of the closest and most controversial elections in history.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Colin Powell becomes the first black secretary of state of the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Russian space station Mir is abandoned and falls into the Pacific Ocean. It had been in service for more than 14 years.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Terrorists attack the World Trade Center in New York City and the Pentagon near Washington, D.C., on September 11. Thousands of people are killed in the largest attack on the United States homeland in its history.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The United States invades Afghanistan to bring down the Taliban-led government. The Taliban was believed to be supporting Osama bin Laden, the prime suspect behind the September 11 attacks.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Adventurer Steve Fossett becomes the first person to successfully complete a solo nonstop balloon flight around the world.
</Question>
<Choice>2002</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>East Timor becomes an independent country.</Question>
<Choice>2002</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Switzerland and East Timor become the 190th and 191st members of the United Nations.
</Question>
<Choice>2002</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The U.S. space shuttle Columbia breaks apart as it is returning to Earth after a 16-day mission. All seven crew members, including the first Israeli astronaut, are killed.
</Question>
<Choice>2003</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The country of Yugoslavia is reorganized as a looser union of its two republics. The name is changed to Serbia and Montenegro.
</Question>
<Choice>2003</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The United States and the United Kingdom lead an invasion against Iraq. The action is part of an ongoing dispute over Iraq's development of weapons of mass destruction. Major combat ends in May with the defeat of Iraqi forces, and in December Iraqi leader Saddam Hussein is captured.
</Question>
<Choice>2003</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Two robot probes are sent to the planet Mars. They land in Late 2003 and early 2004. The robots soon send back photographs and begin a series of tests on the soil.
</Question>
<Choice>2003</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Using a satellite that measures microwave radiation, scientists are able to create a map of the universe just after its creation.
</Question>
<Choice>2003</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Shirin Ebadi becomes the first Muslim woman to be awarded the Nobel prize for peace. She is honored for her work promoting democracy and human rights. Ebadi is an Iranian lawyer and activist.
</Question>
<Choice>2003</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Olympics return to Greece, where the Games originated.
</Question>
<Choice>2004</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The spacecraft Cassini becomes the first to enter into orbit around Saturn. Its mission is to study the planet and its ring system and many moons.
</Question>
<Choice>2004</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An undersea earthquake in the Indian Ocean produces a giant wave, called a tsunami. It is the largest tsunami ever recorded. At least 225,000 people are killed. Many countries, including Indonesia, Sri Lanka, Maldives, and Thailand, sustain massive damage.
</Question>
<Choice>2004</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pope John Paul II dies. Soon after, Joseph Ratzinger becomes Pope Benedict XVI.
</Question>
<Choice>2005</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American cyclist Lance Armstrong wins his seventh Tour de France bicycle race. Afterwards, he retires from racing.
</Question>
<Choice>2005</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hurricane Katrina devastates parts of the U.S. states of Louisiana and Mississippi. Much of the city of New Orleans, Louisiana, is destroyed.
</Question>
<Choice>2005</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A powerful earthquake strikes Pakistan, Afghanistan, and India. Some 80,000 people are killed.
</Question>
<Choice>2005</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the mountains of southwestern Germany, archaeologists find what are believed to be the world's oldest musical instruments. They are a 35,000-year-old flute fashioned out of a wooly mammoth tusk and two smaller flutes made of swan bones.
</Question>
<Choice>2005</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The U.S. spacecraft Stardust returns to Earth with dust particles from a comet. The spaceship had traveled for seven years. Scientists hope the material will offer information on the solar system's origins.
</Question>
<Choice>2006</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ellen Johnson-Sirleaf is sworn in as president of Liberia. She is the first woman elected to head an African country.
</Question>
<Choice>2006</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scientists announce that many new animals and plants have been discovered in a remote jungle in Indonesia. Among their findings are 20 new types of frog and four new butterflies.
</Question>
<Choice>2006</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A group of scientists decides that Pluto should no longer be considered a planet. They say it should be called a dwarf planet instead.
</Question>
<Choice>2006</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Orhan Pamuk wins the Nobel prize for literature. He is the first Turk to receive a Nobel prize.
</Question>
<Choice>2006</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nancy Pelosi becomes the first woman to serve as speaker of the U.S. House of Representatives.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British author J.K. Rowling completes the last book in the Harry Potter series. The book is called Harry Potter and the Deathly Hallows.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Barry Bonds of the San Francisco Giants becomes the all-time home run champion in major league baseball. By the end of the 2007 season he has 762 home runs. Hank Aaron held the previous record of 755 home runs.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pratibha Patil becomes the first woman president of India.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Benazir Bhutto is assassinated in Pakistan. She was the first woman leader of a Muslim country in modern times when she became the prime minister of Pakistan in 1988. She served two separate terms and later left the country for several years. She had just returned when she was assassinated.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Metropolitan Museum of Art in New York City returns a number of items, including a 2,500-year-old Greek bowl, to Italy. The Italian government and others have long claimed that many ancient items in museums were stolen from tombs and other sites in their countries.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
NASA's Messenger spacecraft flys by the planet Mercury. The spacecraft records the first images of the side of Mercury that has not been seen before. The images reveal that the planet once had volcanic activity.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Terrorists attack several sites in Mumbai, India, leading to the death of some 200 people.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Serbian province of Kosovo formally declares its independence. However Russia and Serbia, among others, refuse to recognize it as a country.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scientists announce the discovery of the world's longest insect. With its legs fully extended, Chan's megastick, a type of stick insect, is 22 inches long.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
China becomes the third country to put a human into space, when taikonaut Yang Liwei reaches orbit aboard a Shenzhou 5 rocket.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A magnitude-7.9 earthquake strikes Chinas Sichuan province, killing some 90,000 and leaving millions homeless.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American swimmer Michael Phelps wins a record eight gold medals at the 2008 Olympics in Beijing.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Church of England's General Synod votes to allow women to be ordained as bishops.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Beijing hosts the Summer Olympic Games. It is the first time the Olympics have been held in China.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Barack Obama is sworn in as the 44th president of the United States. He is the first African American to hold the office.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
UNESCO and the International Astronomical Union proclaim 2009 to be the International Year of Astronomy. This year marks the 400th anniversary of Galileos first use of the telescope.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Pittsburgh Steelers defeat the Arizona Cardinals in Super Bowl XLIII to win a record sixth NFL championship.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sonia Sotomayor is sworn in as an associate justice of the U.S. Supreme Court. She is the first Hispanic and third woman to serve on the court.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The International Space Station becomes fully operational when its crew increases from three to six.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A version of the flu virus called H1N1 spread throughout the world. The virus was also called swine flu because it likely started in pigs.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Michael Jackson, known as the "King of Pop" for his best-selling music, dies shortly before the start of a comeback tour.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Burj Khalifa, the world's tallest building to date, officially opens in Dubai, U.A.E.
</Question>
<Choice>2010</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A powerful earthquake strikes Haiti, causing extensive damage and killing more than 150,000 people.
</Question>
<Choice>2010</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scientists identify the color of a dinosaur for the first time. Using fossils, researchers find that the dinosaur Sinosauropteryx had feathers that were white and chestnut in color.
</Question>
<Choice>2010</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
South Africa hosts the World Cup; it is the first time the football (soccer) tournament has been held in Africa.
</Question>
<Choice>2010</Choice>
</item>
</topics>