<topics>
<item>
<Question>Egyptian women begin brewing beer.</Question>
<Choice>c. 3500 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
According to legend, the Chinese empress Se Ling-she is reported to have invented silk cultivation.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 3000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Akkad, theologian and writer Enheduanna, daughter of Sargon, is made chief priestess of the gods at Ur and Uruk.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 2300 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Egyptian texts describe contraceptive suppositories, mixed out of honey and crocodile dung. This is the first known reference to contraceptives.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1850 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hammurabi's code protects a woman's right to hold and inherit property.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1750 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Egyptian medical school at Heliopolis has women students.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1500 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Queen Hatshepsut rules Egypt, fighting against the Nubians, expanding trade, and sponsoring exploration around the Red Sea.
</Question>
<Choice>1472 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
By law and by custom, Mesopotamian women are controlled first by their fathers, then by their husbands and fathers-in-law, and finally by their sons.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1450 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Most Chinese shamans are women. They are particularly important for performing rites to bring rain.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1000 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Athaliah becomes queen of Judah. Her reign is short and bloody, as she tries to murder everyone who might oppose her.
</Question>
<Choice>843 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Women are barred from the first recorded Olympic Games as athletes and as spectators.
</Question>
<Choice>776 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sappho writes poetry on Lesbos, where she also teaches young women poetry, music, and the social graces.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 600 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Sparta, girls are trained in athletics, including running, javelin, and discus, so that they will become strong and healthy mothers.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 600 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ambapali, a wealthy Indian courtesan, gives her mango groves to the Buddha. She becomes his disciple and reaches the status of arhat, holy one.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 600 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Artemisia I, queen of Halicarnassus, commands five ships in the Battle of Salamis on September 23.
</Question>
<Choice>480 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Athens, Aspasia opens a school for upper-class women. She teaches rhetoric and philosophy.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 450 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek women have no independent status in society and may not make transactions worth more than one medimnos of barley, although they may own their own slaves.
</Question>
<Choice>380 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Athenian philosopher Hipparchia studies with the Cynic Crates of Thebes. She forces her parents to let her marry him and boasts of spending her life on education rather than weaving.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 300 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Kao-hou seizes power from her son Hui-ti to become the first woman ruler of China.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 195 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman women successfully insist on the repeal of the Oppian law, a sumptuary tax passed in 215, forbidding them to wear more than half an ounce of gold or to drive chariots in town.
</Question>
<Choice>195 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Cleopatra becomes queen of Egypt.</Question>
<Choice>51 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Sri Lanka, Queen Anula takes the throne. Her reign ends in 42 with her resignation.
</Question>
<Choice>47 BC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Two Vietnamese sisters, Trung Trac and Trung Nhi, lead the first revolt in Southeast Asia against Chinese domination. Despite early successes, the revolt eventually fails.
</Question>
<Choice>39</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Korea, the Queen Mother of Koguryo serves as successful regent for her son King T'aego.
</Question>
<Choice>53</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Queen Boudicca of the Iceni rallies British tribes in an unsuccessful revolt against Romans under the command of Suetonius Paulinus.
</Question>
<Choice>60</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>In Sri Lanka, Queen Sivali rules.</Question>
<Choice>65</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ethiopian women and men fight in Rome as gladiators. Under the emperors Nero and Domitian, women captives (especially German ones) frequently fight in the arena.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 65</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dowager empress Deng holds the real power in China behind the boy-emperor Ngan-ti.
</Question>
<Choice>107</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese poet and historian Pan Chao dies after a long and renowned career.
</Question>
<Choice>115</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Queen Himiko of Yamatai, the first known ruler of Japan, establishes diplomatic relations with China.
</Question>
<Choice>239</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Vietnamese patriot Trieu Au, with an army of 1,000, leads a revolt against the Chinese. She commits suicide after the revolt fails.
</Question>
<Choice>248</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Septimia Zenobia of Palmyra challenges Roman rule after conquering Egypt. The Roman emperor Aurelian captures and parades her and her son through Rome in a triumphal procession.
</Question>
<Choice>269</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Helena, mother of Roman Emperor Constantine I, claims to have found the sites of the Ascension and the Holy Sepulchre. Later legend says she also found the Holy Cross.
</Question>
<Choice>326</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese calligrapher Wei Furen, also known as Wei Shou or Wei Fu-Jen, dies after a career in which she is honoured in the Book of One Hundred Beauties and teaches master calligrapher Wang Xizhi.
</Question>
<Choice>350</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman St. Paulina founds a pilgrims' hospice and communal houses in Bethlehem. Her daughter Eustochium becomes head of the women's community on her death in 404.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 385</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Saint Fabiola founds the first public hospital in the Latin West, in Rome, copying the example she saw in the Byzantine empire on a pilgrimage to the Holy Land.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 397</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Alexandria, Greek-Egyptian scholar and teacher Hypatia is murdered by a mob because of her intimacy with the city's pagan prefect, Orestes.
</Question>
<Choice>415</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The council of Ephesus recognizes Mary as the Mother of God, resulting in the spread westward from Byzantium of the cult of the Virgin.
</Question>
<Choice>431</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Princess Clotilda of Burgundia marries Clovis I, king of the Franks. She converts him to Christianity.
</Question>
<Choice>493</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Justinian Code makes adultery a capital offense for women but not for men.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 535</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese Empress Suiko encourages the spread of Buddhism and orders the construction of Buddhist temples.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 594</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Women in England may be publicly punished as "scolds," a practice that continues for 1,000 years.
</Question>
<Choice>600</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Queen Sondok becomes the ruler of the Korean kingdom of Silla. During her reign, she fights the kingdom of Paekche, sends students to China for education, and constructs Buddhist temples.
</Question>
<Choice>632</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
'A'ishah, widow of Muhammad, rebels against the Caliph ‘Ali in the battle of the Camel at Basra.
</Question>
<Choice>656</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Indian Queen Vidya writes Sanskrit poetry.</Question>
<Choice>c. 659</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Princess Libuse and her husband, Premysl, found the city of Prague.
</Question>
<Choice>721</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Second Council of Nicaea is called by Byzantine Empress Irene to settle the question of worshiping icons. The bishops rule in favour of icon worship.
</Question>
<Choice>787</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the Frankish empire, prostitution is outlawed by Charlemagne.
</Question>
<Choice>801</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The practice of foot binding becomes popular in the Chinese Court.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 900</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An anonymous Norwegian woman writes Wise Women's Prophesy, a history of the world, including prophecies for the future.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 950</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Vladimir I of Russia converts Russia to Christianity and marries Anne, sister of Byzantine emperor Basil II. Anne brings Byzantine culture to Russia and the Crimea as her dowry.
</Question>
<Choice>988</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese author Murasaki Shikibu finishes the Genji Monogatari (The Tale of Genji), the world's first novel.
</Question>
<Choice>1004</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English women create the Bayeux Tapestry, using wool embroidery on linen to record the events of the Norman Conquest.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1070</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Héloïse is made prioress of Argenteuil, where she fled after the discovery of her secret marriage to Peter Abelard.
</Question>
<Choice>1118</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Eleanor of Aquitaine accompanies her husband, French King Louis VII, on the Second Crusade. After their marriage collapses in 1152, she marries the future English King Henry II.
</Question>
<Choice>1147</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Abbess Hildegard of Bingen, currently working on Scivias Domini, ("Know the Ways of the Lord"), is verified as a divinely inspired prophet by an ecclesiastical commission.
</Question>
<Choice>1148</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Frau Ava of Melk is one of Germany's first female poets.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1160</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At the University of Paris, women are banned from practicing medicine.
</Question>
<Choice>1220</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Guan Daosheng, Chinese calligrapher and painter, dies after a career including commissions for Emperor Renzhong.
</Question>
<Choice>1319</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
There are over 3,000 nuns in England, reflecting the flourishing of convents and religious orders for women in the Middle Ages.
</Question>
<Choice>1350</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Under England's Treason Act, it is petty treason for a wife to murder her husband, who is her sovereign lord.
</Question>
<Choice>1351</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jadwiga is crowned "king" of Poland. Two years later she marries Grand Duke Jogaila of Lithuania, thus uniting the kingdoms.
</Question>
<Choice>1384</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
London licensing law for doctors requires a university education, thus barring women from the profession.
</Question>
<Choice>1390</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At the University of Bologna, Dorotea Bocchi takes the chair of medicine and moral philosophy, formerly held by her father.
</Question>
<Choice>1390</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On June 20, Queen Margaret I becomes the sole monarch of Denmark, Sweden, and Norway under the Union of Kalmar.
</Question>
<Choice>1397</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian-born French scholar Christine de Pisan writes The Book of the City of Ladies, a history of civilization from the view of women.
</Question>
<Choice>1405</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Korea plans are made for training women doctors to serve female patients who refuse to be treated by male doctors.
</Question>
<Choice>1406</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Joan of Arc, supported by Queen Yolande, begins her military and religious campaign against the English. At the Battle of Orléans she leads the French army to victory.
</Question>
<Choice>1429</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Margery Kempe, an English mystical writer, finishes The Boke of Margery Kempe.
</Question>
<Choice>1436</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Queens' College, Cambridge, is established by Margaret of Anjou, the queen of England.
</Question>
<Choice>1448</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Female English silk manufacturers petition the Crown to stop competition from silk made in Lombard.
</Question>
<Choice>1455</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Korean law prohibits women from participating in outdoor games and feasts.
</Question>
<Choice>1485</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German cleric Johann Sprenger publishes Malleus maleficarum ("Hammer of Witches"), arguing that women, as the weaker sex, are more likely to be witches.
</Question>
<Choice>1486</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Queen Isabella I of Spain finances Christopher Columbus's voyage of exploration to the East Indies. Columbus instead finds the West Indies.
</Question>
<Choice>1492</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mexican Indian princess and slave Doña Marina becomes translator and mistress of Hernán Cortés as he conquers New Spain.
</Question>
<Choice>1519</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the Gulf of Mexico, 10 Spanish women accompany their husbands on a voyage of discovery. After the men are lost, the women search for them a year, then settle in Veracruz.
</Question>
<Choice>1528</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mary Tudor becomes queen of England and has Lady Jane Grey, who was queen for nine days in July, beheaded. Mary's persecution of Protestants earns her the name Bloody Mary.
</Question>
<Choice>1553</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Elizabeth I, half-sister of Mary Tudor, becomes queen of England. She brings religious tolerance and leads the English to victory over the Spanish Armada in 1588.
</Question>
<Choice>1558</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mary Queen of Scots is beheaded by order of Queen Elizabeth I.
</Question>
<Choice>1587</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Iroquois women are responsible for agricultural production.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1600</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A Japanese dancer of the Izumo shrine invents kabuki theatre.
</Question>
<Choice>1603</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pocahontas saves Jamestown colonist Captain John Smith from execution by Algonkian chief Powhatan.
</Question>
<Choice>1608</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A proposal to give women an equal portion in colonial lands is rejected by the Virginia House of Burgesses.
</Question>
<Choice>1619</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Tokugawa shogun Iemitsu bans women from kabuki theatre because it is considered immoral for women to dance in public.
</Question>
<Choice>1629</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Anne Hutchinson is expelled from the Massachusetts Bay Colony for "traducing the ministers" of the Puritan colony. She and other religious dissenters found Rhode Island.
</Question>
<Choice>1638</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
During the English Civil War, Brilliana, Lady Harley, defends Brampton Bryan Castle from the Royalist army in her husband's absence.
</Question>
<Choice>1642</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Blanche, Lady Arundel, holds off the parliamentary troops under Sir Edward Hungerford who attack Wardour Castle while her husband is away.
</Question>
<Choice>1643</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On her 18th birthday, Queen Christina ascends the throne of Sweden.
</Question>
<Choice>1644</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Margaret Brent, one of the largest landowners in Maryland, asks the Maryland Assembly for two votes, one for herself and one as administrator of Lord Calvert's estate. Her request is denied.
</Question>
<Choice>1648</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Anne Bradstreet's first volume of poems, The Tenth Muse Lately Sprung Up in America, is published in London.
</Question>
<Choice>1650</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mary Dyer is executed in Boston for her Quaker proselytizing.
</Question>
<Choice>1660</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sor Juana Inés de la Cruz enters the convent of San Jerónimo in New Spain. Her religious life allows her to dedicate herself to scholarship and lyric poetry.
</Question>
<Choice>1669</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
La Fontaine makes her debut at the Paris Opéra as the first female professional ballet dancer.
</Question>
<Choice>1681</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mary Rowlandson publishes A Narrative of the Captivity and Restoration of Mrs. Mary Rowlandson, describing her capture by Narragansett warriors and 12 weeks' captivity.
</Question>
<Choice>1682</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sophia Alekseyevna becomes regent of Russia for her brother Ivan after she leads a palace coup against their half-brother Peter, who becomes associate ruler.
</Question>
<Choice>1682</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Salem witch trials condemn 19 to die; most of the accused and the accusers are women.
</Question>
<Choice>1692</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Queen Anne ascends the throne of England.</Question>
<Choice>1702</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Twenty-five Frenchwomen, called "Cassette girls," journey to Mobile on the Gulf Coast to find husbands. They refuse to marry any of the colonists there because of the crude conditions they find.
</Question>
<Choice>1704</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Queen Anne founds the Ascot races and becomes the first monarch of many to use the royal box there.
</Question>
<Choice>1711</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Elizabeth Elstob publishes the first Anglo-Saxon grammar, The Rudiments of Grammar.
</Question>
<Choice>1715</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Lady Mary Wortley Montagu advocates smallpox inoculation, which she has seen in Constantinople.
</Question>
<Choice>1718</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Catherine I becomes ruler of Russia on the death of her husband, Peter the Great.
</Question>
<Choice>1725</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Elizabeth Lucas Pinckney introduces indigo cultivation in South Carolina; by 1742 she has a successful crop.
</Question>
<Choice>1741</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian mathematician Maria Agnesi publishes Instituzioni analitiche uso della gioventù italiana (“Analytical Institutions for the Use of Italian Youth”).
</Question>
<Choice>1748</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hannah Snell publishes The Female Soldier, an account of her exploits in the British army fighting against the supporters of Bonnie Prince Charlie.
</Question>
<Choice>1750</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Russia, Sophie Auguste von Anhalt-Zerbst, widow of Peter III, ascends to the throne as Catherine II. She rules as an "enlightened despot" until 1796.
</Question>
<Choice>1762</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Phillis Wheatley, the first black woman poet in the United States, publishes her poem An Elegiac Poem, on the Death of the Celebrated Divine ... George Whitefield.
</Question>
<Choice>1770</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Fifty-one women in Edenton, N.C., sign a petition endorsing the Nonimportation Association resolves, joining many other colonial women boycotting British goods.
</Question>
<Choice>1774</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mother Ann Lee founds the parent Shaker settlement in America in the woods of Niskeyuna, N.Y.
</Question>
<Choice>1776</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On June 28, Mary Hays ("Molly Pitcher"), wife of an American gunner, brings water to the troops at the Battle of Monmouth. Legend claims that she takes his place when her husband is wounded.
</Question>
<Choice>1778</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Laura Bassi, author of De problemate quodam mechanico and De problemate quodam hydrometrico and the first woman professor of physics (at the University of Bologna), dies.
</Question>
<Choice>1778</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Ladies Association of Philadelphia raises money, buys linen, and makes shirts of it to clothe soldiers during the American Revolution.
</Question>
<Choice>1781</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On May 20, Deborah Sampson, disguised as a man, enlists in the 4th Massachusetts Regiment as Robert Shurtleff. She is one of many women who fight in the American Revolution dressed as men.
</Question>
<Choice>1782</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-born British astronomer Caroline Hershel discovers three nebulae.
</Question>
<Choice>1783</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Catherine II of Russia makes Yekaterina Daskiova head of the new Academy of Sciences and Arts.
</Question>
<Choice>1783</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On October 5, a crowd of Parisian market women numbering over 8,000 march to Versailles and present their demands for more affordable bread to the National Assembly and the king.
</Question>
<Choice>1789</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the United States, the Second Great Awakening begins; significantly more women than men participate in this wave of religious revival.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1790</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
President George Washington praises Eliza Pinckney for her national service and the raising of republican sons. The idea of "Republican Motherhood" stimulates the founding of female academies.
</Question>
<Choice>1791</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French activist Olympe de Gourges writes her Declaration of the Rights of Woman as Citizens, arguing that women are citizens equal to men. She goes to the guillotine in November 1793.
</Question>
<Choice>1791</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mary Wollstonecraft writes A Vindication of the Rights of Woman.
</Question>
<Choice>1792</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On October 16, four years after the start of the French Revolution, French queen Marie-Antoinette is guillotined.
</Question>
<Choice>1793</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mrs. Samuel Slater receives the first United States patent granted to a woman, for a type of cotton thread. Her invention helps her husband build his successful textile business.
</Question>
<Choice>1793</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ann Parrish founds the Friendly Circle (later the Female Society of Philadelphia for the Relief and Employment of the Poor), the first American charitable organization run by and for women.
</Question>
<Choice>1795</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hannah More publishes A Summary History of New England.
</Question>
<Choice>1799</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The highest birthrate in the world is in the United States, 7.04 children per woman.
</Question>
<Choice>1800</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Parliament passes the first British abortion law, prohibiting abortion after quickening.
</Question>
<Choice>1803</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Under France's Napoleonic Code, women are legal minors, as are criminals, children, and the insane. A woman's husband controls her property and, in the case of divorce, gets the children.
</Question>
<Choice>1804</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sacajawea, whose husband is a member of the Lewis and Clark expedition, serves as a guide and interpreter for the group.
</Question>
<Choice>1804</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mercy Otis Warren publishes her influential The Rise, Progress, and Termination of the American Revolution, drawing in part on personal knowledge of the prominent figures of the time.
</Question>
<Choice>1805</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
New Jersey revokes the right of unmarried property-owning women to vote, which they have enjoyed since the adoption of the Constitution of New Jersey on July 2, 1776.
</Question>
<Choice>1807</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In England, Elizabeth Fry advocates reform of Newgate Prison, where the conditions for 300 women and children are appalling.
</Question>
<Choice>1813</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Barbados, slave Nanny Grigg leads blacks in the island's only serious slave rebellion.
</Question>
<Choice>1816</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In South Africa, queen Mmanthatisi becomes the leader of the Tlokwa nation. She plans military strategy and leads the nation to a new homeland in Lesotho.
</Question>
<Choice>1817</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Japan, Tyadano Makuza publishes Hitori jangae, arguing for women's equality.
</Question>
<Choice>1817</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Colombia, women gain the right to go to university.
</Question>
<Choice>1821</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Emma Willard opens the Troy Female Seminary in New York, teaching a rigorous curriculum to girls.
</Question>
<Choice>1821</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Frances Wright founds a utopian community at Nashoba, Tenn., trying to put into practice her ideas for gradual emancipation of slaves. The plantation fails but attracts wide publicity.
</Question>
<Choice>1825</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Lydia Maria Child publishes An Appeal in Favor of That Class of Americans Called Africans, arguing for the abolition of slavery.
</Question>
<Choice>1833</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Marie Grosholtz Tussaud establishes her collection of wax figures in a permanent location on Baker Street in London.
</Question>
<Choice>1833</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British mathematician Lady Byron studies Charles Babbage's "difference engine." She is, arguably, the first computer programmer in the world. The computer language Ada is later named in her honour.
</Question>
<Choice>1833</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Lowell, Mass., women mill workers stage a successful strike to reverse a 25 percent cut in their pay.
</Question>
<Choice>1834</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In New York City, the first women's antislavery convention is held.
</Question>
<Choice>1837</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On June 28, Victoria ascends to the throne of Great Britain. She will rule through the height of the British Empire.
</Question>
<Choice>1838</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Oberlin College is the first American college to admit men and women on an equal basis.
</Question>
<Choice>1838</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At the World's Anti-Slavery Convention in London, female delegates are not admitted. This leads Lucretia Mott and Elizabeth Cady Stanton to call the first women's rights convention.
</Question>
<Choice>1840</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Sydney, Australia, philanthropist Caroline Chisholm founds the Female Immigrants' Home to assist poor women in finding work.
</Question>
<Choice>1841</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dorothea Dix’s reports to the Massachusetts legislature about the conditions in prisons for the insane leads to the beginnings of reform.
</Question>
<Choice>1843</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The English Factory Act establishes the 12-hour workday for female factory workers.
</Question>
<Choice>1844</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>In Sweden, women get equal rights of inheritance.</Question>
<Choice>1845</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first women's rights convention is convened in Seneca Falls, N.Y. The resulting Declaration of Sentiments, patterned after the Declaration of Independence, advocates women's rights.
</Question>
<Choice>1848</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Harriet Tubman escapes from slavery in Maryland to Philadelphia. By the Civil War, Tubman will have returned to the South 19 times and rescued about 300 other slaves.
</Question>
<Choice>1849</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Elizabeth Blackwell becomes the first woman doctor in the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1849</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sojourner Truth gives her famous speech in defense of the rights of black women, "Ain't I a Woman?"
</Question>
<Choice>1851</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Guatemala, the new constitution grants full citizenship to financially independent women.
</Question>
<Choice>1851</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Germany and France, women are banned from political action, which includes editing newspapers. German publisher Louise Otto-Peters' Women's Newspaper is shut down.
</Question>
<Choice>1851</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Harriet Beecher Stowe publishes Uncle Tom's Cabin, one of the most important antislavery novels; it sells 300,000 copies in the first year.
</Question>
<Choice>1852</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Queen Victoria delivers her eighth child under chloroform. Her approval and recommendation of it popularizes use of the anesthetic.
</Question>
<Choice>1853</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Florence Nightingale nurses casualties during the Crimean War. Her efforts help reduce the death rate from injuries in combat from 42 percent to 2.2 percent.
</Question>
<Choice>1854</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Although the mountain is supposed to be forbidden to women, 16 women make a pilgrimage up Mount Fuji.
</Question>
<Choice>1860</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Elizabeth Peabody founds the first English-language preschool in the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1860</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dorothea Dix becomes superintendent of women nurses for the Union Army.
</Question>
<Choice>1861</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Sweden, single women who pay taxes win the right to vote in municipal elections.
</Question>
<Choice>1861</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mary Edwards Walker becomes a surgeon for the Union army. In 1865 she receives a Congressional Medal of Honor. It is revoked shortly before her death and then reawarded posthumously.
</Question>
<Choice>1863</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Over 2,000 warriors form the Dahomey women's army, all of them technically wives of the king. They fight to capture prisoners, using bows, guns, and knives.
</Question>
<Choice>c. 1863</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sarah Edmonds publishes her autobiography, Nurse and Spy in the Union Army, describing her undercover work disguised as a man named Frank Thompson.
</Question>
<Choice>1865</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Astronomer Maria Mitchell is the first female professor at Vassar College.
</Question>
<Choice>1865</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The University of Zürich is the first European university to admit women.
</Question>
<Choice>1865</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Britain, the first petition for woman suffrage is presented to Parliament.
</Question>
<Choice>1867</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Thailand, Amdang Munan refuses to marry the man her parents picked for her; she prevails upon the king to rule that women may pick their own husbands.
</Question>
<Choice>1868</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Married women in Britain gain the right to own property.
</Question>
<Choice>1869</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Iowa, Arabella "Belle" Mansfield is the first woman admitted to the bar in the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1869</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Wyoming is the first state to give women the right to vote.
</Question>
<Choice>1869</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Elizabeth Cady Stanton and Susan B. Anthony found the National Woman Suffrage Association (NWSA).
</Question>
<Choice>1869</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Lucy Stone and Henry Blackwell found the American Woman Suffrage Association (AWSA).
</Question>
<Choice>1869</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Charlotte E. Ray is the first African-American woman lawyer in the United States. She is the first woman admitted to the bar in the District of Columbia.
</Question>
<Choice>1872</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In St. Andrews, Scotland, the Ladies' Golf Club is founded.
</Question>
<Choice>1872</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Japan, primary education for all girls and boys is required by law.
</Question>
<Choice>1872</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Susan B. Anthony leads 15 women to vote in Rochester, N.Y. Anthony is arrested two weeks later for the demonstration.
</Question>
<Choice>1872</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Woman's Christian Temperance Union (WCTU) is founded.
</Question>
<Choice>1874</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Tokyo Women's Normal School trains women as elementary teachers.
</Question>
<Choice>1876</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Eudora Clark Atkinson is the first woman superintendent of the first women's state reformatory in the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1877</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>In Chile, women are allowed to attend university.</Question>
<Choice>1877</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mary Harris "Mother" Jones is one of the leaders of the Pittsburgh railroad strike.
</Question>
<Choice>1877</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mary Baker Eddy is the head of the newly created First Church of Christ, Scientist.
</Question>
<Choice>1879</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Paiute Indian leader Sarah Winnemucca protests conditions on Indian reservations.
</Question>
<Choice>1880</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Women's National Indian Association is founded by Mary Lucinda Bonney and Amelia Stone Quinton.
</Question>
<Choice>1881</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Clara Barton establishes the American branch of the Red Cross and becomes its first president.
</Question>
<Choice>1881</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sofya Perovskaya organizes the assassination of Tsar Alexander II. She is arrested, tried, found guilty, and executed.
</Question>
<Choice>1881</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Helen Hunt Jackson publishes A Century of Dishonor, a profound condemnation of the treatment of Native Americans by the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1881</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At Smith College, the first women's basketball game is introduced by Senda Brenson.
</Question>
<Choice>1882</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Wimbledon holds its first women's singles championship; Maud Watson is the first winner.
</Question>
<Choice>1884</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mary Fitch Scranton, a Protestant missionary, arrives in Korea. She gains some success and popularity by respecting the Korean custom of segregation of men and women.
</Question>
<Choice>1886</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>In Palestine, women agitate for the right to vote.</Question>
<Choice>1886</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Anandibai Joshee is the first Indian woman to earn a medical degree.
</Question>
<Choice>1886</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On November 14, journalist Nellie Bly sets off around the world to beat the fictional record of Phileas Fogg.
</Question>
<Choice>1889</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jane Addams and Ellen Starr found Hull House in Chicago. It is one of the first settlement houses in the United States, and the most famous. Addams wins the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1931.
</Question>
<Choice>1889</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Daughters of the American Revolution (DAR) is founded.
</Question>
<Choice>1890</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Alice Stone Blackwell and others oversee the merger of two older organizations to form the National American Woman Suffrage Association (NAWSA).
</Question>
<Choice>1890</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Liliuokalani becomes queen of Hawaii.</Question>
<Choice>1891</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Belgium, Marie Popelin helps found the Belgian League of Women's Rights.
</Question>
<Choice>1892</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Journalist Ida Wells-Barnett begins her campaign against lynching. Her newspaper offices are burned, and she is driven out of Memphis.
</Question>
<Choice>1892</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Royal Geographical Society admits the first female member, Isabella Bird Bishop.
</Question>
<Choice>1892</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
New Zealand is the first nation to grant women the right to vote.
</Question>
<Choice>1893</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Lillian D. Wald and Mary M. Brewster found the Henry Street Settlement House on Manhattan's Lower East Side. It will become the home of the first visiting nurse organization.
</Question>
<Choice>1893</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Johns Hopkins Medical School opens. The women who donate the funding insist that men and women be admitted equally.
</Question>
<Choice>1896</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Zimbabwe, Ambuya Nehanda starts a revolt against the British.
</Question>
<Choice>1896</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On April 4, the first women's intercollegiate basketball game is played between the University of California at Berkeley and Stanford University.
</Question>
<Choice>1896</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The United States Geological Survey hires its first woman, geologist Florence Bascom.
</Question>
<Choice>1896</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Queen Victoria celebrates her Diamond Jubilee, commemorating 60 years as Great Britain's queen.
</Question>
<Choice>1897</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Alice McLellan Birney founds the National Congress of Mothers, later called the Parent-Teacher Association (PTA).
</Question>
<Choice>1897</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Charlotte Perkins Gilman writes Women and Economics. She argues that the lost talent of women hampers the entire economy.
</Question>
<Choice>1898</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese Dowager Empress Tz’u-hsi seizes power from the emperor. In 1900 she supports the Boxer Rebellion against the foreign powers.
</Question>
<Choice>1898</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In China, revolutionary Ch'iu Chin joins the rebellion against the Manchu dynasty.
</Question>
<Choice>1898</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Kansas, Carry Nation begins her campaign to close saloons; she attacks bars with her hatchet.
</Question>
<Choice>1899</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Korean women organize Yo-u-hoe, the Association of Women Friends, to fight against concubinage.
</Question>
<Choice>1899</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Florence Kelley and the National Consumer's League campaign against child labour and sweatshops and in favour of minimum wage legislation, shorter hours, improved conditions, and safety laws.
</Question>
<Choice>1899</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Efficiency expert and industrial psychologist Lillian Gilbreth is the first female commencement speaker at the University of California at Berkeley.
</Question>
<Choice>1900</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British tennis player Charlotte Cooper wins the first women's gold medal at the Olympics.
</Question>
<Choice>1900</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Japan, Doctor Yoshioka Yayoi founds the country's first medical school for women.
</Question>
<Choice>1900</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japan's Women's College is founded in Tokyo. Many of the women who graduate will participate in the beginning of Japanese feminism.
</Question>
<Choice>1901</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Chicago, glovemaker Agnes Nestor helps found the International Glove Workers Union (IGWU).
</Question>
<Choice>1902</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ida Tarbell begins publishing her The History of the Standard Oil Company in McClure's Magazine. Her exposé will contribute to the breakup of the company by Supreme Court order in 1911.
</Question>
<Choice>1902</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The British Parliament passes the Midwives Act, requiring licensing of midwives.
</Question>
<Choice>1902</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Women's Trade Union League (WTUL) is founded by Mary Kimball Kehew, Mary Kennedy O'Sullivan, Jane Addams, and other middle-class reformers to help working women organize.
</Question>
<Choice>1903</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In French law, women are no longer permanent minors.
</Question>
<Choice>1904</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Lillian D. Wald, Florence Kelley, and other reformers establish the National Child Labor Committee to work for anti-child labour legislation.
</Question>
<Choice>1904</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Helen Keller is the first deaf and blind woman to graduate from Radcliffe College. She graduates cum laude.
</Question>
<Choice>1904</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In England, socialist Beatrice Webb becomes a member of the Royal Commission on the Poor Laws.
</Question>
<Choice>1905</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Iran, Mohtaram Eskandari starts the first women's organization, the Union of Patriotic Women. Religious leaders break up the first meeting, and they burn some of the women alive.
</Question>
<Choice>1905</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Women in Finland get the right to vote.</Question>
<Choice>1906</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian revolutionary Mariya Spiridonova assassinates General Luzhenovsky.
</Question>
<Choice>1906</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Anarchist Emma Goldman begins publishing Mother Earth magazine.
</Question>
<Choice>1906</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Miina Sillanpaa is elected to the Finnish Parliament.
</Question>
<Choice>1907</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Margaret Slocum Sage donates $10 million to endow the Russell Sage Foundation to sponsor research to improve United States social conditions.
</Question>
<Choice>1907</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hannah Schoff organizes the International Conference on Child Welfare in Washington, D.C.
</Question>
<Choice>1908</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On October 13, a mob of women storm the British Parliament demanding suffrage. Twenty-four of them are arrested.
</Question>
<Choice>1908</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Muller v. Oregon, the United States Supreme Court sustains a state law limiting the workday for women factory employees in Oregon to 10 hours.
</Question>
<Choice>1908</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Iran, the government institutes a plan to increase women's literacy.
</Question>
<Choice>1908</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>The Sri Lanka Tamil Women's Union is created.</Question>
<Choice>1909</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mary White Ovington and Ida Wells-Barnett help found the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP).
</Question>
<Choice>1909</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In New York, shirtwaist workers go on strike. The International Ladies' Garment Workers Union (ILGWU) and the Women's Trade Union League work together in support of the strike.
</Question>
<Choice>1909</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In England, suffragists go on hunger strikes in prisons.
</Question>
<Choice>1911</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Marie Curie is awarded the Nobel Prize for Chemistry for the isolation of pure radium.
</Question>
<Choice>1911</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Journalist Kalliroe Parren establishes the Lyceum of Greek Women.
</Question>
<Choice>1911</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In New York City, a fire in the Triangle Shirtwaist Company building kills 146 workers, most of them young women. The doors had been locked to prevent theft.
</Question>
<Choice>1911</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Juliette Low founds the Girl Guides (later Girl Scouts). By 1927 there will be a troop in every state.
</Question>
<Choice>1912</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Maria Paz Mendoxa-Guason becomes the first Filipina doctor.
</Question>
<Choice>1912</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Norwegian women get the right to vote.</Question>
<Choice>1913</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On February 24, English suffragist Emmeline Pankhurst is arrested for conspiracy to blow up Lloyd George's home. While in jail, she goes on a hunger strike.
</Question>
<Choice>1913</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Washington, D.C., Alice Paul and the National American Women's Suffrage Association organize a huge march on the Capitol the day before President Woodrow Wilson's inaugural.
</Question>
<Choice>1913</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Russia, Princess Eugenie Shakhovskaya is the first female military pilot. She flies reconnaissance missions.
</Question>
<Choice>1914</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Aleksandra Kollontay publishes The Social Foundations of the Women's Question.
</Question>
<Choice>1914</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Activist Margaret Sanger is indicted under the Comstock Act for distributing a birth control pamphlet titled Family Limitation.
</Question>
<Choice>1914</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>In Denmark, women win the right to vote.</Question>
<Choice>1915</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Carrie Chapman Catt and Jane Addams combine several pacifist organizations to create the Women's Peace Party.
</Question>
<Choice>1915</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
From April 28 to May 1, the International Congress of Women meets at The Hague to consider ways to end World War I.
</Question>
<Choice>1915</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The British government recruits 400,000 women to work in agriculture while men are at war.
</Question>
<Choice>1916</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jeannette Rankin is elected to Congress from Montana; she is the first female member of the House of Representatives.
</Question>
<Choice>1916</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
María Jesús Alvarado Rivera establishes Evolución Femenina, Peru's first women's organization.
</Question>
<Choice>1916</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Soon after coming to power in Russia, the Bolsheviks reform marriage laws, create maternity leave, and establish equal employment and wages.
</Question>
<Choice>1917</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Cuba, new laws protect women's custody of children, divorce rights, and property rights.
</Question>
<Choice>1917</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
When the United States enters World War I, the Army Nurse Corps has 8,000 trained nurses ready to serve because of the work of Jane Delano.
</Question>
<Choice>1917</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The United States Navy hires 12,000 women as clerks in the same job classifications and for the same pay as men so that it can send men overseas.
</Question>
<Choice>1917</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Japan, Kimura Komako arranges the first woman suffrage meeting.
</Question>
<Choice>1917</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On April 9, 100,000 Russian soldiers' wives march to demand more food.
</Question>
<Choice>1917</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Canada gives women the right to vote. In Great Britain, women over 30 get the right to vote.
</Question>
<Choice>1918</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Indian National Congress endorses giving women the right to vote.
</Question>
<Choice>1918</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Peru, the law grants working women two hours a day to nurse their infants.
</Question>
<Choice>1918</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On March 29, the United States government reports that 1.4 million women work in war industries. After the war these women are forced out of industrial work.
</Question>
<Choice>1918</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Britain, birth control activist Marie Stopes publishes the controversial and best-selling books Married Love and Wise Parenthood.
</Question>
<Choice>1918</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Belgium, Luxembourg, Austria, The Netherlands, Sweden, Germany, and Poland, women get the right to vote.
</Question>
<Choice>1919</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Lady Astor becomes the first female member of the British House of Commons.
</Question>
<Choice>1919</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Chile, the National Council of Women is created to agitate for women's rights.
</Question>
<Choice>1919</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Japan, Hiratsuka Raicho, Oku Mumeo, and Ichikawa Fusae found the Shin Fujin Kyokai (“Association of New Women”) to work for women's unions and equal rights.
</Question>
<Choice>1919</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Treaty of Versailles includes a requirement that women receive equal pay. The clause is universally ignored.
</Question>
<Choice>1919</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On August 26, the 19th Amendment to the Constitution is signed into law, giving women in the United States the right to vote.
</Question>
<Choice>1920</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Despite death threats from the Ku Klux Klan, Mary McLeod Bethune begins a voter registration drive for black women.
</Question>
<Choice>1920</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Edith Eder from Hungary, Rebecca Sief from Britain, and Vera Weizmann from Russia found the Women's International Zionist Organization (WIZO).
</Question>
<Choice>1920</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
University of Oxford admits its first full-degree female students.
</Question>
<Choice>1920</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Joan of Arc is canonized.</Question>
<Choice>1920</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Agnes McPhail becomes the first female Canadian member of Parliament.
</Question>
<Choice>1921</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Grace Abbott becomes head of the United States Children's Bureau. She works for laws against child labour and for better health care for children and mothers.
</Question>
<Choice>1921</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The German Nazi Party excludes women from membership.
</Question>
<Choice>1921</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Margaret Sanger and Mary Ware Dennett found the American Birth Control League, which later becomes the Planned Parenthood Federation of America.
</Question>
<Choice>1921</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Berth Lutx founds the Brazilian Federation for the Advancement of Women.
</Question>
<Choice>1922</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Rebecca Ann Latimer Felton becomes the first woman to serve in the United States Senate. She serves only two days.
</Question>
<Choice>1922</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Egypt, feminist Huda Shaarawi unveils publicly and inspires many other women to do the same.
</Question>
<Choice>1923</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In China, women lead demonstrations after Sun Yat-sen's National Congress denies them suffrage.
</Question>
<Choice>1924</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first women's college in Korea, Ewha Woman's College, offers only two subjects: music and liberal arts.
</Question>
<Choice>1925</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
New Argentine legislation gives women equality under the civil code.
</Question>
<Choice>1926</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Bessie Coleman, the first black woman aviator, dies in a plane crash.
</Question>
<Choice>1926</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American figure skater Sonja Henie wins her first world amateur championship. She will win the next nine championships and gold medals at the Olympics in 1928, 1932, and 1936.
</Question>
<Choice>1927</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Women's Industrial League, the National Council of Jewish Women, the YWCA, and the National Council of Catholic Women unite against new restrictive United States immigration laws.
</Question>
<Choice>1927</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Zora Neale Hurston becomes the first African-American graduate of Barnard College.
</Question>
<Choice>1928</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Margaret Grace Bondfield becomes minister of labour; she is the first British female Cabinet minister.
</Question>
<Choice>1929</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Virginia Woolf publishes A Room of One's Own.</Question>
<Choice>1929</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>White South African women get the right to vote.</Question>
<Choice>1930</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jessie Daniel Ames establishes the Association of Southern Women for the Prevention of Lynching (ASWPL).
</Question>
<Choice>1930</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Ellen Church is the first airline stewardess.</Question>
<Choice>1930</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Jane Addams receives the Nobel Prize for Peace.</Question>
<Choice>1931</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Brazil and Thailand, women get the right to vote.
</Question>
<Choice>1932</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On May 20, Amelia Earhart is the first woman to fly solo across the Atlantic.
</Question>
<Choice>1932</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Frances Perkins is appointed secretary of labor by Franklin D. Roosevelt, becoming the first American female Cabinet member.
</Question>
<Choice>1933</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Portugal's new constitution specifically denies women's equal rights.
</Question>
<Choice>1933</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Nazi Germany, girls are inducted into the Jungmädel (“Young Maidens”) and Bund Deutscher Mädel (“League of German Girls”). The organizations stress the importance of virtue and motherhood.
</Question>
<Choice>1933</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Italy, Mussolini rewards women who have more than 14 children.
</Question>
<Choice>1933</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Cuban law requires equal pay for equal work.</Question>
<Choice>1934</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Anthropologist Margaret Mead publishes Sex and Temperament in Three Primitive Societies, challenging Western assumptions about gender relations.
</Question>
<Choice>1935</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American First Lady Eleanor Roosevelt begins publishing her syndicated column, "My Day."
</Question>
<Choice>1936</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British pilot Beryl Markham is the first person to fly solo across the Atlantic from east to west.
</Question>
<Choice>1936</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Women in the Philippines get the right to vote.</Question>
<Choice>1937</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The American Medical Association recognizes birth control as a legitimate topic for medical school classes.
</Question>
<Choice>1937</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In France, women are admitted into unarmed military divisions.
</Question>
<Choice>1938</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German dictator Adolf Hitler prohibits all independent women's organizations.
</Question>
<Choice>1939</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On April 9, Marian Anderson gives a concert at the Lincoln Memorial after the Daughters of the American Revolution refused to allow her to sing at Constitution Hall.
</Question>
<Choice>1939</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Republican Party comes out in support of the Equal Rights Amendment.
</Question>
<Choice>1940</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the Soviet Union, three regiments of all female pilots are created. The most highly decorated is the 586th Women's Fighter Regiment.
</Question>
<Choice>1941</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pacifist Jeannette Rankin is the only congressperson to vote against United States entry into World War II.
</Question>
<Choice>1941</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the United States, women enter the Women's Army Corps (WAC) and Women Accepted for Voluntary Emergency Service (WAVES).
</Question>
<Choice>1942</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Elise Richter, the first female professor in Austria, dies in the Nazi concentration camp at Theresienstadt.
</Question>
<Choice>1942</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The All-American Girls Professional Baseball League is founded by Chicago Cubs owner Philip Wrigley.
</Question>
<Choice>1943</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Over 310,000 women have jobs in the United States aircraft industry. Wartime propaganda urges women to join the labour force for the duration of the war.
</Question>
<Choice>1943</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Physicist Elda Anderson is one of the scientists recruited to work at Los Alamos on the development of the atomic bomb.
</Question>
<Choice>1943</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nellie Nielson is the first female president of the American Historical Association.
</Question>
<Choice>1944</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian Muslim Noor un Nissa is shot by the Gestapo. She was the first British secret agent in the Nazi Party.
</Question>
<Choice>1944</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In March, Anne Frank dies in the Nazi concentration camp at Bergen-Belsen. Her father has her diary of their years spent in hiding published in 1947.
</Question>
<Choice>1945</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Eleanor Roosevelt becomes a delegate to the newly created United Nations.
</Question>
<Choice>1945</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
During World War II, over six million American women enter the workforce; they are pushed back out of traditionally male jobs at war's end.
</Question>
<Choice>1945</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Queen Homaina organizes the Women's Society, the first women's association in Afghanistan.
</Question>
<Choice>1946</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Sudan's first modern women's organization, the Sudanese Women's League, is founded.
</Question>
<Choice>1946</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Japan, the new constitution guarantees women's equality.
</Question>
<Choice>1947</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the United States, the Army-Navy Nurse Act creates permanent commissions for military nurses. The first officer commission goes to Florence Blanchfield.
</Question>
<Choice>1947</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the newly created nations of Israel and South Korea, women win the right to vote.
</Question>
<Choice>1948</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Argentina, Eva Perón founds the Peronista Feminist Party.
</Question>
<Choice>1949</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French feminist Simone de Beauvoir publishes the controversial and influential Le Deuxième Sexe (The Second Sex).
</Question>
<Choice>1949</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American author and activist Pearl S. Buck founds Welcome House, an organization to arrange adoptions of Asian-American children.
</Question>
<Choice>1949</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Harvard Law School admits women.</Question>
<Choice>1949</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The United States Census Bureau recognizes a woman's right to continue to use her maiden name after marriage.
</Question>
<Choice>1950</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Israel, the Women's Equal Rights Act prohibits gender discrimination.
</Question>
<Choice>1951</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ana Figueroa from Chile becomes the first woman on the United Nations Security Council.
</Question>
<Choice>1952</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On June 2, Queen Elizabeth II's coronation takes place in Westminster Abbey.
</Question>
<Choice>1953</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Colombian women get the right to vote.</Question>
<Choice>1954</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Rosa Parks's arrest for refusing to give up her seat on a bus to a white man sparks the Montgomery bus boycott. African-American women, the system's main users, support the boycott.
</Question>
<Choice>1955</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Golda Meir becomes Israel's minister of foreign affairs. She is the only woman in the Cabinet.
</Question>
<Choice>1956</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The British House of Lords admits its first female members.
</Question>
<Choice>1958</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mary Leakey, working with her husband, Louis, discovers the skull of an early hominid in Tanzania's Olduvai Gorge. The find changes views about the age of human bipedalism.
</Question>
<Choice>1959</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Eleanor Roosevelt chairs President John F. Kennedy's Commission on the Status of Women.
</Question>
<Choice>1961</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Paraguay is the last republic in the Americas to give women the right to vote.
</Question>
<Choice>1961</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Septima Clark becomes the director of education and teaching for the Southern Christian Leadership Conference (SCLC).
</Question>
<Choice>1961</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Wilma Rudolph sets a new world record in the 100-metre dash, 11.2 seconds.
</Question>
<Choice>1961</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On November 1, American women organized by Women Strike for Peace stage a one-day strike asking the government to "End the Arms Race, Not the Human Race."
</Question>
<Choice>1961</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Rubye Doris Smith Robinson is arrested while participating in the Freedom Rides protesting segregation in transportation.
</Question>
<Choice>1961</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American writer Helen Gurley Brown publishes the best-selling Sex and the Single Girl.
</Question>
<Choice>1962</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biologist Rachel Carson publishes Silent Spring.
</Question>
<Choice>1962</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian cosmonaut Valentina Tereshkova becomes the first woman in space.
</Question>
<Choice>1963</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American writer Betty Friedan publishes her highly influential The Feminine Mystique.
</Question>
<Choice>1963</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Yale Law School gives tenure to a woman, Ellen Ash Peters, for the first time.
</Question>
<Choice>1963</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Civil Rights Act of 1964 prohibits discrimination in employment on the basis of race, creed, national origin, or sex.
</Question>
<Choice>1964</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The United States Army's first women in Vietnam, Major Kathleen Wilkes and Master Sergeant Betty Adams, are made advisers to Vietnam's new Women's Armed Forces Corps.
</Question>
<Choice>1965</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The United States Supreme Court rules, in Griswold v. Connecticut, that laws prohibiting the use of birth control are unconstitutional.
</Question>
<Choice>1965</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
National Organization for Women (NOW) is founded by Betty Friedan and other delegates to the Third National Conference of State Commissions on the Status of Women.
</Question>
<Choice>1966</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indira Gandhi becomes head of the Congress Party and the first female prime minister of India.
</Question>
<Choice>1966</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Muriel Siebert becomes the first woman to own a seat on the New York Stock Exchange.
</Question>
<Choice>1967</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On January 15, women in the American peace movement, organized into the Jeannette Rankin Brigade, march on Washington in opposition to the Vietnam War.
</Question>
<Choice>1968</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nguyen Thi Binh, a member of the Central Committee of the National Liberation Front, leads the Vietnamese delegation to the Paris peace conference.
</Question>
<Choice>1968</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Shirley Chisholm becomes the first black woman elected to Congress.
</Question>
<Choice>1968</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Japan, author Michiko Ishumure starts a movement against pollution by publishing Kukai Jodo ("Sea of Suffering"), documenting the damage done by dumping mercury into Minamata Bay.
</Question>
<Choice>1968</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Civil rights activist Anne Moody publishes her autobiography, Coming of Age in Mississippi.
</Question>
<Choice>1968</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Ecuador, a "malaria control" program is used as a cover to sterilize peasant women.
</Question>
<Choice>1969</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Golda Meir becomes the first female prime minister of Israel.
</Question>
<Choice>1969</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Angela Davis is fired from her teaching job at the University of California at Los Angeles for being a communist.
</Question>
<Choice>1970</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Marie Cox founds the North American Indian Women's Association, the first national Native American women's group.
</Question>
<Choice>1970</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Germaine Greer publishes her controversial The Female Eunuch, in which she advocates greater sexual freedom for women.
</Question>
<Choice>1970</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Labour organizer Dolores Huerta becomes vice president of the United Farm Workers.
</Question>
<Choice>1970</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Boston Women's Health Book Collective publishes Our Bodies, Ourselves.
</Question>
<Choice>1970</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The National Commission on the Status of Women in India is created.
</Question>
<Choice>1971</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Helga Pederson of Denmark becomes the first female judge on the European Court of Human Rights.
</Question>
<Choice>1971</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Women in Switzerland get the right to vote.</Question>
<Choice>1971</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The United States Senate approves the Equal Rights Amendment and sends it to the states for ratification.
</Question>
<Choice>1972</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The National Conference of Puerto Rican Women is founded.
</Question>
<Choice>1972</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>The first issue of Ms. magazine is published.</Question>
<Choice>1972</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Tennis champion Billie Jean King defeats champion player Bobby Riggs in a "Battle of the Sexes" match.
</Question>
<Choice>1973</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Women in Jordan get the right to vote.</Question>
<Choice>1973</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Nicaragua, mothers of political prisoners go on a hunger strike.
</Question>
<Choice>1973</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The United States Supreme Court rules in Roe v. Wade that a woman has a constitutional right to abortion.
</Question>
<Choice>1973</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
California makes it legal for women to use the title Ms. rather than Mrs. or Miss.
</Question>
<Choice>1974</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first U.S. service academy to enroll women is the United States Merchant Marine Academy.
</Question>
<Choice>1974</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>The League of Women Voters begins to admit men.</Question>
<Choice>1974</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The United States Supreme Court rules that women cannot be excluded from juries because of their sex.
</Question>
<Choice>1975</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Berlin, the World Congress for International Women's Year opens with almost 2,000 delegates from 141 countries.
</Question>
<Choice>1975</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Barbara Jordan, the first black woman elected to Congress from the Deep South, becomes the first black and the first woman to give the keynote speech at the Democratic National Convention.
</Question>
<Choice>1976</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Labour minister Tina Anselmi is the first woman in the Italian Cabinet.
</Question>
<Choice>1976</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Betty Williams and Mairéad Corrigan-Maguire found the Peace People Organization, a joint Catholic-Protestant group, after three children are killed during fighting between British soldiers and the IRA.
</Question>
<Choice>1976</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Canadian law prohibits discrimination on the basis of sex or marital status.
</Question>
<Choice>1977</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Women in Nigeria get the right to vote.</Question>
<Choice>1977</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Saudi Arabia, Princess Misha is executed for marrying a man she chose.
</Question>
<Choice>1977</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In El Salvador, women establish the Committee of Mothers of Political Prisoners and Frente Femenino (“Woman's Front”).
</Question>
<Choice>1977</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman women demonstrate against rape, beginning a campaign to change rape laws.
</Question>
<Choice>1977</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Argentina, mothers of "disappeared" political prisoners begin a series of vigils.
</Question>
<Choice>1977</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Shere Hite publishes The Hite Report on women's sexuality, which becomes a best-seller.
</Question>
<Choice>1977</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Kuwaiti women successfully demonstrate against a proposed law prohibiting women from office work.
</Question>
<Choice>1978</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Margaret Thatcher becomes the first female prime minister of Great Britain.
</Question>
<Choice>1979</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The First Congress of São Paolo Women starts the Brazilian day-care movement.
</Question>
<Choice>1979</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Federal Bureau of Investigation estimates that a rape occurs every six minutes in the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>1980</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the United States, the first Conference of the National Coalition Against Domestic Violence is held.
</Question>
<Choice>1980</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
New guidelines from the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission prohibit sexual harassment.
</Question>
<Choice>1980</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Gdansk, Poland, 3,000 women defy tanks to pass out flowers and Solidarity literature.
</Question>
<Choice>1980</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sandra Day O'Connor becomes the first woman on the United States Supreme Court.
</Question>
<Choice>1981</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At Greenham Common, 20,000 British women protest the placement of cruise and Pershing missiles there.
</Question>
<Choice>1982</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Iran, women are now required to wear the chador; the sentence for appearing unveiled is prison for 1 to 12 months.
</Question>
<Choice>1983</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Geraldine Ferraro is named Walter Mondale's vice presidential running mate. This is the first time a major American political party nominates a woman for the vice presidency.
</Question>
<Choice>1984</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Santiago, Chile, women demonstrate against the repression of General Augusto Pinochet.
</Question>
<Choice>1985</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The United States Supreme Court upholds affirmative action on the basis of race or gender.
</Question>
<Choice>1986</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Japan, the Supreme Court rules that marital rape is a crime.
</Question>
<Choice>1987</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Benazir Bhutto becomes prime minister of Pakistan.</Question>
<Choice>1988</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American Barbara Harris becomes the first female Episcopal bishop.
</Question>
<Choice>1989</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Canadian women gain access to all combat posts in the military except submarine duty because of a lawsuit filed in 1981 by Isabelle Gauthier.
</Question>
<Choice>1989</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Saudi Arabia, women drive cars in Riyadh to protest laws preventing them from operating motor vehicles. They are imprisoned and fired from their jobs.
</Question>
<Choice>1990</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Violeta Barrios de Chamorro is elected president of Nicaragua, defeating the Sandinistas.
</Question>
<Choice>1990</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Nobel Prize for Peace is awarded to Burmese opposition leader Aung San Suu Kyi.
</Question>
<Choice>1991</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Irish vote to allow free access to abortion information and the right to go abroad to obtain abortions.
</Question>
<Choice>1992</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Janet Reno becomes the first female United States attorney general.
</Question>
<Choice>1993</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ruth Bader Ginsburg becomes the second female United States Supreme Court justice.
</Question>
<Choice>1993</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Turkey, Tansu Ciller becomes her country's first female prime minister.
</Question>
<Choice>1993</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Kim Campbell becomes the first woman prime minister of Canada.
</Question>
<Choice>1993</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hisako Takahashi becomes the first woman justice on Japan's Supreme Court.
</Question>
<Choice>1994</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The United Nations' Fourth World Conference on Women meets in Beijing, China, from September 4 to 15.
</Question>
<Choice>1995</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Afghanistan the ruling Taliban government places strict restrictions on women, forbidding them from working outside the home and receiving an education.
</Question>
<Choice>1996</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A report on female genital mutilation (FGM) urges international action to end the ancient, right-of-passage ritual that has been performed on more than 85 million women worldwide.
</Question>
<Choice>1996</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the United States two new professional women's basketball leagues debut to much fanfare.
</Question>
<Choice>1997</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sonia Gandhi, the Italian-born widow of former Indian prime minister Rajiv Gandhi, is unanimously elected to lead India's Congress Party.
</Question>
<Choice>1998</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mireya Moscoso becomes the first female president of Panama and in December oversees the U.S. handover of the Panama Canal.
</Question>
<Choice>1999</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Elizabeth Dole resigns her position as president of the Red Cross in January to explore a run for the Republican nomination for U.S. president.
</Question>
<Choice>1999</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Beverley McLachlin becomes Canada's first woman Supreme Court chief justice. Some 70 years earlier, the same court had ruled that women were not "persons."
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Tarja Halonen becomes the first woman president of Finland.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At the Sydney Olympics, American athlete Marion Jones becomes the first woman to win five medals in track-and-field events at a single Games; she is stripped of her medals in 2007 after admitting to taking steriods.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sirimavo Bandaranaike of Sri Lanka, the world's first female prime minister, retires in August.
</Question>
<Choice>2000</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hillary Clinton is sworn in as a New York senator, becoming the first first lady to win elected office.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Katherine Graham, former publisher of the Washington Post, dies. She was the first woman to head a Fortune 500 company and at one time was considered the most powerful woman in the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Voters in Bahrain approve a referendum that includes giving women the right to vote.
</Question>
<Choice>2001</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Halle Berry becomes the first African American woman to win an Oscar for best actress. She is honored for her gritty performance in Monster's Ball.
</Question>
<Choice>2002</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Britain's Queen Elizabeth celebrates her Golden Jubilee, marking 50 years on the throne.
</Question>
<Choice>2002</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Iranian lawyer and activist Shirin Ebadi becomes the first Muslim woman to be awarded the Nobel Peace Prize. She is honored for her work promoting democracy and human rights.
</Question>
<Choice>2003</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American bluegrass fiddler and singer Alison Krauss wins 3 Grammy Awards, bringing her total number of Grammys to 17, the most won by a female recording artist.
</Question>
<Choice>2004</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Rosa Martinez and Maria de Corral become the first female curators to preside over the Venice Biennale in the 110-year history of the renowned art exhibition.
</Question>
<Choice>2005</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ellen Johnson-Sirleaf is sworn in as president of Liberia, becoming the first woman elected to head an African country.
</Question>
<Choice>2006</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Historian Drew G. Faust is the first woman elected president of Harvard University.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nancy Pelosi becomes the first woman to serve as speaker of the U.S. House of Representatives.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pratibha Patil becomes the first woman president of India.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Benazir Bhutto, former prime minister of Pakistan who was the first woman leader of a Muslim country in modern times, is assassinated shortly after her return to Pakistan following eight years of self-imposed exile.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
For the first time in UN peacekeeping history, an all-female unit is deployed. The force of more than 100 Indian policewomen is sent to Liberia to train police and to assist with local elections and prison security.
</Question>
<Choice>2007</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Church of England's General Synod votes to allow women to be ordained as bishops.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Gen. Ann Dunwoody becomes the first woman to serve as a four-star general in the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>2008</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Michelle Obama becomes the first African American first lady after her husband, Barack Obama, is sworn in as the 44th president of the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sonia Sotomayor is sworn in as an associate justice of the U.S. Supreme Court; she is the first Hispanic and third woman to serve on the court.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A U.S. government panel announces that women who are not at an increased risk of breast cancer should begin receiving regular mammograms at age 50, instead of the previously recommended age of 40.
</Question>
<Choice>2009</Choice>
</item>
</topics>