<topics>
<item>
<Question>
a distinguished Muslim astronomer and mathematician, who made important contributions to the development of trigonometry.Abu?l-Wafa? worked in a private observatory in Baghdad, where he made observations to determine, among other astronomical parameters, the obliquity of the ecliptic, the length of the seasons, and the latitude of the city. He also worked with astronomers in Khwarezm (now in Uzbekistan) to determine the difference in longitude between the two localities by means of the simultaneous observation of a lunar eclipse. He did not, as is sometimes claimed, discover the inequality in...
</Question>
<Choice>Abu'l-Wafa'</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British mathematician and astronomer, one of two people who independently discovered the planet Neptune. On July 3, 1841, Adams had entered in his journal: “Formed a design in the beginning of this week of investigating, as soon as possible after taking my degree, the irregularities in the motion of Uranus . . . in order to find out whether they may be attributed to the action of an undiscovered planet beyond it. . . .” In September 1845 he gave James Challis, director of the Cambridge Observatory, accurate information on where the new planet, as yet unobserved, could be found; but unfortunate...
</Question>
<Choice>Adams, John Couch</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronomer who is best known for his spectroscopic studies. Using the spectroscope, he investigated sunspots and the rotation of the Sun, the velocities and distances of thousands of stars, and planetary atmospheres.Born of missionary parents who returned to the United States when he was eight years old, Adams studied astronomy at Dartmouth College, Hanover, N.H.; the University of Chicago; and the University of Munich. In 1904 he became a member of the original staff of Mount Wilson Observatory in California, where he served as director from 1923 to 1946. Adams took an important part...
</Question>
<Choice>Adams, Walter Sydney</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English scientist who was astronomer royal from 1835 to 1881.Airy graduated from Trinity College, Cambridge, in 1823. He became Lucasian professor of mathematics at Cambridge in 1826 and Plumian professor of astronomy and director of the Cambridge observatory in 1828. In 1835 he was appointed the seventh astronomer royal, i.e., director of the Royal Greenwich Observatory, a post he would hold for more than 45 years.Airy completely reorganized the Greenwich observatory, installing new apparatus and rescuing thousands of lunar observations from oblivion. Most importantly, he modernized the obser...
</Question>
<Choice>Airy, Sir George Biddell</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronomer who specialized in the study of double stars, of which he discovered more than 3,000.From 1891 to 1895 Aitken was professor of mathematics and astronomy at the University of the Pacific, Stockton, Calif. In 1895 he joined the staff of Lick Observatory, Mt. Hamilton, Calif., as assistant astronomer, becoming associate director in 1923 and director in 1930; he retired in 1935. He published The Binary Stars (1918) and New General Catalogue of Double Stars Within 120° of the North Pole (1932).
</Question>
<Choice>Aitken, Robert Grant</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Soviet astronomer and astrophysicist best known for his theories concerning the origin and evolution of stars and stellar systems. He was also the founder of the school of theoretical astrophysics in the Soviet Union.Ambartsumian was born of Armenian parents. His father, a prominent philologist, encouraged the development of his aptitude for mathematics and physics. In 1925 he entered the University of Leningrad (now Saint Petersburg State University) with the intention of devoting his life to research in astrophysics, and in the following year he published a paper on solar activity, the first...
</Question>
<Choice>Ambartsumian, Viktor Amazaspovich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
astronomer and optician who made important improvements in the mirrors of reflecting telescopes and also developed prisms for use in refracting spectroscopes (instruments used to separate light into its spectral components).Amici served as professor of mathematics at the University of Modena from 1815 to 1825 and then became astronomer to the Grand Duke of Tuscany and director of the observatory at the Royal Museum in Florence, where he also lectured at the museum of natural history. He made major advancements in compound-microscope design and introduced (1840) the oil-immersion technique, in...
</Question>
<Choice>Amici, Giovanni Battista</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
theologian, mathematician, jurist, and astronomer who was a major figure in the cultural revival of ?afavid Iran.Al-?Amili was educated by his father, Shaykh ?usayn, a Shi?ite theologian, and by excellent teachers of mathematics and medicine. After his family left Syria in 1559 to escape persecution by the Ottoman Turks, al-?Amili lived in Herat (now in Afghanistan) and Isfahan, Iran. He attached himself to the court of ?Abbas I the Great, serving for many years as the shaykh al-Islam (chief judge of the Muslim court of law) of E?fahan, and writing during that time a treatise on Shi?ite jurisp...
</Question>
<Choice>Amili, Baha' ad-Din Muhammad ibn Husayn al-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek philosopher who was the first to develop a cosmology, or systematic philosophical view of the world.Only a short fragment of Anaximander's work survives, so reconstructions of his philosophy and astronomy must be based on summaries by later Greek writers, such as the 1st- or 2nd-century CE compiler of philosophical opinions Aëtius, the 3rd-century theologian and antipope Hippolytus, and the 6th-century Neoplatonist philosopher Simplicius. Anaximander is said to have been a pupil or associate of the Greek philosopher Thales of Miletus and to have written about astronomy, geography, and th...
</Question>
<Choice>Anaximander</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek astronomer best known as the architect of the horologium at Athens called the Tower of the Winds. Andronicus also built a multifaced sundial in the sanctuary of Poseidon on the Greek island of Tenos.
</Question>
<Choice>Andronicus of Cyrrhus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German astronomer who established the study of variable stars as an independent branch of astronomy and is renowned for his great catalog listing the positions and magnitudes of 324,188 stars. He studied at the University of Königsberg, Prussia, where he was a pupil and later the successor of German astronomer Friedrich Wilhelm Bessel. Argelander was appointed director of the Åbo (Turku) Observatory in Finland in 1823 and of the Helsinki Observatory in 1832. In 1837 he published a major investigation of the Sun's motion through space, improving on the methods of British astronomer William Hers...
</Question>
<Choice>Argelander, Friedrich Wilhelm August</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek astronomer who maintained that Earth rotates on its axis and revolves around the Sun. On this ground, the Greek philosopher Cleanthes the Stoic declared in his Against Aristarchus that Aristarchus ought to be indicted for impiety “for putting into motion the hearth of the universe.”Aristarchus's work on the motion of Earth has not survived, but his ideas are known from references by the Greek mathematician Archimedes, the Greek biographer Plutarch, and the Greek philosopher Sextus Empiricus. Archimedes said in his Sand-Reckoner that Aristarchus had proposed a new theory which, if true, w...
</Question>
<Choice>Aristarchus of Samos</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronomer noted for challenging the theory that redshifts of quasars indicate their great distance.Arp received a bachelor's degree from Harvard University in 1949 and a Ph.D. from the California Institute of Technology in 1953. He subsequently accepted a research fellowship to conduct postdoctoral studies at the nearby Hale Observatories (now Mount Wilson and Palomar observatories). After he worked as a research associate at Indiana University from 1955 to 1957, Arp returned to Mount Wilson, securing a post as an assistant astronomer on the observatory staff. He was appointed astron...
</Question>
<Choice>Arp, Halton Christian</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German astronomer who, while a student at the Berlin Observatory, hastened the discovery of Neptune by suggesting comparison of the sky, in the region indicated by Urbain Le Verrier's calculations, with a recently prepared star chart. The planet was found the same night.In 1851, while associated with the Leipzig Observatory, d'Arrest discovered a periodic comet that was subsequently named for him. In that same year he published a book on the 13 asteroids known at that time and began his studies of the nebulae for which he received the Gold Medal of the Royal Astronomical Society in 1875.
</Question>
<Choice>Arrest, Heinrich Louis d'</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
astronomer and the earliest Indian mathematician whose work and history are available to modern scholars. Known as Aryabhata I or Aryabhata the Elder to distinguish him from a 10th-century Indian mathematician of the same name, he flourished in Kusumapura—near Patalipurta (Patna), then the capital of the Gupta dynasty—where he composed at least two works, Aryabhatiya (c. 499) and the now lost Aryabhatasiddhanta. Aryabhatasiddhanta circulated mainly in the northwest of India and, through the Sasanian dynasty (224–651) of Iran, had a profound influence on the development of Islamic astronomy. It...
</Question>
<Choice>Aryabhata I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German astronomer known for his star catalogs.After receiving his Ph.D. in astronomy (1862) from the University of Königsberg, Auwers joined the Gotha Observatory. He became astronomer (1866) at the Academy of Science in Berlin and from 1878 served as its permanent secretary. From 1881 to 1889 Auwers was president of the Astronomical Society. He also was elected to the French Académie des Sciences.Auwers' observations and calculations allowed him to develop extremely accurate star catalogs. As part of this process, Auwers researched solar and stellar parallaxes, making a new reduction of James...
</Question>
<Choice>Auwers, Georg Friedrich Julius Arthur von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
astronomer who with his son Horace Welcome Babcock invented (1951) the solar magnetograph, an instrument allowing detailed observation of the Sun'smagnetic field. With their magnetograph the Babcocks demonstrated the existence of the Sun's general field and discovered magnetically variable stars. In 1959 Harold Babcock announced that the Sun reverses its magnetic polarity periodically. He was on the staff of Mount Wilson Observatory, California, from 1909, being semiretired from 1948.
</Question>
<Choice>Babcock, Harold Delos</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronomer who with his father, Harold Delos Babcock, invented the solar magnetograph, an instrument allowing detailed observation of the Sun's magnetic field.Horace Babcock attended the California Institute of Technology in Pasadena and the University of California. He worked at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology and at the California Institute of Technology before joining the staff of Mount Wilson and Palomar Mountain observatories in 1946; he served as director of the observatories from 1964 to 1978. In the 1950s, working with his father, he developed the solar magnetograph;...
</Question>
<Choice>Babcock, Horace Welcome</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English Franciscan philosopher and educational reformer who was a major medieval proponent of experimental science. Bacon studied mathematics, astronomy, optics, alchemy, and languages. He was the first European to describe in detail the process of making gunpowder, and he proposed flying machines and motorized ships and carriages. Bacon (as he himself complacently remarked) displayed a prodigious energy and zeal in the pursuit of experimental science; indeed, his studies were talked about everywhere and eventually won him a place in popular literature as a kind of wonder worker. Bacon therefo...
</Question>
<Choice>Bacon, Roger</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French astronomer noted for his computation of an orbit for Halley's Comet (1759) and for his studies of the four satellites of Jupiter then known. He was also a statesman who took part in the revolutionary events of his age.Bailly began his study of Halley's Comet in 1759. One year later he established an observatory where he could undertake observations of Jupiter's satellites. He was elected to the Académie des Sciences in 1763. His major works include Essai sur la théorie des satellites de Jupiter (1766; “Essay on the Theory of Jupiter's Satellites”) and Mémoires sur les inégalités de la l...
</Question>
<Choice>Bailly, Jean-Sylvain</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
astronomer who detected the phenomenon called “Baily's beads” during an annular eclipse of the Sun on May 15, 1836. His vivid description aroused new interest in the study of eclipses.Baily retired from a successful business career in 1825 and turned his energies to science. He had already, in 1820, taken a leading part in the foundation of the Royal Astronomical Society, which awarded him its Gold Medal in 1827 for his preparation of the society's catalog of 2,881 stars. His protests regarding the British Nautical Almanac, then notorious for its errors, were instrumental in bringing about its...
</Question>
<Choice>Baily, Francis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
astronomer noted for his observations of comets.Bainbridge practiced medicine at Ashby-de-la-Zouch from 1614 to 1618. Soon after he moved to London, he was appointed (1619) Savilian professor of astronomy at the University of Oxford, largely on the basis of his Astronomical Description of the Comet of 1618 (1619). Although this work accepted to a point the superstitious belief that comets appear as signs of impending disaster, in Antiprognosticon (1642) he recanted and vigorously denounced astrological superstition that based predictions on conjunctions of the planets and appearances of comets...
</Question>
<Choice>Bainbridge, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
astronomer who pioneered in celestial photography and who was the leading observational astronomer of his time.In 1889 he began to photograph the Milky Way with large-aperture lenses, revealing much new detail. He discovered 16 comets and Jupiter's fifth satellite (1892). In 1916 he discovered the star (Barnard's star) that has the greatest known proper motion (motion of an individual star relative to the other stars). He published a catalog of dark nebulae in 1919.From 1883 to 1887 he studied at Vanderbilt University, Nashville, and was in charge of the observatory there. In 1887 he was appoi...
</Question>
<Choice>Barnard, Edward Emerson</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Arab astronomer and mathematician who refined existing values for the length of the year and of the seasons, for the annual precession of the equinoxes, and for the inclination of the ecliptic. He showed that the position of the Sun's apogee, or farthest point from the Earth, is variable and that annular (central but incomplete) eclipses of the Sun are possible. He improved Ptolemy's astronomical calculations by replacing geometrical methods with trigonometry. From 877 he carried out many years of remarkably accurate observations at ar-Raqqah in Syria.Al-Battani was the best known of Arab astr...
</Question>
<Choice>Battani, al-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German astronomer whose book Uranometria (1603) promulgated a system of identifying all stars visible to the naked eye.Bayer entered Ingolstadt University in 1592 to study philosophy and later moved to Augsburg. He became a lawyer by profession but, like many of his time, took a curious interest in the new advances in astronomy, leading to his publication of Uranometria, a popular guide to the constellations. In 1612 he was appointed legal adviser to the city council of Augsburg.Before Bayer's work, star charts were based on Ptolemy's star catalog, which was incomplete and ambiguous. Bayer upd...
</Question>
<Choice>Bayer, Johann</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German banker and amateur astronomer who (with Johann Heinrich von Mädler) constructed the most complete map of the Moon of his time, Mappa Selenographica (1836). The first lunar map to be divided into quadrants, it contained a detailed representation of the Moon's face and was accompanied, in 1837, by a volume providing micrometric measurements of the diameters of 148 craters and the elevations of 830 mountains.The Mappa Selenographica remained unsurpassed until 1878, when J.F. Julius Schmidt's more detailed map appeared. Beer and Mädler also published (1830) a description and map of Mars tha...
</Question>
<Choice>Beer, Wilhelm</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German astronomer whose measurements of positions for about 50,000 stars and rigorous methods of observation (and correction of observations) took astronomy to a new level of precision. He was the first to measure accurately the parallax, and hence the distance, of a star other than the Sun.
</Question>
<Choice>Bessel, Friedrich Wilhelm</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian astronomer and mathematician who helped to disseminate the mathematical work of Aryabhata I (born 476).Little is known about the life of Bhaskara; I is appended to his name to distinguish him from a 12th-century Indian astronomer of the same name. In his writings there are clues to possible locations for his life, such as Valabhi, the capital of the Maitraka dynasty, and Ashmaka, a town in Andhra Pradesh and the location of a school of followers of Aryabhata. His fame rests on three treatises he composed on the works of Aryabhata. Two of these treatises, known today as Mahabhaskariya (“...
</Question>
<Choice>Bhaskara I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the leading mathematician of the 12th century, who wrote the first work with full and systematic use of the decimal number system.Bhaskara II was the lineal successor of the noted Indian mathematician Brahmagupta (598–c. 665) as head of an astronomical observatory at Ujjain, the leading mathematical centre of ancient India.In his mathematical works, particularly Lilavati (“The Beautiful”) and Bijaga?ita (“Seed Counting”), he not only used the decimal system but also compiled problems from Brahmagupta and others. He filled many of the gaps in Brahmagupta's work, especially in obtaining a genera...
</Question>
<Choice>Bhaskara II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Persian scholar and scientist, one of the most learned men of his age and an outstanding intellectual figure.Possessing a profound and original mind of encyclopaedic scope, al-Biruni had varying degrees of proficiency in a number of languages, including Khwarezmian (an eastern Middle Iranian language), Persian, Sanskrit, Hebrew, and Syriac, in addition to the Arabic in which he wrote. He applied his talents in many fields of knowledge, excelling particularly in astronomy, mathematics, chronology, physics, medicine, and history. He corresponded with the great philosopher Ibn Sina (Avicenna). So...
</Question>
<Choice>Biruni, al-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Britain's fourth Astronomer Royal.Bliss graduated from Pembroke College, Oxford (B.A., 1720; M.A., 1723), and became rector of St. Ebbe's, Oxford, in 1736. He succeeded Edmond Halley as Savilian professor of geometry at the University of Oxford in 1742 and was elected a fellow of the Royal Society the same year. A correspondent and occasional assistant of James Bradley, third Astronomer Royal, Bliss acted for him in observing the transit of Venus in 1761 and succeeded him as Astronomer Royal in 1762.
</Question>
<Choice>Bliss, Nathaniel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French lawyer and natural scientist who became especially known for his contributions to astronomy.After studies at the Collège Louis-le-Grand, a part of the University of Paris, Saron became legal counselor to the Parlement of Paris in 1748, master of requests in 1750, advocate general in 1753, a judicial president in 1755, and president of the Parlement of Paris in 1789 a few months prior to the outbreak of the French Revolution.Well-to-do, he became a patron of the sciences, financing the publication of the marquis de Laplace'sTheory of the Movement and Elliptic Figure of the Planets (1784)...
</Question>
<Choice>Bochart de Saron, Jean-Baptiste-Gaspard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German astronomer best known for his popularization of Bode's law, or the Titius-Bode rule, an empirical mathematical expression for the relative mean distances between the Sun and its planets.Bode founded in 1774 the well-known Astronomisches Jahrbuch (“Astronomic Yearbook”), 51 yearly volumes of which he compiled and issued. He became director of the Berlin Observatory in 1786 and withdrew from official life in 1825. Among his other publications was Uranographia (1801), a collection of 20 star maps accompanied by a catalog of 17,240 stars and nebulae. In 1776 he propounded a theory of the so...
</Question>
<Choice>Bode, Johann Elert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch-born American astronomer known for his work on the structure and evolution of the Milky Way Galaxy and for his study of “Bok globules,” small dark clouds observable against the background of bright nebulae. Bok suggested that these globules may be condensed clouds of interstellar gas and dust in the process of contracting into stars.Bok studied at the universities of Leiden and Groningen (Ph.D. 1932). He then pursued an academic career of research and teaching at Harvard University (1929–57), the Australian National University (1957–66), and the University of Arizona (1966–74), remaining...
</Question>
<Choice>Bok, Bart Jan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronomer who, with his son George Phillips Bond (1825–65), discovered Hyperion, the eighth satellite of Saturn, and an inner ring called Ring C, or the Crepe Ring. They also took some of the first recognizable photographs of celestial objects.Largely self-educated, Bond was a watchmaker who became interested in astronomy after observing the solar eclipse of 1806. He built a home observatory that was one of the finest in the United States at that time. Bond independently discovered many comets, and in recognition of his efforts, he was appointed the first astronomical observer at Har...
</Question>
<Choice>Bond, William Cranch</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician and nautical astronomer noted for his studies of fluid mechanics and his development of instruments for navigation and geodesy, the study of the size and shape of the Earth.Borda entered the French army at an early age and later transferred to the navy, where he attained the rank of capitaine de vaisseau (“post captain”), took part in several scientific voyages, and played a role in the American Revolution. Borda developed and used many instruments for measuring an arc of a meridian, or longitude line, and helped introduce the metric system into France. He applied his stud...
</Question>
<Choice>Borda, Jean-Charles de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
astronomer and mathematician who gave the first geometric procedure for determining the equator of a rotating planet from three observations of a surface feature and for computing the orbit of a planet from three observations of its position.Boscovich's father was a Croat (some sources say Serb) and his mother was Italian. He entered the Society of Jesus (Jesuits) in 1726 and studied mathematics and physics at the Collegium Romanum, Rome, where he was appointed professor of mathematics in 1740. One of the first scientists of continental Europe to accept Isaac Newton's gravitational theory, he...
</Question>
<Choice>Boscovich, Ruggero Giuseppe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronomer best known for his compilation of star catalogs.Boss worked for the U.S. government at Washington, D.C., and on a survey of the U.S.-Canadian border. In 1876 he became director of the Dudley Observatory at Albany, and in 1882 he led an expedition to Chile to observe a transit of Venus. About 1895 Boss began to plan a general catalog of stars, giving their positions and motions. The project was supported by the Carnegie Institution, Washington, D.C., after 1906. With an enlarged staff he observed the northern stars from Albany and the southern stars from Argentina. With the...
</Question>
<Choice>Boss, Lewis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
versatile French scientist best remembered as one of the founders of photometry, the measurement of light intensities.Bouguer was a prodigy trained by his father, Jean Bouguer, in hydrography and mathematics. Upon his father's death, Pierre—at age 15—succeeded the elder Bouguer as royal professor of hydrography. During the 1720s he made some of the earliest measurements in astronomical photometry, comparing the apparent brightness of celestial objects to that of a standard candle flame. In 1735 he set off on an expedition with C.M. de la Condamine to measure an arc of the meridian near the equ...
</Question>
<Choice>Bouguer, Pierre</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
astronomer and director of the Paris Observatory, who is noted for discovering eight comets and writing Tables astronomiques of Jupiter and Saturn (1808) and of Uranus (1821). Bouvard's tables accurately predicted orbital locations of Jupiter and Saturn, but his tables for Uranus failed, leading him to hypothesize that irregularities in Uranus' motion were caused by the influence of an unknown celestial body. In 1846, three years after Bouvard's death, his hypothesis was confirmed by the discovery of Neptune by John Couch Adams and Urbain-Jean-Joseph Le Verrier. Bouvard was elected to the Acad...
</Question>
<Choice>Bouvard, Alexis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
self-educated American mathematician and astronomer, author of the best American book on navigation of his time and translator from the French of Pierre-Simon Laplace's Celestial Mechanics.Bowditch's formal education ended when he was 10 years old and family circumstances forced him to work, first for two years in his father's cooperage shop and then as a clerk for various local shops. Between 1795 and 1799 Bowditch made four lengthy sea voyages, and in 1802 he was put in command of a merchant vessel. Throughout that period he pursued his interest in mathematics. After investigating the accura...
</Question>
<Choice>Bowditch, Nathaniel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English astronomer who in 1728 announced his discovery of the aberration of starlight, an apparent slight change in the positions of stars caused by the yearly motion of the Earth. That finding provided the first direct evidence for the revolution of the Earth around the Sun.Bradley was educated at Balliol College, Oxford, where he received the B.A. in 1714 and the M.A. in 1717. He was instructed in observational astronomy at Wanstead, Essex, by his uncle, the Rev. James Pound, clergyman and skilled amateur astronomer, who introduced him to the famous astronomer Edmond Halley.Bradley's scienti...
</Question>
<Choice>Bradley, James</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Danish astronomer whose work in developing astronomical instruments and in measuring and fixing the positions of stars paved the way for future discoveries. His observations—the most accurate possible before the invention of the telescope—included a comprehensive study of the solar system and accurate positions of more than 777 fixed stars.
</Question>
<Choice>Brahe, Tycho</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
one of the most accomplished of the ancient Indian astronomers. He also had a profound and direct influence on Islamic and Byzantine astronomy.Brahmagupta was an orthodox Hindu, and his religious views, particularly the Hindu yuga system of measuring the ages of mankind, influenced his work. He severely criticized Jain cosmological views and other heterodox ideas, such as the view of Aryabhata I (b. 476) that the Earth is a spinning sphere, a view that was widely disseminated by Brahmagupta's contemporary and rival Bhaskara I.Brahmagupta's fame rests mostly on his Brahma-sphuta-siddhanta (628;...
</Question>
<Choice>Brahmagupta</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British soldier and astronomical observer for whom the city of Brisbane, Australia, is named. Mainly remembered as a patron of science, he built an astronomical observatory at Parramatta, Australia, and a combined observatory and magnetic station at Makerstoun, Roxburghshire, Scotland.Brisbane entered the army in 1789 and served in Flanders, the West Indies, Canada, and Spain. (His military services were rewarded with a knighthood in 1814.) He first decided to master astronomy in 1795, when a navigational error almost resulted in a shipwreck on his first voyage to the West Indies. In 1821 he w...
</Question>
<Choice>Brisbane, Sir Thomas Makdougall</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch-born U.S. astronomer and geophysicist known for his achievements in celestial mechanics, especially for his pioneering application of high-speed digital computers.After leaving the University of Leiden, Brouwer served as a faculty member at Yale University from 1928 until his death, becoming both professor of astronomy and director of the Yale Observatory in 1941. At Yale he first studied changes in the Earth's rotation, later tackling orbital problems. Along with W.J. Eckert, he developed a method of calculating orbit corrections (1937) that has been widely accepted, and, with Eckert an...
</Question>
<Choice>Brouwer, Dirk</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British-born American mathematician and astronomer known for his theory of the motion of the Moon.Educated at the University of Cambridge in England, Brown began there to study the motion of the Moon by a method devised by G.W. Hill of the United States. Hill had carried the process far enough to show its suitability for solving the problem, and Brown completed the theory. In 1919, after 30 years of work, Brown published his lunar tables, thereby making obsolescent those that had been in use for more than 60 years.Brown returned to Cambridge almost every summer, but he worked chiefly in the Un...
</Question>
<Choice>Brown, Ernest William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British astronomer and writer noted for his design, development, and use of the intensity interferometer.Brown graduated from the University of London in 1935. During and after World War II he worked with Robert Alexander Watson-Watt and then E.G. Bowen to develop radar and its uses in aerial combat. In the 1950s he applied his experience with radar to radio astronomy, developing radio telescope technology at Jodrell Bank Observatory and mapping radio sources in the sky. This work led him to design a radio interferometer capable of resolving radio stars while eliminating atmospheric distortion...
</Question>
<Choice>Brown, Robert Hanbury</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian philosopher, astronomer, mathematician, and occultist whose theories anticipated modern science. The most notable of these were his theories of the infinite universe and the multiplicity of worlds, in which he rejected the traditional geocentric (or Earth-centred) astronomy and intuitively went beyond the Copernican heliocentric (Sun-centred) theory, which still maintained a finite universe with a sphere of fixed stars. Bruno is, perhaps, chiefly remembered for the tragic death he suffered at the stake because of the tenacity with which he maintained his unorthodox ideas at a time when...
</Question>
<Choice>Bruno, Giordano</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English-born American astronomer and first woman to be appointed director of the Royal Greenwich Observatory. She made notable contributions to the theory of quasars (quasi-stellar sources), to measurements of the rotation and masses of galaxies, and to the understanding of how chemical elements are formed in the depths of stars through nuclear fusion. Burbidge also championed the fight for opportunities for women in science.Burbidge served as assistant director (1948–50) and acting director (1950–51) of the Observatory of the University of London. In 1955 her husband, theoretical astrophysici...
</Question>
<Choice>Burbidge, Eleanor Margaret</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
astronomer known particularly for his spectrographic determinations of the radial velocities of stars—i.e., their motions toward the Earth or away from it. In addition, he discovered many spectroscopic binary stars, and in 1924 he published a catalog listing more than 1,000 of them.To include measurements of radial velocities of stars visible only from the Southern Hemisphere, Campbell sent a 36-inch telescope, equipped with spectrograph, to Santiago, Chile. Combining data from Lick Observatory, Mt. Hamilton, California, and from Santiago, he determined the direction and speed of the Sun's mot...
</Question>
<Choice>Campbell, William Wallace</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronomer who specialized in the classification of stellar spectra.Cannon was the oldest daughter of Wilson Cannon, a Delaware state senator, and Mary Jump. She studied physics and astronomy at Wellesley College, graduating in 1884. For several years thereafter she traveled and dabbled in photography and music. In 1894 she returned to Wellesley for a year of advanced study in astronomy, and in 1895 she enrolled at Radcliffe in order to continue her studies under Edward C. Pickering, who was director of the Harvard College Observatory. In 1896 she was named an assistant at the Harvard...
</Question>
<Choice>Cannon, Annie Jump</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English astronomer who, by observing the motions of sunspots, discovered the equatorial acceleration of the Sun; i.e., that it rotates faster at the equator than near the poles. He also discovered the movement of sunspot zones toward the Sun's equator as the solar cycle progresses.The son of a brewer, Carrington was educated at Cambridge and in 1853 established his own observatory at Redhill, Reigate, Surrey. He published A Catalogue of 3,735 Circumpolar Stars (1857), but in 1865 his health failed and he did little work thereafter.
</Question>
<Choice>Carrington, Richard Christopher</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French astronomer and geodesist, who continued surveying work undertaken by his father, Jacques Cassini, and began construction of a great topographical map of France.Although he, his father, and his grandfather had defended the Cartesian view that the Earth is somewhat elongated (with a polar diameter greater than the equatorial diameter), Cassini III abandoned that position in the face of growing evidence that favoured the opposite, so-called Newtonian view that the Earth is flattened at the poles. He succeeded his father as director of the Paris Observatory in 1771, but his achievements as...
</Question>
<Choice>Cassini de Thury, Cesar-Francois</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(count of),French geodesist and astronomer, who completed his father's map of France, which was later used as the basis for the Atlas National (1791). The son of César-François Cassini de Thury, he succeeded him as director of the Observatoire de Paris in 1784, but the French Revolution interrupted his plans for restoring and reequipping the observatory. He briefly cooperated with the revolutionary government, but his monarchist sympathies prevailed, and he was denounced and arrested. After some months in prison he withdrew to Thury in 1794. Later, Napoleon I made him a senator and count.
</Question>
<Choice>Cassini, Dominique, comte de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian-born French astronomer who, among others, discovered the Cassini Division, the dark gap between the rings A and B of Saturn; he also discovered four of Saturn's moons. In addition, he was the first to record observations of the zodiacal light.Cassini's early studies were principally observations of the Sun, but after he obtained more powerful telescopes, he turned his attention to the planets. He was the first to observe the shadows of Jupiter'ssatellites as they passed between that planet and the Sun. His observation of spots on the surface of the planet allowed him to measure Jupiter...
</Question>
<Choice>Cassini, Gian Domenico</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French astronomer who compiled the first tables of the orbital motions of Saturn's satellites.He succeeded his father, the astronomer Gian Domenico Cassini, as head of the Paris Observatory in 1712, and in 1718 he completed the measurement of the arc of the meridian (longitude line) between Dunkerque and Perpignan. In his De la grandeur et de la figure de la terre (1720; “Concerning the Size and Shape of the Earth”), he supported the theory that the Earth is an elongated sphere, rather than flattened.Cassini's astronomical studies are found principally in Éléments d'astronomie (1740; “Elements...
</Question>
<Choice>Cassini, Jacques</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
astronomer who invented the Celsius temperature scale (often called the centigrade scale).Celsius was professor of astronomy at Uppsala University from 1730 to 1744, and in 1740 he built the Uppsala Observatory. In 1733 Celsius published a collection of 316 observations of the aurora borealis, or northern lights, made by himself and others from 1716 to 1732. He advocated the measurement of an arc of a meridian in Lapland and in 1736 took part in an expedition organized for that purpose, which verified Isaac Newton's theory that the Earth is somewhat flattened at the poles. In 1742 he described...
</Question>
<Choice>Celsius, Anders</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British clergyman and astronomer, famous in the history of astronomy for his failure to discover the planet Neptune.Elected a fellow of Trinity College, Cambridge, in 1826 and ordained in 1830, Challis became Plumian professor of astronomy and director of the Cambridge Observatory in 1836. He contributed 225 mathematical, physical, and astronomical papers to scientific journals and published, in 12 volumes, Astronomical Observations Made at the Observatory of Cambridge (1832–64), the chief results of his work.In September 1845 John Couch Adams, another Cambridge astronomer who had been making...
</Question>
<Choice>Challis, James</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronomer best known for his discovery (1884–85) of the Chandler Wobble, a movement in Earth's axis of rotation that causes latitude to vary with a period of about 433 days. A wandering of the rotation axis had been predicted by Swiss mathematician Leonhard Euler in 1765. Chandler's detection of this effect was facilitated by his invention of the almucantar, a device for measuring the positions of stars relative to a circle centred at the zenith rather than to the meridian. The North Pole of Earth's rotation axis wanders in an irregular, quasi-circular path with a radius of about 8–1...
</Question>
<Choice>Chandler, Seth Carlo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist and astronomer whose work lay primarily in infrared spectroscopy. Coblentz developed more accurate infrared spectrometers and extended their measurements to longer wavelengths. In 1905 he published a lengthy study of the infrared emission and absorption spectra of numerous elements and compounds. In 1914–16 he published improved values for the Stefan-Boltzmann constant of blackbody radiation and helped to confirm Planck's radiation law. He turned then to astrophysics and measured the infrared radiation from stars, planets, and nebulae. From 1905 until 1945 Coblentz was chief...
</Question>
<Choice>Coblentz, William W.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
mathematician and astronomer whose work on conic sections (curves of the intersections of a right circular cone with a plane) served as the basis for the fourth book of the Conics of Apollonius of Perga (c. 262–190 BC).From his observations in Italy and Sicily, Conon compiled the parapegma, a calendar of meteorological forecasts and of the risings and settings of the stars. He settled in Alexandria, where he served as court astronomer to Ptolemy III Euergetes I (reigned 246–221). When Berenice II, the consort of Ptolemy III, dedicated her hair as an offering in a temple of Aphrodite and the of...
</Question>
<Choice>Conon of Samos</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polish astronomer who proposed that the planets have the Sun as the fixed point to which their motions are to be referred; that the Earth is a planet which, besides orbiting the Sun annually, also turns once daily on its own axis; and that very slow, long-term changes in the direction of this axis account for the precession of the equinoxes. This representation of the heavens is usually called the heliocentric, or “Sun-centred,” system—derived from the Greek helios, meaning “Sun.” Copernicus's theory had important consequences for later thinkers of the scientific revolution, including such maj...
</Question>
<Choice>Copernicus, Nicolaus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French astronomer noted for his important developments in astronomical instruments and for his studies of the Earth's rotation.Danjon served in the French army (1914–19) and then became an astronomer at the University Observatory at Strasbourg. In 1930 he became its director, and the following year he was appointed professor of astronomy at the University of Strasbourg. In 1945 Danjon became director of the Paris Observatory and in 1946 attained the post of professor of astronomy at the Sorbonne. He became director of the Institute of Astrophysics of Paris in 1954.While studying the methods of...
</Question>
<Choice>Danjon, Andre-Louis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English astronomer who championed the theory that the Moon was once part of the Earth, until it was pulled free to form a satellite.The second son of the eminent naturalist Charles Darwin, he became Plumian professor of astronomy and experimental philosophy at Cambridge University in 1883. His monumental analysis of tides, published in 1884, was based on the methods developed by Pierre-Simon Laplace and Lord Kelvin. In The Tides and Kindred Phenomena in the Solar System (1898), he discussed the effects of tidal friction on the Earth–Moon system and theorized that the Moon was formed from matte...
</Question>
<Choice>Darwin, Sir George Howard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English astronomer known for his extensive measurements of double stars and for his meticulous planetary observations.Trained as a physician, Dawes practiced at Haddenham and (from 1826) Liverpool; subsequently he became a Nonconformist clergyman. In 1829 he set up a private observatory at Ormskirk, Lancashire, where he measured more than 200 double stars before taking charge of George Bishop's Observatory at South Villa, Regent's Park, London, in 1839. He later set up private observatories at Cranbrook, Kent (1844); Wateringbury, Kent (1850); and Haddenham (1857). He was one of several indepe...
</Question>
<Choice>Dawes, William Rutter</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English pioneer in astronomical photography, the method by which nearly all modern astronomical observations are made.Educated at the Collège Sainte-Barbe in Paris, De la Rue entered his father's printing business, and in 1851 he invented the first envelope-making machine. From 1852 his interest centred on the application of photography to astronomy. At Kew, Surrey, with a telescope of a special design, he carried out the proposal of the British astronomer Sir John Herschel to photograph the Sun daily. His stereoscopic pictures (formed by combining two photographs taken in succession) of the S...
</Question>
<Choice>De la Rue, Warren</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French astronomer who prepared tables that plot the location of Uranus.In 1771 Delambre became tutor to the son of M. d'Assy, receiver general of finances. In 1788 d'Assy built an observatory for Delambre's use. There he observed and computed almost uninterruptedly and in 1792 published Tables du Soleil, de Jupiter, de Saturne, d'Uranus et des satellites de Jupiter (“Tables of the Sun, Jupiter, Saturn, Uranus, and Jupiter's Satellites”). He was admitted to the Institut de France upon its organization in 1795 and became, in 1803, perpetual secretary to its mathematical section. He served from 1...
</Question>
<Choice>Delambre, Jean-Baptiste-Joseph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician and astronomer whose theory of lunar motion advanced the development of planetary-motion theories.Delaunay was educated as an engineer at the École des Mines from 1836, becoming an engineer in 1843 and chief engineer in 1858. He studied mathematics and astronomy with Jean-Baptiste Biot at the Sorbonne (1841–48). He taught mechanics at the École Polytechnique from 1850 and also later taught at the École des Mines. He was made a member of the Académie des Sciences in 1855; and in 1870 he succeeded U.-J.-J. Le Verrier as director of the Paris Observatory.He wrote Cours élémen...
</Question>
<Choice>Delaunay, Charles-Eugene</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French astronomer who proposed that the series of coloured rings sometimes observed around the Sun is caused by diffraction of sunlight through water droplets in a cloud. He also worked to find the distance of the Sun from the Earth by observing transits of Venus and Mercury across the face of the Sun.In 1725 Delisle went to St. Petersburg to establish an astronomical institute. Intending to be there only 4 years, he stayed for 22 and trained the first generation of Russian astronomers. His Mémoires pour servir à l'histoire et au progrès de l'astronomie (1738; “Memoirs Recounting the History a...
</Question>
<Choice>Delisle, Joseph-Nicolas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
monk, grammarian, and geographer whose work is important to the history of science and is a testament to Irish learning in the 9th century.Much of Dicuil's astronomical knowledge was gained in calculating dates for religious festivals. Completed in 825, his De mensura orbis terrae (“Concerning the Measurement of the World”) contains the earliest mention of Irish hermits having visited Iceland (795), where they marveled at the midnight sun. The work also contains the most definite Western reference to the old freshwater canal between the Nile River and the Red Sea, which was blocked up in 767....
</Question>
<Choice>Dicuil</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
, in full Abu ?anifah A?mad Ibn Da?ud Al-dinawari Persian astronomer, botanist, and historian, whose interest in Hellenism and the Arabic humanities has been compared with that of the Iraqi scholar al-Ja?i?.Ad-Dinawari studied philology in the Iraqi cities of Basra and Kufah. The systematic approach to learning that he acquired there is reflected in the preserved fragments of his Kitab an-nabat (“Book of Plants”), one of the most famous early Muslim works on botany. Of lexicographical character, it includes oral and written Arabic botanical traditions as well as much Persian material. Written...
</Question>
<Choice>Dinawari, ad-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian scientist, one of the first to develop the technology necessary for producing scientific optical instruments.After some scientific training under Benedetto Castelli, a disciple of Galileo, Divini established himself in Rome in 1646 as a maker of clocks and lenses. He constructed a number of compound microscopes and long-focus telescopes, the latter consisting of wooden tubes with four lenses, with a focal length of more than 15 m (50 feet).In 1649 Divini published a copper engraving of a map of the Moon, based on his own observations made with his invention. He also made a number of as...
</Question>
<Choice>Divini, Eustachio</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French astronomer, successor to Bernard Lyot as the principal French authority on the solar system.Dollfus made several balloon flights for high-altitude observations, including the first stratospheric ascension in France. On the basis of comparative light-polarizing qualities, he concluded that the surface material of Mars consists of pulverized limonite (an iron oxide, Fe2O3) and prepared a map of Venus showing what he believed to be permanent features. On Dec. 15, 1966, he discovered Saturn's 10th known satellite, Janus.
</Question>
<Choice>Dollfus, Audouin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British optician who invented a number of precision instruments used in astronomy, geodesy, and navigation.Throughout most of his life, he worked for the family firm of mathematical instrument makers, assuming full control after the retirement in 1819 of his uncle Peter Dollond. His micrometer made of rock crystal, announced in 1821, was used by the English astronomer William Rutter Dawes in measuring close double stars. Other inventions followed, including improvements to astronomical and navigation devices. Dollond received the council medal of the Great Exhibition of 1851 for his atmospheri...
</Question>
<Choice>Dollond, George</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian astronomer who, on Aug. 5, 1864, was first to observe the spectrum of a comet (Comet 1864 II). This observation indicated correctly that comet tails contain luminous gas and do not shine merely by reflected sunlight.Between 1854 and 1864 Donati discovered six comets, one of which, first seen on June 2, 1858, bears his name. These discoveries led to his appointment as professor of astronomy and director of the observatory at Florence in 1864. He also contributed to early classification systems for stellar spectra. Donati was supervising the building of a new observatory at Arcetri, near...
</Question>
<Choice>Donati, Giovanni Battista</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronomer and archaeologist who established the principles of dendrochronology (the dating and interpreting of past events by the analysis of tree rings). He coined the name of that study when, while working at the Lowell Observatory, Flagstaff, Ariz. (1894–1901), he began to collect tree specimens, believing that variations in the width of tree rings would show a connection between sunspot activity and the terrestrial climate and vegetation.Douglass taught astronomy (from 1906) and dendrochronology (from 1936) at the University of Arizona and directed that university's Steward Obser...
</Question>
<Choice>Douglass, Andrew Ellicott</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician and amateur astronomer who made the first photograph of the spectrum of a star (Vega), in 1872. He was also the first to photograph a nebula, the Orion Nebula, in 1880. His father, John William Draper, in 1840 had made the first photograph of the Moon.Henry Draper was appointed to the medical staff of Bellevue Hospital, New York City, in 1859 and in 1866 became dean of the medical faculty of the University of the City of New York. For his photography of the transit of Venus in 1874, Congress ordered a gold medal struck in his honour. His widow established the Henry Draper Me...
</Question>
<Choice>Draper, Henry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Danish astronomer who compiled the New General Catalogue of Nebulae and Clusters of Stars, published in 1888, and its supplements, published in 1895 and 1908. This work, together with the supplements, was republished in 1953; it still remains one of the standard reference catalogs.In 1874 Dreyer was appointed assistant at Lord Rosse's observatory in Parsonstown (now Birr), County Offaly, Ire. Four years later he moved to Dunsink Observatory in Dublin. In 1882 he became director of the observatory at Armagh, Ire.; he retired from this post in 1916. That same year he was awarded the Gold Medal o...
</Question>
<Choice>Dreyer, Johan Ludvig Emil</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish astronomer who studied the rotational period of the Sun.Dunér was senior astronomer (1864–88) at the Royal University Observatory in Lund, Sweden. In 1867 he began his investigations of binary stars. He also performed pioneering stellar spectroscopy studies (studies of the individual characteristic wavelengths of light).Shortly after he became professor of astronomy at the University of Uppsala and director of the Uppsala Observatory in 1888, Dunér undertook a now-classic study of the Sun's rotation. Using the Doppler shift, he established that the Sun's rotational period is about 25 1...
</Question>
<Choice>Duner, Nils Christofer</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British astronomer who in 1919 organized observations of stars seen near the Sun during a solar eclipse, which provided evidence supporting Einstein's prediction in the theory of general relativity of the bending of light in a gravitational field.In 1894 Dyson became chief assistant at the Royal Greenwich Observatory and was a member of eclipse expeditions to Portugal (1900), Sumatra (1901), and Tunisia (1905). His observations of the corona and chromosphere of the Sun were published in Determination of Wave-Lengths from Spectra Obtained at the Total Solar Eclipses of 1900, 1901, and 1905 (190...
</Question>
<Choice>Dyson, Sir Frank Watson</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English astronomer, physicist, and mathematician who did his greatest work in astrophysics, investigating the motion, internal structure, and evolution of stars. He also was the first expositor of the theory of relativity in the English language.
</Question>
<Choice>Eddington, Sir Arthur Stanley</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German astronomer who in 1819 established the period of the comet now known by his name (seeEncke's Comet).Encke was educated at Hamburg and the University of Göttingen, where he worked under the direction of Carl Friedrich Gauss. In 1816 Encke became assistant at the Seeberg Observatory near Gotha, Ger., where he was made vice director in 1820 and director in 1822. In 1825 he was appointed professor of astronomy and director of the observatory of the University of Berlin. There he planned and supervised the construction of a new observatory, completed in 1835.Besides the comet that bears his...
</Question>
<Choice>Encke, Johann Franz</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek scientific writer, astronomer, and poet, who made the first measurement of the size of Earth for which any details are known.At Syene (now Aswan), some 800 km (500 miles) southeast of Alexandria in Egypt, the Sun's rays fall vertically at noon at the summer solstice. Eratosthenes noted that at Alexandria, at the same date and time, sunlight fell at an angle of about 7.2° from the vertical. (Writing before the Greeks adopted the degree, a Babylonian unit of measure, he actually said “a fiftieth of a circle.”) He correctly assumed the Sun's distance to be very great; its rays therefore are...
</Question>
<Choice>Eratosthenes of Cyrene</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek mathematician and astronomer who substantially advanced proportion theory, contributed to the identification of constellations and thus to the development of observational astronomy in the Greek world, and established the first sophisticated, geometrical model of celestial motion. He also wrote on geography and contributed to philosophical discussions in Plato's Academy. Although none of his writings survive, his contributions are known from many discussions throughout antiquity.
</Question>
<Choice>Eudoxus of Cnidus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English astronomer who, in 1909, discovered the horizontal motion of gases outward from the centres of sunspots, a phenomenon sometimes called the Evershed effect.In 1906 Evershed became assistant director of the Kodaikanal and Madras observatories in India, later becoming director. On an expedition to Kashmir in 1915, he made the first measurements supporting Albert Einstein's prediction that the wavelength of light emitted by a massive body (in this case the Sun) should be increased by an amount proportional to the intensity of the local gravitational field. Evershed retired in 1923, returni...
</Question>
<Choice>Evershed, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch astronomer who may have been the first observer of sunspots (1610/1611) and was the first to publish information on such observations. He did so in his Narratio de maculis in sole observatis et apparente earum cum sole conversione (1611; “Account of Spots Observed on the Sun and of Their Apparent Rotation with the Sun”). The son of the astronomer David Fabricius, Johannes used a camera obscura as well as a telescope in his study of the Sun.
</Question>
<Choice>Fabricius, Johannes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
founder of the Greenwich Observatory, and the first astronomer royal of England.Poor health forced Flamsteed to leave school in 1662. He studied astronomy on his own and later (1670–74) continued his education at the University of Cambridge. In 1677 he became a member of the Royal Society. Ordained a clergyman in 1675, Flamsteed in 1684 received the income of the living of Burstow, Surrey. His report to the Royal Society on the need for a new observatory resulted in the founding (1675) of the Royal Greenwich Observatory, of which he was the first director (and hence astronomer royal). He found...
</Question>
<Choice>Flamsteed, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronomer who pioneered in the classification of stellar spectra.Mina Stevens was educated in public schools and from age 14 was a teacher as well as student. In May 1877 she married James O. Fleming, with whom she immigrated to the United States and settled in Boston the next year. The failure of her marriage in 1879 forced her to seek employment, and she soon became housekeeper for Edward C. Pickering, professor of astronomy and director of the Harvard College Observatory. Before the year was out Pickering had asked her to work at the observatory as a temporary employee, and in 188...
</Question>
<Choice>Fleming, Williamina Paton Stevens</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian physician, poet, astronomer, and geologist, who proposed a scientific germ theory of disease more than 300 years before its empirical formulation by Louis Pasteur and Robert Koch.At the University of Padua Fracastoro was a colleague of the astronomer Copernicus. As a physician, he maintained a private practice in Verona. He is best-known for “Syphilis sive morbus Gallicus” (1530; “Syphilis or the French Disease”), a work in rhyme giving an account of the disease, which he named. He made an intense study of epidemic diseases, and, while in the service of Pope Paul III at the Council of...
</Question>
<Choice>Fracastoro, Girolamo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian mathematician, astronomer, and physicist who is best known for his work in hydraulics. His most significant contributions to science, however, were in the compilation, interpretation, and dissemination of the work of other scientists.Frisi was a member of the Barnabite religious order, a professor at the University of Milan, and a member of most of the major scientific societies of his time. He was held in such esteem by his contemporaries that plans for nearly all the major hydraulic works constructed in northern Italy during his adult life were first shown to him for his inspection....
</Question>
<Choice>Frisi, Paolo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian natural philosopher, astronomer, and mathematician who made fundamental contributions to the sciences of motion, astronomy, and strength of materials and to the development of the scientific method. His formulation of (circular) inertia, the law of falling bodies, and parabolic trajectories marked the beginning of a fundamental change in the study of motion. His insistence that the book of nature was written in the language of mathematics changed natural philosophy from a verbal, qualitative account to a mathematical one in which experimentation became a recognized method for discoveri...
</Question>
<Choice>Galileo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German astronomer who on Sept. 23, 1846, was the first to observe the planet Neptune.Galle joined the staff of the Berlin Observatory, where he served as assistant director under J.F. Encke from 1835 until 1851. He studied the rings of Saturn and suggested a method, later successful, of measuring the scale of the solar system by observing the parallax of asteroids. He looked for Neptune at the request of the French astronomer U.-J.-J. Le Verrier, who had computed the planet's probable position before it was seen. From 1851 until 1897 Galle was director of the Breslau Observatory.
</Question>
<Choice>Galle, Johann Gottfried</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German mathematician, generally regarded as one of the greatest mathematicians of all time for his contributions to number theory, geometry, probability theory, geodesy, planetary astronomy, the theory of functions, and potential theory (including electromagnetism).Gauss was the only child of poor parents. He was rare among mathematicians in that he was a calculating prodigy, and he retained the ability to do elaborate calculations in his head most of his life. Impressed by this ability and by his gift for languages, his teachers and his devoted mother recommended him to the duke of Brunswick...
</Question>
<Choice>Gauss, Carl Friedrich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish astronomer known for his measurements of solar and stellar parallax, showing the distances of the Sun and other stars from Earth, and for his early use of photography in mapping the heavens. To determine the parallaxes, he perfected the use of the heliometer, a telescope that uses a split image to measure the angular separation of celestial bodies.Gill was educated at the University of Aberdeen, and in 1872 he became director of James Ludovic Lindsay's private observatory near Aberdeen. From there he undertook expeditions to Mauritius in 1874, to observe the transit of Venus, and to A...
</Question>
<Choice>Gill, Sir David</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. naval officer and astronomer who founded the Naval Observatory in Washington, D.C., the first U.S. observatory devoted entirely to research.Gilliss entered the U.S. Navy in 1827 and 10 years later was put in charge of the navy's Depot of Charts and Instruments, in Washington, D.C. His responsibilities included making astronomical observations necessary for longitude determinations of newly explored land. At his recommendation, funds were provided by Congress in 1842 for founding the Naval Observatory, and he supervised its construction (1843–44).Gilliss undertook an astronomical expeditio...
</Question>
<Choice>Gilliss, James Melville</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian-born British astronomer who promulgated the steady-state theory of the universe, holding that, although the universe is expanding, a continuous creation of matter in intergalactic space is gradually forming new galaxies, so that the average number of galaxies in any part of the universe remains approximately the same. Many of Gold's theories were unconventional, and they often generated much controversy.Gold studied at Trinity College, Cambridge (B.A., 1942; M.Sc., 1946), and during World War II served in the British Admiralty. He was elected a fellow of Trinity College in 1947 and be...
</Question>
<Choice>Gold, Thomas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English astronomer who was the first to notice that some variable stars (stars whose observed light varies noticeably in intensity) were periodic. He also gave the first accurate explanation for one type of periodic variable.Goodricke was deaf and mute, probably because of a serious illness he had contracted in childhood. He nevertheless proved to be a bright student, and in 1778 he entered Warrington Academy, where he excelled in mathematics and his interest in astronomy was awakened. After leaving the academy in 1781 he started making his own astronomical observations. In November 1782 he wa...
</Question>
<Choice>Goodricke, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronomer whose star catalogs helped fix the list of constellations of the Southern Hemisphere.A child prodigy who could read aloud at age three and compose poems in Latin at age five, Gould studied mathematics and the physical sciences under Benjamin Peirce at Harvard University. In 1845 he went to Germany to study astronomy and was the first American to earn a doctorate in this field, at the University of Göttingen in 1848. Returning to the United States, Gould was anxious to raise American astronomy to the European level. In 1849 he founded The Astronomical Journal, which was mode...
</Question>
<Choice>Gould, Benjamin Apthorp</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish mathematician and astronomer who discovered infinite series representations for a number of trigonometry functions, although he is mostly remembered for his description of the first practical reflecting telescope, now known as the Gregorian telescope.The son of an Anglican priest, Gregory received his early education from his mother. After his father's death in 1650, he was sent to Aberdeen, first to grammar school and then to Marischal College, graduating from the latter in 1657. (This Protestant college was combined with the Roman Catholic King's College in 1860 to form the Universi...
</Question>
<Choice>Gregory, James</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English astronomer, compiler of a star catalog known by his name.Groombridge began observations at Blackheath, London, in 1806 and retired from the West Indian trade in 1815 to devote full time to the project. A Catalogue of Circumpolar Stars, listing 4,243 stars situated within 50° of the North Pole and having apparent magnitudes greater than 9, was published in 1838 after having been edited by the Royal Astronomer Sir George Airy. Groombridge was elected a fellow of the Royal Society of London in 1812, and eight years later he was a founding member of the Astronomical Society of London (late...
</Question>
<Choice>Groombridge, Stephen</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jesuit priest and astronomer who is noted for his discovery and study of dark clouds of tenuous, interstellar matter sometimes known as Hagen's clouds.Hagen served as director of the Georgetown College Observatory, Washington, D.C., from 1888 to 1906, when Pope Pius X appointed him director of the Vatican Observatory. In 1893, while compiling a general catalog of bright and dark nebulae, Hagen began an intensive study of dark nebulae. Over a period of several decades, he became convinced that he sometimes observed dark interstellar matter through the telescope, although he failed to detect it...
</Question>
<Choice>Hagen, Johann Georg</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronomer known for his development of important astronomical instruments, including the Hale Telescope, a 200-inch (508-cm) reflector at the Palomar Observatory, near San Diego. The most effective entrepreneur in 20th-century American astronomy, Hale built four observatories and helped create the new discipline of astrophysics. He is known also for his research in solar physics, particularly his discovery of magnetic fields in sunspots.Hale was born into a wealthy Chicago family and from an early age was enraptured by science. He built his first observatory at age 20 at the Hale hom...
</Question>
<Choice>Hale, George Ellery</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronomer who discovered the two moons of Mars, Deimos and Phobos, in 1877 and calculated their orbits.Hall came from an impoverished family and was largely self-taught, though he did study briefly at Central College, McGrawville, N.Y., and at the University of Michigan. By 1858 he had acquired a minor position at the Harvard University observatory, where he did research and wrote papers. In 1863 he was appointed professor of mathematics at the U.S. Naval Observatory, in Washington, D.C., a position he held until his retirement in 1891. There he was chiefly concerned with planetary a...
</Question>
<Choice>Hall, Asaph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English astronomer and mathematician who was the first to calculate the orbit of a comet later named after him. He is also noted for his role in the publication of Newton'sPhilosophiae Naturalis Principia Mathematica.
</Question>
<Choice>Halley, Edmond</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Arab geographer, poet, grammarian, historian, and astronomer whose chief fame derives from his authoritative writings on South Arabian history and geography. From his literary production al-Hamdani was known as the “tongue of South Arabia.”Most of al-Hamdani's life was spent in Arabia itself. He was widely educated, and he traveled extensively, acquiring a broad knowledge of his country. He became involved in a number of political controversies. When he was imprisoned for one of them, his influence was sufficient to invoke a tribal rebellion in his behalf to secure his release.His encyclopaedi...
</Question>
<Choice>Hamdani, al-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Irish mathematician who contributed to the development of optics, dynamics, and algebra—in particular, discovering the algebra of quaternions. His work proved significant for the development of quantum mechanics.Hamilton was the son of a solicitor. He was educated by his uncle, James Hamilton, an Anglican priest with whom he lived from before the age of three until he entered college. An aptitude for languages was soon apparent: at five he was already making progress with Latin, Greek, and Hebrew, broadening his studies to include Arabic, Sanskrit, Persian, Syriac, French, and Italian before h...
</Question>
<Choice>Hamilton, Sir William Rowan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Danish-born German astronomer whose most important work was the improvement of the theories and tables of the orbits of the principal bodies in the solar system.Hansen became director of the Seeberg Observatory, near Gotha, in 1825, and in 1857 a new observatory was built for him. He worked on theoretical geodesy, optics, and probability theory. His most important books on the theory of the motion of the Moon are the Fundamenta nova investigationis orbitae verae quam Luna perlustrat (1838; “New Foundations of the Investigation of the True Orbit That the Moon Traverses”) and the Darlegung der t...
</Question>
<Choice>Hansen, Peter Andreas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Norwegian astronomer and physicist noted for his research in geomagnetism.At the beginning of the 19th century, measurements of geomagnetic intensity had just begun. Hansteen continued the task, taking measurements in London, Paris, Finland, and (1828–30) Siberia. In 1826 he published the first reliable chart of magnetic intensities. Hansteen's theories of geomagnetism were less successful than his measurements, however, and were ultimately disproved by Carl Friedrich Gauss in 1839.Hansteen, who joined the faculty of the University of Christiania in 1814, established the first astronomical obs...
</Question>
<Choice>Hansteen, Christopher</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
mathematician, astronomer, and investigator of the natural world.Little is known of him before he received his bachelor's degree from the University of Oxford in 1580. Throughout his working life, he was supported by the patronage, at different times, of Sir Walter Raleigh and Henry Percy, the 9th earl of Northumberland; he was never, after his student years, affiliated with an academic institution or commercial organization. From 1585 to 1586 he participated in Raleigh's colony on Roanoke Island, and he may have visited Virginia as early as 1584; upon his return, he published A Briefe and Tru...
</Question>
<Choice>Harriot, Thomas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German astronomer noted for his work in measuring stellar positions and for his studies of relativity and cosmology. He also made notable contributions to statistical mechanics.After obtaining his Ph.D. (1925) at the University of Bonn, Heckmann became assistant astronomer at its observatory (1925–27) and at the University Observatory in Göttingen (1927–35). He became lecturer in astronomy at the University of Göttingen in 1929 and assistant professor in 1935. From 1941 to 1962 he was director of the Hamburg Observatory and head of the department of astronomy at Hamburg University.Heckmann org...
</Question>
<Choice>Heckmann, Otto</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish astronomer who, as royal astronomer at the Cape of Good Hope (1831–33), made measurements that later allowed him to determine the parallax of a star (Alpha Centauri). He announced his findings in 1839, a few months after both German astronomer Friedrich Bessel and Russian astronomer Friedrich Struve had received credit for first measuring stellar parallaxes.Henderson was elected a fellow of the Royal Astronomical Society (1832), the Royal Society of Edinburgh (1834), and the Royal Society of London (1840). Upon his return from the Cape of Good Hope in 1834, he was appointed the first...
</Question>
<Choice>Henderson, Thomas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek philosopher and astronomer who first suggested the rotation of the Earth, an idea that did not dominate astronomy until 1,800 years later. A pupil of Plato, who left the Academy temporarily in his charge, Heracleides is known to have correctly attributed the apparent motion of Mercury and Venus to their revolving around the Sun; whether he realized that the other planets did so is uncertain. He also taught some kind of atomism. His writings, all lost except for a few fragments, include literary criticism and works on musicology. He also studied trances, cosmological visions, prophecies,...
</Question>
<Choice>Heracleides Ponticus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-born British astronomer noted for her contributions to the astronomical researches of her brother, Sir William Herschel; she executed many of the calculations connected with his studies and, on her own, detected by telescope three nebulae in 1783 and eight comets from 1786 to 1797.Caroline assisted her mother in the management of the household until 1772, when her brother, William, took her to Bath, Eng., where he had established himself as a teacher of music. Once settled in Bath, Caroline trained and performed successfully as a singer. Both she and William gave their last public music...
</Question>
<Choice>Herschel, Caroline Lucretia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English astronomer and successor to his father, Sir William Herschel, in the field of stellar and nebular observation and discovery.
</Question>
<Choice>Herschel, Sir John Frederick William, 1st Baronet</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-born British astronomer, the founder of sidereal astronomy for the systematic observation of the heavens. He discovered the planet Uranus, hypothesized that nebulae are composed of stars, and developed a theory of stellar evolution. He was knighted in 1816.
</Question>
<Choice>Herschel, Sir William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Danish astronomer who classified types of stars by relating their colour to their absolute brightness—an accomplishment of fundamental importance to modern astronomy. The Hertzsprung–Russell diagram of stellar types was named (in part) for him. In 1913 he established the luminosity scale of Cepheid variable stars, a tool for measurement of intergalactic distances.He had no formal education in astronomy but studied in technological colleges in Denmark and became a chemical engineer. Keenly interested in the chemistry of photography, he turned to astronomy in 1902, working in small Danish observ...
</Question>
<Choice>Hertzsprung, Ejnar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
astronomer who compiled an atlas of the Moon (Selenographia, published 1647) containing one of the earliest detailed maps of its surface as well as names for many of its features. A few of his names for lunar mountains (e.g., the Alps) are still in use, and a lunar crater is named for him. Hevelius also made a catalog of 1,564 stars, the most comprehensive of its time, and a celestial atlas in which several constellations, now accepted, were shown for the first time. After his death, the catalog and the atlas were published together (Prodromus Astronomiae, 1690) by his wife, Elisabetha, who ha...
</Question>
<Choice>Hevelius, Johannes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. mathematical astronomer considered by many of his peers to be the greatest master of celestial mechanics of his time. After receiving a B.A. from Rutgers College (1859), Hill joined the Nautical Almanac Office in 1861. Among his many accomplishments, Hill was the first to use infinite determinants to analyze the motion of the Moon's perigee (1877). He also developed a theory of the motion of Jupiter and Saturn. His most significant theory, dealing with the effects of the planets on the Moon's motion, is considered fundamental in the development of celestial mechanics.For his research on t...
</Question>
<Choice>Hill, George William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek astronomer and mathematician who made fundamental contributions to the advancement of astronomy as a mathematical science and to the foundations of trigonometry. Although he is commonly ranked among the greatest scientists of antiquity, very little is known about his life, and only one of his many writings is still in existence. Knowledge of the rest of his work relies on second-hand reports, especially in the great astronomical compendium the Almagest, written by Ptolemy in the 2nd century AD.
</Question>
<Choice>Hipparchus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physicist who discovered the law of elasticity, known as Hooke's law, and who did research in a remarkable variety of fields.In 1655 Hooke was employed by Robert Boyle to construct the Boylean air pump. Five years later, Hooke discovered his law of elasticity, which states that the stretching of a solid body (e.g., metal, wood) is proportional to the force applied to it. The law laid the basis for studies of stress and strain and for understanding of elastic materials. He applied these studies in his designs for the balance springs of watches. In 1662 he was appointed curator of experi...
</Question>
<Choice>Hooke, Robert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British astronomer and clergyman who applied Johannes Kepler's laws of planetary motion to the Moon and whose observations of a transit of Venus (1639) are the first recorded.Horrocks studied at the University of Cambridge from 1632 to 1635; he then became a tutor at Toxteth and studied astronomy in his spare time. He was ordained to the curacy of Hoole, Lancashire, in 1639. The transit of Venus, which had been overlooked in Kepler's tables but which Horrocks had predicted, took place on Sunday, November 24 (Old Style), and he observed it between church services.He showed the Moon's orbit to b...
</Question>
<Choice>Horrocks, Jeremiah</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British mathematician and astronomer best known as the foremost proponent and defender of the steady-state theory of the universe. This theory holds both that the universe is expanding and that matter is being continuously created to keep the mean density of matter in space constant.Hoyle was educated at Emmanuel College and St. John's College, Cambridge, and spent six years during World War II with the British Admiralty, working on radar development. In 1945 he returned to Cambridge as a lecturer in mathematics. Three years later, in collaboration with the astronomer Thomas Gold and the math...
</Question>
<Choice>Hoyle, Sir Fred</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronomer who played a crucial role in establishing the field of extragalactic astronomy and is generally regarded as the leading observational cosmologist of the 20th century.He was the son of John Powell Hubble, a businessman who worked in the insurance industry. His mother, the former Virginia Lee James, was a homemaker who ran the household alone during John's frequent absences on business. The Hubbles had eight children.In 1906 Hubble won a scholarship to the University of Chicago, where he served for a year as a student laboratory assistant for physicist Robert Millikan, a futu...
</Question>
<Choice>Hubble, Edwin Powell</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English astronomer who revolutionized observational astronomy by applying spectroscopic methods to the determination of the chemical constituents of stars and other celestial objects.Huggins built a private observatory at Tulse Hill, London, in 1856. From 1859 he was one of a number of astronomers who began to apply Robert Wilhelm Bunsen's and Gustav Robert Kirchhoff's discoveries in spectrum analysis to astronomy. Huggins's first spectroscopic observations, published in 1863, showed that stars are composed of the same elements that occur on the Sun and Earth. In 1864 the spectra he obtained o...
</Question>
<Choice>Huggins, Sir William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch astronomer who predicted theoretically the 21-cm (8.2-inch) radio waves produced by interstellar hydrogen atoms. His calculations later proved valuable in mapping the Milky Way Galaxy and were the basis for radio astronomy during its early development.In 1944, while still a student, van de Hulst made theoretical studies of hydrogen atoms in space. The magnetic fields of the proton and electron in the hydrogen atom can align in either the same or opposite directions. Once every 10 million years or so a hydrogen atom will realign itself and, van de Hulst calculated, emit a radio wave with...
</Question>
<Choice>Hulst, Hendrik Christoffel van de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch mathematician, astronomer, and physicist, who founded the wave theory of light, discovered the true shape of the rings of Saturn, and made original contributions to the science of dynamics—the study of the action of forces on bodies.Huygens was from a wealthy and distinguished middle-class family. His father, Constantijn Huygens, a diplomat, Latinist, and poet, was the friend and correspondent of many outstanding intellectual figures of the day, including the scientist and philosopher René Descartes. From an early age, Huygens showed a marked mechanical bent and a talent for drawing and...
</Question>
<Choice>Huygens, Christiaan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
mathematician and astronomer who made significant contributions to the principles of optics and the use of scientific experiments.
</Question>
<Choice>Ibn al-Haytham</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French Jewish physician, translator, and astronomer whose work was utilized by Copernicus and Dante. He was highly regarded as a physician and served as regent of the faculty of medicine at the University of Montpellier. He was the grandson of the renowned translator Samuel ben Judah ibn Tibbon.Jacob translated into Hebrew a large number of works, including Arabic versions of Euclid's Elements and Ptolemy's encyclopaedic work on astronomy, the Almagest. He also translated Arabic works by al-Ghazali (1058–1111) and Averroës.As a student of astronomy, Jacob described a quadrant of his own invent...
</Question>
<Choice>ibn Tibbon, Jacob ben Machir</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French astronomer who in 1868 discovered how to observe solar prominences without an eclipse. His work was independent of that of the Englishman Joseph Norman Lockyer, who made the same discovery at about the same time.Janssen was permanently lamed by an accident in early childhood. He studied at the University of Paris, and in 1865 he became professor of general science in the school of architecture. He was an enthusiastic observer of eclipses. In 1868 Janssen discovered how to use a spectroscope to observe solar prominences in daylight; this enabled many more such observations to be made tha...
</Question>
<Choice>Janssen, Pierre-Jules-Cesar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physicist and mathematician who was the first to propose that matter is continuously created throughout the universe. He made other innovations in astronomical theory but is perhaps best known as a writer of popular books about astronomy.Jeans taught at the University of Cambridge (1904–05, 1910–12) and at Princeton University (1905–09). In 1923 he became a research associate at Mt. Wilson Observatory, Pasadena, Calif., where he remained until 1944. In 1928, the year he was knighted, he proposed his continuous-creation theory.His work included investigations of spiral nebulae, the sour...
</Question>
<Choice>Jeans, Sir James</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British astronomer and geophysicist noted for his wide variety of scientific contributions.Jeffreys was educated at Armstrong College, Newcastle-upon-Tyne (D.Sc., 1917), and St. John's College, University of Cambridge (M.A., 1917), and was a fellow at St. John's from 1914. He served in the Meteorological Office (1917–22), lectured in mathematics at Cambridge (1923–32), was reader in geophysics at Cambridge (1932–46), and was the university's Plumian professor of astronomy (1945–58). He was knighted in 1953.In his work in astronomy, Jeffreys established that the four large outer planets (Jupite...
</Question>
<Choice>Jeffreys, Sir Harold</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
mathematician and astronomer active at the beginning of the greatest period of traditional Chinese mathematics.Little is known about Jia's life except that he held a relatively low military office during the reign (1022/23–1063/64) of Emperor Renzong of the Song dynasty. He was a pupil of mathematician and astronomer Chu Yan, who contributed to the revision of the Chongtian calendar in 1023, and served in the Imperial Astronomical Bureau in the mid-11th century. Jia's name was mainly quoted in connection with his method of extracting roots (solutions) of polynomials of degree higher than three...
</Question>
<Choice>Jia Xian</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
10th astronomer royal of England (1933–55), who organized a program that led to a more accurate determination of the mean distance between the Earth and the Sun.After studies at the University of Cambridge, Jones became chief assistant at the Royal Observatory in Greenwich in 1913. He was his majesty's astronomer to the observatory at the Cape of Good Hope from 1923 to 1933, and in the latter year he returned to Greenwich as astronomer royal. Jones's scientific work largely concerned determining more accurately the fundamental constants of astronomy and in particular the solar parallax—the ang...
</Question>
<Choice>Jones, Sir Harold Spencer</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch astronomer who used photography and statistical methods in determining the motions and distribution of stars.Kapteyn attended the State University of Utrecht and in 1875 became a member of the staff of Leiden Observatory. In 1877 he was elected to the chair of astronomy and theoretical mechanics at the State University of Groningen.Kapteyn was not the first to use photographic methods in astronomy, but his breadth of scientific vision and capacity for carrying through large programs made him a key figure in the development of photographic astronomy. Using measurements of the positions of...
</Question>
<Choice>Kapteyn, Jacobus Cornelius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
ranks among the greatest mathematicians and astronomers in the Islamic world.
</Question>
<Choice>Kashi, al-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronomer who confirmed that Saturn's ring system is not a solid unit but is composed of a vast swarm of tiny particles.Interested in astronomy from an early age, Keeler became assistant to the noted astronomer Samuel P. Langley at the Allegheny Observatory, Pittsburgh, Pa., in 1881. From 1886 to 1891 he was on the staff of the Lick Observatory, Mount Hamilton, Calif., where he headed the spectroscopic program. Among the outstanding results that he achieved was the measurement of the rate of expansion of the Orion Nebula together with proof that it is located within the Milky Way Gal...
</Question>
<Choice>Keeler, James Edward</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German astronomer who discovered three major laws of planetary motion, conventionally designated as follows: (1) the planets move in elliptical orbits with the Sun at one focus; (2) the time necessary to traverse any arc of a planetary orbit is proportional to the area of the sector between the central body and that arc (the “area law”); and (3) there is an exact relationship between the squares of the planets' periodic times and the cubes of the radii of their orbits (the “harmonic law”). Kepler himself did not call these discoveries “laws,” as would become customary after Isaac Newton derive...
</Question>
<Choice>Kepler, Johannes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Babylonian astronomer who may have been responsible for what modern scholars call System B, a Babylonian theory that described the speed of the Moon's motion around the zodiac as increasing gradually and then decreasing gradually in the course of a month, following a regular sawtooth pattern. In this very successful theory, the Sun also varied its speed in a sawtooth pattern. The Babylonian lunar theory included a scheme for the motion of the Sun, since the Sun figures in the prediction of lunar phenomena such as phases and eclipses. In the simpler and probably older System A for the behaviour...
</Question>
<Choice>Kidinnu</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jesuit priest and scholar, sometimes called the last Renaissance man, important for his prodigious activity in disseminating knowledge.Kircher learned Greek and Hebrew at the Jesuit school in Fulda, pursued scientific and humanistic studies at Paderborn, Cologne, and Koblenz, and in 1628 was ordained at Mainz. He fled the increasing factional and dynastic fighting in Germany (part of the Thirty Years' War) and, after occupying various academic positions at Avignon, settled in 1634 in Rome. There he remained for most of his life, functioning as a kind of one-man intellectual clearinghouse for c...
</Question>
<Choice>Kircher, Athanasius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian astronomer, who claimed to have discovered volcano-like activity on the Moon. His sightings of apparent gaseous emissions from the lunar surface challenged the long-held theory that the Moon is a dead and inert celestial body.In 1931 Kozyrev joined the staff of the Pulkovo Astronomical Observatory, near Leningrad (St. Petersburg), where he studied the planets and auroral phenomena. These studies gained him distinction, but he was imprisoned by the Stalin regime in 1937 and was not released until 1948.In 1954 Kozyrev made a much-disputed report of an aurora, similar to the Earth's Auror...
</Question>
<Choice>Kozyrev, Nikolay Aleksandrovich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch-American astronomer known especially for his discoveries and theories concerning the solar system.Kuiper graduated from the University of Leiden in 1927 and received his Ph.D. from that school in 1933. That same year he moved to the United States, where he became a naturalized citizen (1937). He joined the staff of Yerkes Observatory of the University of Chicago in 1936, twice serving as director (1947–49 and 1957–60) of both Yerkes and McDonald observatories. Kuiper founded the Lunar and Planetary Laboratory at the University of Arizona in 1960 and served as its director until his death...
</Question>
<Choice>Kuiper, Gerard Peter</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French astronomer who mapped the constellations visible from the Southern Hemisphere and named many of them.In 1739 Lacaille was appointed professor of mathematics in the Mazarin College, Paris, and in 1741 was admitted to the Academy of Sciences. He led an expedition (1750–54) to the Cape of Good Hope, where he determined in only two years' time the positions of nearly 10,000 stars—many still referred to by his catalog numbers. His observations from South Africa of the Moon, Venus, and Mars, in conjunction with similar observations already made in the Northern Hemisphere, led to the calculati...
</Question>
<Choice>Lacaille, Nicolas Louis de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French astronomer whose tables of planetary positions were considered the best available until the end of the 18th century.A law student in Paris, Lalande became interested in astronomy while he was lodging at the Hôtel de Cluny, where the noted astronomer Joseph-Nicolas Delisle had his observatory. In 1751 Lalande went to Berlin to make lunar observations in concert with the work of Nicolas Louis de Lacaille at the Cape of Good Hope. The success of this task and the subsequent calculation of the Moon's distance secured for Lalande, before he reached the age of 21, admission to the Academy of...
</Question>
<Choice>Lalande, Jerome</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss German mathematician, astronomer, physicist, and philosopher who provided the first rigorous proof that p (the ratio of a circle's circumference to its diameter) is irrational, meaning that it cannot be expressed as the quotient of two integers.Lambert, the son of a tailor, was largely self-educated and early in his life began geometric and astronomical investigations by means of instruments he designed and built himself. He worked for a time as a bookkeeper, secretary, and editor. As a private tutor in 1748, he gained access to a good library, which he used for self-improvement until 17...
</Question>
<Choice>Lambert, Johann Heinrich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish-born German astronomer noted for discovering that the magnetic field of the Earth fluctuates with a period somewhat in excess of 10 years.In 1827 Lamont began working at the Royal Observatory, Bogenhausen, near Munich. He adopted German nationality and worked at Bogenhausen for the rest of his life, as director of the observatory from 1835 and also as professor of astronomy at the University of Munich from 1852. In addition to his other work, he determined the orbits of Saturn's satellites Enceladus and Tethys, the periods of Uranus' satellites Ariel and Titan, and the mass of Uranus....
</Question>
<Choice>Lamont, Johann von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astrophysicist and aeronautical pioneer who developed new instruments with which to study the Sun and built the first powered heavier-than-air machine of significant size to achieve sustained flight.Following his education at the Boston Latin School, Langley worked as an engineer and architectural draftsman before traveling to Europe in 1864. Following his return in 1866, he was appointed an assistant professor of mathematics at the U.S. Naval Academy in Annapolis, Md. The next year he accepted a position as a professor of physics and astronomy at the Western University of Pennsylvani...
</Question>
<Choice>Langley, Samuel Pierpont</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician, astronomer, and physicist who is best known for his investigations into the stability of the solar system.Laplace successfully accounted for all the observed deviations of the planets from their theoretical orbits by applying Sir Isaac Newton's theory of gravitation to the solar system, and he developed a conceptual view of evolutionary change in the structure of the solar system. He also demonstrated the usefulness of probability for interpreting scientific data.Laplace was the son of a peasant farmer. Little is known of his early life except that he quickly showed his m...
</Question>
<Choice>Laplace, Pierre-Simon, marquis de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
amateur English astronomer who discovered Ariel and Umbriel, satellites of Uranus; and Triton, a satellite of Neptune. He also discovered a satellite of Saturn, Hyperion (also discovered independently by William Bond and George Bond).Lassell started a brewery business about 1825, after a seven-year apprenticeship. He became interested in astronomy and, in 1844, began construction of a 24-inch reflecting telescope, using a machine of his own design for polishing the mirror. With this telescope, the first of its size to be set in an equatorial mounting, he discovered Triton on Oct. 10, 1846, onl...
</Question>
<Choice>Lassell, William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French astronomer who predicted by mathematical means the existence of the planet Neptune.Appointed a teacher of astronomy at the École Polytechnique (“Polytechnic School”), Paris, in 1837, Le Verrier first undertook an extensive study of the theory of the planet Mercury's orbit and compiled greatly improved tables of the motion of that planet.In 1845 he turned his attention to the irregular orbit of Uranus, which he explained by assuming the presence of a previously unknown planet. Independently of the English astronomer John C. Adams, he calculated the size and position of the unknown body a...
</Question>
<Choice>Le Verrier, Urbain-Jean-Joseph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronomer known for her discovery of the relationship between period and luminosity in Cepheid variables, pulsating stars that vary regularly in brightness in periods ranging from a few days to several months.Leavitt attended Oberlin College for two years (1886–88) and then transferred to the Society for the Collegiate Instruction of Women (later Radcliffe College), from which she graduated in 1892. Following an interest aroused in her senior year, she became a volunteer assistant in the Harvard Observatory in 1895. In 1902 she received a permanent staff appointment. From the outset...
</Question>
<Choice>Leavitt, Henrietta Swan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Belgian astronomer and cosmologist who formulated the modern big-bang theory, which holds that the universe began in a cataclysmic explosion of a small, primeval “super-atom.”A civil engineer, Lemaître served as an artillery officer in the Belgian Army during World War I. After the war he entered a seminary and in 1923 was ordained a priest. He studied at the University of Cambridge's solar physics laboratory (1923–24) and then at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge (1925–27), where he became acquainted with the findings of the American astronomers Edwin P. Hubble and Harlow S...
</Question>
<Choice>Lemaitre, Georges</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese mathematician and astronomer.Li was the son of a widely educated state official. He was given a position in the Imperial Astronomical Bureau in 627, following his critique of the Wuyin calendar, which had been introduced in 619. Later he submitted a report concerning the outdated astronomical instruments used in the bureau and was ordered to make a new armillary sphere; it was accomplished in 633 according to his design, which added a third ring to the traditional two-ring structure.Li became the deputy director of the Imperial Astronomical Bureau about 641. He participated in the comp...
</Question>
<Choice>Li Chunfeng</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese mathematician and astronomer who made notable contributions to the revival of traditional Chinese mathematics and astronomy and to the development of the theory of equations.Having failed the Chinese civil service examinations several times, Li Rui could obtain no official position, and he had to make a poor living as an assistant to various mandarin scholar-officials. From about 1800 he began to study the works of the 13th-century mathematicians Li Ye and Qin Jiushao. From these works, he found that the traditional Chinese method of solving higher-degree equations had several advantag...
</Question>
<Choice>Li Rui</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese mathematician, astronomer, and geographer whose translations of European scientific books greatly contributed to the spread of Western science in China.Originally from a military family, Li was made a jinshi (the highest scholar-official title in imperial China) in 1598. In 1601 he met the Italian Jesuit Matteo Ricci, who was one of the first Westerners allowed into the interior of China. To gain acceptance, Ricci had first learned the Chinese language and culture, which in turn enabled him to spread knowledge of Western science and religion. Li was greatly attracted by Ricci's teachin...
</Question>
<Choice>Li Zhizao</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish astronomer who contributed greatly to the theory of galactic structure and motion and to the methods of determining the absolute magnitude (true brightness, disregarding distance) of distant stars.After serving as an assistant at the observatory in Uppsala, Swed., Lindblad joined the Stockholm Observatory and in 1927 was appointed director, a post he held until 1965. He planned the observatory's relocation in 1931 to nearby Saltsjöbaden and modernized its facilities.By the early 1920s the Dutch astronomer Jacobus C. Kapteyn and others had made statistical studies establishing that gene...
</Question>
<Choice>Lindblad, Bertil</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British astronomer who in 1868 discovered in the Sun's atmosphere a previously unknown element that he named helium after Helios, the Greek name for the Sun and the Sun god.Lockyer became a clerk in the War Office in 1857, but his interest in astronomy eventually led to a career in that field. He initiated in 1866 the spectroscopic observation of sunspots, and in 1868 he found that solar prominences are upheavals in a layer that he named the chromosphere. Also in 1868, he and French astronomer Pierre Janssen, working independently, discovered a spectroscopic method of observing solar prominenc...
</Question>
<Choice>Lockyer, Sir Joseph Norman</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish astronomer, noted for his scholarship and teaching, who in 1980 was named astronomer royal for Scotland.Longair was educated at the University of St. Andrews, Dundee, and at the University of Cambridge (M.A., Ph.D., 1967). In 1968–69 he went as an exchange fellow to the Soviet Union, where he worked in Moscow at the P.N. Lebedev Physical Institute of the Academy of Sciences of the U.S.S.R. He was a resident fellow of Cambridge from 1967 to 1971 and an official fellow from 1971 to 1980 and held positions of both demonstrator (1970–75) and lecturer (1975–80). He was a visiting professor...
</Question>
<Choice>Longair, Malcolm Sim</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Danish astronomer and astrologer who is best known for his association with and published support of Tycho Brahe. In 1600, when Johannes Kepler went to Prague to work with Tycho, he found Tycho and Longomontanus engaged in extensive observations and studies of Mars. This turned out to be fortuitous, for, as Kepler later wrote, “Had Christian been treating a different planet, I would have started on it as well.” It was these observations of Mars that eventually enabled Kepler to discover the true laws of planetary motion. Longomontanus later used Tycho's data to compile the Astronomia danica (1...
</Question>
<Choice>Longomontanus, Christian</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English radio astronomer, founder and director (1951–81) of England's Jodrell Bank Experimental Station (now Jodrell Bank Observatory).Lovell attended the University of Bristol, from which he received a Ph.D. in 1936. After a year as an assistant lecturer in physics at the University of Manchester, he became a member of the cosmic-ray research team at that institution, working in this capacity until the outbreak of World War II in 1939, when he published his first book, Science and Civilization. During World War II Lovell worked for the Air Ministry, doing valuable research in the use of radar...
</Question>
<Choice>Lovell, Sir Alfred Charles Bernard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronomer who predicted the existence of a planet beyond the orbit of Neptune and initiated the search that ended in the discovery of Pluto.A member of the distinguished Lowell family of Massachusetts (he was brother to A. Lawrence Lowell and Amy Lowell), he devoted himself (1883–93) to literature and travel, much of the time in the Far East, which he described in Chosön (1886), The Soul of the Far East (1888), Noto (1891), and Occult Japan (1895). During part of this time he was counselor and foreign secretary to the Korean Special Mission to the United States.In the 1890s, inspired...
</Question>
<Choice>Lowell, Percival</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French astronomer who invented the coronagraph (1930), an instrument which allows the observation of the solar corona when the Sun is not in eclipse.Before Lyot's coronagraph, observing the corona had been possible only during a solar eclipse, but this was unsatisfactory because total eclipses occur only rarely and the duration of such eclipses is too short (no more than seven minutes) to allow prolonged scientific observation of the corona. Merely blocking out the Sun's radiant disk was insufficient to view the comparatively dim corona because of the diffusion of the Sun's light by the atmosp...
</Question>
<Choice>Lyot, Bernard Ferdinand</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German astronomer who (with Wilhelm Beer) published the most complete map of the Moon of the time, Mappa Selenographica, 4 vol. (1834–36). It was the first lunar map to be divided into quadrants, and it remained unsurpassed in its detail until J.F. Julius Schmidt's map of 1878. The Mappa Selenographica was accompanied in 1837 by a volume providing micrometric measurements of the diameters of 148 craters and the elevations of 830 mountains on the Moon's surface. Beer and Mädler also collaborated in publishing in 1830 the first systematic chart of the surface features of the planet Mars.Graduati...
</Question>
<Choice>Madler, Johann Heinrich von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(Latin),German astronomer who named the four largest moons of Jupiter: Io, Europa, Ganymede, and Callisto. All four are named after mythological figures with whom Jupiter fell in love. He and Italian astronomer Galileo Galilei both claimed to have discovered them, about 1610, and it is likely both did so independently. A dispute over priority resulted in unwarranted obloquy for Marius. The two were antagonists for the rest of their lives, and on several occasions Galileo attacked Marius in print and accused him of plagiarizing his work.Marius studied briefly with Danish astronomer Tycho Brahe...
</Question>
<Choice>Marius, Simon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British astronomer noted for his contribution to the science of navigation.Maskelyne was ordained a minister in 1755, but his interest in astronomy had been aroused by the eclipse of July 25, 1748. In 1758 he was admitted to the Royal Society of London, which in 1761 sent him to the island of St. Helena to observe a transit of Venus. During the voyage he experimented with the determination of longitude by observations of the Moon's position and introduced this method into navigation by publishing The British Mariner's Guide (1763). Succeeding Nathaniel Bliss as astronomer royal in 1765, he pub...
</Question>
<Choice>Maskelyne, Nevil</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French astronomer and mathematician who worked particularly on the determination of the distances of the stars.After a brief period as an engineer, Mathieu became an astronomer at the Observatoire de Paris and at the Bureau des Longitudes in 1817. He later served as professor of astronomy at the Collège de France, Paris, and from 1829 was professor of analysis at the École Polytechnique, Paris. He represented Macon in the Chamber of Deputies (1834–48). For many years he edited the work on population statistics, L'Annuaire du Bureau des Longitudes, and published L'Histoire de l'astronomie au XV...
</Question>
<Choice>Mathieu, Claude-Louis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician, biologist, and astronomer who helped popularize Newtonian mechanics.Maupertuis became a member of the Academy of Sciences in Paris in 1731 and soon became the foremost French proponent of the Newtonian theory of gravitation. In 1736 he led an expedition to Lapland to measure the length of a degree along the meridian. His measurement verified the Newtonian view that the Earth is an oblate spheroid (a sphere flattened at the poles). The success of his expedition gained him favour with Frederick the Great, who called him to Berlin. He became a member of the Berlin Academy of...
</Question>
<Choice>Maupertuis, Pierre-Louis Moreau de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German astronomer who developed lunar tables that greatly assisted navigators in determining longitude at sea. Mayer also discovered the libration (or apparent wobbling) of the Moon.A self-taught mathematician, Mayer had already published two original geometrical works when, in 1746, he entered the employ of a cartographic establishment in Nürnberg. Mayer published his calculations of the Moon's libration and equatorial inclination in the transactions of the Nürnberg Cosmographic Society, thereby gaining a scientific reputation that led to his appointment to the chair of economy and mathematic...
</Question>
<Choice>Mayer, Johann Tobias</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French astronomer and hydrographer who, with Jean Delambre, measured the meridian arc from Dunkirk, Fr., to Barcelona. The measurement was made between 1792 and 1798 to establish a basis for the unit of length in the metric system called for by the French national legislature. Mechain also discovered 11 comets and calculated the orbits of these and other known comets.Born the son of a master ceiling plasterer, Mechain early in life showed mathematical prowess and worked as a hydrographer for the Naval Map Archives at Versailles during the 1770s. He turned to astronomy, and in 1782 his work wit...
</Question>
<Choice>Mechain, Pierre</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese court official, mathematician, and astronomer.Mei Juecheng learned mathematics from his grandfather Mei Wending (1633–1721), a renowned mathematician and astronomer. In 1712 Mei Juecheng became a court mathematician and the following year joined the Mengyangzhai (an imperial bureau created to synthesize Western and Chinese scientific knowledge) as one of the chief editors of Lüli yuanyuan (c. 1723; “Source of Mathematical Harmonics and Astronomy”), a compendium on music, mathematics, and astronomy. Unlike earlier such endeavours, this was purely a work of Chinese authorship; Jesuits we...
</Question>
<Choice>Mei Juecheng</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese writer on astronomy and mathematics whose work represented an association of Chinese and Western knowledge.In 1645 China adopted a new, controversial calendar that had been prepared under the direction of the Jesuit Adam Schall von Bell. Together with his three younger brothers, Mei studied calendar design under the Daoist Ni Guanghu. A member of a loyalist family, Mei remained independent rather than join the “foreign” Manchu administration, but his fame spread far beyond the boundaries of his province. The Kangxi emperor was interested in Mei's work, the Lixue yiwen (c. 1701; “Inquir...
</Question>
<Choice>Mei Wending</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French astronomer who was the first to compile a systematic catalog of nebulae and star clusters. In Messier's time a nebula was a term used to denote any blurry celestial light source.In 1751 Messier became a draftsman and recorder of astronomical observations for the noted French astronomer Joseph-Nicolas Delisle. Messier was the first in France to observe the anticipated return of Halley's Comet in 1758–59, and from that time he became an ardent searcher for new comets. Called the comet ferret by King Louis XV, Messier independently discovered 13 of them and observed many more.In 1760 he be...
</Question>
<Choice>Messier, Charles</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British geologist and astronomer who is considered one of the fathers of seismology, the science of earthquakes.In 1760, the year in which he was elected a fellow of the Royal Society of London, Michell finished writing Conjectures Concerning the Cause, and Observations upon the Phænomena of Earthquakes, in which he presented the conclusions from his study of the disastrous Lisbon earthquake of 1755. He showed that the focus of that earthquake was underneath the Atlantic Ocean, and he proposed erroneously that the cause of earthquakes was high-pressure steam, created when water comes into cont...
</Question>
<Choice>Michell, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese astronomer and mathematician who studied the power series expansions of trigonometric functions. See the .Minggantu was a Mongolian of the Plain White Banner (one of the administrative units used by the Manchu; seeBanner system). His name first appeared in official Chinese records in 1712, among the Kangxi emperor's retinue, as a shengyuan (state-subsidized student) of the Imperial Astronomical Bureau. He spent his whole career there, at a time when Jesuit missionaries were in charge of calendar reforms. In 1713 Minggantu was appointed to the newly created Office of Mathematics, where...
</Question>
<Choice>Minggantu</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Flemish astronomer and solar physicist who pioneered in solar spectrophotometry and showed how such a technique could reveal much about the structure of the Sun's outer layers.Minnaert was first a botanist, but his desire to understand more fully the effect of light on plants led him to study physics at the University of Leiden, in The Netherlands. Exiled from Belgium for his support of the nationalist Flemish movement before and during World War I, he became a staff member of the solar observatory at Utrecht in 1921.After the invention of the microphotometer about 1920, Minnaert undertook the...
</Question>
<Choice>Minnaert, Marcel Gilles Jozef</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first professional woman astronomer in the United States.Mitchell was educated in schools on her native Nantucket, Massachusetts, including the one conducted by her father. Her interest in astronomy was stimulated by her father, who let her assist in his work of rating chronometers for the Nantucket whaling fleet and who encouraged her independent use of his telescope. From 1836 to 1856 she worked as a librarian in the Nantucket Atheneum during the day (often acting as an informal teacher) and became a regular observer of the skies at night.In October 1847 Mitchell succeeded in establishing th...
</Question>
<Choice>Mitchell, Maria</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German mathematician and theoretical astronomer who is best known for his work in analytic geometry and in topology. In the latter field he is especially remembered as one of the discoverers of the Möbius strip.Möbius entered the University of Leipzig in 1809 and soon decided to concentrate on mathematics, astronomy, and physics. From 1813 to 1814 he studied theoretical astronomy under Carl Friedrich Gauss at the University of Göttingen. He then studied mathematics at the University of Halle before he obtained a position as a professor of astronomy at Leipzig in 1816. From 1818 to 1821 Möbius...
</Question>
<Choice>Mobius, August Ferdinand</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British astronomer and politician.Molyneux received his B.A. (1708) and M.A. (1710) from Trinity College, Dublin. He was elected to the Royal Society in 1712. Besides pursuing a career as an astronomer, he was also active in politics, as a member of both the English parliament (1715, 1726, 1727) and the Irish parliament (1727) and as a lord of the Admiralty (1727–28).Molyneux collaborated (1723–25) with James Bradley to improve the construction of reflecting telescopes. Molyneux worked further with Bradley in 1725, setting up a zenith-pointing telescope to try to observe stellar parallax (appa...
</Question>
<Choice>Molyneux, Samuel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronomer who, in 1951, provided the first evidence that the Milky Way Galaxy has spiral arms.Morgan studied at the University of Chicago (Ph.D., 1931) and then became an instructor at the Yerkes Observatory of the University of Chicago. He taught at that university from 1947 until his retirement in 1974, and he was director of the Yerkes and McDonald Observatories from 1960 to 1963. During his career he received many awards and honours.Morgan was an astronomical morphologist who devoted his career to studying and classifying stars and galaxies. His first significant contribution was...
</Question>
<Choice>Morgan, William Wilson</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the earliest Babylonian astronomer known by name, who devised the so-called System A, a group of ephemerides, or tables, giving the positions of the Moon, Sun, and planets at any given moment. Based on centuries of observation, these tables were nonetheless somewhat crude and were superseded about a century later by Kidinnu's System B, a refined mathematical method for finding celestial positions more accurately. Both systems were in use simultaneously between 250 and 50 BC. Nabu-rimanni also calculated the length of the synodic month (from New Moon to New Moon) to be 29.530614 days, as compar...
</Question>
<Choice>Nabu-rimanni</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Canadian-born American astronomer and mathematician who prepared ephemerides—tables of computed places of celestial bodies over a period of time—and tables of astronomical constants.
</Question>
<Choice>Newcomb, Simon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
cardinal, mathematician, scholar, experimental scientist, and influential philosopher who stressed the incomplete nature of man's knowledge of God and of the universe. At the Council of Basel in 1432, he gained recognition for his opposition to the candidate put forward by Pope Eugenius IV for the archbishopric of Trier. To his colleagues at the council he dedicated De concordantia catholica (1433; “On Catholic Concordance”), in which he expressed support for the supremacy of the general councils of the church over the authority of the papacy. In the same work he discussed the harmony of the c...
</Question>
<Choice>Nicholas of Cusa</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronomer best known for discovering four satellites of Jupiter: the 9th in 1914 (at Lick Observatory, Mount Hamilton, California), the 10th and 11th in 1938, and the 12th in 1951 (all at Mount Wilson Observatory, Calif.).Educated at Drake University, Des Moines, Iowa, and at the University of California (Ph.D., 1915), Nicholson was on the Mount Wilson Observatory staff from 1915 to 1957. Of greater astrophysical significance than his satellite discoveries was his investigation of sunspots, especially their magnetic properties and terrestrial effects. With the American astronomer Edi...
</Question>
<Choice>Nicholson, Seth Barnes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Telugu-speaking Brahman, yogi, minor philosopher, and prominent astronomer who founded the devotional sect called Nimbarkas, Nimandi, or Nimavats, who worshiped the deity Krishna (K???a) and his consort, Radha.Nimbarka has been identified with Bhaskara, a 9th- or 10th-century philosopher and celebrated commentator on the Brahma-sutra (Ve-danta-sutra). Most historians of Hindu mysticism, however, hold that Nimbarka probably lived in the 12th or 13th century because of the similarities between his philosophical and devotional attitudes and those of Ramanuja (traditionally dated 1017–1137). Both...
</Question>
<Choice>Nimbarka</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German astronomer and physician who discovered the asteroidsPallas and Vesta, as well as five comets.In 1779 Olbers devised a new method of calculating the orbits of comets. Two years later he opened his medical practice in Bremen, where he equipped the upper portion of his house for use as an observatory and devoted the greater part of each night to astronomy.He took a leading role in the search for a planet between Mars and Jupiter. In March 1802 he discovered Pallas, the second asteroid to be identified. Because Bode's law (which gave the sequence of planetary distances in terms of a numero...
</Question>
<Choice>Olbers, Wilhelm</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Persian mathematician, astronomer, and poet, renowned in his own country and time for his scientific achievements but chiefly known to English-speaking readers through the translation of a collection of his roba?iyat (“quatrains”) in The Rubáiyát of Omar Khayyám (1859), by the English writer Edward FitzGerald.His name Khayyam (“Tentmaker”) may have been derived from his father's trade. He received a good education in the sciences and philosophy in his native Neyshabur before traveling to Samarkand (now in Uzbekistan), where he completed the algebra treatise, Risalah fi?l-barahin ?ala masa?il a...
</Question>
<Choice>Omar Khayyam</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch astronomer who was one of the most important figures in 20th-century efforts to understand the nature of the Milky Way Galaxy.After studies at the University of Groningen, Oort was appointed astronomer to the Leiden Observatory in 1924 and became director in 1945, a position he held until 1970. In 1925 Bertil Lindblad of Sweden had advanced the theory that the Milky Way rotates in its own plane around the centre of the galaxy. Oort was able to confirm this theory in 1927 through his own direct observations of star velocities in the galaxy, and he modified the theory substantially into th...
</Question>
<Choice>Oort, Jan Hendrick</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Estonian astronomer best known for his studies of meteors and meteorites, and whose life work was devoted to understanding the structure and evolution of the cosmos.Öpik graduated with a gold medal from Tallinn University in Estonia in 1911, and in 1916 he received his degree in astronomy from Moscow University. In 1919 he joined the staff of the Tashkent Observatory (now in Uzbekistan) and from 1921 to 1944 worked at the Astronomical Observatory in Tartu, Estonia. The research he performed during the early 1920s elucidated the theory of the entry of high-speed bodies into the atmosphere and w...
</Question>
<Choice>Opik, Ernest Julius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French Roman Catholic bishop, scholastic philosopher, economist, and mathematician whose work provided some basis for the development of modern mathematics and science and of French prose, particularly its scientific vocabulary.It is known that Oresme was of Norman origin, although the exact place and year of his birth are uncertain. Similarly, the details of his early education are unknown. In 1348 his name appears on a list of graduate scholarship holders in theology at the College of Navarre at the University of Paris. As Oresme became grand master of the college in 1356, he must have compl...
</Question>
<Choice>Oresme, Nicholas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Silesian astronomer best known for his discovery of 120 asteroids. He also prepared two catalogs containing the positions of almost 4,700 stars.Palisa briefly was an assistant astronomer at the observatories in Vienna and Geneva before being appointed director (1872–80) of the Austro-Hungarian naval observatory at Pola (now Pula, Croatia), a position that carried with it the rank of commander. From 1880 to 1919 he was a member of the staff at the Vienna Observatory. By 1891, when the photographic plate was first used in astronomy, he had found 83 of the 120 asteroids he eventually identified b...
</Question>
<Choice>Palisa, Johann</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American mathematician, astronomer, and educator who computed the general perturbations of the planets Uranus and Neptune.Peirce graduated from Harvard University in 1829 and accepted a teaching position with George Bancroft at his Round Hill School in Northampton, Massachusetts. Two years later Peirce was asked to join the faculty at Harvard as a tutor in mathematics. Much of his reputation was based on two of his early works. The first was his solution to a mathematical problem proposed in the journal Mathematical Diary, in which he proved that there is no odd perfect number (a number that i...
</Question>
<Choice>Peirce, Benjamin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French antiquary, Humanist, and influential patron of learning who discovered the Orion Nebula (1610) and was among the first to emphasize the study of coins for historical research.Travels in Italy (1599–1602), studies at Padua, and acquaintance there with Galileo stimulated Peiresc's antiquarian and astronomical interests. A senator at the Parlement of Aix from 1605, he corresponded with the Flemish painter Peter Paul Rubens and many of the noted scholars of the day. Peiresc was first to verify William Harvey's discovery of the circulation of blood, and Sir Isaac Newton made use of his work...
</Question>
<Choice>Peiresc, Nicolas-Claude Fabri de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. astronomer who discovered the sixth and seventh moons of Jupiter in 1904 and 1905, respectively. In 1904 he published a calculation of the solar parallax (a measure of the Earth–Sun distance) based on observations of the minor planet Eros during one of its close approaches to the Earth.Perrine worked at the Lick Observatory in California from 1893 to 1909 and then until his retirement in 1936 was director of the Argentine National Observatory in Córdoba. His work included counts of extragalactic nebulae and the discovery of 13 comets.
</Question>
<Choice>Perrine, Charles Dillon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian mathematician and astronomer instrumental in the European revival of the technical understanding of the astronomical ideas of Ptolemy (fl. c. AD 140) and the early use of sines in Europe.Nothing is known of Peuerbach's life before 1446, when he entered the University of Vienna (B.A., 1448). Between 1448 and 1451 he traveled, notably in northern Italy, where he lectured on astronomy in Padua. Returning to Vienna, he became a master of arts in 1453 and lectured on Latin poetry at the university. His own literary aspirations appear in Latin love poems addressed to a young Carthusian novi...
</Question>
<Choice>Peuerbach, Georg von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian astronomer who discovered (Jan. 1, 1801) and named the first asteroid, or “minor planet,” Ceres.Piazzi became a Theatine monk in about 1764 and a professor of theology in Rome in 1779, and in 1780 he was appointed professor of higher mathematics at the Academy of Palermo. Later, with the aid of the viceroy of Sicily, he founded the Observatory of Palermo. There he produced his great catalog of the positions of 7,646 stars and demonstrated that most stars are in motion relative to the Sun. There also he discovered Ceres and the high proper motion of the important double star 61 Cygni.
</Question>
<Choice>Piazzi, Giuseppe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French astronomer who first accurately measured the length of a degree of a meridian (longitude line) and from that computed the size of the Earth.Picard became professor of astronomy at the Collège de France, Paris, in 1655. His measurement of the Earth was used by Sir Isaac Newton to verify his theory of gravitation. In 1671 Picard went to the observatory of the noted 16th-century Danish astronomer Tycho Brahe at Hven Island, Sweden, to determine its exact location so that Brahe's observations could be more precisely compared with those made elsewhere. He brought back copies of the originals...
</Question>
<Choice>Picard, Jean</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. physicist and astronomer who introduced the use of the meridian photometer to measure the magnitude of stars and established the Harvard Photometry (1884), the first great photometric catalog.In 1867 Pickering became professor of physics at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, where he established the first U.S. laboratory in which students were required to use laboratory instruments to make measurements. In 1876 he was appointed professor of astronomy and director of the Harvard College Observatory.He invented the meridian photometer, which utilized a calcite prism to ju...
</Question>
<Choice>Pickering, Edward Charles</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. astronomer who discovered Phoebe, the ninth satellite of Saturn.In 1891 Pickering joined his brother Edward in establishing the Boyden station of the Harvard Observatory at Arequipa, Peru. He returned to the United States in 1893 and the next year erected the observatory and telescope at Flagstaff, Ariz., for the noted U.S. astronomer Percival Lowell. In 1900 he established a station for the Harvard Observatory at Mandeville.He discovered Phoebe in 1899 and noted that it revolves around Saturn in the opposite direction (retrograde) from that of Saturn's other satellites. His announcement...
</Question>
<Choice>Pickering, William Henry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Canadian astronomer remembered for his expert design of instruments and his extensive spectroscopic observations.Plaskett, a skilled mechanic and photographer, graduated from the University of Toronto in 1899. In 1903 he joined the staff of the Dominion Observatory at Ottawa, where he initiated astrophysical research and devised a spectrograph that made the telescope at Ottawa equivalent to much larger instruments.In 1913 Plaskett persuaded the Canadian government to finance the construction of a 72-inch (183-centimetre) reflector. That instrument, largely designed by Plaskett, was placed in o...
</Question>
<Choice>Plaskett, John Stanley</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician, one of the greatest mathematicians and mathematical physicists at the end of 19th century. He made a series of profound innovations in geometry, the theory of differential equations, electromagnetism, topology, and the philosophy of mathematics.Poincaré grew up in Nancy and studied mathematics from 1873 to 1875 at the École Polytechnique in Paris. He continued his studies at the Mining School in Caen before receiving his doctorate from the École Polytechnique in 1879. While a student, he discovered new types of complex functions that solved a wide variety of differential...
</Question>
<Choice>Poincare, Henri</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
sixth astronomer royal of England, who organized the Royal Greenwich Observatory to an efficiency that made possible a degree of observational precision never before achieved.Pond was elected a fellow of the Royal Society in 1807 and served from 1811 to 1835 as astronomer royal. During Pond's term, obsolete and worn-out instruments at Greenwich were replaced and the staff increased from one to six, enabling him to complete in 1833 a catalog of positions of 1,112 stars with an accuracy previously unknown. He was a member of the Royal Astronomical Society from the time of its founding in 1820.
</Question>
<Choice>Pond, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
an Egyptian astronomer, mathematician, and geographer of Greek descent who flourished in Alexandria during the 2nd century AD. In several fields his writings represent the culminating achievement of Greco-Roman science, particularly his geocentric (Earth-centred) model of the universe now known as the Ptolemaic system.Virtually nothing is known about Ptolemy's life except what can be inferred from his writings. His first major astronomical work, the Almagest, was completed about AD 150 and contains reports of astronomical observations that Ptolemy had made over the preceding quarter of a centu...
</Question>
<Choice>Ptolemy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Belgian mathematician, astronomer, statistician, and sociologist known for his application of statistics and probability theory to social phenomena.From 1819 Quetelet lectured at the Brussels Athenaeum, military college, and museum. In 1823 he went to Paris to study astronomy, meteorology, and the management of an astronomical observatory. While there he learned probability from Joseph Fourier and, conceivably, from Pierre-Simon Laplace. Quetelet founded (1828) and directed the Royal Observatory in Brussels, served as perpetual secretary of the Belgian Royal Academy (1834–74), and organized th...
</Question>
<Choice>Quetelet, Adolphe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the foremost mathematician and astronomer of 15th-century Europe, a sought-after astrologer, and one of the first printers.Königsberg means “King's Mountain,” which is what the Latinized version of his name, Joannes de Regio monte or Regiomontanus, also means. A miller's son, he entered the University of Leipzig at the age of 11 and in 1450 went to the University of Vienna. Regiomontanus was awarded a baccalaureate in 1452, but university regulations forced him to wait until he turned 21 to receive his master's degree. He eventually collaborated with his teacher, the mathematician-astronomer G...
</Question>
<Choice>Regiomontanus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian-born astronomer and mathematician who was among the first to adopt and spread the heliocentric theory of Nicolaus Copernicus.In 1536 Rheticus was appointed to a chair of mathematics and astronomy at the University of Wittenberg. Intrigued by the news of the Copernican theory that Earth revolves around the Sun, he went to Frauenburg (now Frombork, Pol.) in 1539, where he studied for two years with Copernicus. Rheticus published the first account of the new views in his De libris revolutionum…Nic. Copernici…narratio prima… (1540; “The First Account of the Book on the Revolutions by Nico...
</Question>
<Choice>Rheticus, Georg Joachim</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French astronomer whose observations of the planet Mars from Cayenne, French Guiana, in 1671–73 contributed to both astronomy and geodesy. The French government sent Richer to Cayenne to investigate atmospheric refraction at a site near the Equator, to observe the Sun to get a better value for the obliquity of the ecliptic, and especially to measure the parallax of Mars at its opposition. Comparison of Richer's Mars observations with those made elsewhere made it possible to determine the distances of Mars and the Sun from Earth, leading to the first reasonably accurate calculation of the dimen...
</Question>
<Choice>Richer, Jean</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronomer and inventor who was an early observer of the atmosphere of Venus.A clockmaker by trade, Rittenhouse built mathematical instruments and, it is believed, the first telescope in the United States. He also introduced the use of natural spider webbing to form the reticle (system of cross hairs) in telescope transits and other position-measuring instruments. Rittenhouse was highly esteemed as a surveyor; he supervised the establishment of the boundaries between Pennsylvania and Maryland, New Jersey, New York, and the Northwest Territory, and parts of those between New York and N...
</Question>
<Choice>Rittenhouse, David</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British astronomer who was a pioneer in photography of nebulae.In 1883 Roberts began experimenting with astronomical photography, taking pictures of stars, the Orion and Andromeda nebulae, and the Pleiades cluster. Although the photographs proved difficult to interpret, they were revealing. His three-hour exposure of the Pleiades showed the nebulosity surrounding these stars, and his photographs of Andromeda showed its spiral structure. Roberts's photographs were exhibited regularly at the Royal Astronomical Society and earned him the Society's Gold Medal in 1895.
</Question>
<Choice>Roberts, Isaac</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Danish astronomer who demonstrated conclusively that light travels at a finite speed.Rømer went to Paris in 1672, where he spent nine years working at the Royal Observatory. The observatory's director, Italian-born French astronomer Gian Domenico Cassini, was engaged with a problem that had been studied long before by Galileo: how to use the periodic eclipses of the moons of Jupiter as a universal clock that would be an aid to navigation. (As a satellite goes behind Jupiter, it passes into the shadow of the planet and disappears.) Cassini and his coworkers discovered that the times between suc...
</Question>
<Choice>Romer, Ole Christensen</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Irish astronomer and builder of the largest reflecting telescope, the “Leviathan,” of the 19th century.In 1821 Parsons was elected to the House of Commons. He resigned his seat in 1834 but in 1841 inherited his father's title, becoming the 3rd earl of Rosse, and served as one of the Irish peers in the House of Lords.Lord Rosse was obsessed with the idea of constructing a truly large telescope and worked for five years to find an alloy suitable for the mirror. His mirrors were made of speculum metal, an alloy of approximately two parts copper to one part tin by weight. (Some makers added traces...
</Question>
<Choice>Rosse, William Parsons, 3rd earl of</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronomer—one of the most influential during the first half of the 20th century—who played a major role in the establishment of modern theoretical astrophysics by making physics the core of astrophysical practice. Bearing his name is the Hertzsprung-Russell diagram, a graph that demonstrates the relationship between a star's intrinsic brightness and its spectral type and that represents Russell's theory of the way stars evolve.The first of three sons born to Alexander Gatherer Russell, a liberal Presbyterian minister, and Eliza Hoxie Norris, his proud, mathematically adept mother, Ru...
</Question>
<Choice>Russell, Henry Norris</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British radio astronomer who developed revolutionary radio telescope systems and used them for accurate location of weak radio sources. With improved equipment, he observed the most distant known galaxies of the universe. Ryle and Antony Hewish shared the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1974, the first Nobel prize awarded in recognition of astronomical research.Ryle was the nephew of the philosopher Gilbert Ryle. After earning a degree in physics at the University of Oxford in 1939, he worked with the Telecommunications Research Establishment on the design of radar equipment during World War II. Af...
</Question>
<Choice>Ryle, Sir Martin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English astronomer and geodesist noted for his experiments in determining the shape of the Earth and for his studies of the Earth's magnetic field.He served in the Royal Artillery and was appointed astronomer to the Arctic expeditions of Sir John Ross (1818) and Sir William Parry (1819) in search of the Northwest Passage. In 1821 he began experiments on the coasts of Africa and North America and in the Arctic to determine the Earth's shape more precisely by observing the motion of a pendulum. He published the first results of his work in 1825 and three years later continued his research in Par...
</Question>
<Choice>Sabine, Sir Edward</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronomer and science writer. A popular and influential figure in the United States, he was also controversial in scientific, political, and religious circles for his views on extraterrestrial intelligence, nuclear weapons, and religion. Sagan wrote the article “life” for the 1970 printing of the 14th Edition of Encyclopædia Britannica (1929–73).Sagan attended the University of Chicago, where he earned a bachelor's and a master's degree in physics in 1955 and 1956, respectively, and a doctorate in astronomy and astrophysics in 1960. From 1960 to 1962 he was a fellow in astronomy at t...
</Question>
<Choice>Sagan, Carl</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronomer who led an extensive effort to determine Hubble's constant, the rate at which the universe is expanding. He also discovered the first quasi-stellar radio source (quasar), a starlike object that is a strong emitter of radio waves.Sandage received a bachelor's degree in physics from the University of Illinois at Urbana in 1948 and a doctorate in astronomy from the California Institute of Technology at Pasadena in 1953. While in graduate school, he was the observing assistant for American astronomer Edwin Hubble from 1950 until Hubble's death in 1953. He became a member of the...
</Question>
<Choice>Sandage, Allan Rex</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian astronomer and senator whose reports of groups of straight lines on Mars touched off much controversy on the possible existence of life on that planet.Schiaparelli went to Berlin in 1854 to study astronomy under Johann F. Encke. Two years later he was appointed assistant observer at the Pulkovo Observatory, Russia, a post he resigned in 1860 for a similar one at the Brera Observatory, Milan, where he remained until his retirement in 1900; he became director in 1862.In 1861 Schiaparelli discovered the asteroid Hesperia. Five years later he demonstrated that meteor swarms have orbits sim...
</Question>
<Choice>Schiaparelli, Giovanni Virginio</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronomer who pioneered in the use of photography to map stellar positions and to measure stellar parallaxes, from which the most direct determinations of distance can be made.From 1899 to 1903 Schlesinger was in charge of the International Latitude Observatory at Ukiah, Calif. He then was appointed astronomer at the Yerkes Observatory, Williams Bay, Wis., where he began developing a photographic method of determining parallaxes. With great care he worked to eliminate or compensate for all significant sources of error, with such success that his photographic parallax measurement tech...
</Question>
<Choice>Schlesinger, Frank</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch-born American astronomer whose identification of the wavelengths of the radiation emitted by quasars (quasi-stellar objects) led to the theory that they may be among the most distant, as well as the oldest, objects ever observed.Schmidt was educated at the universities of Groningen and Leiden. He received a Ph.D. from Leiden in 1956 and was scientific officer of the Leiden Observatory until 1959. He joined the staff of the Hale Observatories (now Mount Wilson and Palomar observatories) in California in 1959, at the same time joining the faculty of astronomy at the California Institute of...
</Question>
<Choice>Schmidt, Maarten</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
amateur German astronomer who discovered that sunspots vary in number in a cycle of about 10 years; he announced his findings in 1843, after 17 years of almost daily observations. Schwabe also made (1831) the first known detailed drawing of the Great Red Spot on Jupiter. He was awarded the Gold Medal of the Royal Astronomical Society in 1857 and was elected a foreign member of the Royal Society in 1868—a singular honour for an amateur scientist at that time.
</Question>
<Choice>Schwabe, Samuel Heinrich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German astronomer whose contributions, both practical and theoretical, were of primary importance in the development of 20th-century astronomy.Schwarzschild's exceptional ability in science became evident at the age of 16, when his paper on the theory of celestial orbits was published. In 1901 he became professor and director of the observatory at the University of Göttingen, and eight years later he was appointed director of the Astrophysical Observatory at Potsdam.While at Göttingen, Schwarzschild introduced precise methods in photographic photometry. The results of his studies clearly demon...
</Question>
<Choice>Schwarzschild, Karl</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian Jesuit priest and astrophysicist, who made the first survey of the spectra of stars and suggested that stars be classified according to their spectral type.Secchi entered the Society of Jesus in 1833 and became lecturer in physics and mathematics at the Jesuit College in Loreto, Italy, in 1839. He returned to Rome in 1844, where he completed his theological studies and lectured at the Roman College.When the Jesuits were expelled from Rome in 1848, Secchi went to Stonyhurst College, Clitheroe, Lancashire, Eng., and then to Georgetown University, Washington, D.C. Because of his reputatio...
</Question>
<Choice>Secchi, Pietro Angelo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronomer who deduced that the Sun lies near the central plane of the Galaxy some 30,000 light-years away from the centre.In 1911 Shapley, working with results given by Henry N. Russell, began finding the dimensions of stars in a number of binary systems from measurements of their light variation when they eclipse one another. These methods remained the standard procedure for more than 30 years. Shapley also showed that Cepheid variables cannot be star pairs that eclipse each other. He was the first to propose that they are pulsating stars.Shapley joined the staff of the Mount Wilson...
</Question>
<Choice>Shapley, Harlow</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese astronomer, mathematician, and high official whose famous work Mengxi bitan (“Brush Talks from Dream Brook” [Dream Brook was the name of his estate in Jingkou]) contains the first reference to the magnetic compass, the first description of movable type, and a fairly accurate explanation of the origin of fossils. The Mengxi bitan also contains Shen's observations on such varied subjects as mathematics, astronomy, atmospheric phenomena, cartography, optics, and medicine. Shen produced a number of works, including commentaries on the Confucian Classics, atlases, diplomatic reports, and a...
</Question>
<Choice>Shen Kua</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British optician and astronomer who produced the first truly parabolic—hence nearly distortionless—mirrors for reflecting telescopes.Short entered the University of Edinburgh as a candidate for the ministry, but he was inspired to study optics instead by the lectures of the Scottish mathematician Colin Maclaurin. Maclaurin, realizing Short's mathematical talents, encouraged his interest in mathematics and optics, even providing him with an optical workshop. Short settled in London in 1738 and soon gained renown and wealth for his fine work. He manufactured metallic mirrors for more than 1,000...
</Question>
<Choice>Short, James</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian astronomer-astrologer and mathematician whose astrological writings were particularly influential.Shripati wrote various works in the first two of the three branches of astral science (jyotihshastra)—namely, mathematics (including astronomy), horoscopic astrology, and natural astrology (divination). For the first branch, he wrote Ganitatilaka (“The Ornament of Mathematics”) and the astronomical works Siddhantashekhara (“The Crest of Established Doctrines”), Dhikotidakarana (“Procedure Giving Intellectual Climax”), and Dhruvamanasa (“Permanent Mind”). Siddhantashekhara is modeled on Brah...
</Question>
<Choice>Shripati</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch mathematician, astronomer, and cosmologist who developed theoretical models of the universe based on Albert Einstein's general theory of relativity.De Sitter studied mathematics at the State University of Groningen and then joined the astronomical laboratory there, where under J.C. Kapteyn's guidance he developed a liking for astronomy. He spent the years 1897–99 at the Cape Observatory in South Africa and devoted himself to astronomy thereafter. In 1908 de Sitter became professor of astronomy at the University of Leiden, and in 1919 he became director of the Leiden Observatory.In his ea...
</Question>
<Choice>Sitter, Willem de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronomer whose systematic observations (1912–25) of the extraordinary radial velocities of spiral galaxies provided the first evidence supporting the expanding-universe theory.Born on an Indiana farm, Slipher studied at Indiana University (B.A., 1901; M.A., 1903; Ph.D., 1909). In 1901 he joined the staff of the Lowell Observatory at Flagstaff (though he returned to Indiana at times for graduate study), and he became its acting director in 1916 and director in 1926. There he organized and guided the search that resulted in the discovery of Pluto in 1930. Slipher's extensive investiga...
</Question>
<Choice>Slipher, Vesto Melvin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek astronomer and mathematician, probably from Alexandria, employed by Julius Caesar to devise the Julian calendar. He is sometimes confused with Sosigenes the Peripatetic (fl. 2nd century AD), the tutor of the Greek philosopher Alexander of Aphrodisias.At the conclusion of the Roman civil war (49–45 BC), Caesar set out to replace the multitude of inaccurate and diverse calendars of the Roman commonwealth with a single official calendar. At the suggestion of Sosigenes, he adopted a modification of the 365-day Egyptian solar calendar but with an extra day every fourth year (leap year). (The...
</Question>
<Choice>Sosigenes of Alexandria</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Slovakian astronomer and general who, with Tomáš Masaryk and Edvard Beneš, helped found the new nation of Czechoslovakia in 1918–19.After study at the University of Prague, from which he received a doctorate of philosophy in 1904, Štefánik went to Paris. Joining the staff of the astronomical observatory at Meudon, he served on scientific expeditions to Africa, the Americas, and Oceania. Becoming a naturalized French citizen, he joined the army after the outbreak of World War I and eventually was drawn to the Czechoslovak liberation movement. Encouraged by the French government, he was sent on...
</Question>
<Choice>Stefanik, Milan Rastislav</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
one of the greatest 19th-century astronomers and the first in a line of four generations of distinguished astronomers, who founded the modern study of binary stars.To avoid conscription by the Napoleonic armies, Struve left Germany in 1808 and went first to Denmark and then to Russia. In 1813 he became professor of astronomy and mathematics at the University of Dorpat (now Tartu, Estonia), and four years later he was appointed director of the Dorpat Observatory. In 1824 he obtained a refracting telescope with an aperture of 24 cm (9.6 inches), at that time the finest ever built, and used it in...
</Question>
<Choice>Struve, Friedrich Georg Wilhelm von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian-American astronomer known for his contributions to stellar spectroscopy, notably the discovery of the widespread distribution of hydrogen and other elements in space.Struve was the last member of a dynasty of astronomers and a great-grandson of the noted astronomer Friedrich Georg Wilhelm von Struve. His studies at the University of Kharkov were interrupted for service in the Imperial Russian Army (1916–18) and, after the Russian Revolution, in the White Russian Army (1919–20). He endured months of privation in Turkey after the collapse of the White Army, but in 1921 he was able to emi...
</Question>
<Choice>Struve, Otto</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French astronomer noted for his textbook Traité de mécanique céleste, 4 vol. (1889–96; “Treatise on Celestial Mechanics”). This work, an update of Pierre-Simon Laplace's work on the same subject, is still used as a sourcebook by authors writing on celestial mechanics.Before publishing this work, Tisserand had already established his brilliance in his doctoral dissertation (1868), analyzing Charles-Eugène Delaunay's lunar theory, and in his work as director of the Toulouse Observatory (1873–78). In 1874 he was elected to the Academy of Sciences as a corresponding member and was elevated to full...
</Question>
<Choice>Tisserand, Felix</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Prussian astronomer, physicist, and biologist whose law (1766) expressing the distances between the planets and the Sun was popularized by German astronomer Johann Elert Bode in 1772.Having received a degree from the University of Leipzig (1752), Titius joined the faculty of the University of Wittenberg in 1756. Titius proposed his law of planetary distances in an unsigned interpolation in his German translation of Swiss philosopher Charles Bonnet'sContemplation de la nature (“Contemplation of Nature”). Titius fixed the scale by assigning 100 to the distance of Saturn from the Sun. On this sca...
</Question>
<Choice>Titius, Johann Daniel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronomer who discovered Pluto in 1930 after a systematic search for a ninth planet instigated by the predictions of other astronomers. He also discovered several clusters of stars and galaxies, studied the apparent distribution of extragalactic nebulae, and made observations of the surfaces of Mars, Venus, Jupiter, Saturn, and the Moon.Tombaugh initially had no formal training in astronomy, only a keen interest that had been sharpened by his first glimpse of the heavens through his uncle's telescope. After finishing high school, Tombaugh built his own telescope according to specific...
</Question>
<Choice>Tombaugh, Clyde W.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss-born U.S. astronomer who, in his extensive studies of galactic star clusters, demonstrated the presence throughout the galactic plane of a tenuous haze of interstellar material that absorbs light generally and decreases the apparent brightness of distant clusters.Trumpler was educated in Switzerland and Germany, went to the United States in 1915, and joined the staff of Lick Observatory, Mount Hamilton, Calif., three years later. In 1922 he went to Wallal, W.Aus., Austl., on a solar eclipse expedition to test experimentally Albert Einstein's theory of general relativity by observing whet...
</Question>
<Choice>Trumpler, Robert Julius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English astronomer who pioneered many of the procedures now universally employed in determining stellar positions from astronomical photographs.In 1884 Turner was appointed chief assistant at the Royal Observatory, Greenwich, and in 1893 he became Savilian professor of astronomy and director of the University Observatory at Oxford. A plan for international cooperation in compiling an astrographic chart and catalog had been formulated in 1887 at Paris. Turner worked unceasingly on Oxford's share of the project and made innovations in astronomical photography that contributed to the success of t...
</Question>
<Choice>Turner, Herbert Hall</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
outstanding Persian philosopher, scientist, and mathematician.Educated first in ?us, where his father was a jurist in the Twelfth Imam school, the main sect of Shi?ite Muslims, al-?usi finished his education in Neyshabur, about 75 kilometres (50 miles) to the west. This was no doubt a prudent move as Genghis Khan (d. 1227), having conquered Beijing in 1215, turned his attention to the Islamic world and reached the region around ?us by 1220. In about 1227 the Isma?ilite governor Na?ir al-Din ?Abd al-Ra?im offered al-?usi sanctuary in his mountain fortresses in Khorasan. Al-?usi in turn dedicate...
</Question>
<Choice>Tusi, Nasir al-Din al-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Finnish meteorologist and astronomer noted for developing meteorological measuring methods and instruments.After receiving his Ph.D. in 1922, Väisälä joined the faculty of the Geodetic Institute of Turku University (1925) and worked as an astronomer and surveyor, completing a magnetic survey of the Earth and inventing the light-interference system for measuring long paths (on the order of 100 metres) for use as baselines in geodetic surveys (1927). Later in his career, Väisälä turned to meteorology and developed, among other things, a new method of radio direction finding (1951). In 1952 he he...
</Question>
<Choice>Vaisala, Yrjo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian philosopher, astronomer, and mathematician, author of the Pañca-siddhantika (“Five Treatises”), a compendium of Greek, Egyptian, Roman, and Indian astronomy.Varahamihira's knowledge of Western astronomy was thorough. In five sections, his monumental work progresses through native Indian astronomy and culminates in two treatises on Western astronomy, showing calculations based on Greek and Alexandrian reckoning and even giving complete Ptolemaic mathematical charts and tables.Although Varahamihira's writings give a comprehensive picture of 6th-century India, his real interest lay in astr...
</Question>
<Choice>Varahamihira</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German astronomer who discovered spectroscopic binaries—double-star systems that are too close for the individual stars to be discerned by any telescope but, through the analysis of their light, have been found to be two individual stars rapidly revolving around one another.An assistant at the Leipzig Observatory from 1867, Vogel became director of a private observatory at Bothkamp, Ger., in 1870. His early work centred on the study of planetary spectra (the characteristic wavelengths of the light from the planets) to obtain data on the planetary atmospheres; it was published in his Spectra de...
</Question>
<Choice>Vogel, Hermann Karl</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronomer who built Vassar College's research program in astronomy into one of the nation's finest.Whitney graduated from public high school in 1863 and entered Vassar College, Poughkeepsie, New York, with advanced standing in 1865. She immediately came under the influence of the astronomer Maria Mitchell. After graduating in 1868 Whitney returned to Waltham for a time to care for her widowed mother, then taught school in Auburndale, Massachusetts. In 1869 she traveled to Burlington, Iowa, to observe a solar eclipse with her own three-inch Alvan Clark telescope. From 1869 to 1870 she...
</Question>
<Choice>Whitney, Mary Watson</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German astronomer who applied photography to the search for asteroids and discovered 228 of them.Wolf showed an early interest in astronomy; he was only 21 years old when he discovered a comet, now named for him. In 1890 he was appointed Privatdozent (unsalaried lecturer) at the University of Heidelberg. One year later he adapted a camera to a motor-driven telescope to seek out asteroids. (All previous discoveries had been made one by one by direct observation.) Using a time exposure of the heavens, Wolf demonstrated that the asteroids, because of their orbital motion, would show up in the pho...
</Question>
<Choice>Wolf, Max</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss astronomer and astronomical historian.Wolf studied at the universities of Zürich, Vienna, and Berlin and in 1839 went to the University of Bern as a teacher of mathematics and physics; he became professor of astronomy there in 1844. In 1855 he accepted a professorship of astronomy at both the University of Zürich and the Federal Institute of Technology in Zürich. At his instigation an observatory was opened at Zürich in 1864.Wolf confirmed S.H. Schwabe's discovery of a cycle in sunspot activity and by use of earlier records defined the cycle's length more accurately, at an average of 11....
</Question>
<Choice>Wolf, Rudolf</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British scientist who enhanced the techniques of powder metallurgy to become the first to produce and market pure, malleable platinum. He also made fundamental discoveries in many areas of science and discovered the elements palladium (1802) and rhodium (1804).
</Question>
<Choice>Wollaston, William Hyde</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronomer who made the first observations of the flash spectrum of the Sun, during the solar eclipses of 1869 and 1870.He studied the Sun extensively, particularly with the spectroscope, and wrote several important books on astronomy, of which the best known was General Astronomy (1888). In 1879 he made accurate measurements of the diameter of Mars. He was professor of astronomy at Princeton University from 1877 to 1905.
</Question>
<Choice>Young, Charles Augustus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-Hungarian astronomer patronized by Duke Ernst of Saxe-Gotha-Altenburg.Zach built an observatory on the Seeberg near Gotha and directed the observatory—one of the most important of the time—from 1791, when it was completed, until 1806. During this period Zach enlisted 24 astronomers throughout Europe in making a systematic search for new comets and for the planet between Mars and Saturn expected on the basis of Bode's law (the Titius–Bode law). The principal result was the discovery of several asteroids. Zach's most lasting achievement was the editing of three scientific journals during...
</Question>
<Choice>Zach, Franz Xaver, Freiherr von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese astronomer, mathematician, and Daoist who calculated the value of p, constructed astronomical instruments, conducted experiments with a camera obscura, and compiled an influential astronomical compendium.Zhao was one of the patriarchs of the northern branch of the Quanzhen (“Complete Perfection”) sect of Daoism. His astronomical treatise Gexiang xinshu (“New Writing on the Symbol of Alteration”) presents his cosmological theory featuring a flat Earth inside a spherical Heaven, his explanation of the lunar and solar eclipses, and his experiments with a camera obscura to establish the re...
</Question>
<Choice>Zhao Youqin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese astronomer, mathematician, and engineer who created the Daming calendar and found several close approximations for p.Like his grandfather and father, Zu Chongzhi was a state functionary. About 462 he submitted a memorandum to the throne that criticized the current calendar, the Yuanjia (created by He Chengtian [370–447]), and proposed a new calendar system that would provide a more precise number of lunations per year and take into consideration the precession of the equinoxes. His calendar, the Daming calendar, was finally adopted in 510 through the efforts of his son, Zu Geng.Li Chun...
</Question>
<Choice>Zu Chongzhi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese government official, mathematician, astronomer, and son of Zu Chongzhi (429–500).Beginning in 504, Zu Geng actively advocated his father's calendar (the Daming calendar) and finally succeeded in getting it officially adopted in 510. His astronomical observations with gnomons allowed him to measure the angular distance between Polaris and the celestial north pole. Although none of his complete mathematical writings is extant, some scholars suggest that the mathematical treatise Zhuishu (meaning of the title now uncertain), conventionally credited to his father and lost by the 11th centu...
</Question>
<Choice>Zu Gengzhi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian astronomer who, in approximately 1616, designed one of the earliest reflecting telescopes, antedating those of James Gregory and Sir Isaac Newton. A professor at the Jesuit College in Rome, Zucchi developed an interest in astronomy from a meeting with Johannes Kepler. With this telescope Zucchi discovered the belts of the planet Jupiter (1630) and examined the spots on Mars (1640). He also demonstrated (in 1652) that phosphors generate rather than store light. His book Optica philosophia experimentalis et ratione a fundamentis constituta (1652–56) inspired Gregory and Newton to build i...
</Question>
<Choice>Zucchi, Niccolo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss astronomer and physicist who made valuable contributions to the theory and understanding of supernovas (stars that for a short time are far brighter than normal).Zwicky received a doctorate in physics (1922) from the Swiss Federal Institute of Technology, Zürich, and served on the faculty of the California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, from 1925 to 1972.During the early 1930s Zwicky contributed substantially to the physics of the solid state, gaseous ionization, and thermodynamics but soon turned to the study of supernovas, novas, and cosmic rays. In 1933 he discovered the existence...
</Question>
<Choice>Zwicky, Fritz</Choice>
</item>
</topics>