<topics>
<item>
<Question>
Renaissance naturalist and physician noted for his systematic and accurate observations of animals, plants, and minerals.After studying mathematics, Latin, law, and philosophy, Aldrovandi went to Padua in about 1545 to continue his studies. There he began to study medicine, the field in which he eventually earned a degree in 1553. On his return to Bologna in 1549 he was arrested, charged with heresy, and sent to Rome, where he was able to exonerate himself, probably in part because of his noble parentage. Returning to the University of Bologna, he was made a full professor in 1561 as a result...
</Question>
<Choice>Aldrovandi, Ulisse</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
naturalist, explorer, and author, who led many important scientific expeditions for which he obtained financial support through his public lectures and books, particularly on central Asia and eastern Asia.After graduating from Beloit (Wis.) College in 1906, he took a position at the American Museum of Natural History in New York City. In 1908 he went on his first expedition, to Alaska, and on that trip and until 1914 he specialized in the study of whales and other aquatic mammals; through his efforts the museum's collection of cetaceans became one of the best in the world. In 1909–10 he was a...
</Question>
<Choice>Andrews, Roy Chapman</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
ancient Greek philosopher and scientist, one of the greatest intellectual figures of Western history. He was the author of a philosophical and scientific system that became the framework and vehicle for both Christian Scholasticism and medieval Islamic philosophy. Even after the intellectual revolutions of the Renaissance, the Reformation, and the Enlightenment, Aristotelian concepts remained embedded in Western thinking.Aristotle's intellectual range was vast, covering most of the sciences and many of the arts, including biology, botany, chemistry, ethics, history, logic, metaphysics, rhetori...
</Question>
<Choice>Aristotle</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English broadcaster and writer noted for his innovative educational programs on television.Attenborough early developed a strong interest in natural history. He was educated at Clare College, Cambridge (M.A., 1947), and began work at an educational publishing house in 1949. In 1952 he completed a training program at the British Broadcasting Corporation (BBC) and became a television producer for the BBC. Together with the reptile curator Jack Lester, in 1954 he originated the television series “Zoo Quest,” in which live animals were filmed in the wild and in zoos. This show proved enormously po...
</Question>
<Choice>Attenborough, Sir David Frederick</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British explorer, naturalist, and long-time president of the Royal Society, known for his promotion of science.Banks was schooled at Harrow School and Eton College before attending Christ Church College, Oxford, from 1760 to 1763; he inherited a considerable fortune from his father in 1761. Banks then traveled extensively, collecting plant and natural history specimens in journeys to Newfoundland and Labrador (1766), around the world with Captain James Cook (1768–71), and to Iceland (1772).Banks was interested in economic plants and their introduction into countries. He was the first to sugges...
</Question>
<Choice>Banks, Sir Joseph, Baronet</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
naturalist and explorer whose demonstration of the operation of natural selection in animal mimicry (the imitation by a species of other life forms or inanimate objects published in 1861, gave firm support to Charles Darwin's theory of evolution.In 1844 Bates introduced the subject of entomology to Alfred Russel Wallace, who in 1847 suggested a trip to tropical jungles to collect specimens to sell at home and to collect data that might help solve the problem of the origin of species. On May 28, 1848, they arrived at Pará, Braz., near the mouth of the Amazon River. Wallace returned to England i...
</Question>
<Choice>Bates, H. W.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
biologist who founded and named the science of genetics and whose experiments provided evidence basic to the modern understanding of heredity. A dedicated evolutionist, he cited embryo studies to support his contention in 1885 that chordates evolved from primitive echinoderms, a view now widely accepted. In 1894 he published his conclusion (Materials for the Study of Variation) that evolution could not occur through a continuous variation of species, since distinct features often appeared or disappeared suddenly in plants and animals. Realizing that discontinuous variation could be understood...
</Question>
<Choice>Bateson, William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biologist, explorer, and writer on natural history who combined careful biological research with a rare literary skill. He was the coinventor of the bathysphere.Beebe was curator of ornithology at the New York Zoological Gardens from 1899 and director of the department of tropical research of the New York Zoological Society from 1919. He led numerous scientific expeditions abroad and in 1934 with Otis Barton descended in his bathysphere to a then record depth of 3,028 feet (923 metres) in Bermuda waters. A noted lecturer, he received numerous prizes and honours for scientific research...
</Question>
<Choice>Beebe, William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French naturalist whose discussion of dolphin embryos and systematic comparisons of the skeletons of birds and humans mark the beginnings of modern embryology and comparative anatomy.Belon studied botany at the University of Wittenberg (1540) and, under the patronage of François, Cardinal de Tournon, embarked on a tour of eastern Mediterranean countries (1546–48) in order to identify animals, plants, places, and objects described by ancient writers. In the resulting work, Les Observations de plusieurs singularitez et choses mémorables . . . (1553; “Observations of Several Curiosities and Memor...
</Question>
<Choice>Belon, Pierre</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American agricultural scientist, plant pathologist, and winner of the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1970. He was one of those who laid the groundwork of the so-called Green Revolution, the agricultural technological advance that promised to alleviate world hunger.Borlaug studied plant biology and forestry at the University of Minnesota and earned a Ph.D. in plant pathology there in 1941. From 1944 to 1960 he served as a research scientist at the Rockefeller Foundation's Cooperative Mexican Agricultural Program in Mexico. Borlaug's work was founded on earlier discoveries of ways to induce genetic mu...
</Question>
<Choice>Borlaug, Norman Ernest</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British naturalist and paleontologist best known for his studies of British sponges.Bowerbank devoted much time to the study of natural history while running a family business, Bowerbank and Company, distillers, in which he was an active partner until 1847. He lectured on botany (1822–24) and human osteology (1831) and founded, with six others, the London Clay Club (1836). In 1847 he founded the Paleontographical Society as an instrument for publication of undescribed British fossils. His most important publications are A History of the Fossil Fruits and Seeds of the London Clay (1840), a stan...
</Question>
<Choice>Bowerbank, James Scott</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American zoologist known for his research on the anatomy and embryology of marine animals, especially the tunicates, crustaceans (e.g., crayfish), and mollusks (notably the oyster). In his acceptance of evolution, he remained in the tradition of 19th-century descriptive morphology; but, through his more able students, he influenced the transition to an experimental, causal approach to 20th-century biology, particularly in cytology, genetics, and embryology.A student of Louis and Alexander Agassiz at Harvard University, where he received a doctorate in 1875, Brooks advocated the study of marine...
</Question>
<Choice>Brooks, William Keith</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French naturalist, remembered for his comprehensive work on natural history, Histoire naturelle, générale et particulière (begun in 1749). He was created a count in 1773.Buffon's father, Benjamin Leclerc, was a state official in Burgundy; his mother was a woman of spirit and learning, and he was fond of saying that he got his intelligence from her. The name Buffon came from an estate that he inherited from his mother at about the age of 25.Beginning his studies at the College of Godrans in Dijon, which was run by the Jesuits, he seems now to have been only an average student, but one with a ma...
</Question>
<Choice>Buffon, Georges-Louis Leclerc, comte de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French surgeon who received the 1912 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for developing a method of suturing blood vessels.Carrel received an M.D. (1900) from the University of Lyon. Soon after graduating, he became interested in the repair of blood vessels, and he developed a method to suture them together end-to-end with a minimum of stitches. This technique became essential for many surgical operations, including the transplantation of blood vessels and organs. In 1904 Carrel left France for the United States, working first at the University of Chicago and then at the Rockefeller Institu...
</Question>
<Choice>Carrel, Alexis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biologist well known for her writings on environmental pollution and the natural history of the sea.Carson early developed a deep interest in the natural world. She entered Pennsylvania College for Women with the intention of becoming a writer but soon changed her major field of study from English to biology. After taking her bachelor's degree in 1929, she did graduate work at Johns Hopkins University (M.A., 1932) and in 1931 joined the faculty of the University of Maryland, where she taught for five years. From 1929 to 1936 she also taught in the Johns Hopkins summer school and pursu...
</Question>
<Choice>Carson, Rachel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French biologist famous for his research on parasitic protozoans and marine invertebrates.Caullery taught at the University of Marseille (1900) and the University of Paris (1903) and succeeded Alfred Giard as director of the zoological station at Wimereux (1909). He was particularly interested in how the morphology, reproduction, and ecology of tunicates (related to vertebrates) and annelid worms had a bearing on their evolution. He also described and named the marine worm Siboglinum weberi, which later became the basis for establishing the invertebrate phylum Pogonophora.Among Caullery's more...
</Question>
<Choice>Caullery, Maurice-Jules-Gaston-Corneille</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American zoologist and educator whose influence as a teacher was great and enduring in a period when the world of science was just opening to women.Clapp graduated from Mount Holyoke Female Seminary in 1871, and after a year of teaching elsewhere she returned to Mount Holyoke as an instructor in mathematics. Later she also taught gymnastics. Her budding interest in natural history was encouraged when, in 1874, she was selected to attend the summer Anderson School of Natural History conducted by Louis Agassiz at Penikese Island in Buzzards Bay, Massachusetts. Soon Clapp was teaching zoology at...
</Question>
<Choice>Clapp, Cornelia Maria</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish chemist who discovered the elements holmium and thulium.Cleve became assistant professor of chemistry at the University of Uppsala in 1868 and in addition taught at the Technological Institute in Stockholm from 1870 to 1874. He then was appointed professor of general and agricultural chemistry at Uppsala.After extensive chemical investigations, Cleve concluded in 1874 that the element didymium was actually two elements. His theory was vindicated 11 years later by C.A. Welsbach's discovery of neodymium and praseodymium. In 1879 Cleve showed that the newly discovered scandium was the ele...
</Question>
<Choice>Cleve, Per Teodor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American illustrator, writer, and educator remembered for her work in nature study.Anna Botsford entered Cornell University in Ithaca, New York, in 1874, but she left after two years. In 1878 she married John Henry Comstock, a young entomologist on the Cornell faculty who interested her in insect illustration. Throughout their marriage she functioned as his assistant, illustrating his lectures and publications on insects. Her work was usually on an informal, unpaid basis, but when he was chief entomologist in the U.S. Department of Agriculture (1879–81), she received a formal appointment. Ther...
</Question>
<Choice>Comstock, Anna Botsford</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biologist noted for his studies of human evolution, who was a leading critic of society's response to advanced technology.Conklin became professor of biology at Princeton University (1908), where he remained as independent lecturer and researcher after his retirement from the position in 1933. Experimenting in the field of invertebrate embryology, he studied the egg cell, or ovum, and traced the formation of organs to their origins in the egg cell and embryo. Conklin also investigated the physical mechanism of cell division and became an authority on human evolution. As a widely respe...
</Question>
<Choice>Conklin, Edwin Grant</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British biologist whose research on chromosomes influenced the basic concepts of the hereditary mechanisms underlying the evolution of sexually reproducing species.Darlington received a B.S. degree from Wye College, Kent, and subsequently joined the staff of the John Innes Horticultural Institution in Merton (later in Bayfordbury), of which he became director in 1939. In 1953 he was appointed Sherardian professor of botany at the University of Oxford.Darlington began his genetic studies under William Bateson at Innes during the 1920s. Unlike Bateson, however, Darlington became an early adheren...
</Question>
<Choice>Darlington, Cyril Dean</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English naturalist whose theory of evolution by natural selection became the foundation of modern evolutionary studies. An affable country gentleman, Darwin at first shocked religious Victorian society by suggesting that animals and humans shared a common ancestry. However, his nonreligious biology appealed to the rising class of professional scientists, and by the time of his death evolutionary imagery had spread through all of science, literature, and politics. Darwin, himself an agnostic, was accorded the ultimate British accolade of burial in Westminster Abbey, London. (In February 2009, f...
</Question>
<Choice>Darwin, Charles</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American zoologist who contributed substantially to the study of eugenics (the improvement of populations through breeding) and heredity and who pioneered the use of statistical techniques in biological research.After receiving a doctorate in zoology at Harvard University in 1892, Davenport taught there until 1899, when he left to join the faculty of the University of Chicago, where, from 1901 to 1904, he was curator of the zoological museum. He directed the department of genetics (1904–34) for the Station for Experimental Evolution at Cold Spring Harbor, N.Y., and also founded and directed th...
</Question>
<Choice>Davenport, Charles Benedict</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-born U.S. biologist, a pioneer in the study of molecular genetics. With Alfred Day Hershey and Salvador Luria, he was awarded the 1969 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for work on bacteriophages—viruses that infect bacteria.Delbrück received a Ph.D. in physics (1930) from the University of Göttingen. His interest in bacteriophages was aroused while he was a research assistant at the Kaiser Wilhelm Institute for Chemistry in Berlin (1932–37). A refugee from Nazi Germany, Delbrück went to the United States in 1937, serving as a faculty member of the California Institute of Technolog...
</Question>
<Choice>Delbruck, Max</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French biologist and cytologist, noted for his studies in the classification of protozoans and invertebrates.Largely self-educated, Dujardin was appointed to the chair of geology and mineralogy on the faculty of sciences at the University of Toulouse (1839) and professor of botany and zoology and dean of the faculty of sciences at the University of Rennes (1840).His studies of infusoria (microscopic animal life frequently found in infusions of decaying organic materials) led Dujardin in 1834 to propose a new group of one-celled animals (called protozoans) that he called the Rhizopoda (meaning...
</Question>
<Choice>Dujardin, Felix</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German biologist, microscopist, scientific explorer, and a founder of micropaleontology—the study of fossil microorganisms.Ehrenberg studied at the University of Berlin (M.D., 1818) and was associated with the university throughout his career. He took part in a scientific expedition (1820–25) to Egypt, Libya, the Sudan, and the Red Sea under the auspices of the university and the Prussian Academy of Sciences. The expedition's only survivor, he collected about 34,000 animal and 46,000 plant specimens. With Alexander von Humboldt, he participated in 1829 in an expedition, sponsored by Tsar Nicho...
</Question>
<Choice>Ehrenberg, Christian Gottfried</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biologist and educator who in 1990 shared Sweden's Crafoord Prize (established in 1980 and awarded by the Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences, to support those areas of science not covered by the Nobel Prizes) with biologist E.O. Wilson.Ehrlich received early inspiration to study ecology when in his high school years he read William Vogt's Road to Survival (1948), an early study of the problem of rapid population growth and food production. Ehrlich graduated in zoology from the University of Pennsylvania (B.A., 1953) and took M.A. and Ph.D. degrees from the University of Kansas (1955, 1...
</Question>
<Choice>Ehrlich, Paul R.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English biologist credited with framing the basic principles of modern animal ecology.
</Question>
<Choice>Elton, Charles</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physiologist and educator who introduced modern methods of teaching biology and physiology that emphasize laboratory training.Foster earned a medical degree from University College, London, in 1859 and was a protégé of the biologist T.H. Huxley. Foster became an instructor at University College in 1867 and went on to become a teacher (1870–83) and then the first professor of physiology (1883–1903) at the University of Cambridge. He greatly enlarged and modernized the teaching of biology at Cambridge, and under his leadership that school became a world centre for research into physiolog...
</Question>
<Choice>Foster, Sir Michael</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish biologist and sociologist who was one of the modern pioneers of the concept of town and regional planning.Greatly influenced by Charles Darwin's evolutionary arguments and their application to society, Geddes chose to study biology in London under Darwin's champion, Thomas Henry Huxley. While professor of botany at University College in Dundee, Angus (1889–1919), he emphasized the development of sexual reproduction as a major step in organic evolution and, with the naturalist John Arthur Thomson, published The Evolution of Sex (1889).Geddes turned his attention to sociology after an a...
</Question>
<Choice>Geddes, Sir Patrick</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French naturalist who established the principle of “unity of composition,” postulating a single consistent structural plan basic to all animals as a major tenet of comparative anatomy, and who founded teratology, the study of animal malformation.After taking a law degree (1790), Geoffroy studied medicine under Louis Daubenton and enrolled in science courses at the Collège du Cardinal Lemoine in Paris. At the height of the Revolution in 1792, he risked his life to save several of his teachers and fellows from execution. The following year, Daubenton arranged his appointment as superintendent of...
</Question>
<Choice>Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire, Etienne</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss physician and naturalist, best known for his systematic compilations of information on animals and plants.
</Question>
<Choice>Gesner, Conrad</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American paleontologist, evolutionary biologist, and science writer.Gould graduated from Antioch College in 1963 and received a Ph.D. in paleontology at Columbia University in 1967. He joined the faculty of Harvard University in 1967, becoming a full professor there in 1973. Gould's own technical research focused on the evolution and speciation of West Indian land snails. With Niles Eldredge, he developed in 1972 the theory of punctuated equilibrium, a revision of Darwinian theory proposing that the creation of new species through evolutionary change occurs not at slow, constant rates over mil...
</Question>
<Choice>Gould, Stephen Jay</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English zoologist who played a leading part in changing the main objective of 20th-century zoological research from evolutionary comparative anatomy to the functional analysis of living cells and living animals, particularly through his editorship (1925–54) of the Journal of Experimental Biology. He was noted for his work on the mechanism of cellular and animal movement.Gray was educated and spent his career at Cambridge University, where he gradually established one of the major schools of biological research in Britain. In 1948 he received the royal medal of the Royal Society. He was knighte...
</Question>
<Choice>Gray, Sir James</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British geneticist, biometrician, physiologist, and popularizer of science who opened new paths of research in population genetics and evolution.Son of the noted physiologist John Scott Haldane, he began studying science as assistant to his father at the age of eight and later received formal education in the classics at Eton College and at New College, Oxford (M.A., 1914). After World War I he served as a fellow of New College and then taught at the University of Cambridge (1922–32), the University of California, Berkeley (1932), and the University of London (1933–57).In the 1930s Haldane bec...
</Question>
<Choice>Haldane, J. B. S.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biologist who identified the details of reproduction in the development of the fungus ascospore (sexually produced spores of fungi in the class Ascomycetes).After graduating from Oberlin (Ohio) College (M.A., 1891), Harper did graduate study at the University of Bonn while on leave of absence from Lake Forest (Ill.) College, where he was professor of botany and geology (1891–98). In 1896 he received his Ph.D., after which he taught at the University of Wisconsin, Madison (1898–1911), and at Columbia University (1911–30).Working on spore formation of the powdery mildew, Sphaerotheca, a...
</Question>
<Choice>Harper, Robert Almer</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biologist who, along with Max Delbrück and Salvador Luria, won the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1969. The prize was given for research done on bacteriophages (viruses that infect bacteria).Hershey earned a doctorate in chemistry from Michigan State College (now Michigan State University) in 1934 and then took a position at Washington University School of Medicine in St. Louis, Mo. He joined the staff of the Genetics Research Unit of the Carnegie Institution of Washington in 1950 after giving up his position as professor at Washington University. In 1963 he became director...
</Question>
<Choice>Hershey, A. D.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German biologist particularly noted for the development of the germ-layer theory, which proposes that all organs and tissues are derived variously from three basic tissue layers, and for his contributions to the study of protozoans.Educated at the universities of Zürich, Jena, and Bonn, he became a lecturer in zoology at Jena (1875) and professor at the universities of Königsberg (1881), Bonn (1883), and Munich (1885–1925). Hertwig was the first to describe the artificially stimulated development of sea urchin eggs (parthenogenesis). He worked on the theory of coelom formation proposed by Germ...
</Question>
<Choice>Hertwig, Richard Carl Wilhelm Theodor von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Canadian-born American neurobiologist, corecipient with Torsten Nils Wiesel and Roger Wolcott Sperry of the 1981 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine. All three scientists were honoured for their investigations of brain function, Hubel and Wiesel in particular for their collaborative discoveries concerning information processing in the visual system.Hubel attended McGill University in Montreal, receiving a bachelor's degree in 1947 and an M.D. in 1951. He held positions at the Montreal Neurological Institute, at the Johns Hopkins Medical School (where his association with Wiesel began), and...
</Question>
<Choice>Hubel, David Hunter</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
surgeon, founder of pathological anatomy in England, and early advocate of investigation and experimentation. He also carried out many important studies and experiments in comparative aspects of biology, anatomy, physiology, and pathology.Hunter never completed a course of studies in any university, and, as was common for surgeons during the 18th century, he never attempted to become a doctor of medicine. He went to London in 1748 to assist in the preparation of dissections for the course of anatomy taught by his brother William, a famed obstetrician. For 11 winters he studied anatomy in his b...
</Question>
<Choice>Hunter, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English biologist, philosopher, educator, and author who greatly influenced the modern development of embryology, systematics, and studies of behaviour and evolution.Julian, a grandson of the prominent biologist T.H. Huxley, a brother of novelist Aldous Huxley, and the oldest son of the biographer and man of letters Leonard Huxley, was educated at Eton and Balliol College, Oxford. His scientific research included important work on hormones, developmental processes, ornithology, and ethology. He developed and headed the biology department at the newly formed Rice University in Houston, Texas, b...
</Question>
<Choice>Huxley, Sir Julian</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English biologist, educator, and advocate of agnosticism (he coined the word). Huxley's vigorous public support of Charles Darwin's evolutionary naturalism earned him the nickname “Darwin's bulldog,” while his organizational efforts, public lectures, and writing helped elevate the place of science in modern society.
</Question>
<Choice>Huxley, T. H.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French biologist who, together with André Lwoff and Jacques Monod, was awarded the 1965 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for discoveries concerning regulatory activities in bacteria.Jacob received his M.D. degree (1947) and a doctorate in science (1954) from the Faculty of Medicine and the Faculty of Science, respectively, in Paris. Most of the work of Jacob, Lwoff, and Monod was carried out at the Pasteur Institute (Paris), which Jacob had joined as a research assistant in 1950. In 1960 he became head of the department of cellular genetics at the institute, and from 1965 he was also pro...
</Question>
<Choice>Jacob, Francois</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. botanist and agricultural biologist, one of the first and most distinguished of American plant pathologists.Jones studied botany at the University of Michigan (Ph.D., 1889) and afterward left for the University of Vermont to become research botanist at the Agricultural Experiment Station, where he made his first major contribution to plant pathology. He successfully used the French-made Bordeaux mixture fungicide in the prevention and control of potato blight and pear and apple scab. He also studied the problems of bacterial soft rot of vegetables and found that the action of Bacillus car...
</Question>
<Choice>Jones, Lewis Ralph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian biologist who claimed to have produced experimental evidence that acquired traits could be inherited.The results of Kammerer's experiments with salamanders and other amphibians were widely published in technical papers and books, the first of these appearing in 1904 and the last published posthumously in 1928. He claimed to have caused the offspring of the viviparous Alpine salamander to acquire certain characteristics of the spotted oviparous lowland salamander, and vice versa. Following a second series of experiments, Kammerer announced that he could make the male midwife toad, whic...
</Question>
<Choice>Kammerer, Paul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
pioneer French biologist who is best known for his idea that acquired characters are inheritable, an idea known as Lamarckism, which is controverted by modern genetics and evolutionary theory.
</Question>
<Choice>Lamarck, Jean-Baptiste de Monet, chevalier de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-born American biologist noted chiefly for his experimental work on artificial parthenogenesis (reproduction without fertilization).Having received an M.D. degree from the University of Strasbourg (1884), Loeb began work in biology at the University of Würzburg (1886–88) and continued at the University of Strasbourg (1888–90) and the Naples biological station (1889–91). In 1891 he moved to the United States, becoming professor successively at Bryn Mawr (Pa.) College (1891–92), the University of Chicago (1892–1902), and the University of California, Berkeley (1902–10). In 1910 he became a...
</Question>
<Choice>Loeb, Jacques</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian-born American biologist who (with Max Delbrück and Alfred Day Hershey) won the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1969 for research on bacteriophages, viruses that infect bacteria.Luria graduated from the University of Turin in 1935 and became a radiology specialist. He fled Italy for France in 1938 and went to the United States in 1940 after learning the techniques of phage research at the Pasteur Institute in Paris. Soon after his arrival, he met Delbrück, through whom he became involved with the American Phage Group, an informal scientific organization devoted to solving the...
</Question>
<Choice>Luria, Salvador</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French biologist who contributed to the understanding of lysogeny, in which a bacterial virus, or bacteriophage, infects bacteria and is transmitted to subsequent bacterial generations solely through the cell division of its host. Lwoff's discoveries brought him (with François Jacob and Jacques Monod) the Nobel Prize for Medicine or Physiology in 1965.Lwoff, born of Russian-Polish parents, was educated at the University of Paris. He spent most of his research career at the Pasteur Institute in Paris, serving on the board of directors from 1966 to 1972. From 1959 to 1968 he was also a professor...
</Question>
<Choice>Lwoff, Andre</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch naturalist and engraver famed for his skillful dissections and illustrations of insect anatomy.Trained as an attorney, Lyonnet was a respected biologist and spent most of his time engraving objects of natural history. He made the drawings for Friedrich Christian Lesser's Théologie des Insectes (1742; “Theology of Insects”) and for Abraham Trembley's treatise on fresh-water polyps (1744).His monograph on the anatomy of the goat-moth caterpillar, Traité anatomique de la Chenille, qui ronge le bois de Saule (1760), is one of the most beautifully illustrated works on anatomy ever published....
</Question>
<Choice>Lyonnet, Pierre</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Soviet biologist and agronomist, the controversial “dictator” of Communistic biology during Stalin's regime. He rejected orthodox genetics in favour of “Michurinism” (named for the Russian horticulturist I.V. Michurin), which was begun by an uneducated plant breeder fashioning explanations for his hybrid creations. After Michurin's death in 1935, Lysenko led the movement and transformed it into an assault on orthodox genetics.Lysenko was graduated from the Uman School of Horticulture in 1921 and was stationed at the Belaya Tserkov Selection Station in the same year. After his 1925 graduation f...
</Question>
<Choice>Lysenko, Trofim Denisovich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian physician and biologist who, in developing experimental methods to study living things, founded the science of microscopicanatomy. After Malpighi's researches, microscopic anatomy became a prerequisite for advances in the fields of physiology, embryology, and practical medicine.
</Question>
<Choice>Malpighi, Marcello</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-born American biologist known for his work in avian taxonomy, population genetics, and evolution. Considered one of the world's leading evolutionary biologists, he was sometimes referred to as the “Darwin of the 20th century.”Two years after receiving a Ph.D. degree in ornithology from the University of Berlin (1926), Mayr, then a member of the university staff, led the first of three expeditions to New Guinea and the Solomon Islands, where he was profoundly impressed with the effects of geographic distribution among various animal species. His early studies of the ability of one specie...
</Question>
<Choice>Mayr, Ernst</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biologist who, with Oswald Avery and Colin M. MacLeod, provided the first experimental evidence that the genetic material of living cells is composed of deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA).McCarty attended Stanford University (B.S., 1933) and Johns Hopkins School of Medicine (M.D., 1937) before joining William S. Tillett at New York University in 1940. Tillett not only introduced McCarty to the study of pneumococcic bacteria but also arranged for him to work with Avery in his laboratory at the Rockefeller Institute (now Rockefeller University) in New York City. McCarty became a member of the...
</Question>
<Choice>McCarty, Maclyn</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Soviet biologist who became an important dissident historian in the second half of the 20th century.Zhores was the identical twin brother of the Soviet historian Roy Medvedev. He graduated from the Timiriazev Academy of Agricultural Sciences in Moscow in 1950 and received a master's degree in biology that same year from the Moscow Institute of Plant Physiology. He conducted research at the Timiriazev Academy from 195l to 1962, becoming a senior scientist there and winning an international reputation for his work on protein biosynthesis and the physiology of the aging process.In the 1960s Medve...
</Question>
<Choice>Medvedev, Zhores Aleksandrovich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biologist and ethnologist, who helped found the National Geographic Society (1888) and what is now the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service.Merriam studied at the Sheffield Scientific School of Yale University and at the College of Physicians and Surgeons of Columbia University (M.D., 1879). Between 1872 and 1876 he traveled as naturalist with the Hayden Geological Surveys in Utah, Idaho, Montana, and Wyoming. From 1885 to 1910 he headed the U.S. Department of Agriculture's Division of Ornithology and Mammalogy, which became the U.S. Biological Survey (1896) and is now known as the Fish and...
</Question>
<Choice>Merriam, Clinton Hart</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British biologist, a leading critic of Charles Darwin's theory of natural selection.Unable to enter the University of Oxford after his conversion to Roman Catholicism (1844), Mivart continued his studies at St. Mary's, Oscott (1844–46). His research into the anatomy of carnivores and insectivores, conducted while he was lecturing at the medical school of St. Mary's Hospital (1862–84), greatly increased knowledge of the subject. In 1881 he published The Cat: An Introduction to the Study of Backboned Animals, which is considered to rank with T.H. Huxley's Crayfish for its accuracy, detail, and c...
</Question>
<Choice>Mivart, Saint George Jackson</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biologist, educator, and writer, author of many works for children on nature and biology.Morley grew up and attended public schools in Brooklyn, New York. She studied at the Oswego Normal School (now State University of New York College at Oswego) and at New York City Normal College (now Hunter College), graduating from the latter in 1878. She conducted postgraduate studies in biology at Armour Institute (now the Illinois Institute of Technology) in Chicago and at the Woods Hole, Massachusetts, marine laboratory. Morley then embarked on a career of teaching, which took her to several...
</Question>
<Choice>Morley, Margaret Warner</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English naturalist and Roman Catholic divine, first clergyman of his faith to become a fellow of the Royal Society of London (1768).He was ordained in 1738 but spent much of his time as a teacher and tutor. His reading about animalcules (microscopic organisms) aroused an interest in natural science, and from 1746 to 1749 he studied in London and Paris. He became a staunch advocate of the theories of spontaneous generation (life from inorganic matter) and vitalism (doctrine holding that life processes cannot be explained by the laws of chemistry and physics). In 1750 he presented his theory of...
</Question>
<Choice>Needham, John Turberville</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American-born British biologist and physician who contributed substantially to many branches of biology and founded the Molteno Institute of Biology and Parasitology (1921) at the University of Cambridge.Nuttall graduated from the University of California Medical School (M.D., 1884) and received his Ph.D. from the University of Göttingen, Germany (1890). He became a lecturer in bacteriology and preventive medicine at Cambridge, England, in 1900, when he acquired British citizenship. In 1906 he was elected the first Quick Professor of Biology at Cambridge (emeritus 1931). He made significant, i...
</Question>
<Choice>Nuttall, George Henry Falkiner</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French antiquary, Humanist, and influential patron of learning who discovered the Orion Nebula (1610) and was among the first to emphasize the study of coins for historical research.Travels in Italy (1599–1602), studies at Padua, and acquaintance there with Galileo stimulated Peiresc's antiquarian and astronomical interests. A senator at the Parlement of Aix from 1605, he corresponded with the Flemish painter Peter Paul Rubens and many of the noted scholars of the day. Peiresc was first to verify William Harvey's discovery of the circulation of blood, and Sir Isaac Newton made use of his work...
</Question>
<Choice>Peiresc, Nicolas-Claude Fabri de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French naturalist who was a leading advocate of the idea of the spontaneous generation of life from nonliving matter.Pouchet was director of the Rouen Museum of Natural History and the Rouen Jardin des Plantes (1828) and later a professor at the School of Medicine at Rouen (1838). In his major work, Hétérogénie (1859), he detailed the conditions under which living organisms supposedly were produced by chemical processes such as fermentation and putrefaction. His supporters were primarily among those whose religious or philosophical beliefs required the concept of spontaneous generation. Pouche...
</Question>
<Choice>Pouchet, Felix-Archimede</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biologist who helped pioneer the discovery and study of biorhythms and who showed that humans' biological processes can be strongly influenced by learned behaviour.Richter attended Harvard University (B.S., 1917), and after a year as first lieutenant in the U.S. Army he entered Johns Hopkins University, where he was awarded his Ph.D. and joined the faculty, both in 1921. In 1922 he became director of Johns Hopkins' psychiatric clinic, a post that he held until becoming professor of psychobiology in 1957. He introduced the concept of the biological clock in a 1927 paper on the internal...
</Question>
<Choice>Richter, Curt Paul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. paleontologist widely known for his concepts of evolutionary history of vertebrate animals. The explicit use of comparative anatomy and embryology in studies of fossil vertebrates underlies his major contributions to biology.
</Question>
<Choice>Romer, Alfred Sherwood</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physician and naturalist whose collection of books, manuscripts, and curiosities formed the basis for the British Museum in London.After studying medicine in London, Sloane traveled in France, taking his M.D. degree at the University of Orange in 1683. During a visit to Jamaica (1687–88) he collected about 800 new species of plants, of which he published an elaborate catalog in Latin in 1696. Sloane was created a baronet in 1716, being the first medical practitioner to receive a hereditary title. He became first physician to King George II and president of the Royal Society in 1727. Hi...
</Question>
<Choice>Sloane, Sir Hans, Baronet</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American neurobiologist, corecipient with David Hunter Hubel and Torsten Nils Wiesel of the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1981 for their investigations of brain function, Sperry in particular for his study of functional specialization in the cerebral hemispheres.Sperry earned a bachelor's degree in English literature and a master's degree in psychology from Oberlin (Ohio) College and a doctorate in zoology from the University of Chicago in 1941. He then became an associate of Karl Lashley, first at Harvard University and then at the Yerkes Laboratories of Primate Biology in Orange...
</Question>
<Choice>Sperry, Roger Wolcott</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biologist and geneticist who was one of the first scientists to find that sex is determined by a particular configuration of chromosomes.Stevens's early life is somewhat obscure, although it is known that she taught school and attended the State Normal School (now Westfield State College) in Westfield, Massachusetts, in 1881–83. In 1896 she entered Stanford University, earning a B.A. in 1899 and an M.A. in 1900. She began doctoral studies in biology at Bryn Mawr College, which included a year of study (1901–02) at the Zoological Station in Naples, Italy, and at the Zoological Institut...
</Question>
<Choice>Stevens, Nettie Maria</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British biologist who, with Sydney Brenner and H. Robert Horvitz, won the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 2002 for their discoveries about how genes regulate tissue and organ development via a key mechanism called programmed cell death, or apoptosis.Sulston earned a B.A. (1963) and a Ph.D. (1966) from the University of Cambridge. Following three years of postdoctoral work in the United States, he joined Brenner's group at the Medical Research Council in England (1969). From 1992 to 2000 Sulston was director of the Sanger Institute in Cambridge.Sulston's award-winning research examine...
</Question>
<Choice>Sulston, John E.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch naturalist, considered the most accurate of classical microscopists, who was the first to observe and describe red blood cells (1658).Swammerdam completed medical studies in 1667 but never practiced medicine, devoting himself to microscopical investigations instead. Turning to the study of insects, he accurately described and illustrated the life histories and anatomy of many species. His observations of their development led him to separate insects into four major divisions, according to the degree and type of metamorphosis. Three of these divisions have been more or less retained in mo...
</Question>
<Choice>Swammerdam, Jan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician, researcher, author, and teacher best known for his essays, which contain lucid meditations and reflections on a wide range of topics in biology.Lewis attended Princeton University, Princeton, N.J., and Harvard Medical School (M.D., 1937). He served in the U.S. Navy Medical Corps and taught at Johns Hopkins and Tulane universities and at the University of Minnesota Medical School. In 1954 he moved to New York University School of Medicine, which he left as dean in 1969 to teach in the pathology department at Yale University. From 1973 to 1983 he was president of the Memorial...
</Question>
<Choice>Thomas, Lewis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish naturalist whose clearly written books on biology and attempts to correlate science and religion led to wider public awareness of progress in the biological sciences.A professor of natural history at the University of Aberdeen (1899–1930), Thomson concentrated his research on soft corals. He collaborated with the biologist Sir Patrick Geddes in writing several popular books, including The Evolution of Sex (1889), Evolution (1911), Sex (1914), Biology (1924), and Life: Outlines of General Biology (1931). Thomson also wrote Outlines of Zoology (9th ed. 1944), The Wonder of Life (1914),...
</Question>
<Choice>Thomson, Sir John Arthur</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Prussian astronomer, physicist, and biologist whose law (1766) expressing the distances between the planets and the Sun was popularized by German astronomer Johann Elert Bode in 1772.Having received a degree from the University of Leipzig (1752), Titius joined the faculty of the University of Wittenberg in 1756. Titius proposed his law of planetary distances in an unsigned interpolation in his German translation of Swiss philosopher Charles Bonnet'sContemplation de la nature (“Contemplation of Nature”). Titius fixed the scale by assigning 100 to the distance of Saturn from the Sun. On this sca...
</Question>
<Choice>Titius, Johann Daniel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Renaissance physician who revolutionized the study of biology and the practice of medicine by his careful description of the anatomy of the human body. Basing his observations on dissections he made himself, he wrote and illustrated the first comprehensive textbook of anatomy.
</Question>
<Choice>Vesalius, Andreas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian mathematician who strongly influenced the modern development of calculus.Volterra's later work in analysis and mathematical physics was influenced by Enrico Betti while the former attended the University of Pisa (1878–82). Volterra was appointed professor of rational mechanics at Pisa in 1883, the year he began devising a general theory of functionals (functions that depend on a continuous set of values of another function). This concept led to the development of new fields of analysis, including important applications to the solution of integral and differential equations. The importa...
</Question>
<Choice>Volterra, Vito</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British embryologist, geneticist, and philosopher of science.Waddington graduated in geology from the University of Cambridge (1926), and it was only after studying paleontology that he turned to biology. Before World War II he taught zoology and embryology at Strangeways Research Laboratory, Cambridge. From 1947 until his death he was professor of animal genetics at the University of Edinburgh.Waddington performed his first notable work in biology on the development of the embryos of birds and mammals. He showed in 1933 that chemical messengers from certain tissues induce other tissues to dev...
</Question>
<Choice>Waddington, C. H.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ukrainian-born American biochemist who was one of the world's foremost authorities on soil microbiology. After the discovery of penicillin, he played a major role in initiating a calculated, systematic search for antibiotics among microbes. His consequent codiscovery of the antibiotic streptomycin, the first specific agent effective in the treatment of tuberculosis, brought him the 1952 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine.A naturalized U.S. citizen (1916), Waksman spent most of his career at Rutgers University, New Brunswick, New Jersey, where he served as professor of soil microbiology (19...
</Question>
<Choice>Waksman, Selman Abraham</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British humanist, naturalist, geographer, and social critic. He became a public figure in England during the second half of the 19th century, known for his courageous views on scientific, social, and spiritualist subjects. His formulation of the theory of evolution by natural selection, which predated Charles Darwin's published contributions, is his most outstanding legacy, but it was just one of many controversial issues he studied and wrote about during his lifetime. Wallace's wide-ranging interests—from socialism to spiritualism, from island biogeography to life on Mars, from evolution to l...
</Question>
<Choice>Wallace, Alfred Russel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German biologist and one of the founders of the science of genetics, who is best known for his opposition to the doctrine of the inheritance of acquired traits and for his “germ plasm” theory, the forerunner of DNA theory.From early boyhood, when he made expeditions into the surrounding countryside to collect insects and plants, Weismann showed an intense interest in natural history. From 1852 until 1856 he was a student of medicine at the University of Göttingen, after which he briefly held a number of positions: as a chemical assistant in Rostock, as a doctor in the Baden army, and as privat...
</Question>
<Choice>Weismann, August Friedrich Leopold</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian-born American biologist who did pioneering research on the mechanics of nerve regeneration, nerve repair, and cellular organization. During World War II Weiss and his colleagues developed and tested the first practical system of preserving human tissue for later surgical grafting.Weiss was trained at the University of Vienna. As assistant director of the Biological Research Institute of the Vienna Academy of Sciences (1922–29), he conducted analytical studies of cell movement, tissue organization, and organ formation, work that ultimately contributed to the understanding of the mechan...
</Question>
<Choice>Weiss, Paul Alfred</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English naturalist and clergyman, author of The Natural History and Antiquities of Selborne (1789), the first work on natural history to attain the status of an English classic.White was educated at Oriel College, Oxford (1740–43), and, although he remained a fellow there until his death, he spent most of his life in Selborne. In 1751, soon after he was ordained, White began a journal in which he noted observations made in his garden. This account was eventually published as a Calendar of Flora and the Garden (1765), followed by the more sophisticated Naturalist's Journal, begun in 1768. Publi...
</Question>
<Choice>White, Gilbert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish neurobiologist, corecipient with David Hunter Hubel and Roger Wolcott Sperry of the 1981 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine. All three scientists were honoured for their investigations of brain function, Wiesel and Hubel in particular for their collaborative studies of the visual cortex, which is located in the occipital lobes of the cerebrum.Wiesel earned a medical degree from the Karolinska Institute in Stockholm in 1954. After remaining there for a year as an instructor in physiology, he accepted a research appointment at the Johns Hopkins University Medical School in Baltimore,...
</Question>
<Choice>Wiesel, Torsten Nils</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biologist known for his researches in embryology and cytology.In 1891 Wilson joined the faculty of Columbia University, where he elevated the department of zoology to a peak of international prestige. His first experimental studies, in embryology, led him to investigations at the cellular level. He became established as an outstanding pioneer in work on cell lineage—i.e., the tracing of the formation of different kinds of tissues from individual precursor cells. His interest then extended to internal cellular organization; publication of his Cell in Development and Inheritance (1896)...
</Question>
<Choice>Wilson, Edmund Beecher</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biologist recognized as the world's leading authority on ants. He was also the foremost proponent of sociobiology, the study of the genetic basis of the social behaviour of all animals, including humans.Wilson received his early training at the University of Alabama (B.S., 1949; M.S., 1950). After receiving his doctorate in biology at Harvard University in 1955, he was a member of Harvard's biology and zoology faculties from 1956 to 1976. At Harvard he was later Frank B. Baird Professor of Science (1976–94), Mellon Professor of the Sciences (1990–93), and Pellegrino University Profess...
</Question>
<Choice>Wilson, Edward O.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biologist who discovered the occurrence of genetic transduction—the carrying of hereditary material from one strain of microorganisms to another by a filterable agent such as a bacteriophage, or bacterial virus—in species of the Salmonella bacteria.After attending Columbia University, Zinder studied under Joshua Lederberg at the University of Wisconsin (Ph.D., 1952) and then joined the staff at the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (now Rockefeller University) in New York City, where he became a professor in 1964. He later served as dean of graduate and postgraduate studies (...
</Question>
<Choice>Zinder, Norton David</Choice>
</item>
</topics>