<topics>
<item>
<Question>
American pharmacologist and physiological chemist who made important contributions to a modern understanding of the ductless, or endocrine, glands. He isolated adrenaline in the form of a chemical derivative (1897) and crystallized insulin (1926). He also invented a primitive artificial kidney.Abel taught at the University of Michigan, Ann Arbor (1891–93), and at Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore (1893), and directed the Laboratory for Endocrine Research (1932). He also helped found and edit several important scientific periodicals, including the Journal of Pharmacology and Experimental Ther...
</Question>
<Choice>Abel, John Jacob</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English chemist and explosives specialist who, with the chemist Sir James Dewar, invented cordite (1889), later adopted as the standard explosive of the British army. Abel also made studies of dust explosions in coal mines, invented a device for testing the flash point of petroleum, and found a way to prevent guncotton from exploding spontaneously.Abel studied chemistry at the Royal Polytechnic Institution and in 1845 became one of the original 26 students of A.W. von Hofmann at the Royal College of Chemistry. In 1852 he was appointed lecturer in chemistry at the Royal Military Academy in Wool...
</Question>
<Choice>Abel, Sir Frederick Augustus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
a specialist in the chemistry of photography, especially noted for his development of a photographic emulsion that he used to map the solar spectrum far into the infrared.Commissioned in the Royal Engineers (1861), he taught chemistry and photography at the School of Military Engineering at Chatham. He succeeded to various educational posts there and elsewhere.In 1874 Abney made the first quantitative measurements of the action of light on photographic materials. In 1880 he discovered the photographic developing properties of hydroquinone. Elected to the Royal Society (1876), he also held post...
</Question>
<Choice>Abney, Sir William de Wiveleslie</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
chemist and teacher known for determining the chemical constitution of such natural substances as chaulmoogra oil (used in treating leprosy), the toxic cottonseed pigment gossypol, marijuana, and many alkaloids. He also worked in stereochemistry and with platinum catalysts and the synthesis of medicinal compounds.Receiving his Ph.D. from Harvard University (1912), Adams studied in Germany and taught briefly at Harvard. In 1916 he went to the University of Illinois, becoming professor of organic chemistry (1919) and head of the chemistry department (1926). A consultant to the chemical industry,...
</Question>
<Choice>Adams, Roger</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American doctor, corecipient of the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 2003 for his discovery of water channels in cell membranes. He shared the award with Roderick MacKinnon, also of the United States.In 1974 Agre earned an M.D. degree from Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine. In 1981, following postgraduate training and a fellowship, he returned to Johns Hopkins, where in 1993 he advanced to professor of biological chemistry. In 2000 he was elected to the National Academy of Sciences.In the 1980s Agre began conducting his pioneering research on water channels in cell membranes. First menti...
</Question>
<Choice>Agre, Peter</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German chemist who was the corecipient, with the German organic chemist Otto Diels, of the 1950 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for their development of the Diels-Alder reaction, or diene synthesis, a widely used method of synthesizing cyclic organic compounds.Alder studied chemistry at the University of Berlin and then at the University of Kiel in Germany, where he received his doctorate in 1926. In 1928 Alder and Diels discovered, and published a paper on, the reaction of dienes with quinones. The Diels-Alder reaction consists essentially of the linking of a diene, which is a substance containing...
</Question>
<Choice>Alder, Kurt</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Canadian American molecular biologist who, with Thomas R. Cech, received the 1989 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for their discoveries concerning the catalytic properties of RNA, or ribonucleic acid.Altman received a B.S. in physics in 1960 from the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. After a brief period as a graduate student in the physics department at Columbia University, Altman changed his course of study and enrolled in the graduate program in biophysics at the University of Colorado. There he studied chemical compounds called acridines, focusing primarily on how these compounds affect the...
</Question>
<Choice>Altman, Sidney</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
chemist and physicist who established the concepts of critical temperature and pressure and showed that a gas will pass into the liquid state, and vice versa, without any discontinuity, or abrupt change in physical properties. He also proved that ozone is a form of oxygen.Following studies in Britain and Paris, he received a medical degree from the University of Edinburgh (1835). He was appointed vice president of Northern College in Belfast in 1845 and helped to prepare it for its reorganization as Queen's College, Belfast (1849). He was professor of chemistry there from 1849 to 1879.
</Question>
<Choice>Andrews, Thomas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biochemist who, with Stanford Moore and William H. Stein, received the 1972 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for research clarifying the relationship between the molecular structure of proteins and their biological functions.Anfinsen received a doctorate in biochemistry from Harvard University in 1943 and then held various research and teaching positions. He joined the staff of the National Institutes of Health (Bethesda, Md.) in 1950, and he headed the laboratory of chemical biology in the National Institute of Arthritis, Metabolism, and Digestive Diseases from 1963 to 1982. He was a profes...
</Question>
<Choice>Anfinsen, Christian B.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish physicist and physical chemist known for his theory of electrolytic dissociation and his model of the greenhouse effect. In 1903 he was awarded the Nobel Prize for Chemistry.
</Question>
<Choice>Arrhenius, Svante August</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physicist who won the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1922 for his development of the mass spectrograph, a device that separates atoms or molecular fragments of different mass and measures those masses with remarkable accuracy. Aston used the mass spectograph to discover a large number of nuclides, or nuclear species that differ in mass. The mass spectrograph is widely used in geology, chemistry, biology, and nuclear physics.Aston was trained as a chemist, but, upon the rebirth of physics following the discovery of X-rays in 1895 and of radioactivity in 1896, he began in 1903 to study the...
</Question>
<Choice>Aston, Francis William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American scientist who developed agricultural chemistry.Upon completing his undergraduate work at Wesleyan University in Middletown, Conn., Atwater continued his studies at Yale University, where his Ph.D. thesis discussed for the first time how chemical techniques could be applied to food. After further study in Germany, he began to teach at Wesleyan, where he was professor of chemistry for the rest of his life. In 1875 he was instrumental in persuading the Connecticut legislature to set up the first state agricultural research station in the United States, at Middletown. In 1887, again at hi...
</Question>
<Choice>Atwater, Wilbur Olin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
agricultural research chemist, often called the father of scientific dairying chiefly because of his development of the Babcock test, a simple method of measuring the butterfat content of milk. Introduced in 1890, the test discouraged milk adulteration, stimulated improvement of dairy production, and aided in factory manufacture of cheese and butter.Babcock took degrees both in the United States and in Germany, where he earned a Ph.D. in 1879. After working as a teacher and chemist in New York, he joined the staff of the University of Wisconsin, where he remained for the next 43 years. The lab...
</Question>
<Choice>Babcock, Stephen Moulton</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. industrial chemist who helped found the modern plastics industry through his invention of Bakelite, the first thermosetting plastic (a plastic that does not soften when heated).Baekeland received his doctorate maxima cum laude from the University of Ghent at the age of 21 and taught there until 1889, when he went to the U.S. and joined a photographic firm. He soon set up his own company to manufacture his invention, Velox, a photographic paper that could be developed under artificial light. Velox was the first commercially successful photographic paper. In 1899 Baekeland sold his company...
</Question>
<Choice>Baekeland, Leo Hendrik</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German research chemist who synthesized indigo (1880) and formulated its structure (1883). He was awarded the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1905.Baeyer studied with Robert Bunsen, but August Kekule exercised a greater influence on his development. He took his doctorate at the University of Berlin (1858), became a lecturer (Privatdozent) in 1860, and headed the chemistry laboratory at the Berlin Vocational Institute until 1872. After holding a professorship at Strassburg (now Strasbourg, France), he succeeded Justus von Liebig as chemistry professor at the University of Munich (1875), where he s...
</Question>
<Choice>Baeyer, Adolf von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French chemist who in 1826 discovered the element bromine, determined its properties, and studied some of its compounds. Later he proved the presence of bromine in sea plants and animals.In studying salt marsh flora from Mediterranean waters, Balard, after crystallizing sodium chloride and sodium sulfate from the seawater, saturating the residue with chlorine, and distilling the product, discovered the only liquid nonmetallic element, bromine.An exponent of the potential value of the sea as a source of chemicals, Balard taught at Montpellier École de Pharmacie, from which he had graduated in 1...
</Question>
<Choice>Balard, Antoine-Jerome</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
secretary to the American commissioners in France during the American Revolution who spied for the British.Although he had no formal education, Bancroft assumed the title and style of “Doctor.” In 1769 he established his credentials as a scientist with the publication of his “Essay on the Natural History of Guiana.” About 1770 he went to England, where he became friendly with Benjamin Franklin during one of Franklin's early missions to London. Bancroft became an adherent of the American cause and returned to the colonies. As a result of his friendship with Franklin he accompanied Franklin and...
</Question>
<Choice>Bancroft, Edward</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
joint recipient, with Odd Hassel of Norway, of the 1969 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for his work on “conformational analysis,” the study of the three-dimensional geometric structure of complex molecules, now an essential part of organic chemistry.
</Question>
<Choice>Barton, Sir Derek H. R.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
chemist, physician, and adventurer whose theories of combustion influenced Georg Stahl's phlogiston theory. Becher believed substances to be composed of three earths, the vitrifiable, the mercurial, and the combustible. He supposed that when a substance burned, a combustible earth was liberated.During his youth, study was difficult because he had to support his mother and brothers, but at 19 he began an extraordinary career that alternated learned publication with colonization and trade enterprises. His ideas and experiments on the nature of minerals and other substances were set forth in Subt...
</Question>
<Choice>Becher, Johann Joachim</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British industrial chemist who developed the process of manufacturing potassium cyanide by passing ammonia over a heated mixture of charcoal and potassium carbonate. This process helped meet the increased demand for cyanide for use in extracting gold from low-grade ores.After graduating from the University of Edinburgh, Beilby entered the oil-shale industry in 1869 and greatly increased the yield of paraffin and ammonia by introducing the continuous retort. In 1890 he turned his attention to the production of cyanide. Becoming interested in the destruction of metals by ammonia at high temperat...
</Question>
<Choice>Beilby, Sir George Thomas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biochemist whose development of recombinant-DNA techniques won him a share (with Walter Gilbert and Frederick Sanger) of the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1980.After graduating from Pennsylvania State College (later renamed Pennsylvania State University) in 1948 and taking a doctorate from Western Reserve University in 1952, Berg pursued further studies at the Institute of Cytophysiology in Copenhagen and at Washington University in St. Louis, where he remained as assistant professor of microbiology until 1959. From 1959 he was associated with the medical school of Stanford University,...
</Question>
<Choice>Berg, Paul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German chemist and corecipient, with Carl Bosch of Germany, of the 1931 Nobel Prize for Chemistry. Bergius and Bosch were instrumental in developing the hydrogenation method necessary to convert coal dust and hydrogen directly into gasoline and lubricating oils without isolating intermediate products.Bergius was educated at the universities of Breslau, Leipzig, and Berlin and at technical schools in Karlsruhe and Hannover. He described his research in The Use of High Pressure in Chemical Actions (1913). These studies led to his work on converting coal into liquid hydrocarbons.Bergius also rese...
</Question>
<Choice>Bergius, Friedrich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish chemist and naturalist who introduced many improvements in chemical analysis and made important advances in the theory of crystal structure.Bergman was appointed associate professor of mathematics at the University of Uppsala in 1761, and six years later he became professor of chemistry there. His early studies were on rainbows and on the Aurora Borealis, which he estimated to have a height of 740 kilometres (460 miles). Bergman also investigated the pyroelectric properties of the mineral tourmaline and discovered that when a tourmaline crystal is heated, the ends become oppositely cha...
</Question>
<Choice>Bergman, Torbern Olof</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French organic and physical chemist, science historian, and government official. His creative thought and work significantly influenced the development of chemistry in the latter part of the 19th century.Berthelot achieved great renown in his lifetime. He entered the French Academy of Medicine in 1863, became president of the Chemical Society of Paris in 1866, and was elected to the French Academy of Sciences in 1873 and became its permanent secretary in 1889. He also entered the French Academy in 1901. When he died in 1907, he was honoured throughout the nation, with most French towns naming...
</Question>
<Choice>Berthelot, Pierre-Eugene Marcellin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
central French figure in the emergence of chemistry as a modern discipline in the late 18th century. He combined acute experimental skills with fundamental theoretical proposals about the nature of chemical reactions, eventually leading to the law of mass action.
</Question>
<Choice>Berthollet, Claude-Louis, Comte</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
one of the founders of modern chemistry. He is especially noted for his determination of atomic weights, the development of modern chemical symbols, his electrochemical theory, the discovery and isolation of several elements, the development of classical analytical techniques, and his investigation of isomerism and catalysis, phenomena that owe their names to him. He was a strict empiricist and insisted that any new theory be consistent with the sum of chemical knowledge.
</Question>
<Choice>Berzelius, Jons Jacob</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American chemist and businesswoman who is best remembered as the inventor of the cosmetics line that bore her name.Bishop graduated from Barnard College in 1929 and attended graduate night courses at Columbia University. From 1935 to 1942 she was an assistant in a dermatologic laboratory, after which she took a job as an organic chemist with the Standard Oil Development Company (1942–45); she then worked in a similar capacity for the Socony Vacuum Oil Company (1945–50).In 1949, after a long series of home experiments, Bishop perfected a lipstick that stayed on the lips longer than any other pr...
</Question>
<Choice>Bishop, Hazel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British chemist and physicist best known for the rediscovery of “fixed air” (carbon dioxide), the concept of latent heat, and the discovery of the bicarbonates (such as bicarbonate of soda). Black lived and worked within the context of the Scottish Enlightenment, a remarkable flourishing of intellectual life in Edinburgh, Glasgow, and Aberdeen during the latter half of the 18th century. He could count the philosopher David Hume, economist Adam Smith, and geologist James Hutton among his friends.
</Question>
<Choice>Black, Joseph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American chemist and physicist whose work on the radioactive decay of uranium and thorium was important in the development of the theory of isotopes.Boltwood was a member of the Yale faculty from 1897 until 1900, when he established a consulting firm of mining engineers and chemists in partnership with the American chemist Joseph Hyde Pratt. Boltwood grew interested in radioactivity and, in 1904, showed that many of the radioactive elements decay into other radioactive elements. He discovered ionium, now called thorium-230. In 1905 he proposed that lead is the final decay product of uranium an...
</Question>
<Choice>Boltwood, Bertram Borden</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
major Russian nationalist composer of the 19th century. He was also a scientist notable for his research on aldehydes.Borodin's father was a Georgian prince and his mother an army doctor's wife, and he was reared in comfortable circumstances. His gift for languages and music was evident early on, and as a schoolboy he learned to play the piano, flute, and cello and to compose music. From 1850 to 1856 he studied at the Medico-Surgical Academy, specializing in chemistry, and received a doctorate in 1858. From 1859 to 1862 he studied in western Europe. On his return to Russia he became adjunct pr...
</Question>
<Choice>Borodin, Aleksandr</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German industrial chemist who developed the Haber-Bosch process for high-pressure synthesis of ammonia and received, with Friedrich Bergius, the 1931 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for devising chemical high-pressure methods.Bosch was educated at the University of Leipzig, where he studied under Johannes Wislicenus and obtained his doctorate in 1898 for research in organic chemistry. His interests were, however, general, and he studied engineering in Charlottenburg in 1894 and obtained workshop experience.Leaving Leipzig, Bosch worked for BASF AG, of which (when it became part of the cartel IG Farb...
</Question>
<Choice>Bosch, Carl</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French agricultural chemist who helped identify the basic scheme of the biological nitrogen cycle when he demonstrated that plants do not absorb the element from air but from the soil in the form of nitrates.A director of French mining explorations in South America, Boussingault became professor of chemistry at the University of Lyon, Fr., and professor of agricultural chemistry at the Conservatory of Arts and Crafts, Paris (1839–87). After discovering that nitrogen is essential to plants and animals, he disproved the belief that plants absorb the element from the atmosphere and proved that pl...
</Question>
<Choice>Boussingault, Jean-Baptiste</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Canadian geologist who was one of the most important pioneers in the field of experimental petrology (i.e., the experimental study of the origin and chemical composition of rocks). He was widely recognized for his phase-equilibrium studies of silicate systems as they relate to the origin of igneous rocks.Bowen studied chemistry, mineralogy, and geology at Queen's University, Kingston, Ont., earning two degrees there by 1909. He obtained his Ph.D. at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology in 1912. That year he joined the Geophysical Laboratory of the Carnegie Institution of Washington, D.C.,...
</Question>
<Choice>Bowen, Norman L.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biochemist who, with John E. Walker, was awarded the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1997 for their explanation of the enzymatic process involved in the production of the energy-storage molecule adenosine triphosphate (ATP), which fuels the metabolic processes of the cells of all living things. (Danish chemist Jens C. Skou also shared the award for separate research on the molecule.)After receiving his doctorate in biochemistry in 1943 from the University of Wisconsin, Boyer held a number of teaching positions before joining the faculty of the University of California at Los Angeles in 1...
</Question>
<Choice>Boyer, Paul D.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British natural philosopher and theological writer, a preeminent figure of 17th-century intellectual culture. He was best known as a natural philosopher, particularly in the field of chemistry, but his scientific work covered many areas including hydrostatics, physics, medicine, earth sciences, natural history, and alchemy. His prolific output also included Christian devotional and ethical essays and theological tracts on biblical language, the limits of reason, and the role of the natural philosopher as a Christian. He sponsored many religious missions as well as the translation of the Script...
</Question>
<Choice>Boyle, Robert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German chemist who, through his discovery of phosphorus, became the first known discoverer of an element.A military officer and self-styled physician, Brand has often received the undeserved title “last of the alchemists” because of his continual search for the philosopher's stone, which reputedly could change base metals into gold. About 1669 he isolated from urine a white, waxy material and named it phosphorus (“light bearer”), because it glowed in the dark. Although Brand kept his process a secret, phosphorus was discovered independently in 1680 by an English chemist, Robert Boyle.
</Question>
<Choice>Brand, Hennig</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish chemist who, through his discovery and isolation of cobalt, became the first person to discover a metal unknown in ancient times.In 1727 Brandt was appointed director of the chemical laboratory of the Council of Mines, Stockholm, and three years later became warden of the Royal Mint. He discovered and named cobalt in 1730. His findings on the composition and solubility of arsenic compounds were published in 1733; and he then pursued research on antimony, bismuth, mercury, and zinc. His work on methods of producing hydrochloric, nitric, and sulfuric acids was published in 1741 and 1743....
</Question>
<Choice>Brandt, Georg</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
one of the leading American chemists of the 20th century. His seminal work on customized reducing agents and organoborane compounds in synthetic organic chemistry had a major impact on both academic and industrial chemical practice and led to his sharing the 1979 Nobel Prize for Chemistry with the German chemist Georg Wittig.
</Question>
<Choice>Brown, Herbert Charles</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German biochemist who was awarded the 1907 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for demonstrating that the fermentation of carbohydrates results from the action of different enzymes contained in yeast and not the yeast cell itself. He showed that an enzyme, zymase, can be extracted from yeast cells and that it causes sugar to break up into carbon dioxide and alcohol.Buchner studied chemistry under Adolf von Baeyer at the University of Munich, received his doctorate in 1888, and held professorships at the universities of Kiel, Tübingen, Berlin, Breslau, and Würzburg. Despite lack of encouragement, he pers...
</Question>
<Choice>Buchner, Eduard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German chemist who, with Gustav Kirchhoff, about 1859 observed that each element emits a light of characteristic wavelength. These studies opened the field of spectrum analysis, which became of great importance in the study of the Sun and stars and also led Bunsen almost immediately to his discovery of two alkali-group metals, cesium and rubidium.After taking his Ph.D. in chemistry at the University of Göttingen (1830), Bunsen taught at the universities of Marburg and Breslau and elsewhere. As professor at Heidelberg (1852–99), he built up an excellent school of chemistry. Never married, he li...
</Question>
<Choice>Bunsen, Robert Wilhelm</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American chemist who developed a thermal cracking process for increasing the proportion of gasoline obtainable from crude petroleum.Burton began work as a chemist at the Standard Oil Co. (Indiana) refinery at Whiting, Ind., in 1890, rising swiftly to serve as president from 1918 to 1927. Crude oil, a mixture of various hydrocarbons, can be separated into several groups of constituents by physical means, commonly distillation. His thermal cracking process, patented in 1913, utilized chemical methods that doubled the yield of gasoline by transforming many of the less volatile components into gas...
</Question>
<Choice>Burton, William Merriam</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German biochemist who, with Leopold Ruzicka, was awarded the 1939 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for his work on sex hormones. Although forced by the Nazi government to refuse the prize, he was able to accept the honour in 1949.Butenandt studied at the universities of Marburg and Göttingen, receiving his Ph.D. from the latter in 1927. He then taught at Göttingen and at the Institute of Technology in Danzig (now Gdansk, Pol.). Butenandt was director of the Kaiser Wilhelm Institute (later the Max Planck Institute) for Biochemistry in Berlin beginning in 1936, and when the institute moved to Tübingen...
</Question>
<Choice>Butenandt, Adolf Friedrich Johann</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian chemist who helped advance the theory of structure in chemistry, especially with regard to tautomerism, the facile interconvertibility of certain structurally similar compounds.Joining the faculty of Kazan University in 1849, Butlerov took up the new theories of the French chemists Auguste Laurent and Charles Gerhardt and worked on new methods of synthesizing known compounds and on entirely new synthetics.In 1861 Butlerov stated his concept of chemical structure: that the chemical nature of a molecule is determined not only by the number and type of atoms but also by their arrangement....
</Question>
<Choice>Butlerov, Aleksandr</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biochemist who received the 1961 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for his discovery of the chemical pathways of photosynthesis.Calvin was the son of immigrant parents. His father was from Kalvaria, Lith., so the Ellis Island immigration authorities renamed him Calvin; his mother was from Russian Georgia. Soon after his birth, the family moved to Detroit, Mich., where Calvin showed an early interest in science, especially chemistry and physics. In 1927 he received a full scholarship from the Michigan College of Mining and Technology (now Michigan Technological University) in Houghton, where h...
</Question>
<Choice>Calvin, Melvin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian chemist who was closely associated with a crucial reform movement in science.
</Question>
<Choice>Cannizzaro, Stanislao</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American chemist who developed nylon, the first synthetic polymer fibre to be produced commercially (in 1938) and one that laid the foundation of the synthetic-fibre industry.At the University of Illinois and later at Harvard University, Carothers did research and teaching in organic chemistry. In 1928 he was appointed director of research in organic chemistry by E.I. du Pont de Nemours &amp; Company at its laboratory in Wilmington, Del. He investigated the structure of substances of high molecular weight and their formation by polymerization. These fundamental investigations led to the develo...
</Question>
<Choice>Carothers, Wallace Hume</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American agricultural chemist, agronomist, and experimenter whose development of new products derived from peanuts (groundnuts), sweet potatoes, and soybeans helped revolutionize the agricultural economy of the South. For most of his career he taught and conducted research at the Tuskegee Normal and Industrial Institute (now Tuskegee University) in Tuskegee, Ala.Carver was the son of a slave woman owned by Moses Carver. During the Civil War, slave owners found it difficult to hold slaves in the border state of Missouri, and Moses Carver therefore sent his slaves, including the young child and...
</Question>
<Choice>Carver, George Washington</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
natural philosopher, the greatest experimental and theoretical English chemist and physicist of his age. Cavendish was distinguished for great accuracy and precision in researches into the composition of atmospheric air, the properties of different gases, the synthesis of water, the law governing electrical attraction and repulsion, a mechanical theory of heat, and calculations of the density (and hence the weight) of the Earth. His experiment to weigh the Earth has come to be known as the Cavendish experiment.
</Question>
<Choice>Cavendish, Henry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biochemist and molecular biologist who, with Sidney Altman, was awarded the 1989 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for their discoveries concerning RNA (ribonucleic acid).Cech attended Grinnell College in Grinnell, Iowa (B.A., 1970), and the University of California at Berkeley (Ph.D., 1975, in chemistry). After serving as a National Cancer Institute fellow at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (1975–77), he joined the Department of Chemistry at the University of Colorado in 1978, becoming a full professor in 1983. Concurrently he was an investigator for the National Institutes of Heal...
</Question>
<Choice>Cech, Thomas Robert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French chemist and industrialist who first developed and manufactured rayon.Trained as a civil engineer after completing scientific studies under Louis Pasteur, Chardonnet began to develop an artificial fibre in 1878. Obtaining a patent in 1884 on a fibre produced by extruding a solution of cellulose nitrate through fine glass capillaries, he worked for several years on the problem of reducing the flammability of the new substance. At the Paris Exposition of 1889 he showed rayon products to the public for the first time. Soon afterward he opened a factory, Société de la Soie de Chardonnet (“So...
</Question>
<Choice>
Chardonnet, Louis-Marie-Hilaire Bernigaud, comte de
</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French chemist who was corecipient, with Robert H. Grubbs and Richard R. Schrock, of the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 2005 for developing metathesis, an important chemical reaction used in organic chemistry. Chauvin offered a detailed explanation of “how metatheses reactions function and what types of metal compound act as catalysts in the reactions.”Chauvin graduated in 1954 from the Lyon School of Chemistry, Physics, and Electronics. From 1960 he spent most of his career conducting research at the French Institute of Petroleum (IFP), where he was named research director in 1991 and honorary...
</Question>
<Choice>Chauvin, Yves</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French chemist who elucidated the chemical composition of animal fats and whose theories of colour influenced the techniques of French painting.
</Question>
<Choice>Chevreul, Michel-Eugene</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Israeli biochemist who shared the 2004 Nobel Prize for Chemistry with Avram Hershko and Irwin Rose for their joint discovery of the mechanism by which the cells of most living organisms cull unwanted proteins.Ciechanover received an M.D. (1974) from Hebrew University–Hadassah Medical School in Jerusalem and a D.Sc. (1981) from the Technion–Israel Institute of Technology in Haifa, where he was taught by Hershko. In 1977 Ciechanover joined the faculty at the Technion, where he held a variety of academic positions.In the late 1970s and early '80s, Ciechanover, Hershko, and Rose worked together at...
</Question>
<Choice>Ciechanover, Aaron J.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
engineer, chemist, and inventor of the neon light, which found widespread use in signs and was the forerunner of the fluorescent light.In 1897 Claude discovered that acetylene gas could be transported safely by dissolving it in acetone. His method was generally adopted and brought a wide expansion to the acetylene industry. Independently of the German chemist Carl von Linde, he developed a process for producing liquefied air in quantity (1902). Although he proposed the use of liquid oxygen in iron smelting as early as 1910, his suggestion was not adopted until after World War II.While studying...
</Question>
<Choice>Claude, Georges</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish chemist who discovered the elements holmium and thulium.Cleve became assistant professor of chemistry at the University of Uppsala in 1868 and in addition taught at the Technological Institute in Stockholm from 1870 to 1874. He then was appointed professor of general and agricultural chemistry at Uppsala.After extensive chemical investigations, Cleve concluded in 1874 that the element didymium was actually two elements. His theory was vindicated 11 years later by C.A. Welsbach's discovery of neodymium and praseodymium. In 1879 Cleve showed that the newly discovered scandium was the ele...
</Question>
<Choice>Cleve, Per Teodor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch chemist noted for his extensive work on the allotropy of metals, particularly tin, and for his research in piezochemistry and electrochemical thermodynamics.Cohen was educated under J.H. van't Hoff at the University of Amsterdam (Ph.D., 1893) and worked in Paris with Henri Moissan before returning to teach chemistry in Amsterdam. In 1902 he moved to the University of Utrecht as director of a chemical laboratory. Cohen helped discover the two allotropes of tin (white tin and gray tin) and determined their differing properties. He lectured throughout Europe and the United States and publis...
</Question>
<Choice>Cohen, Ernst Julius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American educator and scientist, president of Harvard University, and U.S. high commissioner for western Germany following World War II.Conant received his A.B. and Ph.D. (1916) degrees from Harvard and, after spending a year in the research division of the chemical warfare service during World War I, returned to Harvard as instructor in chemistry. He won recognition as a brilliant research chemist, becoming department chairman by the age of 38. He specialized in research into free radicals, the chemical structure of chlorophyll, and the quantitative study of organic reactions.In 1933 Conant w...
</Question>
<Choice>Conant, James B.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American chemist, director of a research group that developed syntheses of scores of complicated organic molecules and winner of the 1990 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for his original contributions to the theory and methods of organic synthesis.
</Question>
<Choice>Corey, Elias James</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British chemist who was corecipient, with Vladimir Prelog, of the 1975 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for his research on the stereochemistry of enzyme-catalyzed reactions. Stereochemistry is the study of how the properties of a chemical compound are affected by the spatial arrangement of atoms in molecules and complexes.Cornforth suffered since childhood from a progressive hearing loss which later rendered him completely deaf. He graduated from the University of Sydney in 1937 and earned his doctorate from Oxford University in 1941, and in that same year he married Rita Harradence, an organic chem...
</Question>
<Choice>Cornforth, Sir John Warcup</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. educator, scientist, and inventor of the electrostatic precipitator, a device that removes suspended particles from streams of gases.Cottrell taught chemistry at the University of California, Berkeley, from 1902 to 1911 and began his work on electrostatic precipitators in 1906. In 1912 he founded the Research Corporation, a nonprofit organization that supports basic research in colleges and universities, and he assigned his precipitator patents to the corporation as an endowment.From 1911 to 1920 Cottrell was associated with the United States Bureau of Mines as chief physical chemist, chi...
</Question>
<Choice>Cottrell, Frederick Gardner</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish chemist who, independently of August Kekule, proposed the tetravalency of carbon and the ability of carbon atoms to bond with one another.Couper was a student at the universities of Glasgow and Paris and became an assistant at the University of Edinburgh. Through Charles-Adolphe Wurtz, Couper submitted the paper on which his fame rests to the French Academy, but because Wurtz was not a member of the academy, the paper's presentation was delayed until June 14, 1858, about two months after Kekule's paper containing the same revolutionary theory had been presented. A controversy about pr...
</Question>
<Choice>Couper, Archibald Scott</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French chemist who discovered the element iodine.Courtois served as a pharmacist in the French Army and later joined his father's saltpetre business. In 1811 he added too much sulfuric acid to seaweed ash, a major raw material in saltpetre production, and obtained a violet vapour that condensed to form dark crystals. He prepared numerous compounds of this new element and investigated its properties. His work was announced in 1813, and the element was later named iodine.After the Napoleonic Wars his saltpetre business failed. Although he turned to the manufacture of iodine, this business also f...
</Question>
<Choice>Courtois, Bernard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American chemist who, along with Charles J. Pedersen and Jean-Marie Lehn, was awarded the 1987 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for his creation of molecules that mimic the chemical behaviour of molecules found in living systems.Cram was educated at Rollins College in Winter Park, Florida, and at the University of Nebraska, and he received a doctorate in organic chemistry from Harvard University in 1947. He joined the faculty of the University of California at Los Angeles in 1947 and became a full professor there in 1956 and emeritus in 1990.Cram amplified and expanded upon Pedersen's ground-breaking...
</Question>
<Choice>Cram, Donald J.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish mineralogist and chemist noted for his work on the chemistry of metallic elements and for his efforts to establish a new mineralogical system. He is also credited with developing an experimental procedure involving the systematic use of blowpipes for analyzing the chemical composition of minerals.Cronstedt was the first to isolate nickel (1751). He also made a detailed analysis of calcium tungstate, a previously unknown mineral of high specific gravity, and studied the properties of gypsum and a hydrous mineral he named zeolite. Such experiments revealed certain laws governing the inte...
</Question>
<Choice>Cronstedt, Axel Fredrik</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British chemist and physicist noted for his discovery of the element thallium and for his cathode-ray studies, fundamental in the development of atomic physics.After studying at the Royal College of Chemistry, London, Crookes became superintendent of the meteorological department at Radcliffe Observatory, Oxford, in 1854, and the following year gained a post at the College of Science in Chester, Cheshire. Having inherited a large fortune from his father, he devoted himself from 1856 entirely to scientific work of various kinds at his private laboratory in London. His researches on electrical d...
</Question>
<Choice>Crookes, Sir William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch chemist who received the 1995 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for demonstrating, in 1970, that chemical compounds of nitrogen oxide accelerate the destruction of stratospheric ozone, which protects the Earth from the Sun's ultraviolet radiation. He shared the honour with American chemists Mario Molina and F. Sherwood Rowland, who discovered in 1974 that manufactured chlorofluorocarbon gases also contribute to ozone depletion.Crutzen received a doctorate in meteorology from Stockholm University in 1973. He worked at the Max Planck Institute for Chemistry in Mainz, Ger. In 1970 he discovered tha...
</Question>
<Choice>Crutzen, Paul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polish-born French physicist, famous for her work on radioactivity and twice a winner of the Nobel Prize. With Henri Becquerel and her husband, Pierre Curie, she was awarded the 1903 Nobel Prize for Physics. She was the sole winner of the 1911 Nobel Prize for Chemistry. She was the first woman to win a Nobel Prize, and she is the only woman to win the award in two different fields.From childhood she was remarkable for her prodigious memory, and at the age of 16 she won a gold medal on completion of her secondary education at the Russian lycée. Because her father, a teacher of mathematics and p...
</Question>
<Choice>Curie, Marie</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physical chemist, cowinner of the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1903. He and his wife, Marie Curie, discovered radium and polonium in their investigation of radioactivity. An exceptional physicist, he was one of the main founders of modern physics.Educated by his father, a doctor, Curie developed a passion for mathematics at the age of 14 and showed a particular aptitude for spatial geometry, which was later to help him in his work on crystallography. Matriculating at the age of 16 and obtaining his licence ès sciences at 18, he was in 1878 taken on as laboratory assistant at the Sorbonne....
</Question>
<Choice>Curie, Pierre</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American chemist who with Richard E. Smalley and Sir Harold W. Kroto discovered buckminsterfullerene, a spherical form of carbon comprising 60 atoms, in 1985. The discovery opened a new branch of chemistry, and all three men were awarded the 1996 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for their work.Curl studied at Rice University (B.A., 1954) in Houston and then completed his doctoral studies in chemistry at the University of California at Berkeley in 1957. He joined the faculty at Rice in 1958. In September 1985 Curl met with Kroto, of the University of Sussex, Eng., and Smalley, a colleague at Rice. In...
</Question>
<Choice>Curl, Robert F., Jr.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English meteorologist and chemist, a pioneer in the development of modern atomic theory.
</Question>
<Choice>Dalton, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British chemist and meteorologist who invented the Daniell cell, which was a great improvement over the voltaic cell used in the early days of battery development.In 1820 Daniell invented a dew-point hygrometer (a device that indicates atmospheric humidity), which came into widespread use. In his Meteorological Essays and Observations (1823), Daniell revealed his findings on the behaviour of the atmosphere and on trade winds, in addition to giving details of improved meteorological equipment. In a later edition he also discussed the meteorological effects of solar radiation and the cooling of...
</Question>
<Choice>Daniell, John Frederic</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
physician, chemist, and inventor who devised the electromagnetic repeater for relaying telegraphic signals and invented an electrochemical telegraph (1838).Davy, who wrote an Experimental Guide to Chemistry (1836), emigrated in 1839 to Australia, where, in addition to practicing medicine, he worked as an editor, farmer, and factory manager. Before leaving Great Britain he sold the patent for his telegraph; the purchasers never exploited the invention commercially, and for several decades Davy's contributions were ignored. He developed the electromagnetic repeater, which consisted of a relay to...
</Question>
<Choice>Davy, Edward</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English chemist who discovered several chemical elements (including sodium and potassium) and compounds, invented the miner's safety lamp, and became one of the greatest exponents of the scientific method.
</Question>
<Choice>Davy, Sir Humphry, Baronet</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
physical chemist whose investigations of dipole moments, X rays, and light scattering in gases brought him the 1936 Nobel Prize for Chemistry.After receiving his Ph.D. in physics from the University of Munich (1910), Debye taught physics at the universities of Zürich, Utrecht, Göttingen, and Leipzig before becoming director of the Kaiser Wilhelm Institute for Theoretical Physics at Berlin (1935). Two months before the German invasion of his native country (1940), he went to Ithaca, N.Y., to deliver a lecture at Cornell University and remained there until he retired as chemistry department chai...
</Question>
<Choice>Debye, Peter</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German biochemist who, along with Hartmut Michel and Robert Huber, received the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1988 for their determination of the structure of certain proteins that are essential to photosynthesis.Deisenhofer earned his doctorate from the Max Planck Institute for Biochemistry in Martinsried, W.Ger., in 1974. He conducted research there until 1987, when he joined the scientific staff at the Howard Hughes Medical Institute in Dallas, Texas.Together with Michel and Huber, Deisenhofer set out to study the structure of a protein complex found in certain photosynthetic bacteria. This...
</Question>
<Choice>Deisenhofer, Johann</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British chemist and physicist whose study of low-temperature phenomena entailed the use of a double-walled vacuum flask of his own design which has been named for him.Educated at the University of Edinburgh, Dewar became a professor at the University of Cambridge (1875) and at the Royal Institution of Great Britain, London (1877), holding both posts throughout his life.Dewar developed structural formulas for benzene (1867), did research in spectroscopy for more than 25 years, and by 1891 had constructed a machine for producing liquid oxygen in quantity. About 1892 he conceived the idea of usin...
</Question>
<Choice>Dewar, Sir James</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German organic chemist who with Kurt Alder was awarded the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1950 for their joint work in developing a method of preparing cyclic organic compounds.Diels studied chemistry at the University of Berlin under Emil Fischer and after various appointments was made professor of chemistry at the University of Kiel (1916). He became emeritus in 1945.In 1906 Diels discovered a highly reactive substance, carbon suboxide (the acid anhydride of malonic acid), and determined its properties and chemical composition. He also devised an easily controlled method of removing some of th...
</Question>
<Choice>Diels, Otto Paul Hermann</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German chemist whose observation of similarities among certain elements anticipated the development of the periodic system of elements.As a coachman's son, Döbereiner had little opportunity for formal schooling, but he was apprenticed to an apothecary, read widely, and attended learned science lectures. Eventually he was able to attend the University of Jena, where he became an assistant professor (1810) and later was supervisor of science instruction. He was a lifelong friend of Johann Wolfgang von Goethe.During the 1820s Döbereiner's experiments with the ignition of hydrogen on contact with...
</Question>
<Choice>Dobereiner, Johann Wolfgang</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British chemist whose work was instrumental in the development of colloid chemistry.Donnan was educated at Queen's College in Belfast, N.Ire., and at the Universities of Leipzig, Berlin, and London. From 1904 to 1913 he taught at the University of Liverpool, and from 1913 to his retirement in 1937 he was professor of chemistry at University College, London.In 1911 Donnan studied the conditions under which equilibrium is established between two electrolytic solutions separated by a semipermeable membrane—that is, by a membrane through which the solvent and some, but not all, of the dissolved io...
</Question>
<Choice>Donnan, Frederick George</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
pioneer in the American chemical industry and founder of the Dow Chemical Company.Dow first became interested in brines (concentrated solutions of salts and water) while attending Case School of Applied Science (now Case Western Reserve University) in Cleveland (B.S.; 1888). His analysis of brines from several sites revealed that those of Canton, Ohio, and Midland, Mich., were rich in bromine. He developed and patented electrolytic methods for extracting bromine from brine and in 1890 organized the Midland Chemical Company. The Dow process was remarkable in that it did not result in a salt by-...
</Question>
<Choice>Dow, Herbert H.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biochemist and winner of the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1955 for the isolation and synthesis of two pituitary hormones: vasopressin, which acts on the muscles of the blood vessels to cause elevation of blood pressure; and oxytocin, the principal agent causing contraction of the uterus and secretion of milk.Du Vigneaud studied at the University of Illinois, Urbana, took his doctorate from the University of Rochester, N.Y. (1927), then studied at Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, the Kaiser Wilhelm Institute, Berlin, and the University of Edinburgh. He headed the biochemistry depar...
</Question>
<Choice>du Vigneaud, Vincent</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
chemist and physicist who helped formulate the Dulong–Petit law of specific heats (1819), which proved useful in determining atomic weights.He was an assistant to Claude-Louis Berthollet, eventually became a professor of physics at the Polytechnical School, Paris (1820), and was appointed its director (1830). While working in chemistry he impoverished himself purchasing equipment. During investigations of the highly explosive nitrogen trichloride, which he discovered in 1813, he lost the sight in one eye and nearly lost a hand. His important research in physics was carried out with Alexis-Thér...
</Question>
<Choice>Dulong, Pierre-Louis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American plant geneticist, botanist, agronomist, and chemist, whose experiments, along with those of others, led to the development of hybrid corn (maize). He was particularly interested in determining and controlling the protein and fat content of corn, both of which have significant influence upon that grain's value as animal feed.A precocious youth, East finished high school at age 15 and then worked in a machine shop for two years to earn money for college. Trained as a chemist, he developed an interest in genetics and in 1900 became an assistant to Cyril George Hopkins of the Illinois Agr...
</Question>
<Choice>East, Edward Murray</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist who was corecipient, with R.G.W. Norrish and George Porter, of the 1967 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for work on extremely rapid chemical reactions.Eigen was educated in physics and chemistry at the University of Göttingen (Ph.D., 1951). He worked at the university's Institute of Physical Chemistry from 1951 to 1953, when he joined the Max Planck Institute for Biophysical Chemistry, Göttingen, where he became director in 1964 and later chairman.Eigen was able to study many extremely fast chemical reactions by a variety of methods that he introduced and which are called relaxation...
</Question>
<Choice>Eigen, Manfred</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish chemist who in 1802 discovered the element tantalum. After graduation from the University of Uppsala (1788) and travels in Germany, Ekeberg returned to Uppsala and began teaching (1794), introducing the chemistry of Antoine-Laurent Lavoisier. Though he was partly deaf from a childhood infection and had been blinded in one eye by an exploding flask (1801), he carried on admirably. Perhaps his greatest contribution to chemistry was the discovery of the talent of his student Jöns Jacob Berzelius.
</Question>
<Choice>Ekeberg, Anders Gustav</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish chemist and mineralogist who in partnership with his brother Juan José was the first to isolate tungsten, or wolfram (1783), though not the first to recognize its elemental nature. After teaching at Vergara, in Spain (1781–85), Fausto accompanied his brother to several European colleges, including the Freiberg (Saxony) School of Mining and the University of Uppsala in Sweden. In 1788 he was appointed supervisor of the Mexican mining industry; his work was ended by the revolutionary movement early in the 19th century. On his return to Spain he was named director general of mines and min...
</Question>
<Choice>Elhuyar y de Suvisa, Fausto d'</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss researcher and teacher who in 1991 won the Nobel Prize for Chemistry for his development of techniques for high-resolution nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) spectroscopy. Ernst's refinements made NMR techniques a basic and indispensable tool in chemistry and also extended their usefulness to other sciences.Ernst received both his B.A. in chemistry (1957) and his Ph.D. in physical chemistry (1962) from the Federal Institute of Technology in Zürich. From 1963 to 1968 he worked as a research chemist in Palo Alto, Calif. In 1966, working with an American colleague, Ernst discovered that the s...
</Question>
<Choice>Ernst, Richard R.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish biochemist who shared the 1929 Nobel Prize for Chemistry with Sir Arthur Harden for work on the role of enzymes in the fermentation of sugar.After graduating from the University of Berlin (1895), Euler-Chelpin worked with Walther Nernst and in 1897 became assistant to Svante Arrhenius at the Royal Institute of Technology in Stockholm. He joined the faculty at the University of Stockholm (1900), where he became professor of general and inorganic chemistry (1906) and director of the new biochemical institute (1929).Euler-Chelpin's research on enzymes showed that when an enzyme acts on an...
</Question>
<Choice>Euler-Chelpin, Hans von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physicist and chemist whose many experiments contributed greatly to the understanding of electromagnetism.Faraday, who became one of the greatest scientists of the 19th century, began his career as a chemist. He wrote a manual of practical chemistry that reveals his mastery of the technical aspects of his art, discovered a number of new organic compounds, among them benzene, and was the first to liquefy a “permanent” gas (i.e., one that was believed to be incapable of liquefaction). His major contribution, however, was in the field of electricity and magnetism. He was the first to prod...
</Question>
<Choice>Faraday, Michael</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American scientist who, with Tanaka Koichi and Kurt Wüthrich, won the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 2002 for developing techniques to identify and analyze proteins and other large biological molecules.Fenn received a Ph.D. in chemistry from Yale University in 1940. He then spent more than a decade working for various companies before joining Princeton University in 1952. In 1967 he moved to Yale, where he became professor emeritus in 1987. Fenn took a post as research professor at Virginia Commonwealth University in 1994.Fenn's prizewinning research expanded the applications of mass spectrometr...
</Question>
<Choice>Fenn, John B.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German chemist who was awarded the 1902 Nobel Prize for Chemistry in recognition of his investigations of the sugar and purine groups of substances.
</Question>
<Choice>Fischer, Emil</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German theoretical chemist and educator who received the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1973 for his identification of a completely new way in which metals and organic substances can combine. He shared the prize with Geoffrey Wilkinson of Great Britain.Fischer served in the German army before and during World War II. In 1952 he received a doctorate in natural sciences from the Technical University in Munich. He lectured there in 1954–57 and became professor of inorganic chemistry and director of the Inorganic Chemistry Institute in 1964. He served on faculties at the University of Munich (1957...
</Question>
<Choice>Fischer, Ernst Otto</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German biochemist who was awarded the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1930 for research into the constitution of hemin, the red blood pigment, and chlorophyll, the green pigment in plants.After receiving his Ph.D. in chemistry from the University of Marburg (1904) and his M.D. from the University of Munich (1908), Fischer worked as a physician and in medical chemical research, going on to become professor of medical chemistry (1916) at the University at Innsbruck, Austria. In 1921 he returned to Munich as professor of organic chemistry.Hemin is a crystalline product of hemoglobin. By splitting in...
</Question>
<Choice>Fischer, Hans</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American polymer chemist who was awarded the 1974 Nobel Prize for Chemistry “for his fundamental achievements, both theoretical and experimental, in the physical chemistry of macromolecules.”
</Question>
<Choice>Flory, Paul J.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American chemist whose research on vitamins resulted in the isolation of vitamin B12, the only effective agent known in countering pernicious anemia.In 1934 Folkers joined the research laboratories of Merck and Co., Inc., Rahway, New Jersey. His early work included pioneering studies of curare, erythrina alkaloids, and morphine alkaloids. During the 1930s his research team synthesized and helped establish the chemical structure of numerous B vitamins.Folkers's search for the anti-pernicious-anemia factor, begun in 1938, ended in 1948 with the isolation of a red crystalline compound now called...
</Question>
<Choice>Folkers, Karl August</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English chemist who was one of the first investigators in the field of structural chemistry.While apprenticed to a druggist, Frankland learned to perform chemical experiments. Subsequent studies took him to laboratories at the University of Marburg, where he took his Ph.D. (1849). He became the first professor of chemistry at Owens College, Manchester (1851), and succeeded Michael Faraday as professor of chemistry at the Royal Institution of Great Britain, London (1863). In 1865 he began 20 years of service at the Royal School of Mines.Research beginning about 1850 led him to the idea that an...
</Question>
<Choice>Frankland, Sir Edward</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. chemist who devised the sulfur mining process named in his honour. The Frasch process, patented in 1891, was first used successfully in Louisiana and in east Texas. It made possible the exploitation of extensive sulfur deposits otherwise obtainable only at prohibitive expense.Emigrating to the U.S. in 1868, Frasch worked as a chemist in Philadelphia and Cleveland, and in 1885 he organized the Empire Oil Company, Petrolia, Ont. For this firm he devised a method (also called the Frasch process) of removing sulfur from crude oil. He also patented processes for manufacturing white lead, sodiu...
</Question>
<Choice>Frasch, Herman</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French chemist best known for his investigations of fluorine compounds. In 1831 he entered the laboratory of Joseph-Louis Gay-Lussac and, after holding several teaching posts, succeeded Gay-Lussac in the chemistry chair at the Museum of Natural History, Paris (1850), of which he became director (1879–91).Frémy investigated osmic acid, ozone, and compounds of iron, tin, and lead, among others. He sought to isolate free fluorine and discovered hydrogen fluoride and a series of its salts. He studied the colouring matters of leaves and flowers and the composition of animal substances. He contribut...
</Question>
<Choice>Fremy, Edmond</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German analytical chemist whose textbooks on qualitative analysis (1841) and quantitative analysis (1846) became standard works. They passed through many editions and were widely translated.Apprenticed to an apothecary (1836), he became an assistant to Justus von Liebig at the University of Giessen (1841) and a privatdocent (1843). From 1845 he was active in scientific and technological education and research at Wiesbaden. Many of his papers appeared in the Zeitschrift für Analytische Chemie (“Journal of Analytical Chemistry”), which he founded (1862) and edited until his death.
</Question>
<Choice>Fresenius, Carl Remigius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese chemist, corecipient with Roald Hoffmann of the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1981 for their independent investigations of the mechanisms of chemical reactions.Fukui took little interest in chemistry before enrolling at Kyoto University, where he studied engineering, receiving a Ph.D. in 1948. He was professor of physical chemistry at Kyoto from 1951 to 1982 and was president of the Kyoto Institute of Technology from 1982 to 1988.In 1952 Fukui published his first exposition of the concept that the crucial process in many chemical reactions consists of an interaction between the highest...
</Question>
<Choice>Fukui Kenichi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish mineralogist and crystallographer who discovered manganese in 1774. His failure to win fame may be related to the fact that he published little. He saved the notes, papers, and letters of his friend Carl Wilhelm Scheele, who discovered chlorine, but not his own. His essays on the balance and use of the blowpipe in analysis were recorded by Jöns Jacob Berzelius of Sweden. Gahn was assistant to Torbern Bergman, pioneer analytical chemist and physicist at the University of Uppsala. With Scheele, Gahn discovered phosphoric acid in bones and prepared phosphorus from bones. He improved coppe...
</Question>
<Choice>Gahn, Johan Gottlieb</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French chemist and physicist who pioneered investigations into the behaviour of gases, established new techniques for analysis, and made notable advances in applied chemistry.
</Question>
<Choice>Gay-Lussac, Joseph-Louis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French chemist, the first chemist to speak of affinity in terms of fixed attractions between different bodies.Assuming that one acid displaces another acid of weaker affinity for a specific base in the salt of that base, Geoffroy composed tables (1718) listing the relative affinities of different reagents for particular substances. Geoffroy's tables remained an authoritative reference throughout most of the 18th century, until they were invalidated by Claude-Louis Berthollet's demonstration that the thoroughness of chemical reactions depends upon the relative quantities of the starting materia...
</Question>
<Choice>Geoffroy, Etienne-Francois</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Canadian-born American physical chemist and winner of the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1949 for his studies of the properties of matter at temperatures close to absolute zero.After earning his Ph.D. from the University of California, Berkeley, in 1922, Giauque joined the chemistry faculty there and held posts at the school until 1981. In 1927 he proposed a new method of achieving extremely low temperatures using a process called adiabatic demagnetization. By 1933 he had a working apparatus that obtained a temperature within one-tenth of a degree of absolute zero (-273.15° C). His research conf...
</Question>
<Choice>Giauque, William Francis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
theoretical physicist and chemist who was one of the greatest scientists in the United States in the 19th century. His application of thermodynamic theory converted a large part of physical chemistry from an empirical into a deductive science.Gibbs was the fourth child and only son of Josiah Willard Gibbs, Sr., professor of sacred literature at Yale University. There were college presidents among his ancestors and scientific ability in his mother's family. Facially and mentally, Gibbs resembled his mother. He was a friendly youth but was also withdrawn and intellectually absorbed. This circums...
</Question>
<Choice>Gibbs, J. Willard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English chemist whose most important contribution was his study of nitrogen fertilizers and their effects on crops.In 1843 Gilbert joined Sir John Bennet Lawes as co-director of agricultural research at the newly founded Rothamsted Experimental Station, Hertfordshire, the first organized agricultural experiment station in the world. Their collaboration lasted for more than half a century. In the 1840s they initiated the manufacture of superphosphate fertilizer, one of their inventions. From 1884 to 1890 Gilbert was Sibthorpian professor of rural economy at Oxford University. He was knighted in...
</Question>
<Choice>Gilbert, Sir Joseph Henry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American molecular biologist who was awarded a share (with Paul Berg and Frederick Sanger) of the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1980 for his development of a method for determining the sequence of nucleotide links in the chainlike molecules of nucleic acids (DNA and RNA).Gilbert graduated from Harvard University with a degree in physics in 1953 and took a Ph.D. in mathematics from Cambridge University in 1957. He joined the Harvard faculty as a lecturer in physics in 1958 and, as his interests changed, advanced to assistant professor of physics in 1959, associate professor of biophysics in 1964...
</Question>
<Choice>Gilbert, Walter</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-Dutch chemist, sometimes called the German Boyle; i.e., the father of chemistry.Settling in Holland, Glauber made his living chiefly by the sale of secret chemicals and medicinals. He prepared hydrochloric acid from common salt and sulfuric acid and pointed out the virtues of the residue, sodium sulfate—sal mirabile, or Glauber's salt; he also noted the formation of nitric acid from potassium nitrate and sulfuric acid.Glauber prepared many substances, made useful observations on dyeing, and described the preparation of tartar emetic. He urged that Germany's natural resources be develope...
</Question>
<Choice>Glauber, Johann Rudolf</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German chemist who invented the alumino-thermic process (1905). Sometimes called the Goldschmidt reduction process, this operation involves reactions of oxides of certain metals with aluminum to yield aluminum oxide and the free metal. The process has been employed to produce such metals as chromium, manganese, and cobalt from oxide ores. It is also used for welding; in this case, iron oxides react with aluminum to produce intense heat and molten iron. Besides this invention, Goldschmidt developed, in collaboration with Alfred Stock, a commercial process for beryllium production about 1918.
</Question>
<Choice>Goldschmidt, Hans</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian-born American chemist who initiated the study of free radicals in chemistry when in 1900 he prepared the first authentic one, triphenylmethyl.At age 18 Gomberg migrated with his family to the United States because his father's antitsarist activities made them unwelcome in Russia. He overcame poverty and language difficulties to earn his undergraduate degree (1890) and Ph.D. (1894) at the University of Michigan, Ann Arbor. Except for a year of study abroad, he was active in teaching and research at the university and was head of the chemistry department from 1927 to his retirement in 19...
</Question>
<Choice>Gomberg, Moses</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British chemist often referred to as “the father of colloid chemistry.”Educated in Scotland, Graham persisted in becoming a chemist, though his father disapproved and withdrew his support. He then made his living by writing and teaching. He was a professor at a school in Edinburgh (1830–37) and at University College, London (1837–55), and was master of the mint (1855–69).Graham's first important paper dealt with the diffusion of gases (1829). He developed “Graham's law” of the diffusion rate of gases and also found that the relative rates of the effusion of gases are comparable to the diffusio...
</Question>
<Choice>Graham, Thomas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French chemist and corecipient, with Paul Sabatier, of the 1912 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for his development of the Grignard reaction. This work in organomagnesium compounds opened a broad area of organic synthesis.In 1898, while a student under Philippe Barbier at Lyon, Grignard began his prizewinning work with a study of the alkylzinc compounds developed earlier by Sir Edward Frankland. It was Barbier who had Grignard repeat some experiments on the preparation of a tertiary alcohol from a mixture of methyl heptyl ketone, magnesium, and methyl iodide. Grignard hit upon the idea of treating t...
</Question>
<Choice>Grignard, Victor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American chemist who, with Richard R. Schrock and Yves Chauvin, won the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 2005 for developing metathesis, an important type of chemical reaction used in organic chemistry. Schrock and Grubbs were honoured for their advances in more-effective catalysts based on a mechanism first proposed by Chauvin.Grubbs studied chemistry at the University of Florida (B.S., 1963; M.S., 1965) and at Columbia University, New York City (Ph.D., 1968). After a year as a postdoctoral fellow at Stanford University, he joined the chemistry faculty at Michigan State University. In 1978 he mov...
</Question>
<Choice>Grubbs, Robert H.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Norwegian chemist who, with Peter Waage, formulated the law of mass action, which details the effects of concentration, mass, and temperature on chemical reaction rates.Guldberg was educated at the University of Christiania and taught at the royal military schools before becoming professor of mathematics at the University of Christiania in 1869. His study of chemical thermodynamics preceded his formulation in 1890 of Guldberg's law, which states that on the absolute scale the boiling point of a substance is two-thirds its critical temperature (the maximum at which a gas can be liquefied by pre...
</Question>
<Choice>Guldberg, Cato Maximilian</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French chemist who played a major part in the reform of chemical nomenclature.
</Question>
<Choice>Guyton de Morveau, Louis Bernard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physical chemist and winner of the 1918 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for his successful work on nitrogen fixation. The Haber-Bosch process combined nitrogen and hydrogen to form ammonia in industrial quantities for production of fertilizer and munitions. Haber is also well known for his supervision of the German poison gas program during World War I.
</Question>
<Choice>Haber, Fritz</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German chemist who, with the radiochemist Fritz Strassmann, is credited with the discovery of nuclear fission. He was awarded the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1944 and shared the Enrico Fermi Award in 1966 with Strassmann and Lise Meitner.
</Question>
<Choice>Hahn, Otto</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American chemist who discovered the electrolytic method of producing aluminum, thus bringing the metal into wide commercial use.While a student at Oberlin (Ohio) College Hall became interested in producing aluminum inexpensively. He continued to use the college laboratory after his graduation in 1885, discovering his method eight months later. Paul-Louis-Toussaint Héroult of France independently discovered the identical process at about the same time.After several failures to interest financial backers, Hall obtained the support of the Mellon family, and the Pittsburgh Reduction Company (later...
</Question>
<Choice>Hall, Charles Martin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German chemist who won fame at the age of 25 for devising the synthesis of substituted pyridines.Hantzsch was a professor at Zürich (1885), Würzburg (1893), and Leipzig (1903). With his student Alfred Werner he investigated the stereochemistry of nitrogen compounds. He discovered that many diazonium compounds are salts or bases. Investigating triphenylmethane dyes led him to pioneer in spectrophotometry. He also advanced a theory of chemical indicators. In his studies of the dissociation of acids, Hantzsch demonstrated the formation of oxonium salts and concluded that acid dissociation occurs...
</Question>
<Choice>Hantzsch, Arthur Rudolf</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American chemist whose investigations of nuclear chemistry, particularly the structure of the nucleus, first revealed the basic process of nuclear fusion, the fundamental principle of the thermonuclear bomb.Harkins received his Ph.D. (1908) from Stanford University, Calif., and taught chemistry at the University of Montana, Missoula, from 1900 to 1912. He spent the rest of his career at the University of Chicago.Harkins predicted the existence of the neutron and heavy hydrogen (or deuterium) and introduced the concept of the packing fraction, a measure of the energy involved in the association...
</Question>
<Choice>Harkins, William Draper</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Norwegian physical chemist and corecipient, with Derek H.R. Barton of Great Britain, of the 1969 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for his work in establishing conformational analysis (the study of the three-dimensional geometric structure of molecules).Hassel studied at the University of Oslo and received his doctorate at the University of Berlin in 1924. He joined the faculty of the University of Oslo in 1925 and from 1934 to 1964 was a professor of physical chemistry and director of the physical chemistry department. He began intensive research on the structure of cyclohexane (a 6-carbon hydrocarbo...
</Question>
<Choice>Hassel, Odd</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English manufacturer, chemist, and discoverer in 1801 of niobium, which he called columbium.Because of his expertise in analysis, Hatchett was frequently called on as a consultant. Mineral substances found in Australia (hatchettine or hatchettite) and North Carolina (hatchettolite) were named for him. Hatchett gave up chemistry on his father's death and succeeded him as coachbuilder to the king.
</Question>
<Choice>Hatchett, Charles</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American mathematician and crystallographer who, along with Jerome Karle, received the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1985. They developed mathematical methods for deducing the molecular structure of chemical compounds from the patterns formed when X rays are diffracted by their crystals.Hauptman was a classmate with Karle at City College of New York, from which they both graduated in 1937. Hauptman went on to study mathematics further at Columbia University (M.A., 1939) and at the University of Maryland (Ph.D., 1955). After World War II, Hauptman was reunited with Karle at the Naval Research La...
</Question>
<Choice>Hauptman, Herbert A.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British chemist, cowinner, with the Swiss chemist Paul Karrer, of the 1937 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for his work in determining the chemical structures of carbohydrates and vitamin C.Haworth graduated from the University of Manchester in 1906 and received a Ph.D. degree from the University of Göttingen in 1910. He taught at the University of St. Andrews (1912–20) and the University of Durham (1920–25). Haworth joined the faculty of St. Andrews University in 1912. While at St. Andrews, he worked with the British chemists Sir James Irvine and Thomas Purdie in the study of carbohydrates, includi...
</Question>
<Choice>Haworth, Sir Norman</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American automobile pioneer who built one of the first automobiles.He successfully tested his one-horsepower, one-cylinder vehicle at 6 or 7 miles (10 or 11 km) per hour on July 4, 1894, at Kokomo, Ind. Haynes claimed that he received the first U.S. traffic ticket when in 1895 a policeman on a bicycle ordered him and his automobile off the streets of Chicago. Now on exhibition at the Smithsonian Institution, Washington, D.C., Haynes's vehicle is the oldest American-made automobile in existence.In partnership with Edgar and Elmer Apperson, Haynes formed the Haynes–Apperson Company, Kokomo, and...
</Question>
<Choice>Haynes, Elwood</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American chemist who, with Alan G. MacDiarmid and Shirakawa Hideki, won the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 2000 for their discovery that certain plastics can be chemically modified to conduct electricity almost as readily as metals.After receiving a Ph.D. in physics from the University of California at Berkeley in 1961, Heeger taught and conducted research at the University of Pennsylvania until 1982, when he became professor at the University of California at Santa Barbara and director of its Institute for Polymers and Organic Solids. In 1990 Heeger founded the UNIAX Corporation to develop and...
</Question>
<Choice>Heeger, Alan J.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Flemish physician, philosopher, mystic, and chemist who recognized the existence of discrete gases and identified carbon dioxide.
</Question>
<Choice>Helmont, Jan Baptista van</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physician and chemist who in 1803 proposed what is now called Henry's law, which states that the amount of a gas absorbed by a liquid is in proportion to the pressure of the gas above the liquid, provided that no chemical action occurs.Henry took his doctor of medicine degree at Edinburgh (1807). When ill health forced him to retire from medical practice, he turned to chemistry. He was awarded the Copley Medal in 1808 and the following year became a fellow of the Royal Society. His Elements of Experimental Chemistry went through 11 editions. He took his own life.
</Question>
<Choice>Henry, William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French chemist who invented the electric-arc furnace—widely used in making steel—and, independently of the simultaneous work of Charles M. Hall of the United States, devised the electrolytic process for preparing aluminum. This process made low-priced aluminum available for the first time, securing the widespread use of the metal and its alloys.While a student at the École des Mines, Paris, Héroult began working on the electrolysis of aluminum compounds. In 1886 he found that electrolysis of a solution of alumina (aluminum oxide) in molten cryolite (sodium aluminum fluoride) resulted in the fo...
</Question>
<Choice>Heroult, Paul-Louis-Toussaint</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American chemist and educator who, with Yuan T. Lee and John C. Polanyi, was awarded the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1986 for his pioneering use of molecular beams to analyze chemical reactions.Herschbach attended Stanford University (B.S., M.S.) and received his Ph.D. in chemical physics from Harvard University in 1958. He taught at the University of California at Berkeley from 1959 to 1963 and at Harvard University from 1963, becoming Baird professor of science there in 1976.In an attempt to discover in detail the changes that occur in chemical reactions, Herschbach applied a technique that...
</Question>
<Choice>Herschbach, Dudley R.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English astronomer and successor to his father, Sir William Herschel, in the field of stellar and nebular observation and discovery.
</Question>
<Choice>Herschel, Sir John Frederick William, 1st Baronet</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hungarian-born Israeli biochemist who shared the 2004 Nobel Prize for Chemistry with Aaron J. Ciechanover and Irwin Rose for their joint discovery of the mechanism by which the cells of most living organisms remove unwanted proteins.Hershko's family emigrated from Hungary to Israel. He studied at the Hebrew University–Hadassah Medical School in Jerusalem, receiving an M.D. (1965) and a Ph.D. (1969). In 1972 he joined the faculty of the Technion–Israel Institute of Technology in Haifa, where Ciechanover was one of his students. Hershko became a distinguished professor at the Technion in 1998.In...
</Question>
<Choice>Hershko, Avram</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Canadian physicist and winner of the 1971 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for his work in determining the electronic structure and geometry of molecules, especially free radicals—groups of atoms that contain odd numbers of electrons. His work provided the foundation for molecular spectroscopy.Herzberg became Privatdozent (unsalaried lecturer) at the Darmstadt Institute of Technology in 1930 but fled Nazi Germany in 1935 and obtained a position with the University of Saskatchewan. From 1945 to 1948 he worked at the University of Chicago's Yerkes Observatory in Williams Bay, Wisconsin, after which he...
</Question>
<Choice>Herzberg, Gerhard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
chemist whose studies of heat in chemical reactions formed the foundation of thermochemistry.After practicing medicine for several years in Irkutsk, Russia, Hess became professor of chemistry in 1830 at the Technological Institute, University of St. Petersburg. His early investigations concerned minerals and the natural gas found near Baku. He discovered the oxidation of sugars to yield saccharic acid and in 1834 published a work on chemistry that became a standard text in Russia for many years.In 1840 Hess announced the law of constant heat summation, also known as Hess's law, which states th...
</Question>
<Choice>Hess, Germain Henri</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
chemist and recipient of the 1943 Nobel Prize for Chemistry. His development of isotopic tracer techniques greatly advanced understanding of the chemical nature of life processes. In 1923 he also discovered, with the Dutch physicist Dirk Coster, the element hafnium.Educated at the University of Budapest, the Technische Hochschule in Berlin, and the University of Freiburg, Hevesy became an assistant at the Technische Hochschule in Zürich. In 1911 he began work at the University of Manchester, England, under Ernest Rutherford on the chemical separation of radium D from lead. Though his at...
</Question>
<Choice>Hevesy, Georg Charles von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Czech chemist who received the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1959 for his discovery and development of polarography.Educated at the Charles University (Universita Karlova) of Prague and at University College, London, Heyrovský worked in London under Sir William Ramsay and F.G. Donnan. After holding several posts at the Charles University, he became professor and director of the department of physical chemistry (1926–54), and he was director of the Polarography Institute at the Czechoslovak Academy of Sciences (1950, 1952–63).The work that eventually led to the discovery of polarography was begu...
</Question>
<Choice>Heyrovsky, Jaroslav</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. educator and chemist whose monograph Solubility (1924; later editions, Solubility of Non-Electrolytes) was the classic reference for almost a half century.Hildebrand spent the greater part of his professional life at the University of California, Berkeley, where he was in turn dean of the College of Letters and Science and the College of Chemistry.Hildebrand was the author of more than 200 scientific papers and a number of chemistry texts and was sought as a speaker and consultant in the United States and abroad. Cited for his research and consultative services in World Wars I and II, he...
</Question>
<Choice>Hildebrand, Joel H.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British chemist who worked on reaction rates and reaction mechanisms, particularly that of the combination of hydrogen and oxygen to form water, one of the most fundamental combining reactions in chemistry. For this work he shared the 1956 Nobel Prize for Chemistry with the Soviet scientist Nikolay Semyonov.Hinshelwood obtained his doctorate at the University of Oxford in 1924 and became professor of chemistry there in 1937. After retiring from Oxford in 1964 he became a senior research fellow at Imperial College, London.About 1930 Hinshelwood began investigating the complex reaction in which...
</Question>
<Choice>Hinshelwood, Sir Cyril Norman</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish chemist who discovered the element molybdenum in 1782.Educated at the University of Uppsala, in 1782 Hjelm became master of assaying for the Royal Mint, Stockholm, and in 1794 was appointed director of chemical laboratories at the Swedish bureau of mines. His research interests included mineralogy, metallurgy, and industrial chemistry. He is credited with the observation that pig iron made from ore containing manganese, which he isolated successfully in 1781, frequently produced superior steel.
</Question>
<Choice>Hjelm, Peter Jacob</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English chemist whose determination of the structure of penicillin and vitamin B12 brought her the 1964 Nobel Prize for Chemistry.
</Question>
<Choice>Hodgkin, Dorothy Mary Crowfoot</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch physical chemist and first winner of the Nobel Prize for Chemistry (1901), for work on rates of chemical reaction, chemical equilibrium, and osmotic pressure.
</Question>
<Choice>Hoff, Jacobus Henricus van't</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polish-born American chemist, corecipient, with Fukui Kenichi of Japan, of the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1981 for their independent investigations of the mechanisms of chemical reactions.Hoffmann immigrated to the United States with his family in 1949. He graduated from Columbia University and received his Ph.D. from Harvard University in 1962. He collaborated with Robert B. Woodward at Harvard during the next three years and then joined the Cornell University faculty in 1965.Hoffmann undertook the research leading to his share of the prize when he and Woodward sought an explanation of the...
</Question>
<Choice>Hoffmann, Roald</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German biochemist who, along with Johann Deisenhofer and Hartmut Michel, received the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1988 for their determination of the structure of a protein complex that is essential to photosynthesis in bacteria.Huber received his doctorate from the Munich Technical University. In 1972 he joined the staff of the Max Planck Institute for Biochemistry at Martinsried, Ger., where he conducted his award-winning research with Deisenhofer and Michel. He alternately worked there and at the Munich Technical University.Huber was an internationally recognized expert in the use of X-ray...
</Question>
<Choice>Huber, Robert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish geologist, chemist, naturalist, and originator of one of the fundamental principles of geology—uniformitarianism, which explains the features of the Earth's crust by means of natural processes over geologic time.Hutton was the son of a merchant and city officeholder. Though Hutton's father died when his son was quite young, Hutton managed an education in the local grammar school and at the University of Edinburgh. Although already interested in chemistry, he entered the legal profession. But as a lawyer's apprentice, he is said to have devoted more time to amusing his fellow clerks wi...
</Question>
<Choice>Hutton, James</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian-born U.S. chemist who was one of the first to investigate high-pressure catalytic reactions of hydrocarbons and who developed a process for manufacturing high-octane gasoline.In 1887 Ipatieff became an officer in the Imperial Russian Army and later attended the Mikhail Artillery Academy (1889–92), St. Petersburg, where he served as professor of chemistry (1898–1906). In 1897 he went to Munich to study and, while there, discovered the structure of isoprene, the basic molecular unit of rubber. Continuing his studies of hydrocarbons after his return to Russia, he soon learned to control a...
</Question>
<Choice>Ipatieff, Vladimir Nikolayevich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
alchemist known as the father of Arab chemistry. He systematized a “quantitative” analysis of substances and was the inspiration for Geber, a Latin alchemist who developed an important corpuscular theory of matter.
</Question>
<Choice>Jabir ibn Hayyan, Abu Musa</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician, chemist, and pioneer geologist and mineralogist.Jackson received his M.D. from Harvard Medical School in 1829. He continued his medical studies at the University of Paris, also attending lectures on geology at the Royal School of Mines. He returned to Boston in 1832 and started a private medical practice but abandoned medicine in 1836 to establish a laboratory for the teaching of analytic chemistry. One of his students was a young dental surgeon, William Thomas Green Morton, with whom Jackson worked on chemical methods for painless dentistry.In 1845 Morton learned from Hora...
</Question>
<Choice>Jackson, Charles Thomas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physical chemists, husband and wife, who were jointly awarded the 1935 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for their discovery of new radioactive isotopes prepared artificially. They were the son-in-law and daughter of Nobel Prize winners Pierre and Marie Curie.Irène Curie from 1912 to 1914 prepared for her baccalauréat at the Collège Sévigné and in 1918 became her mother's assistant at the Institut du Radium of the University of Paris. In 1925 she presented her doctoral thesis on the alpha rays of polonium. In the same year she met Frédéric Joliot in her mother's laboratory; she was to find in h...
</Question>
<Choice>Joliot-Curie, Frederic & Irene</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American chemist, synthesist of cortisone, hormones, and other products from soybeans.Julian attended De Pauw University (A.B., 1920) and Harvard University (M.A., 1923) and studied under Ernst Späth, who synthesized nicotine and ephedrine, at the University of Vienna (Ph.D., 1931). Julian also taught chemistry at Fisk University, West Virginia State College for Negroes, and Howard and De Pauw universities before, in 1936, directing research into soybeans at the Glidden Company in Chicago. He became director of chemicals development there before leaving in 1953 to found his own companies.In hi...
</Question>
<Choice>Julian, Percy L.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American crystallographer who, along with Herbert A. Hauptman, was awarded the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1985 for their development of mathematical methods for deducing the molecular structure of chemical compounds from the patterns formed when X rays are diffracted by their crystals.Karle was a classmate of Hauptman's at City College in New York, from which they both graduated in 1937. Karle went on to earn his Ph.D. degree in physical chemistry at the University of Michigan in 1943. After working on the Manhattan Project in 1943–44, he joined the Naval Research Laboratory in 1944, becomin...
</Question>
<Choice>Karle, Jerome</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss chemist who investigated the constitution of carotenoids, flavins, and vitamins A and B2, for which he shared the 1937 Nobel Prize for Chemistry with Sir Norman Haworth of Great Britain.Born in Russia of Swiss parents, Karrer was educated in Switzerland and received his doctoral degree at the University of Zürich in 1911. After a year spent in the Chemical Institute at Zürich, he joined Paul Ehrlich at the Georg Speyer Haus in Frankfurt am Main, Ger., where he remained for six years. In 1918 Karrer returned to Zürich as professor of chemistry and in 1919 became director of the Chemical I...
</Question>
<Choice>Karrer, Paul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American chemist who, with Philip S. Hench and Tadeus Reichstein, won the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1950 for research on the structure and biological effects of adrenal cortex hormones.A graduate of Columbia University (Ph.D. 1910), Kendall joined the staff of the Mayo Foundation, Rochester, Minn., in 1914. His early research concerned the isolation of the active constituent (thyroxine) of the thyroid hormone. He also crystallized and established the chemical nature of glutathione, a compound important to biological oxidation-reduction reactions.Kendall's most important researc...
</Question>
<Choice>Kendall, Edward Calvin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British biochemist who determined the three-dimensional structure of the muscle protein myoglobin, which stores oxygen in muscle cells. For his achievement he shared the Nobel Prize for Chemistry with Max Ferdinand Perutz in 1962.Kendrew was educated at Trinity College, Cambridge, receiving his Ph.D. there in 1949. In 1946–47 he and Perutz founded the Medical Research Council Unit for Molecular Biology at Cambridge. They used the technique of X-ray crystallography to study the structures of proteins, with Perutz studying hemoglobin and Kendrew trying to determine the structure of the somewhat...
</Question>
<Choice>Kendrew, Sir John Cowdery</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Irish chemist known for his contributions in several areas of science.Kirwan, who was born a Roman Catholic, attended the University of Poitiers in France from about 1750 to 1754. He entered the Jesuit novitiate at Saint-Omer, France, that same year; but, when his elder brother (and the heir to the family estates) was killed in a duel in 1755, Kirwan left Saint-Omer and returned to Ireland.From 1777 to 1787 Kirwan lived in London. While there, he was elected to the Royal Society (1780) and wrote a series of papers on chemical affinity, in addition to the volume Elements of Mineralogy (1784) an...
</Question>
<Choice>Kirwan, Richard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German chemist who discovered uranium (1789), zirconium (1789), and cerium (1803). He described them as distinct elements, though he did not obtain them in the pure metallic state.Klaproth was an apothecary for many years, but his own study of chemistry enabled him to obtain a post as pharmaceutical assessor in a medical school in Berlin in 1782. He began teaching chemistry at various military and other schools, and he was chosen to be professor of chemistry at the newly founded University of Berlin in 1810.The leading chemist of his time in Germany, Klaproth was an exact and conscientious wor...
</Question>
<Choice>Klaproth, Martin Heinrich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian chemist (of German origin) credited with the discovery of ruthenium in 1844.Klaus was educated at Dorpat, where he became a pharmacist; later he taught chemistry and pharmacy at the universities of Dorpat and Kazan. Klaus was noted for his researches on the platinum metals osmium, palladium, iridium, and rhodium, and it was in the course of investigating the waste residues of the platinum refinery in St. Petersburg that he discovered ruthenium.
</Question>
<Choice>Klaus, Karl Karlovich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British chemist who was awarded the 1982 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for his investigations of the three-dimensional structure of viruses and other particles that are combinations of nucleic acids and proteins, and for the development of crystallographic electron microscopy.Klug was taken by his parents from Lithuania to South Africa when he was three years old. He entered the University of the Witwatersrand at Johannesburg intending to study medicine, but he graduated with a science degree. He then began a doctoral program in crystallography at the University of Cape Town but left with a master...
</Question>
<Choice>Klug, Aaron</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American chemist who, with Noyori Ryoji and K. Barry Sharpless, won the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 2001 for developing the first chiral catalysts.Knowles earned a Ph.D. from Columbia University in 1942, after which he conducted research at the Monsanto Company in St. Louis, Missouri, until his retirement in 1986.Many molecules are chiral—they exist in two structural forms (enantiomers) that are nonsuperimposable mirror images. Likewise, the receptors, enzymes, and other cellular components made from these molecules are chiral and tend to interact selectively with only one or two enantiomers...
</Question>
<Choice>Knowles, William S.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian-born American physicist who, with John A. Pople, received the 1998 Nobel Prize in Chemistry. The award recognized their individual work on computations in quantum chemistry. Kohn's share of the prize acknowledged his development of the density-functional theory, which made it possible to apply the complicated mathematics of quantum mechanics to the description and analysis of the chemical bonding between atoms.Having emigrated from his native Austria, Kohn received a master's degree from the University of Toronto (Ontario, Canada) in 1946. He earned a Ph.D. in physics from Harvard Uni...
</Question>
<Choice>Kohn, Walter</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German chemist who accomplished the first generally accepted synthesis of an organic compound from inorganic materials.Kolbe studied chemistry with Friedrich Wöhler at the University of Göttingen and earned his doctorate in 1843 with Robert Bunsen at the University of Marburg (Hesse). After serving as Bunsen's assistant, Kolbe accepted in 1845 a postdoctoral position in London as assistant to Lyon Playfair, a chemist and a member of the British Parliament. Two years later, Kolbe began working as a scientific editor and writer with the Vieweg publishing house in Braunschweig. In 1851 he finally...
</Question>
<Choice>Kolbe, Hermann</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German chemist and historian of chemistry whose studies of the relation of physical properties to chemical structure pioneered physical organic chemistry.Kopp became Privatdozent (unsalaried lecturer) at the University of Giessen in 1841. In that year he began work on one of his most notable achievements, the great Geschichte der Chemie, 4 vol. (1843–47; “History of Chemistry”). Although he spent his life gathering material for a second edition, it was never finished.Extraordinary professor of chemistry at Giessen from 1843, in 1863 Kopp was appointed professor of chemistry at the University o...
</Question>
<Choice>Kopp, Hermann Franz Moritz</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English chemist who, with Richard E. Smalley and Robert F. Curl, Jr., was awarded the 1996 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for their joint discovery of the carbon compounds called fullerenes.Kroto received a Ph.D. from the University of Sheffield in 1964. He joined the faculty of the University of Sussex in 1967 and became a professor of chemistry there in 1985. In the course of his research, Kroto used microwave spectroscopy to discover long, chainlike carbon molecules in the atmospheres of stars and gas clouds. Wishing to study the vaporization of carbon in order to find out how these carbon chain...
</Question>
<Choice>Kroto, Sir Harold W.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German biochemist who was awarded the 1938 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for work on carotenoids and vitamins. Forbidden by the Nazis to accept the award, he finally received his diploma and gold medal after World War II.Kuhn took his doctorate from the University of Munich in 1922 for work on enzymes under Richard Willstätter. He spent 1926–29 at the technical school in Zürich and then became professor at the University of Heidelberg and director of the Kaiser Wilhelm Institute for Medical Research (later renamed for Max Planck) at Heidelberg.Kuhn investigated the structure of compounds related t...
</Question>
<Choice>Kuhn, Richard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American chemist, a pioneer in polymer research whose work yielded Kevlar, an ultrastrong and ultrathick material best known for its use in bulletproof vests.Kwolek's father, a foundry worker, died when she was 10 years old, and her mother raised her and a brother alone. In 1946 she received a Bachelor of Science degree in chemistry from the Carnegie Institute of Technology (now Carnegie Mellon University), Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania. Intending eventually to go to medical school, she went to work as a laboratory chemist at the rayon department of the DuPont Company in Buffalo, New York. DuPont h...
</Question>
<Choice>Kwolek, Stephanie</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physical chemist who was awarded the 1932 Nobel Prize for Chemistry “for his discoveries and investigations in surface chemistry.” He was the second American and the first industrial chemist to receive this honour. Besides surface chemistry, his scientific research, spanning more than 50 years, included chemical reactions, thermal effects, and electrical discharges in gases; atomic structure; surface phenomena in a vacuum; and atmospheric science.
</Question>
<Choice>Langmuir, Irving</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American chemist who, with English physicist Sir Peter Mansfield, won the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 2003 for the development of magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), a computerized scanning technology that produces images of internal body structures, especially those comprising soft tissues.Lauterbur received a Ph.D. in chemistry from the University of Pittsburgh in 1962. He served as a professor at the University of New York at Stony Brook from 1969 to 1985, when he accepted the position of professor at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign and director of its Biomedical...
</Question>
<Choice>Lauterbur, Paul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prominent French chemist and leading figure in the 18th-century chemical revolution who developed an experimentally based theory of the chemical reactivity of oxygen and coauthored the modern system for naming chemical substances. Having also served as a leading financier and public administrator before the French Revolution, he was executed with other financiers during the revolutionary terror.
</Question>
<Choice>Lavoisier, Antoine-Laurent</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French chemist who is best known for Le Chatelier's principle, which makes it possible to predict the effect a change of conditions (such as temperature, pressure, or concentration of reaction components) will have on a chemical reaction. His principle proved invaluable in the chemical industry for developing the most-efficient chemical processes.
</Question>
<Choice>Le Chatelier, Henry-Louis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian chemist who developed a method for industrial production of synthetic rubber.Lebedev joined the faculty of St. Petersburg University in 1902 and in 1910, while researching processes by which small molecules combine to form large ones, Lebedev produced an elastic rubber from butadiene. He founded the Laboratory for Petroleum Refining in 1925 and served as director of the Laboratory of Synthetic Rubber in Leningrad (1928–30). He was made a fellow of the Soviet Academy of Sciences in 1932. During World War II his process of obtaining butadiene from ethyl alcohol was used not only by the S...
</Question>
<Choice>Lebedev, Sergey Vasilyevich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French surgeon and chemist who in 1790 developed the process for making soda ash (sodium carbonate) from common salt (sodium chloride). This process, which bears his name, became one of the most important industrial-chemical processes of the 19th century.Leblanc was the son of the director of an ironworks. He received a medical education, and about 1780 he became a private surgeon to the Duke d'Orléans. Five years earlier the Academy of Sciences had offered a prize for a process to convert salt to soda ash. Extracted at that time by crude methods from wood or seaweed ashes, soda ash was used i...
</Question>
<Choice>Leblanc, Nicolas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French engineer and chemist, inventor of illuminating gas.While employed as an engineer at Angoulême, Lebon was called to be professor of mechanics at the School of Bridges and Highways in Paris. In 1797 he began work that led to his invention of gas lighting and heating. His “thermolampe,” which he patented and exhibited in 1799, burned gas distilled from wood. Invited to aid in preparations for the coronation of Napoleon I in 1804, he was murdered by prowlers on the day of the ceremony, according to the most common account of his mysterious death.Lebon is also credited with having planned a...
</Question>
<Choice>Lebon, Philippe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French chemist who developed improved spectroscopic techniques for chemical analysis and discovered the elements gallium (1875), samarium (1880), and dysprosium (1886).In 1858 Lecoq de Boisbaudran began working in the family wine business, though he pursued scientific studies in his spare time. He took up the study of spectroscopic analysis and began a search for new elements in 1859. In 1869 Mendeleyev published his periodic table, from which he predicted the existence and properties of several unknown elements, including one he called eka-aluminum. When Lecoq de Boisbaudran discovered galliu...
</Question>
<Choice>Lecoq de Boisbaudran, Paul-Emile</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Taiwanese-American chemist who, with Dudley R. Herschbach and John C. Polanyi, received the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1986 for his role in the development of chemical-reaction dynamics.Lee was educated in Taiwan and at the University of California at Berkeley (Ph.D., 1965). He did postdoctoral work at Harvard University and Berkeley and then taught at the University of Chicago from 1968 to 1974. He became a U.S. citizen in 1974 and moved from Chicago to Berkeley, where he continued his research.As a postdoctoral researcher, Lee experimented with and further developed Herschbach's invention...
</Question>
<Choice>Lee, Yuan T.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French chemist who, together with Charles J. Pedersen and Donald J. Cram, was awarded the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1987 for his contribution to the laboratory synthesis of molecules that mimic the vital chemical functions of molecules in living organisms.Lehn earned a Ph.D. in chemistry from the University of Strasbourg in 1963, and in 1970 he became a professor of chemistry at Louis Pasteur University in Strasbourg. From 1979 he was also a professor at the Collège de France in Paris.Lehn expanded on Pedersen's achievement in creating crown ethers, a class of two-dimensional, ring-shaped o...
</Question>
<Choice>Lehn, Jean-Marie</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Argentine biochemist who won the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1970 for his investigations of the processes by which carbohydrates are converted into energy in the body.After serving as an assistant at the Institute of Physiology, University of Buenos Aires, from 1934 to 1935, Leloir worked a year at the biochemical laboratory at the University of Cambridge and in 1937 returned to the Institute of Physiology, where he undertook investigations of the oxidation of fatty acids. In 1947 he obtained financial support to set up the Institute for Biochemical Research, Buenos Aires, where he began rese...
</Question>
<Choice>Leloir, Luis Federico</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish physicist and mathematician who first created artificial ice.In 1802 Leslie's explanation of capillary action was the first that is consistent with present-day theory. Two years later he published An Experimental Inquiry into the Nature and Propagation of Heat. In 1810 he froze water by using an air pump. Elected to the chair of mathematics at the University of Edinburgh in 1805, he was transferred to the chair of natural philosophy in 1819 and was knighted in 1832.
</Question>
<Choice>Leslie, Sir John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian-born American chemist and pioneer in the study of nucleic acids.On receiving his M.D. degree from the St. Petersburg Imperial Medical Academy in 1891, Levene fled from Russian anti-Semitism and settled in New York City. While practicing medicine there, he studied chemistry at Columbia University and ultimately decided to devote his life to chemical research. From 1905 to 1939 he worked at the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research.Although Levene's studies encompassed nearly every major class of organic compounds, his most valuable work was on the nucleic acids. He isolated the nuc...
</Question>
<Choice>Levene, Phoebus Aaron Theodor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physical chemist best known for his contributions to chemical thermodynamics, the electron-pair model of the covalent bond, the electronic theory of acids and bases, the separation and study of deuterium and its compounds, and his work on phosphorescence and the triplet state (in which the quantum number for total spin angular momentum is 1).
</Question>
<Choice>Lewis, G. N.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(Latin),German chemist, physician, and alchemist who made important chemical discoveries but is most noted as the author of the first modern chemistry textbook.Libavius was professor of history and poetry at the University of Jena from 1586 to 1591 and then became town physician and inspector of the Gymnasium at Rothenburg. In 1605 he established the Gymnasium Casimirianum at Coburg.Of his numerous works, all of which were noted for clear, unambiguous writing, the most important was Alchymia (1606; “Alchemy”), a work that established the tradition for 17th-century French chemistry textbooks. A...
</Question>
<Choice>Libavius, Andreas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American chemist whose technique of carbon-14 (or radiocarbon) dating provided an extremely valuable tool for archaeologists, anthropologists, and earth scientists. For this development he was honoured with the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1960.Libby, the son of farmer Ora Edward Libby and his wife, Eva May (née Rivers), attended the University of California at Berkeley, where he received a bachelor's degree (1931) and a doctorate (1933). After graduation, he joined the faculty at Berkeley, where he rose through the ranks from instructor (1933) to assistant professor (1938) to associate profes...
</Question>
<Choice>Libby, Willard Frank</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German chemist who made significant contributions to the analysis of organic compounds, the organization of laboratory-based chemistry education, and the application of chemistry to biology (biochemistry) and agriculture.
</Question>
<Choice>Liebig, Justus, Freiherr von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physical chemist who won the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1976 for his research on the structure and bonding of boron compounds and the general nature of chemical bonding.Lipscomb graduated from the University of Kentucky in 1941 and earned his Ph.D. in 1946 from the California Institute of Technology. He worked as a physical chemist in the Office of Science Research and Development from 1942 to 1946 and then joined the University of Minnesota as assistant professor. By 1959, when he left the university, he was professor and chief of the physical chemistry division. He then became pro...
</Question>
<Choice>Lipscomb, William Nunn, Jr.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian poet, scientist, and grammarian who is often considered the first great Russian linguistic reformer. He also made substantial contributions to the natural sciences, reorganized the St. Petersburg Imperial Academy of Sciences, established in Moscow the university that today bears his name, and created the first coloured glass mosaics in Russia.Lomonosov was the son of a poor fisherman. At the age of 10 he too took up that line of work. When the few books he was able to obtain could no longer satisfy his growing thirst for knowledge, in December 1730, he left his native village, penniles...
</Question>
<Choice>Lomonosov, Mikhail Vasilyevich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German chemist who made advances in the study of aromatic hydrocarbons.The son of poor peasants, Loschmidt gained an education through the help of his village priest, and by 1839 he was a student at the German University in Prague. Moving to Vienna in 1841, he completed his university studies in 1843 but was unable to obtain a teaching post. His attempts to succeed in business ended in bankruptcy in 1854, and he decided to return to his studies in the natural sciences. In 1856 Loschmidt qualified as a teacher and obtained a post at the Vienna Realschule. He turned to research in chemistry and...
</Question>
<Choice>Loschmidt, Joseph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
New Zealand-born American chemist who, with Alan J. Heeger and Shirakawa Hideki, was awarded the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 2000 for their discovery that certain plastics can be chemically modified to conduct electricity almost as readily as metals.MacDiarmid earned Ph.D.'s in chemistry at the University of Wisconsin at Madison (1953) and the University of Cambridge (1955). He then joined the faculty of the University of Pennsylvania, becoming full professor in 1964 and Blanchard Professor of Chemistry in 1988.During a visit to Japan in the mid-1970s, MacDiarmid met Shirakawa, who reported t...
</Question>
<Choice>MacDiarmid, Alan G.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish chemist, best known for his invention in 1823 of a method for making waterproof garments by using rubber dissolved in coal-tar naphtha for cementing two pieces of cloth together. The mackintosh garment was named for him.In 1823, while trying to find uses for the waste products of gasworks, Macintosh noted that coal-tar naphtha dissolved india rubber. He then took wool cloth, painted one side of it with the rubber preparation, and placed another thickness of wool cloth on top, thereby producing a waterproof fabric. Soon after he began the manufacture of coats and other garments. But pr...
</Question>
<Choice>Macintosh, Charles</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American doctor, corecipient of the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 2003 for his pioneering research on ion channels in cell membranes. He shared the award with Peter Agre, also of the United States.MacKinnon earned an M.D. degree from Tufts University School of Medicine in 1982. After practicing medicine for several years, he turned to basic research, beginning in 1986 with postdoctoral work on ion channels at Brandeis University. In 1989 he joined Harvard University, and in 1996 he moved to Rockefeller University as a professor and laboratory head. A year later he was appointed an investigator...
</Question>
<Choice>MacKinnon, Roderick</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Canadian-born American chemist, winner of the 1992 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for his work on the theory of electron-transfer reactions in chemical systems. The Marcus theory shed light on diverse and fundamental phenomena such as photosynthesis, cell metabolism, and simple corrosion.Marcus received his doctorate from McGill University, Montreal, in 1946. From 1951 he worked at the Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn. In 1964 he joined the faculty of the University of Illinois, leaving in 1978 for the California Institute of Technology.Marcus began studying electron-transfer reactions in the 1950...
</Question>
<Choice>Marcus, Rudolph A.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German chemist whose discovery of beet sugar in 1747 led to the development of the modern sugar industry.Marggraf served as assistant (1735–38) to his father, the court apothecary at Berlin, and as director of the chemical laboratory of the German Academy of Sciences of Berlin (1754–60). He distinguished between the oxides of aluminum (alumina) and calcium (lime) found in common clay, and he simplified the process for obtaining phosphorus from urine. Although Marggraf noted the weight increase upon the oxidation of phosphorus to form phosphates, he remained the last eminent German adherent of...
</Question>
<Choice>Marggraf, Andreas Sigismund</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss chemist whose work with atomic weights suggested the possibility of isotopes and the packing fraction of nuclei and whose study of the rare-earth elements led to his discovery of ytterbium in 1878 and codiscovery of gadolinium in 1880.After studying at the Paris Polytechnic School and School of Mines, he worked for a year with Justus von Liebig at Giessen, in Germany. He became professor of chemistry (1841) and of mineralogy (1845) at Geneva, posts he held until his retirement (1878) from the university. In establishing the formula of silica as SiO2, he made a substantial contribution to...
</Question>
<Choice>Marignac, Jean-Charles-Galinard de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British biochemist who was awarded (with R.L.M. Synge) the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1952 for development of paper partition chromatography, a quick and economical analytical technique permitting extensive advances in chemical, medical, and biological research.Martin obtained a Ph.D. from the University of Cambridge in 1936 and worked as a research chemist for the Wool Industries Research Association in Leeds from 1938 to 1946. He then became head of biochemical research at the Boots Pure Drug Company, Nottingham, and held the post until 1948, when he was appointed to the staff of the Briti...
</Question>
<Choice>Martin, A. J. P.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English chemist and physiologist who, about a hundred years before Joseph Priestley and Antoine-Laurent Lavoisier, identified spiritus nitroaereus (oxygen) as a distinct atmospheric entity.Though a doctor of law from the University of Oxford (1670), Mayow made medicine his profession. His writings include a remarkably correct anatomical description of respiration and a recognition of the role of oxygen in the combustion of metals.
</Question>
<Choice>Mayow, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American nuclear physicist who shared the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1951 with Glenn T. Seaborg for his discovery of element 93, neptunium, the first element heavier than uranium, thus called a transuranium element.McMillan was educated at the California Institute of Technology and at Princeton University, where he earned a Ph.D. in 1932. He then joined the faculty of the University of California, Berkeley, and became a full professor in 1946 and director of the Lawrence Radiation Laboratory in 1958. He retired in 1973.While studying nuclear fission, McMillan discovered neptunium, a decay pr...
</Question>
<Choice>McMillan, Edwin Mattison</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian chemist who developed the periodic classification of the elements. Mendeleyev found that, when all the known chemical elements were arranged in order of increasing atomic weight, the resulting table displayed a recurring pattern, or periodicity, of properties within groups of elements. In his version of the periodic table of 1871, he left gaps in places where he believed unknown elements would find their place. He even predicted the likely properties of three of the potential elements. The subsequent proof of many of his predictions within his lifetime brought fame to Mendeleyev as the...
</Question>
<Choice>Mendeleyev, Dmitry Ivanovich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biochemist and educator, who in 1984 received the Nobel Prize for Chemistry for his development of a simple and ingenious method for synthesizing chains of amino acids, or polypeptides, in any predetermined order.Merrifield graduated from the University of California at Los Angeles (UCLA) in 1943 and earned a Ph.D. in biochemistry there in 1949. That same year he joined the staff of the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (now Rockefeller University), New York City, where he became professor emeritus in 1992.Merrifield's innovative method, developed during the 1950s and '60s, g...
</Question>
<Choice>Merrifield, Bruce</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German chemist who, independently of Dmitry Mendeleyev, developed a periodic classification of the chemical elements. Though originally educated as a physician, he was chiefly interested in chemistry and physics.In 1859 Meyer began his career as a science educator, holding various appointments before serving as professor of chemistry at the University of Tübingen (1876–95). His book Die modernen Theorien der Chemie (1864; “Modern Chemical Theory”), a lucid treatise on the fundamental principles of chemical science, contained a preliminary scheme for the arrangement of elements by atomic weight...
</Question>
<Choice>Meyer, Julius Lothar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German chemist who contributed greatly to knowledge of both organic and inorganic chemistry.Meyer studied under the analytic chemist Robert Bunsen, the organic chemist Emil Erlenmeyer, and the physicist Gustav Kirchhoff at the University of Heidelberg, where he received his Ph.D. in 1867 and where he later succeeded Bunsen (1889–97). Meyer earlier had served as professor of chemistry at the Zürich Polytechnic Institute (1872–85) and the University of Göttingen (1885–89).Devising a method of determining the vapour densities of inorganic substances at high temperatures (1871), Meyer found that d...
</Question>
<Choice>Meyer, Viktor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polish-born French chemist and philosopher of science whose concepts of rational understanding based on realism and causalism were popular among scientific theorists in the 1930s.Educated in classical science and chemistry under Robert Wilhelm Bunsen in Germany, Meyerson emigrated to Paris (1882), where he became an industrial chemist, foreign editor for the Havas news agency, and, later, director of the Jewish Colonization Association for Europe and Asia Minor. Although he had no formal university connection, his erudite works—especially Identité et réalité (1908; Identity and Reality), De l'...
</Question>
<Choice>Meyerson, Emile</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German biochemist who, along with Johann Deisenhofer and Robert Huber, received the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1988 for their determination of the structure of certain proteins that are essential for photosynthesis.Michel earned his doctorate from the University of Würzburg in 1977. In 1979 he joined the staff of the Max Planck Institute for Biochemistry in Martinsried, W.Ger., where he conducted his award-winning research. He became head of the Max Planck Institute for Biophysics in Frankfurt am Main in 1987.It was Michel's preliminary work, done in the period from 1978 to 1982, that cleare...
</Question>
<Choice>Michel, Hartmut</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American engineer and chemist who discovered the effectiveness of tetraethyl lead as an antiknock additive for gasoline.The son of an immigrant inventor from London, Midgley grew up in Pennsylvania and Ohio and graduated from Cornell University (1911). He held various jobs before joining the research staff of the Dayton (Ohio) Engineering Laboratories Company (Delco) in 1916. He served as vice president of the Ethyl Gasoline Corporation from 1923, vice president of Kinetic Chemicals, Inc., from 1930, and director of the Ethyl-Dow Chemical Company from 1933. From 1940 to 1944 he was a director...
</Question>
<Choice>Midgley, Thomas, Jr.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British chemist who won the 1978 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for helping to clarify how ADP (adenosine diphosphate) is converted into the energy-carrying compound ATP (adenosine triphosphate) in the mitochondria of living cells.Mitchell received his Ph.D. from the University of Cambridge in 1950. He served as director of the chemistry and biology unit in the department of zoology of the University of Edinburgh from 1955 to 1963. In 1964 he joined the Glynn Research Laboratories as director of research.Mitchell studied the mitochondrion, the organelle that produces energy for the cell. ATP is mad...
</Question>
<Choice>Mitchell, Peter Dennis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German chemist who promulgated the theory of isomorphism, a relationship between crystalline structure and chemical composition.From 1818 to 1820 Mitscherlich worked in the Berlin laboratory of the German botanist Heinrich F. Link, where he first undertook the study of arsenates and phosphates. In 1819 he discovered from this study that compounds with similar composition often have the same crystalline structure. In 1821 he became professor of chemistry at the University of Berlin. He continued his studies of isomorphism and also made other important discoveries, including selenic acid (1827)...
</Question>
<Choice>Mitscherlich, Eilhardt</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French chemist who received the 1906 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for the isolation of the element fluorine and the development of the Moissan electric furnace.After attending the Museum of Natural History and the School of Pharmacy in Paris, Moissan became professor of toxicology (1886) and of inorganic chemistry (1889) at the School of Pharmacy and professor of inorganic chemistry (1900) at the Sorbonne. He took up the study of fluorine compounds in 1884. Two years later, by electrolyzing a solution of potassium fluoride in hydrofluoric acid, he prepared the highly reactive gas fluorine. He mad...
</Question>
<Choice>Moissan, Henri</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mexican-born American chemist who was jointly awarded the 1995 Nobel Prize for Chemistry, along with chemists F. Sherwood Rowland and Paul Crutzen, for research in the 1970s concerning the decomposition of the ozonosphere, which shields the Earth from dangerous solar radiation. The discoveries of Molina and Rowland—that some industrially manufactured gases deplete the ozone layer—led to an international movement in the late 20th century to limit the widespread use of chlorofluorocarbon (CFC) gases.Molina studied chemical engineering at the National Autonomous University of Mexico (B.S., 1965)...
</Question>
<Choice>Molina, Mario</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-born British chemist and industrialist who improved the Solvay alkali process and devised a process for the extraction of nickel.The son of a wealthy Jewish family, Mond studied chemistry at Marburg and Heidelberg, entered the chemical industry, and went to England in 1862. There his method for recovering sulfur from the by-products of the Leblanc alkali process was a commercial success. In 1873 he and John Tomlinson Brunner founded the important chemical-manufacturing firm of Brunner, Mond and Company. They began on a large scale to make soda ash (sodium carbonate) by the newly develop...
</Question>
<Choice>Mond, Ludwig</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biochemist, who, with Christian B. Anfinsen and William H. Stein, received the 1972 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for their research on the molecular structures of proteins.Moore received his Ph.D. degree from the University of Wisconsin in 1938 and joined the staff of the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (now Rockefeller University) in New York City in 1939, attaining the rank of professor in 1952.Working together at the Rockefeller Institute, Moore and Stein pioneered new methods of chromatography for use in analyzing amino acids and small peptides obtained by the hydrolysis o...
</Question>
<Choice>Moore, Stanford</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American chemist who is best known for his collaboration with the physicist A.A. Michelson in an attempt to measure the relative motion of the Earth through a hypothetical ether.Morley graduated from Williams College in 1860 and then pursued both scientific and theological studies. He took up a Congregational pastorate in Ohio in 1868 and in the following year joined the faculty of Western Reserve College, remaining with the school when it moved to Cleveland in 1882 and became Western Reserve University. He continued to teach there until his retirement in 1906. From 1873 to 1888 he also taught...
</Question>
<Choice>Morley, Edward Williams</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish chemist whose work revealed the existence of numerous rare-earth elements with closely similar chemical properties.In 1826 Mosander was placed in charge of the chemical laboratory of the Caroline Medical Institute, Stockholm, and in 1832 became professor of chemistry and mineralogy. While studying a compound of cerium, he discovered the element lanthanum in 1839. He pursued his investigations of the rare earths and in 1843 reported discovery of the elements erbium, terbium, and didymium. In 1885 the Austrian chemist Baron Carl Auer von Welsbach found that didymium was in reality a mixt...
</Question>
<Choice>Mosander, Carl Gustaf</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss chemist who received the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1948 for discovering the potent toxic effects on insects of DDT. With its chemical derivatives, DDT became the most widely used insecticide for more than 20 years and was a major factor in increased world food production and the suppression of insect-borne diseases.A research chemist at the J.R. Geigy Company, Basel (1925–65), Müller began his career with investigations of dyes and tanning agents. In 1935 he began his search for an “ideal” insecticide, one that would show rapid, potent toxicity for the greatest number of...
</Question>
<Choice>Muller, Paul Hermann</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American chemist and physicist who received the 1966 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for “fundamental work concerning chemical bonds and the electronic structure of molecules.”A graduate of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Mulliken worked, during World War I and for a few years afterward, in government chemical research. He then studied under the physicist Robert A. Millikan at the University of Chicago, receiving his Ph.D. in 1921. He taught at New York University (1926–28) and then joined the faculty of the University of Chicago (1928–85).Mulliken began working on his theory of molecular...
</Question>
<Choice>Mulliken, Robert Sanderson</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biochemist, cowinner of the 1993 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for his invention of the polymerase chain reaction (PCR), a simple technique that allows a specific stretch of DNA to be copied billions of times in a few hours.After receiving a doctorate in biochemistry from the University of California, Berkeley, in 1973, Mullis held research posts at various universities. In 1979 he joined Cetus Corp., a California biotechnology firm, where he carried out his prizewinning research. From 1986 to 1988 he was director of molecular biology for Xytronyx, Inc., in San Diego, Calif.; thereafter h...
</Question>
<Choice>Mullis, Kary B.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian chemist who contributed to the development of high polymers useful in the manufacture of films, plastics, fibres, and synthetic rubber. Along with Karl Ziegler of Germany, he was honoured in 1963 with the Nobel Prize for Chemistry for the development of Ziegler-Natta catalysts.Natta took his doctorate in chemical engineering at Milan Polytechnic (1924) and held chairs in chemistry at the universities of Pavia, Rome, and Turin before returning to the Polytechnic as professor and research director of industrial chemistry (1938). His earlier work formed the basis of modern industrial synt...
</Question>
<Choice>Natta, Giulio</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American chemist whose studies demonstrated that carbon can have a valence (i.e., affinity for electrons) of two as well as a valence of four, thus greatly advancing the understanding of theoretical organic chemistry.Brought to the United States by his father, Nef studied at Harvard University (A.B., 1884) and at the University of Munich (Ph.D., 1886), where he was a student of Alfred von Baeyer. After working a year in Baeyer's laboratory, Nef taught at Purdue University from 1887 to 1889 and at Clark University from 1889 to 1892, when he resigned to become professor of chemistry at the Unive...
</Question>
<Choice>Nef, John Ulric</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German scientist who was one of the founders of modern physical chemistry. His theoretical and experimental work in chemistry, including his formulation of the heat theorem, known as the third law of thermodynamics, gained him the 1920 Nobel Prize for Chemistry.
</Question>
<Choice>Nernst, Walther Hermann</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British chemist whose “law of octaves” noted a pattern in the atomic structure of elements with similar chemical properties and contributed in a significant way to the development of the periodic law.Newlands studied at the Royal College of Chemistry, London, fought as a volunteer under Giuseppe Garibaldi for Italian unification (1860), and later worked as an industrial chemist. In 1864 he published his concept of the periodicity of the chemical elements, which he had arranged in order of atomic weight. He pointed out that every eighth element in this grouping shared a resemblance and suggeste...
</Question>
<Choice>Newlands, John Alexander Reina</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English chemist, discoverer of the electrolysis of water, which has become a basic process in both chemical research and industry.Nicholson was at various times a hydraulic engineer, inventor, translator, and scientific publicist. He invented a hydrometer (an instrument for measuring the density of liquids) in 1790. In 1800, after he heard of the invention of the electric battery by the Italian physicist Alessandro Volta, he built one of his own. He then discovered that when leads from the battery are placed in water, the water breaks up into hydrogen and oxygen, which collect separately to fo...
</Question>
<Choice>Nicholson, William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Belgian-born American chemist whose studies of acetylene culminated in the discovery of lewisite, a chemical-warfare agent, and neoprene, the first commercially successful synthetic rubber.Nieuwland, emigrating with his parents to the United States in 1880, graduated in 1899 from the University of Notre Dame, Ind. Ordained a Roman Catholic priest in 1903, he studied botany and chemistry at the Catholic University of America, Washington, D.C., receiving a Ph.D. in 1904. Returning to Notre Dame, he was professor of botany from 1904 to 1918 and professor of organic chemistry from 1918 to 1936. Hi...
</Question>
<Choice>Nieuwland, Julius Arthur</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish chemist, engineer, and industrialist, who invented dynamite and other, more powerful explosives and who also founded the Nobel Prizes.Alfred Bernhard Nobel was the fourth son of Immanuel and Caroline Nobel. Immanuel was an inventor and engineer who had married Caroline Andrietta Ahlsell in 1827. The couple had eight children, of whom only Alfred and three brothers reached adulthood. Alfred was prone to illness as a child, but he enjoyed a close relationship with his mother and displayed a lively intellectual curiosity from an early age. He was interested in explosives, and he learned t...
</Question>
<Choice>Nobel, Alfred Bernhard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British chemist who was the corecipient, with fellow Englishman Sir George Porter and Manfred Eigen of West Germany, of the 1967 Nobel Prize for Chemistry. All three were honoured for their studies of very fast chemical reactions.Norrish did his undergraduate and doctoral work at the University of Cambridge, served as research fellow at Emmanuel College, Cambridge, and directed the university's physical chemistry department for 28 years. Norrish and Porter, who worked together between 1949 and 1965, used the new technique of flash photolysis to study the intermediate stages involved in extreme...
</Question>
<Choice>Norrish, Ronald George Wreyford</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biochemist who received (with James B. Sumner and Wendell M. Stanley) the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1946 for successfully purifying and crystallizing certain enzymes, thus enabling him to determine their chemical nature.Northrop was educated at Columbia University, where he received his doctorate in chemistry in 1915. In World War I he was a captain in the U.S. Army Chemical Warfare Service.During World War I Northrop conducted research on fermentation processes suitable for the industrial production of acetone and ethyl alcohol. This work led to a study of enzymes essential for di...
</Question>
<Choice>Northrop, John Howard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese chemist who, with K. Barry Sharpless and William S. Knowles, won the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 2001 for developing the first chiral catalysts.Noyori earned a Ph.D. from Kyoto University in 1967 and the following year joined the faculty at Nagoya University. In 2000 he assumed the directorship of the university's Research Center for Materials Science.Many molecules are chiral—they exist in two structural forms (enantiomers) that are nonsuperimposable mirror images. Likewise, the receptors, enzymes, and other cellular components made from these molecules are chiral and tend to intera...
</Question>
<Choice>Noyori Ryoji</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hungarian-American chemist who won the 1994 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for work conducted in the early 1960s that isolated the positively charged, electron-deficient fragments of hydrocarbons known as carbocations (or carbonium ions).In 1949 Olah received a doctorate from the Technical University of Budapest, where he taught until 1954. He worked at the Hungarian Academy of Sciences for two years before emigrating from Hungary during the revolution of 1956. He became a research scientist at the Dow Chemical Company in Canada (1957–64) and in Framingham, Mass., U.S. (1964–65). He was a professor...
</Question>
<Choice>Olah, George A.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Norwegian-born American chemist whose development of a general theory of irreversible chemical processes gained him the 1968 Nobel Prize for Chemistry.His early work in statistical mechanics attracted the attention of the Dutch chemist Peter Debye, under whose direction Onsager studied at the Federal Institute of Technology, Zürich (1926–28). He then went to the United States and taught at Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, and Brown University, Providence, R.I. He received his Ph.D. from Yale University in 1935. He had joined the faculty of Yale in 1933 and became professor of theoretical c...
</Question>
<Choice>Onsager, Lars</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Danish physicist and chemist who discovered that electric current in a wire can deflect a magnetized compass needle, a phenomenon the importance of which was rapidly recognized and which inspired the development of electromagnetic theory.In 1806 Ørsted became a professor at the University of Copenhagen, where his first physical researches dealt with electric currents and acoustics. During an evening lecture in April 1820, Ørsted discovered that a magnetic needle aligns itself perpendicularly to a current-carrying wire, definite experimental evidence of the relationship between electricity and...
</Question>
<Choice>Orsted, Hans Christian</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian-German chemist and philosopher who was instrumental in establishing physical chemistry as an acknowledged branch of chemistry. He was awarded the 1909 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for his work on catalysis, chemical equilibria, and chemical reaction velocities.
</Question>
<Choice>Ostwald, Wilhelm</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German chemist who devoted his life as a teacher, researcher, and editor to the advancement of colloid chemistry.Ostwald, the second son of Wilhelm Ostwald, spent most of his career at the University of Leipzig, beginning as a zoology student before turning to chemistry; he became a full professor there in 1935. As the editor (from 1909) of Kolloidchemische Beihefte and other journals and as the founder (1922) and president of the Kolloid Gesellschaft, Ostwald exerted international influence in fostering and forwarding research in colloids. His own work included discoveries of electrical and o...
</Question>
<Choice>Ostwald, Wolfgang</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian chemist who with George Charles de Hevesy introduced radioactive tracer techniques (1912–13).Paneth, the son of noted physiologist Joseph Paneth, studied at Munich, Glasgow, and Vienna, then held positions at the Radium Institute, Vienna, and at research facilities in Prague, Hamburg, Berlin, and Königsberg. Upon the rise of the Nazi movement, he went to England and took a position as guest lecturer at the Imperial College of Science and Technology, London (1933–38), and then became professor of chemistry at the University of Durham (1939). In 1953 he returned to West Germany as direc...
</Question>
<Choice>Paneth, Friedrich Adolf</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British chemist and inventor noted for his development of various industrial processes and materials.Much of Parkes's work was related to metallurgy. He was one of the first to propose introducing small amounts of phosphorus into metal alloys to enhance their strength. One of his most significant inventions was a method of extracting silver from lead ore. This procedure, commonly called the Parkes process (patented in 1850), involves adding zinc to lead and melting the two together. When stirred, the molten zinc reacts and forms compounds with any silver and gold present in the lead. These zin...
</Question>
<Choice>Parkes, Alexander</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French chemist and microbiologist who was one of the most important founders of medical microbiology. Pasteur's contributions to science, technology, and medicine are nearly without precedent. He pioneered the study of molecular asymmetry; discovered that microorganisms cause fermentation and disease; originated the process of pasteurization; saved the beer, wine, and silk industries in France; and developed vaccines against anthrax and rabies.Pasteur's academic positions were numerous, and his scientific accomplishments earned him France's highest decoration, the Legion of Honour, as well as...
</Question>
<Choice>Pasteur, Louis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American theoretical physical chemist who became the only person to have won two unshared Nobel Prizes. His first prize (1954) was awarded for research into the nature of the chemical bond and its use in elucidating molecular structure; the second (1962) recognized his efforts to ban the testing of nuclear weapons.
</Question>
<Choice>Pauling, Linus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French chemist who made important contributions to industrial chemistry and discovered cellulose, a basic constituent of plant cells.Payen, the son of an industrialist, was put in charge of a borax-refining plant in 1815. He broke the Dutch monopoly on borax—most of which was mined in the Dutch East Indies—by discovering a process for producing borax from boric acid. In 1820 he turned his efforts to refining beet sugar. Two years later he introduced the use of activated charcoal to remove coloured impurities from beet sugar. In 1833 he discovered and isolated diastase, the first enzyme (organi...
</Question>
<Choice>Payen, Anselme</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American chemist who, along with Jean-Marie Lehn and Donald J. Cram, was awarded the 1987 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for his synthesis of the crown ethers—a group of organic compounds that would selectively react with other atoms and molecules much as do the molecules in living organisms.Born to a Norwegian father and a Korean mother, Pedersen went in the early 1920s to the United States to study chemical engineering at the University of Dayton in Ohio, where he took his bachelor's degree. He received a master's degree in organic chemistry at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology and in 192...
</Question>
<Choice>Pedersen, Charles J.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French chemist who helped found the chemistry of alkaloids.Pelletier was professor at and, from 1832, director of the School of Pharmacy, Paris. In 1817, in collaboration with the chemist Joseph-Bienaimé Caventou, he isolated chlorophyll, the green pigment in plants that is essential to the process of photosynthesis. His interests soon turned to a new class of vegetable bases now called alkaloids, and he isolated emetine. With Caventou he continued his search for alkaloids, and in 1820 they discovered brucine, cinchonine, colchicine, quinine, strychnine, and veratrine. Some of these compounds...
</Question>
<Choice>Pelletier, Pierre-Joseph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British chemist who discovered aniline dyes.In 1853 Perkin entered the Royal College of Chemistry, London, where he studied under August Wilhelm von Hofmann. While Perkin was working as Hofmann's laboratory assistant, he undertook the synthesis of quinine. He obtained instead a bluish substance with excellent dyeing properties that later became known as aniline purple, Tyrian purple, or mauve. In 1856 he obtained a patent for manufacturing the dye, and the next year, with the aid of his father and his brother Thomas, he set up an aniline manufacturing plant near Harrow.In 1858 he and B.F. Dupp...
</Question>
<Choice>Perkin, Sir William Henry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian-born British biochemist, corecipient of the 1962 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for his X-ray diffraction analysis of the structure of hemoglobin, the protein that transports oxygen from the lungs to the tissues via blood cells. He shared the award with British biochemist John C. Kendrew.Perutz was educated at the University of Vienna and at the University of Cambridge, where he received a Ph.D. in 1940. While at Cambridge he began research at the Cavendish Laboratory (1937), taking the first X-ray diffraction pictures of hemoglobin crystals and working with the most powerful tool for exam...
</Question>
<Choice>Perutz, Max Ferdinand</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
chemist and educator who, with Dudley R. Herschbach and Yuan T. Lee, received the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1986 for his contribution to the field of chemical-reaction dynamics.Born to an expatriate Hungarian family, Polanyi was reared in England and attended Manchester University (Ph.D., 1952; D.Sc., 1964). He accepted a research position with the National Research Council of Canada in 1952 and began teaching at the University of Toronto in 1956, accepting the title of university professor in 1974.Polanyi developed a technique that is known as infrared chemiluminescence based on the observ...
</Question>
<Choice>Polanyi, John C.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British mathematician and chemist who, with Walter Kohn, received the 1998 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for work on computational methodology in quantum chemistry. Pople's share of the prize recognized his development of computer-based methods of studying the quantum mechanics of molecules.Pople was educated at the University of Cambridge and received a Ph.D. in mathematics from that institution in 1951. He was a fellow at Trinity College, Cambridge, from 1951 to 1958 and a lecturer in mathematics there from 1954 to 1958. He then headed the Basic Physics Division of the National Physical Laborato...
</Question>
<Choice>Pople, Sir John A.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English chemist, corecipient with fellow Englishman Ronald George Wreyford Norrish and Manfred Eigen of West Germany of the 1967 Nobel Prize for Chemistry. All three were honoured for their studies in flash photolysis, a technique for observing the intermediate stages of very fast chemical reactions.After undergraduate work at the University of Leeds, Porter earned a doctorate at the University of Cambridge under Norrish in 1949. He continued on there, developing the technique of flash photolysis with Norrish. In this technique, a gas or liquid in equilibrium is illuminated with an ultrashort...
</Question>
<Choice>Porter, Sir George, Baron Porter of Luddenham</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian chemist awarded the 1923 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for developing techniques in the microanalysis of organic compounds.Pregl received a medical degree from the University of Graz (1894), where he was associated for most of his professional life with the Medico-Chemical Institute. About 1905 he began researches on bile acids and other substances. The difficulty of obtaining these materials in quantities sufficient for the use of conventional analytic techniques impelled him to devise new analytic methods. By 1912 he was able to make reliable measurements of carbon, hydrogen, nitrogen,...
</Question>
<Choice>Pregl, Fritz</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss chemist who shared the 1975 Nobel Prize for Chemistry with John W. Cornforth for his work on the stereochemistry of organic molecules and reactions. (Stereochemistry is the study of the three-dimensional arrangements of atoms within molecules.)Prelog was born of Croatian parents in Sarajevo. He was educated at the Institute Technical School of Chemistry in Prague, receiving his doctorate in 1929. After several years in a commercial laboratory, he began teaching at the University of Zagreb in 1935, first as a lecturer and later as professor of organic chemistry. In 1942 he joined the facu...
</Question>
<Choice>Prelog, Vladimir</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English clergyman, political theorist, and physical scientist whose work contributed to advances in liberal political and religious thought and in experimental chemistry. He is best remembered for his contribution to the chemistry of gases.
</Question>
<Choice>Priestley, Joseph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian-born Belgian physical chemist who received the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1977 for contributions to nonequilibrium thermodynamics.Prigogine was taken to Belgium as a child. He received a doctorate in 1941 at the Free University in Brussels, where he accepted the position of professor in 1947. In 1962 he became director of the International Institute of Physics and Chemistry in Solvay, Belg. He also served as director of the Center for Statistical Mechanics and Thermodynamics at the University of Texas in Austin from 1967 until his death.Prigogine's work dealt with the application of...
</Question>
<Choice>Prigogine, Ilya</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French chemist who proved that the relative quantities of any given pure chemical compound's constituent elements remain invariant, regardless of the compound's source. This is known as Proust's law, or the law of definite proportions (1793), and it is the fundamental principle of analytical chemistry. Proust also carried out important applied research in metallurgy, explosives, and nutritional chemistry.
</Question>
<Choice>Proust, Joseph-Louis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English chemist and biochemist noted for his discoveries concerning digestion, metabolic chemistry, and atomic weights.The son of a tenant farmer, Prout graduated from the University of Edinburgh in 1811 with a medical degree. Thereafter he practiced as a successful physician, specializing in the treatment of urinary and digestive ailments. Prout's other career, as an experimentalist and theorist, was many-sided. Between 1815 and 1827 he published a number of papers that helped establish the barely explored areas of metabolic and physiological chemistry. He discovered that the gastric juices o...
</Question>
<Choice>Prout, William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physical chemist who discovered four gases (neon, argon, krypton, xenon) and showed that they (with helium and radon) formed an entire family of new elements, the noble gases. He was awarded the 1904 Nobel Prize for Chemistry in recognition of this achievement.
</Question>
<Choice>Ramsay, Sir William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French chemist who formulated a law on solutions (called Raoult's law) that made it possible to determine the molecular weights of dissolved substances.Raoult taught at the University of Grenoble from 1867 and was professor there from 1870 until his death. About 1886 he discovered that the freezing point of an aqueous solution is lowered in proportion to the amount of a nonelectrolytic substance dissolved.This observation led to the expression of Raoult's law, which states that the changes in certain related properties of a liquid (e.g., vapour pressure, boiling point, or freezing point) that...
</Question>
<Choice>Raoult, Francois-Marie</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French chemist and physicist noted for his work on the properties of gases.After studying with Justus von Liebig, in Giessen, Regnault became professor of chemistry successively at the University of Lyon, the École Polytechnique (1840), and the Collège de France (1841). His four-volume work on chemistry appeared in 1847. While director of the porcelain factory at Sèvres (from 1854), he continued his work in science. During the Franco-German War (1870–71) his laboratory there was destroyed, and his son Henri, the painter, was killed.Regnault designed apparatus for a large number of physical mea...
</Question>
<Choice>Regnault, Henri-Victor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American chemist and university president, codiscoverer of saccharin.After studying at Columbia University (M.D., 1867) and at the universities of Munich and Göttingen in Germany (Ph.D., 1870), Remsen began his investigations into pure chemistry at the University of Tübingen, where he was assistant (1870–72) to Rudolf Fittig. Returning to the United States, he became one of the original faculty of Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, where he was professor of chemistry (1876–1913), director of the chemical laboratory (1876–1908), secretary of the Academic Council (1887–1901), and president of...
</Question>
<Choice>Remsen, Ira</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American chemist and founder of the home economics movement in the United States.Ellen Swallow was educated mainly at home. She briefly attended Westford Academy and also taught school for a time. Swallow was trained as a chemist, earning an A.B. from Vassar College in 1870 and, as the first woman admitted to the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT), a B.S. in 1873. Vassar accepted her master's thesis the same year. She remained at MIT for two more years of graduate studies, but she was not awarded a Ph.D. In 1875 she married Robert Hallowell Richards, an expert in mining and metallurgy...
</Question>
<Choice>Richards, Ellen Swallow</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American chemist whose accurate determination of the atomic weights of approximately 25 elements indicated the existence of isotopes and earned him the 1914 Nobel Prize for Chemistry.Richards graduated from Haverford College, Pa., in 1885 and took advanced degrees at Harvard University, where he became instructor in chemistry in 1891 and full professor in 1901.Richards greatly improved the technique of gravimetric atomic weight determinations, introducing quartz apparatus, the bottling device, and the nephelometer (an instrument for measuring turbidity). Although the atomic weight values of Je...
</Question>
<Choice>Richards, Theodore William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British chemist, recipient of the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1947 for his research on a wide range of organic compounds, notably alkaloids.After obtaining his doctorate from Victoria University of Manchester in 1910, Robinson taught at various British universities before being appointed to the Waynflete chair of chemistry at the University of Oxford in 1930, from which he retired in 1955. He was knighted in 1939.Robinson conducted research on the structure and synthesis of many different organic compounds. His early studies of plant pigments enabled him to synthesize anthocyanins and flavone...
</Question>
<Choice>Robinson, Sir Robert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physician, chemist, and inventor, perhaps best-known for having subsidized the experiments of the Scottish engineer James Watt that led to the development of the first commercially practical condensing steam engine (1769).Roebuck devoted much of his time to chemistry, especially its practical applications. Among the most important of his early achievements in this field was the introduction of leaden condensing chambers in the manufacture of sulfuric acid (1746). The substitution of leaden chambers for glass globes, which had been employed for years, revolutionized the production proce...
</Question>
<Choice>Roebuck, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biochemist who shared the 2004 Nobel Prize for Chemistry with Aaron J. Ciechanover and Avram Hershko for their joint discovery of the process by which the cells of most living organisms remove unwanted proteins.Rose received a Ph.D. in biochemistry from the University of Chicago in 1952. He later served (1954–63) on the faculty at the Yale University School of Medicine and was a senior member (1963–95) of the Fox Chase Cancer Center in Philadelphia. In 1997 he accepted a special appointment as emeritus researcher at the University of California, Irvine.In the late 1970s and early '80s...
</Question>
<Choice>Rose, Irwin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American chemist who shared the 1995 Nobel Prize for Chemistry with chemists Mario Molina and Paul Crutzen for research on the depletion of the Earth's ozone layer. Working with Molina, Rowland discovered that man-made chlorofluorocarbon (CFC) propellants accelerate the decomposition of the ozonosphere, which protects the Earth from ultraviolet radiation. Their findings eventually brought about international changes in the chemical industry.Rowland was educated in his hometown at Ohio Wesleyan University (B.A., 1948) and at the University of Chicago (M.S., 1951; Ph.D., 1952). He held academic...
</Question>
<Choice>Rowland, F. Sherwood</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German chemist considered to be the originator of the widely used analytic technique of paper chromatography.Runge earned a medical degree from the University of Jena in 1819 and a doctorate in chemistry from the University of Berlin in 1822. He was a professor at the University of Breslau (now Wroclaw, Pol.) before taking a post as a chemist in a chemical factory at Oranienburg in 1831. In the course of his research on synthetic dyes, he isolated and named several important components of coal-tar oil, among them carbolic acid (now called phenol), pyrrole, rosolic acid (aurin), and cyanol (ani...
</Question>
<Choice>Runge, Friedlieb Ferdinand</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician and political leader, a member of the Continental Congress and a signer of the Declaration of Independence. His encouragement of clinical research and instruction was frequently offset by his insistence upon bloodletting, purging, and other debilitating therapeutic measures.Rush was born into a pious Presbyterian family. He was sent to a private academy and on to the College of New Jersey at Princeton, from which he was graduated in 1760. After a medical apprenticeship of six years, he sailed for Europe. He took a medical degree at the University of Edinburgh in 1768 and the...
</Question>
<Choice>Rush, Benjamin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
New Zealand-born British physicist considered the greatest experimentalist since Michael Faraday (1791–1867). Rutherford was the central figure in the study of radioactivity, and with his concept of the nuclear atom he led the exploration of nuclear physics. He won the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1908, was president of the Royal Society (1925–30) and the British Association for the Advancement of Science (1923), was conferred the Order of Merit in 1925, and was raised to the peerage as Lord Rutherford of Nelson in 1931.
</Question>
<Choice>
Rutherford, Ernest, Baron Rutherford of Nelson, of Cambridge
</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss chemist and joint recipient, with Adolf Butenandt of Germany, of the 1939 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for his work on ringed molecules, terpenes (a class of hydrocarbons found in the essential oils of many plants), and sex hormones.While working as an assistant to the German chemist Hermann Staudinger, Ružicka investigated the composition of the insecticides in pyrethrum (1911–16). Accompanying Staudinger to the Federal Institute of Technology in Zürich, he became a Swiss citizen and lectured at the institute. In 1926 he became professor of organic chemistry at the University of Utrecht in...
</Question>
<Choice>Ruzicka, Leopold</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French organic chemist and corecipient, with Victor Grignard, of the 1912 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for researches in catalytic organic synthesis, in particular for discovering the use of nickel as a catalyst in hydrogenation (the addition of hydrogen to molecules of carbon compounds).Sabatier studied at the École Normale Supérieure and under Marcellin Berthelot at the Collège de France, earning his doctorate in 1880. After a year at the University of Bordeaux, he moved to the University of Toulouse in 1882, where he became professor (1884) and dean (1905) and where he remained until retiremen...
</Question>
<Choice>Sabatier, Paul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French chemical researcher who invented the first economical process for producing aluminum.Sainte-Claire Deville was the son of a French diplomat. He received a degree in medicine in Paris in 1843 but was already attracted to chemistry. He established his own laboratory and published a paper on his turpentine researches, winning a doctorate in science. As professor of chemistry and dean of science at the University of Besançon from 1845 to 1851, he proved exceptionally capable of combining research with teaching. In 1851 he was appointed professor of chemistry at the École Normale Supérieure...
</Question>
<Choice>Sainte-Claire Deville, Henri-Etienne</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English biochemist who was twice the recipient of the Nobel Prize for Chemistry. He was awarded the prize in 1958 for his determination of the structure of the insulin molecule. He shared the prize (with Paul Berg and Walter Gilbert) in 1980 for his determination of base sequences in nucleic acids. Sanger was only the fourth two-time recipient of the Nobel Prize.
</Question>
<Choice>Sanger, Frederick</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss chemist and plant physiologist whose quantitative experiments on the influence of water, air, and nutrients on plants laid the foundation for plant biochemistry.Saussure was the son of the geologist Horace-Bénédict de Saussure, whom he assisted in a number of experiments and expeditions. Saussure's work built on that of Joseph Priestley, his teacher Jean Senebier, and Jan Ingenhousz. In 1797 he published three articles on carbonic acid and its formation in plant tissues in the Annales de chimie (“Annals of Chemistry”). In Recherches chimiques sur la végétation (1804; “Chemical Research o...
</Question>
<Choice>Saussure, Nicolas-Theodore de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American research chemist and meteorologist, who in 1946 carried out the first systematic series of experiments to investigate the physics of precipitation. From an aircraft over Massachusetts he seeded clouds with pellets of Dry Ice (solid carbon dioxide) and succeeded in producing snow, initiating the science of experimental meteorology and weather control.Schaefer attended classes at Union College in New York and graduated in 1928 from the Davey Institute of Tree Surgery. From 1933 to 1954 he worked in research at General Electric Laboratories, where his efforts during the war were directed...
</Question>
<Choice>Schaefer, Vincent Joseph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German Swedish chemist who independently discovered oxygen, chlorine, and manganese.
</Question>
<Choice>Scheele, Carl Wilhelm</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German chemist who discovered and named ozone (1840) and was the first to describe guncotton (nitrocellulose). His teaching posts included one at Epsom, Eng., before he joined the faculty at the University of Basel, Switz. (1828), where he was appointed professor of chemistry and physics in 1835.His discovery of guncotton began with an accident in his wife's kitchen. When he used her cotton apron to wipe up some spilled nitric and sulfuric acid, it disintegrated, leading to his work on nitrocellulose. He also did research on the passivity of iron, the properties of hydrogen peroxide, and catal...
</Question>
<Choice>Schonbein, Christian Friedrich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American chemist who, with Robert H. Grubbs and Yves Chauvin, was awarded the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 2005 for developing metathesis, one of the most important types of chemical reactions used in organic chemistry. Schrock was honoured as “the first to produce an efficient metal-compound catalyst for metathesis.”Schrock received a B.A. (1967) from the University of California, Riverside, and a Ph.D. (1971) from Harvard University. He held a one-year National Science Foundation postdoctoral fellowship at the University of Cambridge and spent three years doing research at E.I. du Pont de Ne...
</Question>
<Choice>Schrock, Richard R.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American nuclear chemist best known for his work on isolating and identifying transuranium elements (those heavier than uranium). He shared the 1951 Nobel Prize for Chemistry with Edwin Mattison McMillan for their independent discoveries of transuranium elements. Seaborgium was named in his honour, making him the only person for whom a chemical element was named during his lifetime.Seaborg learned Swedish from his immigrant mother before he learned English. When he was 10, his family moved to a suburb of Los Angeles. He received a bachelor's degree (1934) from the University of California, Los...
</Question>
<Choice>Seaborg, Glenn T.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian chemist and toxicologist who is considered one of the founders of colloid chemistry.Selmi held several teaching positions in Turin and Modena before accepting the post of professor of chemical pharmacology and toxicology at the University of Bologna in 1867. He published (1845–50) the first systematic study of inorganic colloids, in particular silver chloride, Prussian blue, and sulfur. His work in toxicology was mainly in the study of putrefaction and poisoning. In 1870 he coined the phrase “ptomaine poisoning.” Selmi's Enciclopedia di chimica scientifica e industriale, 11 vol. (1868–...
</Question>
<Choice>Selmi, Francesco</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Soviet physical chemist who shared the 1956 Nobel Prize for Chemistry with Sir Cyril Hinshelwood for research in chemical kinetics. He was the second Soviet citizen (after the émigré writer Ivan Bunin) to receive a Nobel Prize.Semyonov was educated in St. Petersburg, graduating from the city's university in 1917, the year of the Russian Revolution, and taught for a time at the University of Tomsk in western Siberia. Associated with the Leningrad A.F. Ioffe Physicotechnical Institute from 1920 to 1931, he became a professor at the Leningrad (St. Petersburg) Polytechnic Institute in 1928. He was...
</Question>
<Choice>Semyonov, Nikolay Nikolayevich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American scientist who, with William S. Knowles and Noyori Ryoji, won the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 2001 for developing the first chiral catalysts.Sharpless received a Ph.D. from Stanford University in 1968. After postdoctoral work, he joined the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) in 1970. In 1990 he became W.M. Keck Professor of Chemistry at the Scripps Research Institute in La Jolla, California.Many molecules are chiral—they exist in two structural forms (enantiomers) that are nonsuperimposable mirror images. Likewise, the receptors, enzymes, and other cellular components made fr...
</Question>
<Choice>Sharpless, K. Barry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese chemist who, with Alan G. MacDiarmid and Alan J. Heeger, won the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 2000 for their discovery that certain plastics can be chemically altered to conduct electricity almost as readily as metals.Shirakawa earned a Ph.D. from the Tokyo Institute of Technology in 1966. That same year he joined the faculty of the Institute of Materials Science at the University of Tsukuba, where he became professor of chemistry in 1982.In 1974 Shirakawa and associates serendipitously synthesized polyacetylene, a polymer that was known to exist as a black powder, into a silvery film...
</Question>
<Choice>Shirakawa Hideki</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English chemist who contributed to the understanding of chemical bonding, especially in coordination compounds.Sidgwick's work in organic nitrogen compounds, presented in his Organic Chemistry of Nitrogen (1910), was of enduring value. With Sir Ernest Rutherford he developed an interest in the forces that hold molecules together. After World War I he advanced the idea of the hydrogen bond to explain the behaviour of some organic molecules. During the 1920s he extended Gilbert N. Lewis' concept of electron sharing in covalent bonds and expressed the idea that one atom could donate a pair of ele...
</Question>
<Choice>Sidgwick, Nevil Vincent</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
geologist and chemist who founded the American Journal of Science and wielded a powerful influence in the development of science in the United States.Silliman was appointed professor of chemistry and natural history at Yale, from which he had graduated in 1796. He was instrumental in expanding the college's educational resources through the acquisition of extensive mineralogical collections and the foundation of the Sheffield Scientific School, the Trumbull Gallery, and the medical school. Much in demand as a lecturer on science, Silliman was also a popular and well-known teacher.In 1818 he st...
</Question>
<Choice>Silliman, Benjamin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Danish biophysicist who (with Paul D. Boyer and John E. Walker) was awarded the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1997 for his discovery of the enzyme called sodium-potassium-activated adenosine triphosphatase (Na+-K+ ATPase), which is found in the plasma membrane of animal cells and acts as a pump that exchanges sodium (Na+) for potassium (K+).Skou studied medicine at the University of Copenhagen and in 1954 earned a doctorate degree at Aarhus University, where he later taught. His research on ion-carrying enzymes was based on the work of Sir Alan Hodgkin and Richard Keynes, who followed the movem...
</Question>
<Choice>Skou, Jens C.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American chemist and physicist, who shared the 1996 Nobel Prize for Chemistry with Robert F. Curl, Jr., and Sir Harold W. Kroto for their joint discovery of carbon-60 (C60, or buckminsterfullerene) and the fullerenes.Smalley received a Ph.D. from Princeton University in 1973. After postdoctoral work at the University of Chicago, he began his teaching career at Rice University (Houston, Texas) in 1976. He was named Gene and Norman Hackerman Professor of Chemistry there in 1982 and became a professor of physics in 1990.It was at Rice University that Smalley and his colleagues discovered fulleren...
</Question>
<Choice>Smalley, Richard E.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British-born Canadian biochemist who won (with Kary B. Mullis) the 1993 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for his development of a technique called oligonucleotide-based site-directed mutagenesis, which enabled researchers to introduce specific mutations into genes and, thus, to the proteins that they encode. Using site-directed mutagenesis, scientists have been able to dissect the structure and function relationships involved in protein plaque formation in the pathophysiology of Alzheimer disease; study the feasibility of gene therapy approaches for cystic fibrosis, sickle-cell disease, and hemophili...
</Question>
<Choice>Smith, Michael</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English chemist and recipient of the 1921 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for investigating radioactive substances and for elaborating the theory of isotopes. He is credited, along with others, with the discovery of the element protactinium in 1917.Educated in Wales and at the University of Oxford, he worked under the physicist Sir Ernest Rutherford at McGill University, Montreal (1900–02), then under the chemist Sir William Ramsay at University College, London. After teaching at the University of Glasgow, Scotland (1904–14), Soddy became a professor of chemistry at Oxford (1919–37).Soddy worked wit...
</Question>
<Choice>Soddy, Frederick</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Belgian industrial chemist, best known for his development of a commercially viable ammonia-soda process for producing soda ash (sodium carbonate), widely used in the manufacture of such products as glass and soap.After attending local schools, Solvay entered his father's salt-making business. At the age of 21 he began working with an uncle at a gasworks near Brussels, and while there he began to develop the conversion method for which he is known.Although the ammonia-soda process had been understood since 1811, a suitable and economical means of large-scale commercial production had evaded in...
</Question>
<Choice>Solvay, Ernest</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American chemist who, during the 1940s and '50s, developed processes for reducing individual rare-earth elements to the metallic state at low cost, thereby making these substances available to industry at reasonable prices. He also helped to purify the uranium used in 1942 for the first self-sustaining nuclear chain reaction experiment.After studying at several American institutions of higher education, Spedding held various teaching and research positions until he became professor of physical chemistry at Iowa State University of Science and Technology, Ames, in 1941. The following year he jo...
</Question>
<Choice>Spedding, Frank Harold</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German educator, chemist, and esteemed medical theorist and practitioner. His chemical theory of phlogiston dominated European chemistry until the “Chemical Revolution” at the end of the 18th century.
</Question>
<Choice>Stahl, Georg Ernst</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biochemist who received (with John Northrop and James Sumner) the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1946 for his work in the purification and crystallization of viruses, thus demonstrating their molecular structure.Stanley obtained his doctorate from the University of Illinois in 1929. He worked from 1932 to 1948 at the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (now Rockefeller University) facilities in Princeton, N.J. In 1935 Stanley crystallized tobacco mosaic virus (TMV, the causative agent of a plant disease) and showed that it is a rod-shaped aggregate of protein and nucleic acid mol...
</Question>
<Choice>Stanley, Wendell Meredith</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German chemist who won the 1953 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for demonstrating that polymers are long-chain molecules. His work laid the foundation for the great expansion of the plastics industry later in the 20th century.Staudinger studied chemistry at the universities of Darmstadt and Munich, and he received a Ph.D. from the University of Halle in 1903. He held academic posts at the universities of Strassburg (now Strasbourg) and Karlsruhe before joining the faculty at the Swiss Federal Institute of Technology in Zürich in 1912. He left the institute in 1926 to become a lecturer at the Albert...
</Question>
<Choice>Staudinger, Hermann</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biochemist who, along with Stanford Moore and Christian B. Anfinsen, was a cowinner of the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1972 for their studies of the composition and functioning of the pancreatic enzyme ribonuclease.Stein received his Ph.D. degree from the Columbia College of Physicians and Surgeons, New York City, in 1938. In that year he joined the staff of the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (now Rockefeller University), also in New York City. He was promoted to a professorship there in 1954.With Moore, who was his colleague at the Rockefeller Institute, Stein between 19...
</Question>
<Choice>Stein, William H.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. chemist who interpreted the behaviour and structure of organic compounds in the light of valence theory and applied the methods of physical chemistry to organic chemistry.Stieglitz received his Ph.D. from the University of Berlin (1889) and later was associated with the University of Chicago, where he headed the chemistry department (1915–33). He studied molecular rearrangements, catalysis, the theory of chemical indicators, and the structure of organic nitrogen compounds. Stieglitz introduced theories of ionization and chemical equilibrium in Elements of Quantitative Chemical Analysis, 2...
</Question>
<Choice>Stieglitz, Julius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physical chemist who, with Otto Hahn, discovered neutron-induced nuclear fission in uranium (1938) and thereby opened the field of atomic energy.Strassmann received his Ph.D. from the Technical University in Hannover in 1929. He helped develop the rubidium-strontium method of dating widely used in geochronology. Beginning in 1934 he joined Hahn and Lise Meitner in their investigations of the radioactive products formed when uranium is bombarded by neutrons. Strassmann's mastery of analytic chemistry contributed to the team's recognition of the lighter elements produced from neutron bomb...
</Question>
<Choice>Strassmann, Fritz</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biochemist and corecipient, with John Howard Northrop and Wendell Meredith Stanley, of the 1946 Nobel Prize for Chemistry. Sumner was the first to crystallize an enzyme, an achievement that revealed the protein nature of enzymes.After crystallizing the enzyme urease in 1926, Sumner went to Stockholm to study with Hans von Euler-Chelpin and Theodor Svedberg. He crystallized the enzyme catalase in 1937 and also contributed to the purification of several other enzymes. He was a professor at the Cornell University Medical School in Ithaca, New York, from 1929 to 1955 and became director i...
</Question>
<Choice>Sumner, James Batcheller</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish chemist who won the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1926 for his studies in the chemistry of colloids and for his invention of the ultracentrifuge, an invaluable aid in those and subsequent studies.After receiving his doctorate from the University of Uppsala in 1907, Svedberg joined the faculty there. When he retired in 1949 he was named director of the new Gustaf Werners Institute for Nuclear Chemistry, a post he held until 1967.Svedberg's early research was on colloids, in which particles too small to be resolved by ordinary light microscopes are dispersed throughout water or some other...
</Question>
<Choice>Svedberg, Theodor H.E.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physicist and chemist who produced an early electric light bulb and invented the dry photographic plate, an important improvement in photography and a step in the development of modern photographic film.After serving his apprenticeship with a druggist in his native town, Swan became first assistant and later partner in a firm of manufacturing chemists in Newcastle. Working with wet photographic plates, he noticed that heat increased the sensitivity of the silver bromide emulsion. By 1871 he had devised a method of drying the wet plates, initiating the age of convenience in photography....
</Question>
<Choice>Swan, Sir Joseph Wilson</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
physician, physiologist, anatomist, and chemist who is considered the founder of the 17th-century iatrochemical school of medicine, which held that all phenomena of life and disease are based on chemical action. His studies helped shift medical emphasis from mystical speculation to a rational application of universal laws of physics and chemistry.Basing his medical system on the recent discovery of the circulation of the blood by the English anatomist William Harvey, while keeping it within the general framework of the classic Greek physician Galen's humoral theories, Sylvius felt that the mos...
</Question>
<Choice>Sylvius, Franciscus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British biochemist who in 1952 shared the Nobel Prize for Chemistry with A.J.P. Martin for their development of partition chromatography, notably paper chromatography.Synge studied at Winchester College, Cambridge, and received his Ph.D. at Trinity College there in 1941. He spent his entire professional career conducting research, initially with Martin under the auspices of the Wool Industries Research Association, Leeds (1941–43). The two men developed partition chromatography, a technique that is used to separate mixtures of closely related chemicals such as amino acids for identification an...
</Question>
<Choice>Synge, R. L. M.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English chemist, linguist, archaeologist, and pioneer photographer. He is best known for his development of the calotype (q.v.), an early photographic process that was an improvement over the daguerreotype of the French inventor L.-J.-M. Daguerre. Talbot's calotypes involved the use of a photographic negative, from which multiple prints could be made; had his method been announced but a few weeks earlier, he and not Daguerre would probably have been known as the founder of photography.Talbot was educated at Harrow and at Trinity College, Cambridge, and published many articles in the fields of...
</Question>
<Choice>Talbot, William Henry Fox</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian chemist who helped to found the science of metallurgy and pioneered in the study of the internal structure and physical properties of metals and their alloys. In addition, his studies on heterogenous equilibria (i.e., the behaviour of matter as a function of chemical composition, temperature, and pressure) played a major role in systematizing inorganic chemistry and contributed significantly to the development of physical chemistry as a discipline.Relatively little was known about metallic compounds when Tammann began studying them in 1903. His research revealed that, in many cases, al...
</Question>
<Choice>Tammann, Gustav Heinrich Johann Apollon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese scientist who, with John B. Fenn and Kurt Wüthrich, won the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 2002 for developing techniques to identify and analyze proteins and other large biological molecules.Tanaka received an engineering degree from Tohoku University in 1983. Later that year he joined Shimadzu Corporation, a maker of scientific and industrial instruments, and he remained there in various research capacities. In 2002 he was appointed fellow of the corporation, a position comparable to executive director.Tanaka's prizewinning work expanded the applications of mass spectrometry (MS), an...
</Question>
<Choice>Tanaka Koichi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Canadian-born American chemist, who won the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1983 for his extensive research into the properties and reactions of dissolved inorganic substances, particularly oxidation-reduction processes involving the ions of metallic elements (seeoxidation-reduction reaction).Taube was educated at the University of Saskatchewan (B.S., 1935; M.S., 1937) and the University of California, Berkeley (Ph.D., 1940). He later taught at Cornell University (1941–46) and the University of Chicago (1946–61) before joining the faculty of Stanford University in 1962; he was named professor eme...
</Question>
<Choice>Taube, Henry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French chemist, teacher, and author of an influential four-volume text on basic chemical theory and practice (1813–16).A peasant's son, Thenard endured extreme hardships to gain his scientific education. His several teaching posts were obtained through the influence of Nicolas-Louis Vauquelin, who also arranged Thenard's succession to his own chair in chemistry at the Collège de France in 1802. He later taught at the École Polytechnique and the Sorbonne and eventually became chancellor of the University of Paris.In 1799 he discovered Thenard's blue, a pigment used in the colouring of porcelain...
</Question>
<Choice>Thenard, Louis-Jacques</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Danish chemist who determined the amount of heat evolved from or absorbed in a large number of chemical reactions.Thomsen held two teaching posts before he became professor of chemistry at the University of Copenhagen (1866–91). He verified Gustav Kirchhoff's equation concerning heats of reaction and confirmed the theory of mass action advanced by Cato Maximilian Guldberg and Peter Waage, both of Norway. Thomsen also devised the first table of the relative strengths of acids. He became prosperous from developing a process (patented in 1853) for the manufacture of soda from the mineral cryolite...
</Question>
<Choice>Thomsen, Hans Peter Jorgen Julius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish biochemist who won the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1948 for his work on electrophoresis and adsorption analysis.As an assistant to The Svedberg at the University of Uppsala (1925–32), Tiselius developed the use of electrophoresis for the delicate task of separating proteins in suspension on the basis of their electrical charge. For this work he was awarded his doctorate in 1930.After lecturing at Uppsala, he conducted research at the Institute for Advanced Study at Princeton (1934–35). Returning to Uppsala (1937), he became a professor of biochemistry and was provided with a newly bui...
</Question>
<Choice>Tiselius, Arne</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British biochemist whose research on the structure and synthesis of nucleotides, nucleosides, and nucleotide coenzymes gained him the 1957 Nobel Prize for Chemistry.After receiving doctorates from the universities of Frankfurt am Main (1931) and Oxford (1933), Todd held posts with the Lister Institute of Preventive Medicine, London, and the University of London before becoming professor of organic chemistry at the University of Manchester (1938–44) and then at Cambridge (1944–71), where he was also master of Christ's College (1963–78). He was named chancellor of the University of Strathclyde i...
</Question>
<Choice>
Todd of Trumpington, Alexander Robertus Todd, Baron
</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
botanist and chemist known for his extensive studies of North American flora.Torrey was educated at the College of Physicians and Surgeons in New York City (M.D., 1818), where he became a cofounder of the Lyceum of Natural History, later the New York Academy of Sciences. In 1817 he and several members of the Lyceum prepared A Catalogue of Plants Growing Spontaneously within Thirty Miles of the City of New York, which came to be known as “Torrey's catalog.” He made an extensive study of the plants of the northeastern U.S., and the unidentified plants collected on government expeditions to the w...
</Question>
<Choice>Torrey, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American scientist awarded the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1934 for his discovery of the heavy form of hydrogen known as deuterium. He was a key figure in the development of the atomic bomb and made fundamental contributions to a widely accepted theory of the origin of the Earth and other planets.
</Question>
<Choice>Urey, Harold C.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French chemist who discovered the elements chromium (1797) and beryllium (1798).A peasant's son, Vauquelin went to work in an apothecary shop, where he was befriended by Antoine-François Fourcroy, who made him his laboratory assistant (1783–91). Vauquelin began publishing on his own authority in 1790 and was associated with 376 scientific papers. His teaching and consultative posts date from 1794. In 1809 he succeeded Fourcroy as chemistry professor at the Paris Faculty of Medicine.Vauquelin detected chromium in a lead ore from Siberia and beryllium in beryl. His other chemical discoveries inc...
</Question>
<Choice>Vauquelin, Nicolas-Louis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French scientist, known for his invention of smokeless powder.After studying with the chemist Marcellin Berthelot, Vieille collaborated with him in researches that led to important discoveries of the physics of shock waves (1881). He then undertook to solve the problem of harnessing the powerful but unstable substance nitrocellulose as a propellant charge to replace black powder. Utilizing the colloiding action of certain solvents, he molded the resultant gelatinous mass into shapes of controlled dimensions, resulting in the formation of an explosive that came to be known as Powder B, its Fren...
</Question>
<Choice>Vieille, Paul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Finnish biochemist whose investigations directed toward improving the production and storage of protein-rich green fodder, vitally important to regions characterized by long, severe winters, brought him the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1945.As a chemistry instructor at the University of Helsinki (1924–39), where he became professor of biochemistry (1939–48), Virtanen studied the fermentation processes that spoil stores of silage. Knowing that the fermentation product, lactic acid, increases the acidity of the silage to a point at which destructive fermentation ceases, he developed a procedure...
</Question>
<Choice>Virtanen, Artturi Ilmari</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physical chemist and metallurgist who helped advance the understanding of the chemistry of solid-state materials, especially the effects of imperfections at the atomic level on the properties of compounds such as oxides and sulfides, and of metals and alloys.Wagner was educated at the universities of Munich and Leipzig and taught and carried out research in a number of German universities. He was a member of the faculty of metallurgy at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, from 1949 to 1958, and from 1958 to 1968 he was director of the Max Planck Institute of Chemistry...
</Question>
<Choice>Wagner, Carl</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
chemist who discovered the Walden inversion, a reversal of stereochemical configuration that occurs in many reactions of covalent compounds.Walden went to Germany after the Russian Revolution of 1917 and served as head of the chemistry department of the University of Rostock from 1919 to 1934. He became professor of chemistry at the University of Tübingen in 1947. Walden is also responsible for Walden's rule, which relates the conductivity and viscosity of nonaqueous solutions.
</Question>
<Choice>Walden, Paul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German chemist awarded the 1910 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for analyzing fragrant essential oils and identifying the compounds known as terpenes.Wallach studied under Friedrich Wöhler at the University of Göttingen, receiving his doctorate in 1869. He joined August Kekule at the University of Bonn (1870), where he taught pharmacy and became professor in 1876. From 1889 to 1915 he was director of the Chemical Institute at Göttingen.While at Bonn, Wallach became interested in the molecular structure of a group of essential oils that were widely used in pharmaceutical preparations. Many of these o...
</Question>
<Choice>Wallach, Otto</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first president of the new nation of Israel (1949–52), who was for decades the guiding spirit behind the World Zionist Organization.
</Question>
<Choice>Weizmann, Chaim Azriel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(baron of) Austrian chemist and engineer who invented the gas mantle, thus allowing the greatly increased output of light by gas lamps.In 1885 Welsbach discovered and isolated the elements neodymium and praseodymium from a mixture called didymium, which was previously considered an element. His interest in rare-earth elements continued, and he found that a fabric impregnated with a mixture of thorium nitrate and cerium nitrate could be made into a mantle that glowed brightly when heated by a gas flame. Patented in 1885, the Welsbach mantle greatly improved gas lighting and, although largely su...
</Question>
<Choice>Welsbach, Carl Auer, Freiherr von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss chemist and winner of the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1913 for his research into the structure of coordination compounds.
</Question>
<Choice>Werner, Alfred</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American chemist and founder of the General Electric Company's research laboratory, where he directed pioneering work in electrical technology and was credited with setting the pattern for industrial scientific laboratory research in the United States.Whitney studied at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, and earned his Ph.D. from the University of Leipzig in 1896. Upon joining General Electric, Whitney founded (1900) its research laboratory at Schenectady, N.Y., and was its director (1900–28) and later vice president in charge of research (1928–41). There he found, in 1902,...
</Question>
<Choice>Whitney, Willis Rodney</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German chemist, winner of the 1927 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for his determination of the molecular structure of bile acids.Wieland obtained his doctorate at the University of Munich in 1901 and remained in that city to teach and conduct research. He became professor of chemistry at the University of Munich in 1925 and held that post until his retirement in 1950. Wieland made important contributions to structural organic chemistry with his findings (1911) that different forms of nitrogen in organic compounds can be detected and distinguished from one another. The following year he began his re...
</Question>
<Choice>Wieland, Heinrich Otto</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British chemist, joint recipient with Ernst Fischer of the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1973 for their independent work in organometallic chemistry.After studying at the Imperial College of Science and Technology, University of London, Wilkinson worked with the Atomic Energy Project in Canada from 1943 to 1946. He taught at the University of California at Berkeley (1946–50), the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (1950–51), and Harvard University (1951–55) before returning in 1956 to the Imperial College in London, where he became professor emeritus in 1988. Wilkinson was knighted in 1976....
</Question>
<Choice>Wilkinson, Sir Geoffrey</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English chemist whose research on alcohols and ethers clarified organic molecular structure.From 1849 to 1887 Williamson served on the faculty of University College, London. In 1850 he discovered the structural relation between ethers and alcohols: in ethers the oxygen atom links two hydrocarbon groups, whereas in alcohols the oxygen is bonded to a hydrocarbon group and a hydrogen atom. In further studies, Williamson created an understanding of reversible reactions. He also was the first to explain the state of dynamic equilibrium, in which two opposing reactions have equal rates, resulting in...
</Question>
<Choice>Williamson, Alexander William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German chemist whose study of the structure of chlorophyll and other plant pigments won him the 1915 Nobel Prize for Chemistry.Willstätter obtained his doctorate from the University of Munich (1894) for work on the structure of cocaine. While serving as an assistant to Adolf von Baeyer at Munich, he continued research into the structure of alkaloids and synthesized several.In 1905 he was given a professorship at the University of Zürich and began working on chlorophyll. He elucidated its structure and showed that the blood pigment heme bears a structural resemblance to the porphyrin compound f...
</Question>
<Choice>Willstatter, Richard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German organic chemist, winner of the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1928 for research on substances, notably vitamin D, that play important biological roles.Windaus switched from medical to chemical studies. After receiving his Ph.D. from the University of Freiburg (1899), he held positions there and at Innsbruck, Austria, before his appointment as head of the chemical institute at the University of Göttingen (1915–44). His studies of the chemical structure of cholesterol, begun in 1901, spanned some 30 years. This work was part of his study of the complex alcohols known as sterols.Windaus disc...
</Question>
<Choice>Windaus, Adolf</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German chemist who discovered the element germanium.After 12 years managing a cobalt glassworks, Winkler joined the faculty of the Freiberg School of Mining in 1873. In 1886, while analyzing the mineral argyrodite, he discovered germanium. It proved to be the element predicted in 1871 by Dmitry I. Mendeleyev, who had called it ekasilicon.
</Question>
<Choice>Winkler, Clemens Alexander</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German chemist whose pioneering work led to the recognition of the importance of the spatial arrangement of atoms within a molecule.Wislicenus's education included study at Harvard and Zürich, where he taught, prior to professorships elsewhere. He anticipated the structural theory of Jacobus van't Hoff and Joseph-Achille Le Bel by several years in his work on lactic acid, which led to his discovery (1873) that two compounds might have the same chemical formula but exhibit different characteristics. Wislicenus attributed this phenomenon (isomerism) to the different molecular structure or arrang...
</Question>
<Choice>Wislicenus, Johannes Adolph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German chemist whose studies of organic phosphorus compounds won him a share (with Herbert C. Brown) of the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1979.Wittig graduated from the University of Marburg in 1923, received his doctorate there in 1926, and remained as a lecturer in chemistry until 1932. He taught at the Technical University in Braunschweig and at the universities of Braunschweig, Freiburg, and Tübingen before joining the faculty of the University of Heidelberg in 1956, where he became emeritus in 1965 but continued to pursue research.In investigating reactions involving carbanions, negatively...
</Question>
<Choice>Wittig, Georg</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German chemist who was one of the finest and most prolific of the 19th century.
</Question>
<Choice>Wohler, Friedrich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British scientist who enhanced the techniques of powder metallurgy to become the first to produce and market pure, malleable platinum. He also made fundamental discoveries in many areas of science and discovered the elements palladium (1802) and rhodium (1804).
</Question>
<Choice>Wollaston, William Hyde</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American chemist best known for his syntheses of complex organic substances, including cholesterol and cortisone (1951), strychnine (1954), and vitamin B12 (1971). He was awarded the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1965, “for his outstanding achievements in the art of organic chemistry.”
</Question>
<Choice>Woodward, Robert Burns</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French chemist and educator noted for his research on organic nitrogen compounds, hydrocarbons, and glycols.Following medical studies and a period of teaching, Wurtz studied at Giessen and then at Strasbourg (1843). He became an assistant (1845) to Jean-Baptiste-André Dumas, whom he succeeded at the School of Medicine (1852). He was the first to occupy the chair of organic chemistry at the Sorbonne (1875).His work on the acids of phosphorus led him to discover phosphorus oxychloride. In 1849 he synthesized the first organic derivative of ammonia, ethylamine, and six years later devised a metho...
</Question>
<Choice>Wurtz, Charles-Adolphe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss scientist who, with John B. Fenn and Tanaka Koichi, won the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 2002 for developing techniques to identify and analyze proteins and other large biological molecules.After receiving a Ph.D. in organic chemistry from the University of Basel in 1964, Wüthrich took his postdoctoral training in Switzerland and the United States. In 1969 he joined the Swiss Federal Institute of Technology, where he became a professor of biophysics in 1980. In 2001 he joined Scripps Research Institute in La Jolla, California, as a visiting professor.In the early 1980s Wüthrich began dev...
</Question>
<Choice>Wuthrich, Kurt</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American research scientist, a pioneer in the application of X-ray methods to determine crystal structures and one of the first to use these methods for studying biological substances.Wyckoff was educated at Cornell University and was an instructor in analytical chemistry from 1917 to 1919. He subsequently worked in the Geophysical Laboratory of the Carnegie Institute of Washington (1919–27). From 1927 to 1937 he was associated with the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, after which he joined Lederle Laboratories and then Reichel Laboratories. He subsequently worked for the U.S. Publi...
</Question>
<Choice>Wyckoff, Ralph Walter Graystone</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Egyptian-born chemist who won the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1999 for developing a rapid laser technique that enabled scientists to study the action of atoms during chemical reactions. The breakthrough created a new field of physical chemistry known as femtochemistry.After receiving B.S. (1967) and M.S. (1969) degrees from the University of Alexandria, Zewail attended the University of Pennsylvania, where he earned a doctorate in 1974. Two years later he joined the faculty at the California Institute of Technology and in 1990 was selected as the school's first Linus Pauling professor of chem...
</Question>
<Choice>Zewail, Ahmed H.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German chemist who shared the 1963 Nobel Prize for Chemistry with the Italian chemist Giulio Natta. Ziegler's research with organometallic compounds made possible industrial production of high-quality polyethylene. Natta used Ziegler's organometallic compounds to make commercially useful polypropylene.
</Question>
<Choice>Ziegler, Karl</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian chemist who received the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1925 for research on colloids, which consist of submicroscopic particles dispersed throughout another substance. He invented the ultramicroscope in the pursuit of his research.After receiving his doctorate from the University of Munich in 1889, Zsigmondy worked in research at Berlin and then joined the faculty of the University of Graz, Austria. From 1908 to 1929 he was director of the Institute for Inorganic Chemistry at the University of Göttingen.While employed in a glassworks (1897) Zsigmondy directed his attention to colloidal...
</Question>
<Choice>Zsigmondy, Richard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German meteorologist and climatologist best known for his delineation and mapping of the climatic regions of the world. He played a major role in the advancement of climatology and meteorology for more than 70 years. His achievements, practical and theoretical, profoundly influenced the development of atmospheric science.Köppen remained in Russia until he was 20. His grandfather was one of the German physicians invited to Russia by the empress Catherine the Great to improve sanitation in the provinces. He later became personal physician to the tsar. His father, Peter von Köppen (1793–1864), wo...
</Question>
<Choice>Koppen, Wladimir Peter</Choice>
</item>
</topics>