<topics>
<item>
<Question>
Norwegian mathematician, a pioneer in the development of several branches of modern mathematics.Abel's father was a poor Lutheran minister who moved his family to the parish of Gjerstad, near the town of Risør in southeast Norway, soon after Niels Henrik was born. In 1815 Niels entered the cathedral school in Oslo, where his mathematical talent was recognized in 1817 with the arrival of a new mathematics teacher, Bernt Michael Holmboe, who introduced him to the classics in mathematical literature and proposed original problems for him to solve. Abel studied the mathematical works of the 17th-c...
</Question>
<Choice>Abel, Niels Henrik</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish Jewish philosopher, astronomer, astrologer, and mathematician whose writings were among the first scientific and philosophical works to be written in Hebrew. He is sometimes known as Savasorda, a corruption of an Arabic term indicating that he held some civic office in the Muslim administration of Barcelona.In addition to translating scientific books from Arabic into Latin and Hebrew, Abraham also wrote a number of original works, among them a scientific encyclopaedia (the first in the Hebrew language) and a book on mathematics, ?ibbur ha-Meshi?ah ve-ha-Tishboret (“Treatise on Measurem...
</Question>
<Choice>Abraham bar Hiyya</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
a distinguished Muslim astronomer and mathematician, who made important contributions to the development of trigonometry.Abu?l-Wafa? worked in a private observatory in Baghdad, where he made observations to determine, among other astronomical parameters, the obliquity of the ecliptic, the length of the seasons, and the latitude of the city. He also worked with astronomers in Khwarezm (now in Uzbekistan) to determine the difference in longitude between the two localities by means of the simultaneous observation of a lunar eclipse. He did not, as is sometimes claimed, discover the inequality in...
</Question>
<Choice>Abu'l-Wafa'</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British mathematician and astronomer, one of two people who independently discovered the planet Neptune. On July 3, 1841, Adams had entered in his journal: “Formed a design in the beginning of this week of investigating, as soon as possible after taking my degree, the irregularities in the motion of Uranus . . . in order to find out whether they may be attributed to the action of an undiscovered planet beyond it. . . .” In September 1845 he gave James Challis, director of the Cambridge Observatory, accurate information on where the new planet, as yet unobserved, could be found; but unfortunate...
</Question>
<Choice>Adams, John Couch</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
physicist who discovered (1756) pyroelectricity in the mineral tourmaline and published (1759) the first mathematical theory of electric and magnetic phenomena.Aepinus studied medicine and briefly taught mathematics at the University of Rostock, where his father was a professor of theology. In 1755 he became director of the astronomical observatory in Berlin and a member of the Berlin Academy of Sciences. In 1757 he moved to Russia, where he was appointed a full member of the Imperial Academy of Sciences (now the Russian Academy of Sciences) in St. Petersburg. After retiring in 1798, he settle...
</Question>
<Choice>Aepinus, Franz Maria Ulrich Theodor Hoch</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian mathematician and philosopher, considered to be the first woman in the Western world to have achieved a reputation in mathematics.Agnesi was the eldest child of a wealthy silk merchant who provided her with the best tutors available. She was an extremely precocious child who mastered Latin, Greek, Hebrew, and several modern languages at an early age, and her father liked to host gatherings where she could display her knowledge. Propositiones philosophicae (“Propositions of Philosophy”), a series of essays on natural philosophy and history based on her discussions before such gatherings...
</Question>
<Choice>Agnesi, Maria Gaetana</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Finnish mathematician who was awarded one of the first two Fields Medals in 1936 for his work with Riemann surfaces. He also won the Wolf Prize in 1981.Ahlfors received his Ph.D. from the University of Helsinki in 1932. He held an appointment there from 1938 to 1944, then went to the University of Zürich, Switz. He joined the faculty at Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass., U.S., in 1946, remaining there until his retirement.Ahlfors was awarded the Fields Medal at the International Congress of Mathematicians in Oslo, Nor., in 1936. He was cited for methods he had developed to analyze Riemann s...
</Question>
<Choice>Ahlfors, Lars Valerian</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
mathematician who invented the Harvard Mark I, forerunner of the modern electronic digitalcomputer.Aiken did engineering work while he attended the University of Wisconsin, Madison. After completing his doctorate at Harvard University in 1939, he remained there for a short period to teach before undertaking war work for the U.S. Navy Board of Ordnance.With three other engineers—Clair D. Lake, B.M. Durfee, and F.E. Hamilton—Aiken began work in 1939 on an automatic calculating machine that could perform any selected sequence of five arithmetical operations (addition, subtraction, multiplication,...
</Question>
<Choice>Aiken, Howard Hathaway</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian mathematician who made important contributions to topology.In 1897 Aleksandrov moved with his family to Smolensk, where his father had accepted a position as a surgeon with the Smolensk State Hospital. His early education was supplied by his mother, who gave him French, German, and music lessons. At grammar school he soon showed an aptitude for mathematics, and on graduation in 1913 he entered Moscow State University.Aleksandrov had his first major mathematical success in 1915, proving a fundamental theorem in set theory: Every non-denumerable Borel set contains a perfect subset. As of...
</Question>
<Choice>Aleksandrov, Pavel Sergeevich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician, philosopher, and writer, who achieved fame as a mathematician and scientist before acquiring a considerable reputation as a contributor to and editor of the famous Encyclopédie.
</Question>
<Choice>Alembert, Jean Le Rond d'</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American mathematician and a founder of the branch of mathematics originally known as analysis situs, now called topology.The son of John White Alexander, an American painter who created murals for the Library of Congress, James studied mathematics and physics at Princeton University, obtaining a B.S. degree in 1910 and an M.S. degree the following year. For the next few years he traveled and studied in Europe before submitting his doctoral dissertation (1915) to Princeton, where he taught until the United States' entry into World War I in 1917. He was commissioned as a lieutenant in the U.S....
</Question>
<Choice>Alexander, James W., II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
theologian, mathematician, jurist, and astronomer who was a major figure in the cultural revival of ?afavid Iran.Al-?Amili was educated by his father, Shaykh ?usayn, a Shi?ite theologian, and by excellent teachers of mathematics and medicine. After his family left Syria in 1559 to escape persecution by the Ottoman Turks, al-?Amili lived in Herat (now in Afghanistan) and Isfahan, Iran. He attached himself to the court of ?Abbas I the Great, serving for many years as the shaykh al-Islam (chief judge of the Muslim court of law) of E?fahan, and writing during that time a treatise on Shi?ite jurisp...
</Question>
<Choice>Amili, Baha' ad-Din Muhammad ibn Husayn al-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
mathematician, known by his contemporaries as “the Great Geometer,” whose treatise Conics is one of the greatest scientific works from the ancient world. Most of his other treatises are now lost, although their titles and a general indication of their contents were passed on by later writers, especially Pappus of Alexandria (fl. c.AD 320). Apollonius's work inspired much of the advancement of geometry in the Islamic world in medieval times, and the rediscovery of his Conics in Renaissance Europe formed a good part of the mathematical basis for the scientific revolution.As a youth, Apollonius s...
</Question>
<Choice>Apollonius of Perga</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the most famous mathematician and inventor of ancient Greece. Archimedes is especially important for his discovery of the relation between the surface and volume of a sphere and its circumscribing cyclinder. He is known for his formulation of a hydrostatic principle (known as Archimedes' principle) and a device for raising water, still used in developing countries, known as the Archimedes screw.
</Question>
<Choice>Archimedes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek scientist, philosopher, and major Pythagorean mathematician. Plato, a close friend, made use of his work in mathematics, and there is evidence that Euclid borrowed from him for the treatment of number theory in Book VIII of his Elements. Archytas was also an influential figure in public affairs, and he served for seven years as commander in chief of his city.A member of the second generation of followers of Pythagoras, the Greek philosopher who stressed the significance of numbers in explaining all phenomena, Archytas sought to combine empirical observation with Pythagorean theory. In ge...
</Question>
<Choice>Archytas of Tarentum</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austro-German mathematician who made fundamental contributions to class field theory, notably the general law of reciprocity.After one year at the University of Göttingen, Artin joined the staff of the University of Hamburg in 1923. He emigrated to the United States in 1937, where he taught at Notre Dame University (1937–38), Indiana University, Bloomington (1938–46), and Princeton University (1946–58). In 1958 he returned to the University of Hamburg.Artin's early work centred on the analytical and arithmetic theory of quadratic number fields. He made major advances in abstract algebra in 192...
</Question>
<Choice>Artin, Emil</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
astronomer and the earliest Indian mathematician whose work and history are available to modern scholars. Known as Aryabhata I or Aryabhata the Elder to distinguish him from a 10th-century Indian mathematician of the same name, he flourished in Kusumapura—near Patalipurta (Patna), then the capital of the Gupta dynasty—where he composed at least two works, Aryabhatiya (c. 499) and the now lost Aryabhatasiddhanta. Aryabhatasiddhanta circulated mainly in the northwest of India and, through the Sasanian dynasty (224–651) of Iran, had a profound influence on the development of Islamic astronomy. It...
</Question>
<Choice>Aryabhata I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British mathematician who was awarded the Fields Medal in 1966 primarily for his work in topology. Atiyah received a knighthood in 1983 and the Order of Merit in 1992. He also served as president of the Royal Society (1990–95).Atiyah's father was Lebanese and his mother Scottish. He attended Victoria College in Egypt and Trinity College, Cambridge (Ph.D., 1955). He held appointments at the Institute for Advanced Study, Princeton, New Jersey, U.S. (1955), and at the University of Cambridge (1956–61). In 1961 Atiyah moved to the University of Oxford, where from 1963 to 1969 he held the Savilian...
</Question>
<Choice>Atiyah, Sir Michael Francis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Israeli mathematician, who shared the 2005 Nobel Prize for Economics with Thomas C. Schelling. Aumann's primary contribution to economics involved the analysis of repeated noncooperative encounters, a subject in the mathematical discipline of game theory. The cowinners were cited “for having enhanced our understanding of conflict and cooperation through game-theory analysis.”Aumann emigrated to the United States with his family in 1938. He was educated at the City College of New York (B.S., 1950) and the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (S.M., 1952; Ph.D., 1955), followed by postdoctoral...
</Question>
<Choice>Aumann, Robert J.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English mathematician and inventor who is credited with having conceived the first automatic digitalcomputer.In 1812 Babbage helped found the Analytical Society, whose object was to introduce developments from the European continent into English mathematics. In 1816 he was elected a fellow of the Royal Society of London. He was instrumental in founding the Royal Astronomical (1820) and Statistical (1834) societies.The idea of mechanically calculating mathematical tables first came to Babbage in 1812 or 1813. Later he made a small calculator that could perform certain mathematical computations...
</Question>
<Choice>Babbage, Charles</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English Franciscan philosopher and educational reformer who was a major medieval proponent of experimental science. Bacon studied mathematics, astronomy, optics, alchemy, and languages. He was the first European to describe in detail the process of making gunpowder, and he proposed flying machines and motorized ships and carriages. Bacon (as he himself complacently remarked) displayed a prodigious energy and zeal in the pursuit of experimental science; indeed, his studies were talked about everywhere and eventually won him a place in popular literature as a kind of wonder worker. Bacon therefo...
</Question>
<Choice>Bacon, Roger</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician whose study of irrational numbers and the concept of continuity of functions that approximate them greatly influenced the French school of mathematics.The son of a tailor, Baire won a scholarship in 1886 that enabled him to attend better schools, and in 1891 he passed the entrance examinations for both the École Polytechnique and the École Normale Supérieure. Baire chose the latter institution and graduated with a B.S. in 1895 and a Ph.D. in 1899. His doctoral thesis on the theory of functions of real variables applied concepts from set theory to classify (“categorize”) fu...
</Question>
<Choice>Baire, Rene-Louis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British mathematician who was awarded the Fields Medal in 1970 for his work in number theory.Baker attended University College, London (B.S., 1961), and Trinity College, Cambridge (M.A. and Ph.D., 1964). He held an appointment at University College (1964–65) and then joined the faculty of Trinity College in 1966.Baker received the Fields Medal at the International Congress of Mathematicians in Nice, France, in 1970. His work showed, at least in theory, that it is possible to determine all the solutions explicitly for a large class of equations. Building on the work of the Norwegian Axel Thue,...
</Question>
<Choice>Baker, Alan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss mathematician who discovered a formula basic to the development of atomic theory and the field of atomic spectroscopy.A secondary-school teacher in Basel from 1859 until his death, Balmer also lectured (1865–90) on geometry at the University of Basel. In 1885 he announced a simple formula representing the wavelengths of the spectral lines of hydrogen—the “Balmer series” (seespectral line series). Why the formula held true, however, was not explained until 1913, when Niels Bohr found that it fit into and supported his theory of discrete energy states within the hydrogen atom.
</Question>
<Choice>Balmer, Johann Jakob</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polish mathematician who founded modern functional analysis and helped develop the theory of topological vector spaces.Banach was given the surname of his mother, who was identified as Katarzyna Banach on his birth certificate, and the first name of his father, Stefan Greczek. He never knew his mother, and when still a young boy he was sent by his father to be raised by a family in Kraków. Banach apparently worked his way through the engineering school at the Lvov Technical University from 1910 to 1914. Unfit for military service because of poor eyesight, he worked on road constructions and ta...
</Question>
<Choice>Banach, Stefan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
optician and mathematician who invented two varieties of achromatic (non-colour-distorting) telescope lenses known as Barlow lenses.Self-educated, he became assistant mathematics master at the Royal Military Academy, Woolwich, in 1801. He published numerous mathematical works, including New Mathematical Tables (1814). Later known as Barlow's Tables, this compilation of factors and functions of all numbers from 1 to 10,000 was considered so accurate and so useful that it has been regularly reprinted ever since.In 1819 Barlow began work on the problem of deviation in ship compasses caused by the...
</Question>
<Choice>Barlow, Peter</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English classical scholar, theologian, and mathematician who was the teacher of Isaac Newton. He developed a method of determining tangents that closely approached the methods of calculus, and he first recognized that what became known as the processes of integration and differentiation in calculus are inverse operations.Barrow entered Trinity College, Cambridge, in 1643. There he distinguished himself as a classical scholar as well as a mathematician, earning his bachelor's degree in 1648. He was elected a fellow of the college in 1649 and received his master's degree in 1652. Such precocious...
</Question>
<Choice>Barrow, Isaac</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Danish physician, mathematician, and physicist who discovered the optical phenomenon of double refraction.While professor of medicine (1657–98) at the University of Copenhagen, Bartholin observed that images seen through Icelandic feldspar (calcite) were doubled and that, when the crystal was rotated, one image remained stationary while the other rotated with the crystal. Perceiving that light passing through calcite was split into two rays, he called the stationary image the “ordinary beam” and the moving image the “extraordinary beam.” Although Bartholin himself was unable to explain double...
</Question>
<Choice>Bartholin, Erasmus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Arab astronomer and mathematician who refined existing values for the length of the year and of the seasons, for the annual precession of the equinoxes, and for the inclination of the ecliptic. He showed that the position of the Sun's apogee, or farthest point from the Earth, is variable and that annular (central but incomplete) eclipses of the Sun are possible. He improved Ptolemy's astronomical calculations by replacing geometrical methods with trigonometry. From 877 he carried out many years of remarkably accurate observations at ar-Raqqah in Syria.Al-Battani was the best known of Arab astr...
</Question>
<Choice>Battani, al-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English Nonconformist theologian and mathematician who was the first to use probability inductively and who established a mathematical basis for probability inference (a means of calculating, from the frequency with which an event has occurred in prior trials, the probability that it will occur in future trials. Seeprobability theory: Bayes's theorem.Bayes set down his findings on probability in “Essay Towards Solving a Problem in the Doctrine of Chances” (1763), published posthumously in the Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society. That work became the basis of a statistical technique...
</Question>
<Choice>Bayes, Thomas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish American mathematician, educator, and writer who made significant contributions to analytic number theory.Bell emigrated to the United States at the age of 19 and immediately enrolled at Stanford University, where after only two years he earned his bachelor's degree. He received his master's degree from the University of Washington after one year of effort in 1908. Similarly, he received his doctorate in mathematics from Columbia University in 1912 after another year of matriculation. In between these years, Bell married and tried his hand as a mule skinner, ranch hand, surveyor, teac...
</Question>
<Choice>Bell, Eric Temple</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian mathematician known for his description of non-Euclidean geometry and for his theories of surfaces of constant curvature.Following his studies at the University of Pavia (1853–56) and later in Milan, Beltrami was invited to join the faculty at the University of Bologna in 1862 as a visiting professor of algebra and analytic geometry; four years later he was appointed professor of rational mechanics (the application of calculus to the study of the motion of solids and liquids). He also held professorships at universities in Pisa, Rome, and Pavia.Influenced by the Russian Nikolay Ivanovi...
</Question>
<Choice>Beltrami, Eugenio</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss mathematician whose work in proof theory and axiomatic set theory helped create the new discipline of mathematical logic.After obtaining his doctorate from the University of Göttingen in Germany under Edmund Landau in 1912, Bernays taught for five years at the University of Zürich before returning to Göttingen. There he collaborated closely with the prominent mathematician David Hilbert, who in the twilight of his career sought to overcome the challenges to classical mathematics posed by L.E.J. Brouwer's intuitionism. Bernays's own philosophical views remained in the background during th...
</Question>
<Choice>Bernays, Paul Isaak</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the most distinguished of the second generation of the Bernoulli family of Swiss mathematicians. He investigated not only mathematics but also such fields as medicine, biology, physiology, mechanics, physics, astronomy, and oceanography.Bernoulli's theorem (q.v.), which he derived, is named after him.Daniel Bernoulli was the second son of Johann Bernoulli, who first taught him mathematics. After studying philosophy, logic, and medicine at the universities of Heidelberg, Strasbourg, and Basel, he received an M.D. degree (1721). In 1723–24 he wrote Exercitationes quaedam Mathematicae on differen...
</Question>
<Choice>Bernoulli, Daniel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first of the Bernoulli family of Swiss mathematicians. He introduced the first principles of the calculus of variation. Bernoulli numbers, a concept that he developed, were named for him.The scion of a family of drug merchants, Jakob Bernoulli was compelled to study theology but became interested in mathematics despite his father's opposition. His travels led to a wide correspondence with mathematicians. Refusing a church appointment, he accepted a professorial chair of mathematics at the University of Basel in 1687; and, following his mastery of the mathematical works of John Wallis, Isaac Ba...
</Question>
<Choice>Bernoulli, Jakob</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
major member of the Bernoulli family of Swiss mathematicians. He investigated the then new mathematical calculus, which he applied to the measurement of curves, to differential equations, and to mechanical problems.The son of a pharmacist, Johann studied medicine and obtained his doctor's degree in Basel in 1694, with a thesis on muscular contraction. However, he turned to mathematics despite his father's opposition. In 1691–92 he wrote two texts, not published until later, on differential and integral calculus. In 1692 he taught calculus to the mathematician Guillaume-François-Antoine de L'Ho...
</Question>
<Choice>Bernoulli, Johann</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician and educator remembered for his elegant applications of differential equations to analytical mechanics, particularly in thermodynamics, and for his work on statistical probability and the theory of curves and surfaces.The nephew of the mathematician Jean-Marie-Constant Duhamel, Bertrand was also related by marriage to the mathematicians Paul Appell, Émile Borel, Charles Hermite, and Émile Picard. Bertrand graduated from the École Polytechnique in 1839 with a doctorate in thermodynamics and continued his work in engineering at the École Nationale Supérieure des Mines while...
</Question>
<Choice>Bertrand, Joseph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
mathematician who wrote a pioneering memoir on topology, the study of surfaces and higher-dimensional spaces, and wrote one of the first rigorous expositions of the theory of equations developed by the noted French mathematician Évariste Galois (1811–32).Betti studied mathematics and physics at the University of Pisa. After graduating with a degree in mathematics in 1846, he stayed on to work as an assistant until 1849 when he returned home to Pistoia to teach at a secondary school. From 1854 he taught at another secondary school in Florence. In 1857 he obtained a professorship in mathematics...
</Question>
<Choice>Betti, Enrico</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian astronomer and mathematician who helped to disseminate the mathematical work of Aryabhata I (born 476).Little is known about the life of Bhaskara; I is appended to his name to distinguish him from a 12th-century Indian astronomer of the same name. In his writings there are clues to possible locations for his life, such as Valabhi, the capital of the Maitraka dynasty, and Ashmaka, a town in Andhra Pradesh and the location of a school of followers of Aryabhata. His fame rests on three treatises he composed on the works of Aryabhata. Two of these treatises, known today as Mahabhaskariya (“...
</Question>
<Choice>Bhaskara I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the leading mathematician of the 12th century, who wrote the first work with full and systematic use of the decimal number system.Bhaskara II was the lineal successor of the noted Indian mathematician Brahmagupta (598–c. 665) as head of an astronomical observatory at Ujjain, the leading mathematical centre of ancient India.In his mathematical works, particularly Lilavati (“The Beautiful”) and Bijaga?ita (“Seed Counting”), he not only used the decimal system but also compiled problems from Brahmagupta and others. He filled many of the gaps in Brahmagupta's work, especially in obtaining a genera...
</Question>
<Choice>Bhaskara II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
foremost American mathematician of the early 20th century, who formulated the ergodic theorem.Birkhoff attended the Lewis Institute (now the Illinois Institute of Technology) in Chicago from 1896 to 1902 and then spent a year at the University of Chicago before switching to Harvard University in 1903 (A.B., 1905; A.M., 1906). He returned to Chicago in 1905 and received a doctorate there in 1907.Birkhoff taught at the University of Wisconsin (1907–09), Princeton University (1909–12), and Harvard (1912–44). He was an extraordinarily stimulating lecturer and director of research. By the mid 20th...
</Question>
<Choice>Birkhoff, George David</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American Analytical philosopher who was concerned with the nature of clarity and meaning in language.Black studied at the Universities of Cambridge (B.A., 1930), Göttingen (1930–31), and London (Ph.D., 1939). He immigrated to the United States in 1940 and became a naturalized citizen in 1948. He taught philosophy at the University of Illinois from 1940 to 1946 and thereafter taught at Cornell University, becoming professor emeritus in 1977.Black's early interest in mathematics resulted in The Nature of Mathematics (1933), a study of the various historical conceptions of that field. Black was h...
</Question>
<Choice>Black, Max</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Galician-born American mathematician who made profound contributions to harmonic analysis, probability theory, differential geometry, and other areas of mathematics.Fearful of a Russian invasion in 1914, Bochner's family moved to Berlin, Germany. Bochner attended the University of Berlin (Ph.D., 1921) but turned to commerce to help his family during Germany's postwar hyperinflation. From 1924 to 1926 he was a fellow of the International Education Board (a John D. Rockefeller, Jr. foundation). He then lectured at the University of Munich, where he wrote his first book, Vorlesungen über Fouriers...
</Question>
<Choice>Bochner, Salomon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Danish mathematician who devised a theory that concerned generalizations of functions with periodic properties, the theory of almost periodic functions.The brother of the noted physicist Niels Bohr, he became professor at the Polytechnic Institute in Copenhagen in 1915 and at the University of Copenhagen in 1930. His early mathematical research was mainly concerned with the Dirichlet series, a series introduced by Peter Dirichlet of Germany in the application of analysis to the theory of numbers. Later, in collaboration with Edmund Landau of Germany, Bohr concentrated his efforts on a study of...
</Question>
<Choice>Bohr, Harald August</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hungarian mathematician and one of the founders of non-Euclidean geometry— a geometry that differs from Euclidean geometry in its definition of parallel lines. The discovery of a consistent alternative geometry that might correspond to the structure of the universe helped to free mathematicians to study abstract concepts irrespective of any possible connection with the physical world.By the age of 13, Bolyai had mastered calculus and analytic mechanics under the tutelage of his father, the mathematician Farkas Bolyai. He also became an accomplished violinist at an early age and later was renow...
</Question>
<Choice>Bolyai, Janos</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Bohemian mathematician and theologian who provided a more detailed proof for the binomial theorem in 1816 and suggested the means of distinguishing between finite and infinite classes.Bolzano graduated from the University of Prague as an ordained priest in 1805 and was immediately appointed professor of philosophy and religion at the university. Within a matter of years, however, Bolzano alienated many faculty and church leaders with his teachings of the social waste of militarism and the needlessness of war. He urged a total reform of the educational, social, and economic systems that would d...
</Question>
<Choice>Bolzano, Bernhard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian mathematician who was awarded the Fields Medal in 1974 for his work in number theory. Between 1979 and 1982 Bombieri served on the executive committee of the International Mathematical Union.Bombieri received a Ph.D. from the University of Milan in 1963. He held appointments at the University of Pisa (1966–73) and the Scuola Normale Superiore in Pisa (1974– ) and held the IBM von Neumann Chair at the Institute for Advanced Study, Princeton, New Jersey, U.S.Bombieri was awarded the Fields Medal at the International Congress of Mathematicians in Vancouver, British Columbia, Canada, in 19...
</Question>
<Choice>Bombieri, Enrico</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian-born British mathematician and cosmologist who, with Fred Hoyle and Thomas Gold, formulated the steady-state theory of the universe.Bondi received an M.A. from Trinity College, Cambridge. During World War II he worked in the British Admiralty (1942–45). He then taught mathematics at Cambridge (1945–54) and at King's College in London (1954–85; emeritus 1985); he served as master of Churchill College, Cambridge, from 1983 to 1990. Bondi combined his academic career with active involvement in public service. He was director general of the European Space Research Organization (1967–71),...
</Question>
<Choice>Bondi, Sir Hermann</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English mathematician who helped establish modern symbolic logic and whose algebra of logic, now called Boolean algebra, is basic to the design of digital computer circuits.Boole was given his first lessons in mathematics by his father, a tradesman, who also taught him to make optical instruments. Aside from his father's help and a few years at local schools, however, Boole was self-taught in mathematics. When his father's business declined, George had to work to support the family. From the age of 16 he taught in village schools in the West Riding of Yorkshire, and he opened his own school in...
</Question>
<Choice>Boole, George</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British mathematician who won the Fields Medal in 1998 for his work in algebra.Borcherds studied undergraduate mathematics at the University of Cambridge and went on to finish his doctorate there in 1983. Afterward he held teaching and research positions at Cambridge and at the University of California at Berkeley.Borcherds received the Fields Medal at the International Congress of Mathematicians in Berlin in 1998 for his work on vertex algebras and Kac-Moody Lie algebras, which he used to prove the so-called Moonshine conjectures. The Moonshine conjectures asserted a mysterious connection bet...
</Question>
<Choice>Borcherds, Richard Ewen</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician and nautical astronomer noted for his studies of fluid mechanics and his development of instruments for navigation and geodesy, the study of the size and shape of the Earth.Borda entered the French army at an early age and later transferred to the navy, where he attained the rank of capitaine de vaisseau (“post captain”), took part in several scientific voyages, and played a role in the American Revolution. Borda developed and used many instruments for measuring an arc of a meridian, or longitude line, and helped introduce the metric system into France. He applied his stud...
</Question>
<Choice>Borda, Jean-Charles de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician who created the first effective theory of the measure of sets of points and who shares credit with René-Louis Baire and Henri Lebesgue of France for launching the modern theory of functions of a real variable.The son of a Protestant pastor, Borel exhibited his mathematical talent from a young age. After placing first in the 1889 entrance exams for the École Normale Supérieure and the École Polytechnique, both in Paris, he decided that the former was the best avenue to an academic career. He graduated first in his class of 1893 and then taught at the University of Lille, wh...
</Question>
<Choice>Borel, Emile</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
astronomer and mathematician who gave the first geometric procedure for determining the equator of a rotating planet from three observations of a surface feature and for computing the orbit of a planet from three observations of its position.Boscovich's father was a Croat (some sources say Serb) and his mother was Italian. He entered the Society of Jesus (Jesuits) in 1726 and studied mathematics and physics at the Collegium Romanum, Rome, where he was appointed professor of mathematics in 1740. One of the first scientists of continental Europe to accept Isaac Newton's gravitational theory, he...
</Question>
<Choice>Boscovich, Ruggero Giuseppe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian mathematician and physicist noted for his collaboration with Albert Einstein in developing a theory regarding the gaslike qualities of electromagnetic radiation (seeBose-Einstein statistics).Bose, a graduate of the University of Calcutta, taught at the University of Dacca (1921–45) and then at Calcutta (1945–56). Bose's numerous scientific papers (published from 1918 to 1956) contributed to statistical mechanics, the electromagnetic properties of the ionosphere, the theories of X-ray crystallography and thermoluminescence, and unified field theory. Bose's Planck's Law and the Hypothesis...
</Question>
<Choice>Bose, Satyendra Nath</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Belgian mathematician who was awarded the Fields Medal in 1994 for his work in analysis.Bourgain received a Ph.D. from the Free University of Brussels (1977). He held appointments at the Free University (1981–85); jointly at the University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign (U.S.), and the Institute of Advanced Scientific Studies, Bures-sur-Yvette, France (1985–94); and from 1994 at the Institute for Advanced Study, Princeton, New Jersey, U.S.Bourgain received the Fields Medal at the International Congress of Mathematicians in Zürich, Switzerland, in 1994, where his achievements in several fields w...
</Question>
<Choice>Bourgain, Jean</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
self-educated American mathematician and astronomer, author of the best American book on navigation of his time and translator from the French of Pierre-Simon Laplace's Celestial Mechanics.Bowditch's formal education ended when he was 10 years old and family circumstances forced him to work, first for two years in his father's cooperage shop and then as a clerk for various local shops. Between 1795 and 1799 Bowditch made four lengthy sea voyages, and in 1802 he was put in command of a merchant vessel. Throughout that period he pursued his interest in mathematics. After investigating the accura...
</Question>
<Choice>Bowditch, Nathaniel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
archbishop of Canterbury, theologian, and mathematician.Bradwardine studied at Merton College, Oxford, and became a proctor there. About 1335 he moved to London, and in 1337 he was made chancellor of St. Paul's Cathedral. He became a royal chaplain and confessor to King Edward III. In 1349 he was made archbishop of Canterbury but died of the plague soon afterward during the Black Death.Bradwardine's most famous work in his day was a treatise on grace and free will entitled De causa Dei (1344), in which he so stressed the divine concurrence with all human volition that his followers concluded f...
</Question>
<Choice>Bradwardine, Thomas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
one of the most accomplished of the ancient Indian astronomers. He also had a profound and direct influence on Islamic and Byzantine astronomy.Brahmagupta was an orthodox Hindu, and his religious views, particularly the Hindu yuga system of measuring the ages of mankind, influenced his work. He severely criticized Jain cosmological views and other heterodox ideas, such as the view of Aryabhata I (b. 476) that the Earth is a spinning sphere, a view that was widely disseminated by Brahmagupta's contemporary and rival Bhaskara I.Brahmagupta's fame rests mostly on his Brahma-sphuta-siddhanta (628;...
</Question>
<Choice>Brahmagupta</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-born American mathematician and educator, a pioneer in the development of modern algebra.Brauer graduated from the University of Königsberg and received his Ph.D. in 1925 from the University of Berlin. He accepted a teaching position at Königsberg and remained there until 1933, when all Jews were dismissed from their academic posts in Germany. He immediately obtained a position in the United States at the University of Kentucky, and the following year he left to work with Hermann Weyl at the Institute for Advanced Study, Princeton, New Jersey. Their work later had a bearing on Nobel lau...
</Question>
<Choice>Brauer, Richard Dagobert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician who derived a geometrical theorem (now known as Brianchon's theorem) useful in the study of the properties of conic sections (circles, ellipses, parabolas, and hyperbolas) and who was innovative in applying the principle of duality to geometry.In 1804 Brianchon entered the École Polytechnique in Paris, where he became a student of the noted French mathematician Gaspard Monge. While still a student, he published his first paper, “Mémoire sur les surfaces courbes du second degré” (1806; “Memoir on Curved Surfaces of Second Degree”), in which he recognized the projective natu...
</Question>
<Choice>Brianchon, Charles-Julien</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English mathematician who invented the common, or Briggsian, logarithm. His writings were mainly responsible for the widespread acceptance of logarithms throughout Europe. His innovation was instrumental in easing the burden of mathematicians, astronomers, and other scientists who must make long and tedious calculations.About 1577 Briggs entered St. John's College, Cambridge, where he received a bachelor's degree in 1581 and a master's degree in 1585. He was elected a fellow of St. John's in 1589 and a lecturer in mathematics and medicine there in 1592. While at St. John's, Briggs began resear...
</Question>
<Choice>Briggs, Henry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polish-born British mathematician and man of letters who eloquently presented the case for the humanistic aspects of science.While Bronowski was still a child, his family immigrated to Germany and then to England, where he became a naturalized British subject. He won a scholarship to the University of Cambridge, where he studied mathematics. He not only achieved high honours in mathematics but also received critical acclaim for his poetry and prose. After receiving his Ph.D. (1933) from Cambridge, he taught mathematics (1934–42) at the University College of Hull. During World War II Bronowski...
</Question>
<Choice>Bronowski, Jacob</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch mathematician who founded mathematical intuitionism (a doctrine that views the nature of mathematics as mental constructions governed by self-evident laws) and whose work completely transformed topology, the study of the most basic properties of geometric surfaces and configurations.Brouwer studied mathematics at the University of Amsterdam from 1897 to 1904. Even then he was interested in philosophical matters, as evidenced by his Leven, Kunst, en Mystiek (1905; “Life, Art, and Mysticism”). In his doctoral thesis, “Over de grondslagen der wiskunde” (1907; “On the Foundations of Mathemat...
</Question>
<Choice>Brouwer, Luitzen Egbertus Jan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British-born American mathematician and astronomer known for his theory of the motion of the Moon.Educated at the University of Cambridge in England, Brown began there to study the motion of the Moon by a method devised by G.W. Hill of the United States. Hill had carried the process far enough to show its suitability for solving the problem, and Brown completed the theory. In 1919, after 30 years of work, Brown published his lunar tables, thereby making obsolescent those that had been in use for more than 60 years.Brown returned to Cambridge almost every summer, but he worked chiefly in the Un...
</Question>
<Choice>Brown, Ernest William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian philosopher, astronomer, mathematician, and occultist whose theories anticipated modern science. The most notable of these were his theories of the infinite universe and the multiplicity of worlds, in which he rejected the traditional geocentric (or Earth-centred) astronomy and intuitively went beyond the Copernican heliocentric (Sun-centred) theory, which still maintained a finite universe with a sphere of fixed stars. Bruno is, perhaps, chiefly remembered for the tragic death he suffered at the stake because of the tenacity with which he maintained his unorthodox ideas at a time when...
</Question>
<Choice>Bruno, Giordano</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
mathematician who invented logarithms independently of the Scottish mathematician John Napier.Bürgi served as court watchmaker to Duke Wilhelm IV of Hesse-Kassel from 1579 to 1592 and worked in the royal observatory at Kassel, where he developed geometrical and astronomical instruments. Word of his exceptional instruments reached Prague, where Holy Roman Emperor Rudolf II was trying to establish a science centre, and in about 1603 Bürgi journeyed to Prague to take up the post of imperial clockmaker. Later he also became assistant to the German astronomer Johannes Kepler.Bürgi was a major contr...
</Question>
<Choice>Burgi, Joost</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss-born U.S. educator and mathematician whose works on the history of mathematics were among the most eminent of his time.Cajori emigrated to the United States in 1875 and taught at Tulane University in New Orleans (1885–88) and at Colorado College (1889–1918), where he also served as dean of the department of engineering (1903–18). In 1918 he became professor of the history of mathematics at the University of California, Berkeley.His major works include A History of Mathematics (2nd ed. 1919), A History of Mathematical Notations, 2 vol. (1928–29), A History of Physics in Its Elementary Bra...
</Question>
<Choice>Cajori, Florian</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German mathematician who founded set theory and introduced the mathematically meaningful concept of transfinite numbers, indefinitely large but distinct from one another.
</Question>
<Choice>Cantor, Georg Ferdinand Ludwig Philipp</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German historian of mathematics, one of the greatest of the 19th century.Cantor spent his career at the University of Heidelberg, where he began as a tutor in 1853. His first important book was Mathematische Beiträge zum Kulturleben der Völker (1863; “Mathematical Contributions to the Cultural Life of the People”). It was followed by his Vorlesungen über Geschichte der Mathematik (“Lectures on the History of Mathematics”), the first volume of which was published in 1880, the second in 1892, and the third in successive parts between 1894 and 1896. By this time Cantor was too old to undertake th...
</Question>
<Choice>Cantor, Moritz Benedikt</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German mathematician of Greek origin who made important contributions to the theory of real functions, to the calculus of variations, and to the theory of point-set measure.After two years as an assistant engineer with the British Asyu? Dam project in Egypt, Carathéodory began his study of mathematics at the University of Berlin in 1900. In 1902 he entered the University of Göttingen, where he received his Ph.D. (1904) under the German mathematician Hermann Minkowski. After teaching at the Universities of Hannover (1909), Breslau (1910–13), Göttingen (1913–18), and Berlin (1918–20), he accepte...
</Question>
<Choice>Caratheodory, Constantin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian physician, mathematician, and astrologer who gave the first clinical description of typhus fever and whose book Ars magna (The Great Art; or, The Rules of Algebra) is one of the cornerstones in the history of algebra.Educated at the universities of Pavia and Padua, Cardano received his medical degree in 1526. In 1534 he moved to Milan, where he lived in great poverty until he became a lecturer in mathematics. Admitted to the college of physicians in 1539, he soon became rector. His fame as a physician grew rapidly, and many of Europe's crowned heads solicited his services; however, he...
</Question>
<Choice>Cardano, Girolamo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician who greatly developed the theory of Lie groups and contributed to the theory of subalgebras.In 1894 Cartan became a lecturer at the University of Montpellier, where he studied the structure of continuous groups introduced by the noted Norwegian mathematician Sophus Lie. He later examined theories of equivalence and their relation to the theory of integral invariants, mechanics, and the general theory of relativity. After he moved to the University of Lyon in 1896, he worked on linear associative algebra, developing general theorems based on the work of Benjamin Peirce of H...
</Question>
<Choice>Cartan, Elie-Joseph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician who made fundamental advances in the theory of analytic functions.Son of the distinguished mathematician Élie Cartan, Henri Cartan began his academic career as professor of mathematics at the Lycée Caen (1928–29). He was appointed deputy professor at the University of Lille in 1929 and two years later became professor of mathematics at the University of Strasbourg. In 1940 he joined the faculty of the University of Paris, where he remained until 1965; from 1970 to 1975 he taught at Orsay.Cartan ran an influential seminar for many years, and contributed to the theory of she...
</Question>
<Choice>Cartan, Henri-Paul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician who pioneered in analysis and the theory of substitution groups (groups whose elements are ordered sequences of a set of things). He was one of the greatest of modern mathematicians.At the onset of the Reign of Terror (1793–94) during the French Revolution, Cauchy's family fled from Paris to the village of Arcueil, where Cauchy first became acquainted with the mathematician Pierre-Simon Laplace and the chemist Claude-Louis Berthollet.Cauchy became a military engineer and in 1810 went to Cherbourg to work on the harbours and fortifications for Napoleon's English invasion fl...
</Question>
<Choice>Cauchy, Augustin-Louis, Baron</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian mathematician who made developments in geometry that were precursors to integral calculus.As a boy Cavalieri joined the Jesuati, a religious order (sometimes called “Apostolic Clerics of St. Jerome”) that followed the rule of St. Augustine and was suppressed in 1668 by Pope Clement IX. Euclid's works stimulated his interest in mathematics, and, after he met Galileo, Cavalieri considered himself a disciple of that great astronomer.By 1629, when he was appointed professor of mathematics of the University of Bologna, Cavalieri had completely developed his method of indivisibles, a means o...
</Question>
<Choice>Cavalieri, Francesco Bonaventura</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English mathematician and leader of the British school of pure mathematics that emerged in the 19th century. The interested viewer may read an extract from the geometry article he wrote for the 9th edition of the Encyclopædia Britannica (1875–89).Although Cayley was born in England, his first seven years were spent in St. Petersburg, Russia, where his parents lived in a trading community affiliated with the Muscovy Company. On the family's permanent return to England in 1828 he was educated at a small private school in Blackheath, followed by the three-year course at King's College, London. Ca...
</Question>
<Choice>Cayley, Arthur</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian mathematician, physicist, and hydraulic engineer best known for the geometric theorem bearing his name concerning straight lines that intersect at a common point when drawn through the vertices of a triangle.The details of Ceva's early life are known only through his correspondence and the prefaces to some of his works. He was educated in a Jesuit college in Milan and then at the University of Pisa, where the work of Galileo Galilei (1564–1642) and his followers on geometry and mechanics exerted a great influence on his education and research interests. He may have taught in Pisa durin...
</Question>
<Choice>Ceva, Giovanni</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jesuit mathematician and poet, who was the younger brother of Giovanni Ceva.In 1663 Tommaso Ceva entered the Society of Jesus at the Brera College in Milan and soon became a professor of rhetoric and mathematics, teaching at Brera for more than 40 years. Ceva's only mathematical work is Opuscula mathematica (1699; “Mathematical Essays”), which collects his papers on physics, arithmetic, and geometry. Ceva's “scientific” work, De natura gravium (1699; “The Nature of Gravity”), deals with gravity from a philosophical and theological perspective.Ceva's fame derives primarily from his Latin verses...
</Question>
<Choice>Ceva, Tommaso</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician, physicist, and inventor who, with Nicolas Robert, was the first to ascend in a hydrogen balloon (1783). About 1787 he developed Charles's law (q.v.) concerning the thermal expansion of gases.From clerking in the finance ministry Charles turned to science and experimented with electricity. He developed several inventions, including a hydrometer and reflecting goniometer, and improved the Gravesand heliostat and Fahrenheit's aerometer. With the Robert brothers, Nicolas and Anne-Jean, he built one of the first hydrogen balloons (1783). In several flights he rose more than a...
</Question>
<Choice>Charles, Jacques-Alexandre-Cesar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician who, independently of the Swiss German mathematician Jakob Steiner, elaborated on the theory of modern projective geometry, the study of the properties of a geometric line or other plane figure that remain unchanged when the figure is projected onto a plane from a point not on either the plane or the figure.Chasles was born near Chartres and entered the École Polytechnique in 1812. He was eventually made professor of geodesy and mechanics there in 1841. His Aperçu historique sur l'origine et le développement des méthodes en géométrie (1837; “Historical Survey of the Origin...
</Question>
<Choice>Chasles, Michel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician and physicist who was the mistress of Voltaire.She was married at 19 to the Marquis Florent du Châtelet, governor of Semur-en-Auxois, with whom she had three children. The marquis then took up a military career and thereafter saw his wife only infrequently. Mme du Châtelet returned to Paris and its dazzling social life in 1730 and had several lovers before entering into an affair and intellectual alliance with Voltaire in 1733. She was able to extricate the intemperate Voltaire from many personal and political difficulties, such as those that followed the publication of hi...
</Question>
<Choice>
Chatelet, Gabrielle-Emilie Le Tonnelier de Breteuil, Marquise du
</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
founder of the St. Petersburg mathematical school (sometimes called the Chebyshev school), who is remembered primarily for his work on the theory of prime numbers and on the approximation of functions.Chebyshev became assistant professor of mathematics at the University of St. Petersburg (now St. Petersburg State University) in 1847. In 1860 he became a correspondent and in 1874 a foreign associate of the Institut de France. He developed a basic inequality of probability theory called Chebyshev's inequality, a generalized form of the Bienaymé-Chebyshev inequality, and used the latter inequalit...
</Question>
<Choice>Chebyshev, Pafnuty Lvovich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese American mathematician and educator whose researches in differential geometry developed ideas that now play a major role in mathematics and in mathematical physics.Chern graduated from Nankai University in Tianjin, China, in 1930; he received an M.S. degree in 1934 from Tsinghua University in Beijing and a doctor of sciences degree from the University of Hamburg (Germany) in 1936. A year later he returned to Tsinghua as professor of mathematics. Chern was a member of the Institute for Advanced Study at Princeton, New Jersey, from 1943 to 1945. In 1946 he returned to China to become act...
</Question>
<Choice>Chern, Shiing-shen</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British philosopher and mathematician who, influenced by the non-Euclidean geometries of Bernhard Riemann and Nikolay Lobachevsky, wrote “On the Space-Theory of Matter” (1876). He presented the idea that matter and energy are simply different types of curvature of space, thus foreshadowing Albert Einstein's general theory of relativity.Clifford was educated at King's College, London, and at Trinity College, Cambridge, and was elected a fellow of the latter in 1868. In 1871 he was named professor of mathematics at University College, London. Three years later he was elected a fellow of the Roya...
</Question>
<Choice>Clifford, William Kingdon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
reputed English author of Cocker's Arithmetic, a famous textbook, the popularity of which gave rise to the phrase “according to Cocker,” meaning “quite correct.”Cocker worked very skillfully as an engraver and is mentioned favourably in Samuel Pepys' Diary. His other works include several writing manuals, poems for transcription or translation, and an English dictionary. In 1657 Cocker was living in London, where he also taught writing and arithmetic. The Arithmetic was edited and published in 1678 and passed through more than 100 editions. A 19th-century writer declared the editor of the 1678...
</Question>
<Choice>Cocker, Edward</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American mathematician, who was awarded the Fields Medal in 1966 for his proof of the independence of the continuum hypothesis from the other axioms of set theory.Cohen attended the University of Chicago (M.S., 1954; Ph.D., 1958). He held appointments at the University of Rochester, N.Y. (1957–58), and the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (1958–59) before joining the Institute for Advanced Study, Princeton, N.J. (1959–61). In 1961 he moved to Stanford University in California; he became professor emeritus in 2004.Cohen was awarded the Fields Medal at the International Congress of Mathemat...
</Question>
<Choice>Cohen, Paul Joseph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. sociologist, a pioneer in mathematical sociology whose studies strongly influenced education policy in the United States.Coleman received his B.S. from Purdue University (1949) and his Ph.D. from Columbia University (1955), where he was a research associate in the Bureau of Applied Social Research (1953–55). While there he was influenced by the style and ability of Paul Lazarsfeld to stimulate creative problem-solving, an influence demonstrated in two major works: Introduction to Mathematical Sociology (1964) and Mathematics of Collective Action (1973).Coleman was a fellow at the Center f...
</Question>
<Choice>Coleman, James S.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician who won the Fields Medal in 1982 for his work in operator theory.Connes received a bachelor's degree (1970) and a doctorate (1973) from the École Normale Supérieure (now part of the University of Paris). He held appointments at the National Centre for Scientific Research, Paris (1970–74; 1981–84); Queen's University, Kingston, Ont., Can. (1975); the University of Paris VI (1976–80); the Institute of Advanced Scientific Studies, Bures-sur-Yvette, France (1979– ); Collège de France, Paris (1984– ); and Vanderbilt University, Nashville, Tenn., U.S. (2003– ).Connes received th...
</Question>
<Choice>Connes, Alain</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
mathematician and astronomer whose work on conic sections (curves of the intersections of a right circular cone with a plane) served as the basis for the fourth book of the Conics of Apollonius of Perga (c. 262–190 BC).From his observations in Italy and Sicily, Conon compiled the parapegma, a calendar of meteorological forecasts and of the risings and settings of the stars. He settled in Alexandria, where he served as court astronomer to Ptolemy III Euergetes I (reigned 246–221). When Berenice II, the consort of Ptolemy III, dedicated her hair as an offering in a temple of Aphrodite and the of...
</Question>
<Choice>Conon of Samos</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. mathematician and educator who published numerous works on theoretical mathematics along the lines of the Study-Segre school.Coolidge was born to a family of well-established Bostonians; his paternal grandmother was Thomas Jefferson's granddaughter. Following the family tradition, Coolidge attended Exeter Academy and then Harvard College where, in 1895, he graduated summa cum laude. He next enrolled at Oxford and in 1897 received the first B.Sc. ever awarded by that university. For two years he taught mathematics at the Groton School before joining the mathematics department at Harvard in...
</Question>
<Choice>Coolidge, Julian Lowell</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French engineer and mathematician who first described the Coriolis force, an effect of motion on a rotating body, of paramount importance to meteorology, ballistics, and oceanography.An assistant professor of analysis and mechanics at the École Polytechnique, Paris (1816–38), he introduced the terms work and kinetic energy in their modern scientific meanings in his first major book, Du calcul de l'effet des machines (1829; “On the Calculation of Mechanical Action”), in which he attempted to adapt theoretical principles to applied mechanics.In 1835 he published a paper, “Sur les équations du mo...
</Question>
<Choice>Coriolis, Gustave-Gaspard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-born American mathematician and educator who made significant advances in the calculus of variations.Courant received his secondary education in Germany and Switzerland and his doctorate from the University of Göttingen in 1910 under David Hilbert. For the next four years he taught mathematics at Göttingen. Then, at age 26, his teaching and research were interrupted by World War I. A few years after the war, Courant returned to Göttingen, where he founded and, from 1920 until 1933, was director of the university's mathematics institute. While at the institute he wrote a two-volume treat...
</Question>
<Choice>Courant, Richard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French economist and mathematician. Cournot was the first economist who, with competent knowledge of both subjects, endeavoured to apply mathematics to the treatment of economics. His main work in economics is Recherches sur les principes mathématiques de la théorie des richesses (1838; Researches into the Mathematical Principles of the Theory of Wealth). His primary concern was the analysis of partial market equilibrium, which he based on the assumption that participants in the process of exchange are either producers or merchants whose goal is the maximization of profit. He therefore ignored...
</Question>
<Choice>Cournot, Antoine-Augustin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German mathematician and engineer who advanced the work and careers of many young mathematicians of his day and founded the Journal für die reine und angewandte Mathematik (“Journal for Pure and Applied Mathematics”), now known as Crelle's Journal.A civil engineer in the service of the Prussian government until 1828, he worked on the planning and construction of roads and the first railroad (completed 1838) in Germany. Crelle was more interested in educational matters, however, and in 1828 he left government service to work with the Ministry of Ecclesiastical Affairs and Public Education. His...
</Question>
<Choice>Crelle, August Leopold</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian mathematician who was an originator of graphical statics, the use of graphical methods to study forces in equilibrium.Following his appointment as professor of higher geometry at the University of Bologna in 1860, he published “Introduzione ad una teoria geometrica delle curve piane” (1862; “Introduction to a Geometrical Theory of the Plane Curve”), his first paper on transformations (rules that associate with every point in a space one or more points in the same space) in planes and in space. This paper, upon which his reputation mainly rests, proclaims him a member of the Steinerian,...
</Question>
<Choice>Cremona, Antonio Luigi Gaudenzio Giuseppe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician who made important contributions to geometry and analysis and after whom the Darboux integral is named.After acting as an assistant in mathematical physics (1866–67) at the Collège de France, Paris, Darboux taught at the Lycée Louis le Grand (1867–72), the École Normale Supérieure (1872–73), and the Sorbonne (1873–90). Besides being an excellent teacher and a notable mathematician, he was a very capable administrator.Practically all Darboux's mathematical work was in geometry. His early papers (1864 and 1866) on orthogonal surfaces were followed by a memoir (1870) on parti...
</Question>
<Choice>Darboux, Jean-Gaston</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English mathematician and logician whose major contributions to the study of logic include the formulation of De Morgan's laws and work leading to the development of the theory of relations and the rise of modern symbolic, or mathematical, logic.De Morgan was educated at Trinity College, Cambridge. In 1828 he became professor of mathematics at the newly established University College in London, where, except for a period of five years (1831–36), he taught until 1866, when he helped found and became the first president of the London Mathematical Society. One of his earliest works, Elements of A...
</Question>
<Choice>De Morgan, Augustus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German mathematician who developed a major redefinition of irrational numbers in terms of arithmetic concepts. Although not fully recognized in his lifetime, his treatment of the ideas of the infinite and of what constitutes a real number continues to influence modern mathematics.Dedekind was the son of a lawyer. While attending the Gymnasium Martino-Catharineum in 1838–47 in Braunschweig, he was at first interested primarily in chemistry and physics. At the Caroline College in 1848–50, however, he turned to calculus, algebra, and analytic geometry, which helped qualify him to study advanced m...
</Question>
<Choice>Dedekind, Julius Wilhelm Richard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English mathematician, natural philosopher, and student of the occult.Dee entered St. John's College, Cambridge, in 1542, where he earned a bachelor's degree (1545) and a master's degree (1548); he also was made a fellow of Trinity College, Cambridge, on its founding in 1546. Dee furthered his scientific studies on the Continent with a short visit in 1547 and then from 1548 to 1551 under the mathematician-cartographers Pedro Nuñez, Gemma Frisius, Abraham Ortelius, and Gerardus Mercator, as well as through his own studies in Paris and elsewhere. Dee turned down a mathematical professorship at t...
</Question>
<Choice>Dee, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician and astronomer whose theory of lunar motion advanced the development of planetary-motion theories.Delaunay was educated as an engineer at the École des Mines from 1836, becoming an engineer in 1843 and chief engineer in 1858. He studied mathematics and astronomy with Jean-Baptiste Biot at the Sorbonne (1841–48). He taught mechanics at the École Polytechnique from 1850 and also later taught at the École des Mines. He was made a member of the Académie des Sciences in 1855; and in 1870 he succeeded U.-J.-J. Le Verrier as director of the Paris Observatory.He wrote Cours élémen...
</Question>
<Choice>Delaunay, Charles-Eugene</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Belgian mathematician who was awarded the Fields Medal at the International Congress of Mathematicians in Helsinki, Fin., in 1978 for his work in algebraic geometry.Deligne received a bachelor's degree in mathematics (1966) and a doctorate (1968) from the Free University of Brussels. After a year at the National Foundation for Scientific Research, Brussels, he joined the Institute of Advanced Scientific Studies, Bures-sur-Yvette, France, in 1968. In 1984 he became a professor at the Institute for Advanced Study, Princeton, N.J., U.S.In 1949 the French mathematician André Weil made a series of...
</Question>
<Choice>Deligne, Pierre Rene</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician who figures prominently in the history of projective geometry. Desargues's work was well known by his contemporaries, but half a century after his death he was forgotten. His work was rediscovered at the beginning of the 19th century, and one of his results became known as Desargues's theorem.Not much is known about Desargues's early life, which he spent in Lyon where his father worked for the local diocese. In 1626 Desargues proposed a water project to the municipality of Paris, and by 1630 he had become associated with a group of Parisian mathematicians gathered around F...
</Question>
<Choice>Desargues, Girard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American mathematician who made important contributions to the theory of numbers and the theory of groups.Appointed associate professor of mathematics at the University of Texas at Austin in 1899, Dickson joined the staff of the University of Chicago in 1900, where he remained until 1939. A prolific mathematician, Dickson published the first extensive work on the theory of finite fields and expanded the Wedderburn and Cartan theories of linear associative algebras. One of his most-engrossing studies concerned the relationships between the theory of invariants and number theory. Using the analy...
</Question>
<Choice>Dickson, Leonard Eugene</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician and educator known for his writings on abstract algebra, functional analysis, topology, and his theory of Lie groups.Dieudonné was educated in Paris, receiving both his bachelor's degree (1927) and his doctorate (1931) from the École Normale Supérieure. He was a founding member of the Nicolas Bourbaki (q.v.) group in the mid-1930s. After teaching at universities in Rennes and Nancy, France, and in São Paulo, Brazil, Dieudonné came to the United States in 1952 and taught mathematics at the University of Michigan and at Northwestern University. He returned to Paris to teach...
</Question>
<Choice>Dieudonne, Jean</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek mathematician, famous for his work in algebra.What little is known of Diophantus's life is circumstantial. From the appellation “of Alexandria” it seems that he worked in the main scientific centre of the ancient Greek world; and because he is not mentioned before the 4th century, it seems likely that he flourished during the 3rd century. An arithmetic epigram from the Anthologia Graeca of late antiquity, purported to retrace some landmarks of his life (marriage at 33, birth of his son at 38, death of his son four years before his own at 84), may well be contrived. Two works have come do...
</Question>
<Choice>Diophantus of Alexandria</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German mathematician who made valuable contributions to number theory, analysis, and mechanics. He taught at the universities of Breslau (1827) and Berlin (1828–55) and in 1855 succeeded Carl Friedrich Gauss at the University of Göttingen.Dirichlet made notable contributions still associated with his name in many fields of mathematics. In number theory he proved the existence of an infinite number of primes in any arithmetic series a + b, 2a + b, 3a + b, . . . , na + b, in which a and b are not divisible by one another. He developed the general theory of units in algebraic number theory. His V...
</Question>
<Choice>Dirichlet, Peter Gustav Lejeune</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British mathematician who was awarded the Fields Medal in 1986 for his work in topology.Donaldson attended Pembroke College, Cambridge (B.A., 1979), and Worcester College, Oxford (Ph.D., 1983). From 1983 to 1985 he was a Junior Research Fellow at All Souls College, Oxford, before becoming a fellow and professor at St. Anne's College, Oxford. In 1997 Donaldson joined the faculty of Stanford University in California, U.S., and in 1999 became a professor at Imperial College, London.Donaldson was awarded the Fields Medal at the International Congress of Mathematicians in Berkeley, California, in 1...
</Question>
<Choice>Donaldson, Simon Kirwan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American mathematician who was awarded one of the first two Fields Medals in 1936 for solving the Plateau problem.Douglas attended City College of New York and Columbia University (Ph.D., 1920). He remained at Columbia until 1926, when he was awarded a National Research Fellowship. He subsequently held appointments at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (1930–36) and the Institute for Advanced Study, Princeton, New Jersey. In 1942 he returned to New York, where he taught at Columbia (1942–54) and City College (1955–65).Douglas was awarded one of the first two Fields Medals at the Interna...
</Question>
<Choice>Douglas, Jesse</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician and physicist who proposed a theory dealing with the transmission of heat in crystal structures, based on the work of the French mathematicians Jean-Baptiste-Joseph Fourier and Siméon-Denis Poisson.Duhamel attended the École Polytechnique in Paris from 1814 to 1816 before moving to Rennes to study jurisprudence. He later returned to Paris where he taught at the Institut Massin and the Collège Louis-le-Grand. In 1830 he began teaching analysis at the École Polytechnique, where, highly regarded as a teacher, he remained until his retirement in 1869. While at the École he eng...
</Question>
<Choice>Duhamel, Jean-Marie-Constant</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English astronomer, physicist, and mathematician who did his greatest work in astrophysics, investigating the motion, internal structure, and evolution of stars. He also was the first expositor of the theory of relativity in the English language.
</Question>
<Choice>Eddington, Sir Arthur Stanley</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Irish economist and statistician who innovatively applied mathematics to the fields of economics and statistics.Edgeworth was educated at Trinity College in Dublin and Balliol College, Oxford, graduating in 1869. In 1877 he qualified as a barrister. He lectured at King's College in London from 1880, becoming professor of political economy in 1888. From 1891 to 1922 he was Drummond Professor of Economics at Oxford. He also played an important role as editor of the Economic Journal (1891–1926).Although Edgeworth was strong in mathematics, he was weak at prose, and his publications failed to reac...
</Question>
<Choice>Edgeworth, Francis Ysidro</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German mathematician who made important contributions to number theory.Eisenstein's family converted to Protestantism from Judaism just before his birth. He was the oldest of six children and the only one of them to survive childhood meningitis. Eisenstein entered the Friedrich Wilhelm University (now the Humboldt University of Berlin) in 1843 and the following year published 25 papers in August Leopold Crelle's prestigious mathematical journal. Crelle introduced him to the naturalist Alexander von Humboldt, who became his lifelong mentor and sponsor. Humboldt in turn encouraged an exchange of...
</Question>
<Choice>Eisenstein, Ferdinand Gotthold Max</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hungarian “freelance” mathematician (known for his work in number theory and combinatorics) and legendary eccentric who was arguably the most prolific mathematician of the 20th century, in terms of both the number of problems he solved and the number of problems he convinced others to tackle.The son of two high-school mathematics teachers, Erdös had two sisters, ages three and five, who contracted scarlet fever and died the day he was born. His mother, fearing that he, too, might contract a fatal childhood disease, kept him home from school until the age of 10. With his father confined to a Ru...
</Question>
<Choice>Erdos, Paul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the most prominent mathematician of Greco-Roman antiquity, best known for his treatise on geometry, the Elements.
</Question>
<Choice>Euclid</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek mathematician and astronomer who substantially advanced proportion theory, contributed to the identification of constellations and thus to the development of observational astronomy in the Greek world, and established the first sophisticated, geometrical model of celestial motion. He also wrote on geography and contributed to philosophical discussions in Plato's Academy. Although none of his writings survive, his contributions are known from many discussions throughout antiquity.
</Question>
<Choice>Eudoxus of Cnidus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss mathematician and physicist, one of the founders of pure mathematics. He not only made decisive and formative contributions to the subjects of geometry, calculus, mechanics, and number theory but also developed methods for solving problems in observational astronomy and demonstrated useful applications of mathematics in technology and public affairs.Euler's mathematical ability earned him the esteem of Johann Bernoulli, one of the first mathematicians in Europe at that time, and of his sons Daniel and Nicolas. In 1727 he moved to St. Petersburg, where he became an associate of the St. Pe...
</Question>
<Choice>Euler, Leonhard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician who is often called the founder of the modern theory of numbers. Together with René Descartes, Fermat was one of the two leading mathematicians of the first half of the 17th century. Independently of Descartes, Fermat discovered the fundamental principle of analytic geometry. His methods for finding tangents to curves and their maximum and minimum points led him to be regarded as the inventor of the differential calculus. Through his correspondence with Blaise Pascal he was a co-founder of the theory of probability.
</Question>
<Choice>Fermat, Pierre de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian mathematician who was the first to find an algebraic solution to the biquadratic, or quartic, equation (an algebraic equation that contains the fourth power of the unknown quantity but no higher power).From a poor family, Ferrari was taken into the service of the noted Italian mathematician Gerolamo Cardano as an errand boy at the age of 15. By attending Cardano's lectures, he learned Latin, Greek, and mathematics. In 1540 he succeeded Cardano as public mathematics lecturer in Milan, at which time he found the solution of the quartic equation, later published in Cardano's Ars magna (15...
</Question>
<Choice>Ferrari, Lodovico</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician, known also as an Egyptologist and administrator, who exerted strong influence on mathematical physics through his Théorie analytique de la chaleur (1822; The Analytical Theory of Heat). He showed how the conduction of heat in solid bodies may be analyzed in terms of infinite mathematical series now called by his name, the Fourier series. Far transcending the particular subject of heat conduction, his work stimulated research in mathematical physics, which has since been often identified with the solution of boundary-value problems, encompassing many natural occurrences su...
</Question>
<Choice>Fourier, Jean-Baptiste-Joseph, Baron</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician known chiefly for his contributions to real analysis. He is credited with being the founder of the theory of abstract spaces.Fréchet was professor of mechanics at the University of Poitiers (1910–19) before moving to the University of Strasbourg, where he was professor of higher calculus (1920–27). Joining the faculty of the University of Paris, he served as lecturer on the calculus of probabilities (1928–33), professor of general mathematics (1933–35), professor of differential and integral calculus (1935–40), and professor of the calculus of probabilities (1940–48).Fréch...
</Question>
<Choice>Frechet, Maurice</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish mathematician who founded modern integral equation theory.Fredholm entered the University of Uppsala in 1886. There, and later at the University of Stockholm (1888–93), he was mainly interested in mathematical physics. After receiving his Ph.D. from Uppsala in 1898, he turned to integral equations. He also worked as an actuary until 1906, when he was appointed professor of theoretical physics at the University of Stockholm.In a paper that appeared in 1900 entitled “Sur une nouvelle méthode pour la résolution du problème de Dirichlet” (“On a New Method for the Resolution of Dirichlet's...
</Question>
<Choice>Fredholm, Ivar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American mathematician who was awarded the Fields Medal in 1986 for his solution of the Poincaré conjecture in four dimensions.Freedman received his Ph.D. from Princeton (N.J.) University in 1973. Following appointments at the University of California, Berkeley (1973–75), and the Institute for Advanced Study, Princeton, N.J. (1975–76), Freedman became a professor at the University of California, San Diego, in 1976. In 1998 he became the first Fields Medal winner to leave the academic world when he accepted a position with the Theory Group at Microsoft Research, a division of Microsoft Corporat...
</Question>
<Choice>Freedman, Michael Hartley</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German mathematician and logician, who founded modern mathematical logic. Working on the borderline between philosophy and mathematics—viz., in the philosophy of mathematics and mathematical logic (in which no intellectual precedents existed)—Frege discovered, on his own, the fundamental ideas that have made possible the whole modern development of logic and thereby invented an entire discipline.Frege was the son of Alexander Frege, a principal of a girls' high school in Wismar. His mother, Auguste Frege, née Bialloblotzky, who was perhaps of Polish origin, outlived her husband, who died in 18...
</Question>
<Choice>Frege, Friedrich Ludwig Gottlob</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian mathematician and physical scientist.After graduating from the University of St. Petersburg in 1910, Friedmann joined the Pavlovsk Aerological Observatory and, during World War I, did aerological work for the Russian army. After the war he was on the staff of the University of Perm (1918–20) and then on the staffs of the Main Physical Observatory and other institutions until his death in 1925.In 1922–24 Friedmann used Einstein'sgeneral theory of relativity to formulate the mathematics of a dynamic (time-dependent) universe. (Einstein and Dutch mathematician Willem de Sitter had earlier...
</Question>
<Choice>Friedmann, Aleksandr Aleksandrovich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian mathematician, astronomer, and physicist who is best known for his work in hydraulics. His most significant contributions to science, however, were in the compilation, interpretation, and dissemination of the work of other scientists.Frisi was a member of the Barnabite religious order, a professor at the University of Milan, and a member of most of the major scientific societies of his time. He was held in such esteem by his contemporaries that plans for nearly all the major hydraulic works constructed in northern Italy during his adult life were first shown to him for his inspection....
</Question>
<Choice>Frisi, Paolo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German mathematician who made major contributions to group theory.Frobenius studied for one year at the University of Göttingen before returning home in 1868 to study at the University of Berlin. After receiving a doctorate in 1870, he taught at various secondary schools before he became an assistant professor of mathematics at the University of Berlin in 1874. He was appointed a professor of mathematics at the Federal Polytechnic in Zürich, Switzerland, in 1875. Frobenius finally returned to the University of Berlin in 1892 to occupy the mathematics chair vacated by the death of Leopold Krone...
</Question>
<Choice>Frobenius, Georg</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. engineer and architect who developed the geodesic dome, the only large dome that can be set directly on the ground as a complete structure, and the only practical kind of building that has no limiting dimensions (i.e., beyond which the structural strength must be insufficient). Among the most noteworthy geodesic domes is the United States pavilion for Expo 67 in Montreal. Also a poet and a philosopher, he was noted for unorthodox ideas on global issues.
</Question>
<Choice>Fuller, R. Buckminster</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian natural philosopher, astronomer, and mathematician who made fundamental contributions to the sciences of motion, astronomy, and strength of materials and to the development of the scientific method. His formulation of (circular) inertia, the law of falling bodies, and parabolic trajectories marked the beginning of a fundamental change in the study of motion. His insistence that the book of nature was written in the language of mathematics changed natural philosophy from a verbal, qualitative account to a mathematical one in which experimentation became a recognized method for discoveri...
</Question>
<Choice>Galileo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician famous for his contributions to the part of higher algebra now known as group theory. His theory provided a solution to the long-standing question of determining when an algebraic equation can be solved by radicals (a solution containing square roots, cube roots, and so on but no trigonometry functions or other nonalgebraic functions).Galois was the son of Nicolas-Gabriel Galois, an important citizen in the Paris suburb of Bourg-la-Reine. In 1815, during the Hundred Days regime that followed Napoleon's escape from Elba, his father was elected mayor. Galois was educated at...
</Question>
<Choice>Galois, Evariste</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German mathematician, generally regarded as one of the greatest mathematicians of all time for his contributions to number theory, geometry, probability theory, geodesy, planetary astronomy, the theory of functions, and potential theory (including electromagnetism).Gauss was the only child of poor parents. He was rare among mathematicians in that he was a calculating prodigy, and he retained the ability to do elaborate calculations in his head most of his life. Impressed by this ability and by his gift for languages, his teachers and his devoted mother recommended him to the duke of Brunswick...
</Question>
<Choice>Gauss, Carl Friedrich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian mathematician who originated basic techniques in the study of transcendental numbers (numbers that cannot be expressed as the root or solution of an algebraic equation with rational coefficients). He profoundly advanced transcendental number theory and the theory of interpolation and approximation of complex variable functions.Gelfond taught mathematics at the Moscow Technological College (1929–30) and, from 1931, at Moscow State University, at various times holding chairs of analysis, number theory, and history of mathematics.In 1934 Gelfond proved that ab is transcendental if a is an...
</Question>
<Choice>Gelfond, Aleksandr Osipovich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician who contributed notably to the study of acoustics, elasticity, and the theory of numbers.As a girl Germain read widely in her father's library and then later, using the pseudonym of M. Le Blanc, managed to obtain lecture notes for courses from the newly organized École Polytechnique in Paris. It was through the École Polytechnique that she met the mathematician Joseph-Louis Lagrange, who remained a strong source of support and encouragement to her for several years. Germain's early work was in number theory, her interest having been stimulated by Adrien-Marie Legendre's Th...
</Question>
<Choice>Germain, Sophie</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian statistician and demographer.Gini was educated at Bologna, where he studied law, mathematics, economics, and biology. He was a statistics professor at Cagliari in 1909 and at Padua in 1913. After founding the statistical journal Metron (1920), Gini became a professor at the University of Rome (1925). At Rome he pioneered in the teaching of sociology, treating the subject as a study of populations and their measurable characteristics, drawing on biological concepts for his view of social development. His statistical studies began with the relationship of probability to population statis...
</Question>
<Choice>Gini, Corrado</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian-born mathematician, logician, and philosopher who obtained what may be the most important mathematical result of the 20th century: his famous incompleteness theorem, which states that within any axiomatic mathematical system there are propositions that cannot be proved or disproved on the basis of the axioms within that system; thus, such a system cannot be simultaneously complete and consistent. This proof established Gödel as one of the greatest logicians since Aristotle, and its repercussions continue to be felt and debated today.
</Question>
<Choice>Godel, Kurt</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian mathematician whose contributions to number theory include Goldbach's conjecture.In 1725 Goldbach became professor of mathematics and historian of the Imperial Academy at St. Petersburg. Three years later he went to Moscow as tutor to Tsar Peter II, and from 1742 he served as a staff member of the Russian Ministry of Foreign Affairs.Goldbach first proposed the conjecture that bears his name in a letter to the Swiss mathematician Leonhard Euler in 1742. He claimed that “every number greater than 2 is an aggregate of three prime numbers.” Because mathematicians in Goldbach's day consider...
</Question>
<Choice>Goldbach, Christian</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British mathematician who won the Fields Medal in 1998 for his work in the theory of Banach spaces.Gowers studied undergraduate mathematics at the University of Cambridge and went on to finish his doctorate there in 1990. He held teaching and research positions at Cambridge and at University College, London.Gowers received the Fields Medal at the International Congress of Mathematicians in Berlin in 1998 for his solution of several outstanding problems of Banach spaces. His dichotomy theorem asserts that either every subspace of a given Banach space has many symmetries or the subspaces have on...
</Question>
<Choice>Gowers, William Timothy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German mathematician chiefly remembered for his development of a general calculus of vectors in Die lineale Ausdehnungslehre, ein neuer Zweig der Mathematik (1844; “The Theory of Linear Extension, a New Branch of Mathematics”).Grassmann taught at the Gymnasium in Stettin from 1831 until his death, except for two years (1834–36) of teaching at an industrial school in Berlin. He pursued wide interests, writing on electricity, colour, acoustics, linguistics, botany, and folklore.In Ausdehnungslehre Grassmann developed Gottfried Leibniz' idea of an algebra in which symbols representing geometric e...
</Question>
<Choice>Grassmann, Hermann Gunther</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English mathematician who was first to attempt to devise a theory of electricity and magnetism. This work heralded the beginning of modern mathematical physics in Great Britain.The son of a prosperous miller and a miller by trade himself, Green was almost completely self-taught in mathematical physics; he published his most important work five years before he went to the University of Cambridge at the age of 40. That he was self-taught may explain his unusual methods of solving physical problems.In his Essay on the Application of Mathematical Analysis to the Theory of Electricity and Magnetism...
</Question>
<Choice>Green, George</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish mathematician and astronomer who discovered infinite series representations for a number of trigonometry functions, although he is mostly remembered for his description of the first practical reflecting telescope, now known as the Gregorian telescope.The son of an Anglican priest, Gregory received his early education from his mother. After his father's death in 1650, he was sent to Aberdeen, first to grammar school and then to Marischal College, graduating from the latter in 1657. (This Protestant college was combined with the Roman Catholic King's College in 1860 to form the Universi...
</Question>
<Choice>Gregory, James</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German French mathematician who was awarded the Fields Medal in 1966 for his work in algebraic geometry.After studies at the University of Montpellier (France) and a year at the École Normale Supérieure in Paris, Grothendieck received his doctorate from the University of Nancy (France) in 1953. After appointments at the University of São Paulo in Brazil and the University of Kansas and Harvard University in the United States, he accepted a position at the Institute of Advanced Scientific Studies, Bures-sur-Yvette, France, in 1959. He left in 1970, eventually settling at the University of Montp...
</Question>
<Choice>Grothendieck, Alexandre</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English mathematician who invented many useful measuring devices, including a forerunner of the slide rule.Gunter was professor of astronomy at Gresham College, London, from 1619 until his death. Descriptions of some of his inventions were given in his treatises on the sector, cross-staff, bow, quadrant, and other instruments. In Canon Triangulorum, or Table of Artificial Sines and Tangents (1620), the first published table of common logarithms of the sine and tangent functions, he introduced the terms cosine and cotangent. He also suggested to his friend Henry Briggs, the inventor of common l...
</Question>
<Choice>Gunter, Edmund</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician who proved the prime number theorem, which states that as n approaches infinity, p(n) approaches nln n, where p(n) is the number of positive prime numbers not greater than n.The Hadamard family moved to Paris in 1869, just before the beginning of the Franco-German War. In 1884 Hadamard took first place in entrance exams for both the École Polytechnique and the École Normale Supérieure. He chose to study mathematics at the École Normale Supérieure, receiving a bachelor's degree in 1888 and a doctorate in 1892. The latter year was particulary significant for Hadamard: he was...
</Question>
<Choice>Hadamard, Jacques-Salomon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British mathematician and inventor who improved the reflecting telescope, producing the first such instrument of sufficient accuracy and power to be useful in astronomy.Hadley's first Newtonian reflector, built in 1721, had a mirror about 6 inches (15 cm) in diameter. The favourable response it evoked inspired him to build another equally large one, with numerous improvements. His telescopes played a major part in bringing reflectors into general use by astronomers. In 1730, independently of Thomas Godfrey of Philadelphia, Hadley invented a quadrant (actually a double-reflecting octant) for me...
</Question>
<Choice>Hadley, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English jurist and mathematician who invented the achromatic lens, which he utilized in building the first refracting telescope free from chromatic aberration (colour distortion).Convinced from study of the human eye that achromatic lenses were feasible, Hall experimented with different kinds of glass until he found (1729) a combination of crown glass and flint glass that met his requirements. In 1733 he built several telescopes with apertures of 2.5 inches (6.5 cm) and focal lengths of 20 inches (50 cm).John Dollond of London received the Copley Medal of the Royal Society in 1758 for the inve...
</Question>
<Choice>Hall, Chester Moor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English astronomer and mathematician who was the first to calculate the orbit of a comet later named after him. He is also noted for his role in the publication of Newton'sPhilosophiae Naturalis Principia Mathematica.
</Question>
<Choice>Halley, Edmond</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Irish mathematician who contributed to the development of optics, dynamics, and algebra—in particular, discovering the algebra of quaternions. His work proved significant for the development of quantum mechanics.Hamilton was the son of a solicitor. He was educated by his uncle, James Hamilton, an Anglican priest with whom he lived from before the age of three until he entered college. An aptitude for languages was soon apparent: at five he was already making progress with Latin, Greek, and Hebrew, broadening his studies to include Arabic, Sanskrit, Persian, Syriac, French, and Italian before h...
</Question>
<Choice>Hamilton, Sir William Rowan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
leading English pure mathematician whose work was mainly in analysis and number theory.Hardy graduated from Trinity College, Cambridge, in 1899, became a fellow at Trinity in 1900, and lectured there in mathematics from 1906 to 1919. In 1912 Hardy published, with John E. Littlewood, the first of a series of papers that contributed fundamentally to many realms in mathematics, including the theory of Diophantine analysis, divergent series summation (seeinfinite series), Fourier series, the Riemann zeta function, and the distribution of primes. The collaboration between Hardy and Littlewood is on...
</Question>
<Choice>Hardy, Godfrey Harold</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
mathematician, astronomer, and investigator of the natural world.Little is known of him before he received his bachelor's degree from the University of Oxford in 1580. Throughout his working life, he was supported by the patronage, at different times, of Sir Walter Raleigh and Henry Percy, the 9th earl of Northumberland; he was never, after his student years, affiliated with an academic institution or commercial organization. From 1585 to 1586 he participated in Raleigh's colony on Roanoke Island, and he may have visited Virginia as early as 1584; upon his return, he published A Briefe and Tru...
</Question>
<Choice>Harriot, Thomas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American mathematician and crystallographer who, along with Jerome Karle, received the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1985. They developed mathematical methods for deducing the molecular structure of chemical compounds from the patterns formed when X rays are diffracted by their crystals.Hauptman was a classmate with Karle at City College of New York, from which they both graduated in 1937. Hauptman went on to study mathematics further at Columbia University (M.A., 1939) and at the University of Maryland (Ph.D., 1955). After World War II, Hauptman was reunited with Karle at the Naval Research La...
</Question>
<Choice>Hauptman, Herbert A.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist and philosopher who discovered (1925) a way to formulate quantum mechanics in terms of matrices. For that discovery, he was awarded the Nobel Prize for Physics for 1932. In 1927 he published his uncertainty principle, upon which he built his philosophy and for which he is best known. He also made important contributions to the theories of the hydrodynamics of turbulent flows, the atomic nucleus, ferromagnetism, cosmic rays, and subatomic particles, and he was instrumental in planning the first West German nuclear reactor at Karlsruhe, together with a research reactor in Munich...
</Question>
<Choice>Heisenberg, Werner</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German scientist and philosopher who made fundamental contributions to physiology, optics, electrodynamics, mathematics, and meteorology. He is best known for his statement of the law of the conservation of energy. He brought to his laboratory research the ability to analyze the philosophical assumptions on which much of 19th-century science was based, and he did so with clarity and precision.
</Question>
<Choice>Helmholtz, Hermann von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician whose work in the theory of functions includes the application of elliptic functions to provide the first solution to the general equation of the fifth degree, the quintic equation.Although Hermite had proved himself a creative mathematician at the age of 20, his difficulty in passing his formal examinations forced him to devote five of his most productive years to preparing for his examination for the bachelor of science degree, which he obtained in 1848. He was given a minor teaching position at the École Polytechnique, Paris, before being appointed to the Collège de Fra...
</Question>
<Choice>Hermite, Charles</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek geometer and inventor whose writings preserved for posterity a knowledge of the mathematics and engineering of Babylonia, ancient Egypt, and the Greco-Roman world.Heron's most important geometric work, Metrica, was lost until 1896. It is a compendium, in three books, of geometric rules and formulas that Heron gathered from a variety of sources, some of them going back to ancient Babylon, on areas and volumes of plane and solid figures. Book I enumerates means of finding the area of various plane figures and the surface areas of common solids. Included is a derivation of Heron's formula (...
</Question>
<Choice>Heron of Alexandria</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English astronomer and successor to his father, Sir William Herschel, in the field of stellar and nebular observation and discovery.
</Question>
<Choice>Herschel, Sir John Frederick William, 1st Baronet</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German mathematician who reduced geometry to a series of axioms and contributed substantially to the establishment of the formalistic foundations of mathematics. His work in 1909 on integral equations led to 20th-century research in functional analysis.The first steps of Hilbert's career occurred at the University of Königsberg, at which, in 1884, he finished his Inaugurel-dissertation (Ph.D.); he remained at Königsberg as a Privatdozent (lecturer, or assistant professor) in 1886–92, as an Extraordinarius (associate professor) in 1892–93, and as an Ordinarius in 1893–95. In 1892 he married Kät...
</Question>
<Choice>Hilbert, David</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek astronomer and mathematician who made fundamental contributions to the advancement of astronomy as a mathematical science and to the foundations of trigonometry. Although he is commonly ranked among the greatest scientists of antiquity, very little is known about his life, and only one of his many writings is still in existence. Knowledge of the rest of his work relies on second-hand reports, especially in the great astronomical compendium the Almagest, written by Ptolemy in the 2nd century AD.
</Question>
<Choice>Hipparchus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sophist philosopher who contributed significantly to mathematics by discovering the quadratrix, a special curve he may have used to trisect an angle.A man of great versatility, with an assurance characteristic of the later Sophists, Hippias lectured on poetry, grammar, history, politics, archaeology, mathematics, and astronomy. His vast literary output included elegies and tragedies besides technical treatises in prose. He is credited with an excellent work on Homer, collections of Greek and foreign literature, and archaeological treatises; but nothing remains except a few fragments. He is dep...
</Question>
<Choice>Hippias of Elis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek geometer who compiled the first known work on the elements of geometry nearly a century before Euclid. Although the work is no longer extant, Euclid may have used it as a model for his Elements.According to tradition, Hippocrates was a merchant whose goods had been captured by pirates. He went to Athens to prosecute them but met with little success in recovering his property. He remained in Athens, however, where he attended lectures on mathematics and finally took up teaching geometry to support himself. Aristotle (384–322 BC) recounts a different story, claiming that Hippocrates was ch...
</Question>
<Choice>Hippocrates of Chios</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese mathematician who was awarded the Fields Medal in 1970 for his work in algebraic geometry.Hironaka graduated from Kyoto University (1954) and Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass., U.S. (Ph.D., 1960). He held an appointment at Columbia University, New York City, from 1964 to 1968 and afterward jointly at Harvard and Kyoto.Hironaka was awarded the Fields Medal at the International Congress of Mathematicians in Nice, France, in 1970 for a number of technical results, including the resolution of certain singularities and torus imbeddings with implications in the theory of analytic functio...
</Question>
<Choice>Hironaka Heisuke</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
one of the pioneering theorists in nonlinear mathematics and the use of new mathematical techniques in understanding problems in disciplines as diverse as economics, biology, and computer science.In 1950 Holland received a bachelor's degree in mathematics from the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. He then entered the graduate school in communication science at the University of Michigan in Ann Arbor, where he received his doctorate in 1954—arguably the first Ph.D. in computer science. He remained at Michigan and played an active role in the development of computer science as a department...
</Question>
<Choice>Holland, John Henry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American mathematician and rear admiral in the U.S. Navy who was a pioneer in developing computer technology, helping to devise UNIVAC I, the first commercial electronic computer, and naval applications for COBOL (common-business-oriented language).After graduating from Vassar College (B.A., 1928), Hopper attended Yale University (M.A., 1930; Ph.D., 1934). She taught mathematics at Vassar before joining the Naval Reserve in 1943. She became a lieutenant and was assigned to the Bureau of Ordnance's Computation Project at Harvard University (1944), where she worked on Mark I, the first large-sca...
</Question>
<Choice>Hopper, Grace Murray</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish mathematician who was awarded the Fields Medal in 1962 for his work on partial differential equations. Between 1987 and 1990 he served as a vice president of the International Mathematical Union. In 1988 Hörmander was awarded the Wolf Prize.Hörmander attended the University of Lund, Sweden. He held appointments at Lund (1955–57), Stockholm University (1957–64), and Stanford University, Calif., U.S. (1963–64). Following research at the Institute for Advanced Study, Princeton, N.J. (1964–68), he returned to Lund in 1968.Hörmander was awarded the Fields Medal at the International Congress...
</Question>
<Choice>Hormander, Lars V.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British mathematician and astronomer best known as the foremost proponent and defender of the steady-state theory of the universe. This theory holds both that the universe is expanding and that matter is being continuously created to keep the mean density of matter in space constant.Hoyle was educated at Emmanuel College and St. John's College, Cambridge, and spent six years during World War II with the British Admiralty, working on radar development. In 1945 he returned to Cambridge as a lecturer in mathematics. Three years later, in collaboration with the astronomer Thomas Gold and the math...
</Question>
<Choice>Hoyle, Sir Fred</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese mathematician and translator of Western mathematical works.Apparently inspired by Li Shanlan (1811–82), Hua was an early enthusiastic proponent of Western-style mathematics. Like Li, Hua served as a translator, mainly in collaboration with the English missionary John Fryer, of Western works on mathematics and science. Not a particularly talented mathematician, Hua's personal struggles to understand mathematical materials resulted in exceptionally lucid translations—particularly his fluent and accessible presentations of works on algebra and calculus. His translations were widely read a...
</Question>
<Choice>Hua Hengfang</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch mathematician and statesman who promoted Cartesian geometry and philosophy in Holland and contributed to the theory of equations.Born of a patrician family, Hudde served for some 30 years as burgomaster of Amsterdam. In his De reductione aequationum (1713; “Concerning Reduction of Equations”), he was the first to take literal coefficients in algebra as indifferently positive or negative. Two of his discoveries, dating from 1657 to 1658, are known as Hudde's rules and point clearly toward algorithms (a special process for solving certain types of problems) of calculus. Hudde also anticipa...
</Question>
<Choice>Hudde, Johan van Waveren</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch mathematician, astronomer, and physicist, who founded the wave theory of light, discovered the true shape of the rings of Saturn, and made original contributions to the science of dynamics—the study of the action of forces on bodies.Huygens was from a wealthy and distinguished middle-class family. His father, Constantijn Huygens, a diplomat, Latinist, and poet, was the friend and correspondent of many outstanding intellectual figures of the day, including the scientist and philosopher René Descartes. From an early age, Huygens showed a marked mechanical bent and a talent for drawing and...
</Question>
<Choice>Huygens, Christiaan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Egyptian Neoplatonist philosopher who was the first notable woman in mathematics.The daughter of Theon, also a notable mathematician and philosopher, Hypatia became the recognized head of the Neoplatonist school of philosophy at Alexandria about 400, and her eloquence, modesty, and beauty, combined with her remarkable intellectual gifts, attracted a large number of pupils. Among them was Synesius of Cyrene, afterward bishop of Ptolemais (c. 410), several of whose letters to her are still extant.Hypatia lectured on mathematics and on the philosophical teachings of two Neoplatonists: Plotinus (c...
</Question>
<Choice>Hypatia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
mathematician and astronomer who made significant contributions to the principles of optics and the use of scientific experiments.
</Question>
<Choice>Ibn al-Haytham</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German mathematician who, with Niels Henrik Abel of Norway, founded the theory of elliptic functions.Jacobi was first tutored by an uncle, and, by the end of his first year at the Gymnasium (1816–17), he was ready to enter the University of Berlin. Because the university would not accept students younger than 16, he had to bide his time until 1821, yet, at the end of the 1823–24 academic year, he was qualified to teach mathematics, Greek, and Latin. With the submission of his doctoral dissertation and his conversion to Christianity, a position opened for him at the University of Berlin in 1825...
</Question>
<Choice>Jacobi, Carl</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physicist and mathematician who was the first to propose that matter is continuously created throughout the universe. He made other innovations in astronomical theory but is perhaps best known as a writer of popular books about astronomy.Jeans taught at the University of Cambridge (1904–05, 1910–12) and at Princeton University (1905–09). In 1923 he became a research associate at Mt. Wilson Observatory, Pasadena, Calif., where he remained until 1944. In 1928, the year he was knighted, he proposed his continuous-creation theory.His work included investigations of spiral nebulae, the sour...
</Question>
<Choice>Jeans, Sir James</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
mathematician and astronomer active at the beginning of the greatest period of traditional Chinese mathematics.Little is known about Jia's life except that he held a relatively low military office during the reign (1022/23–1063/64) of Emperor Renzong of the Song dynasty. He was a pupil of mathematician and astronomer Chu Yan, who contributed to the revision of the Chongtian calendar in 1023, and served in the Imperial Astronomical Bureau in the mid-11th century. Jia's name was mainly quoted in connection with his method of extracting roots (solutions) of polynomials of degree higher than three...
</Question>
<Choice>Jia Xian</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
New Zealand mathematician who was awarded the Fields Medal in 1990 for his study of functional analysis and knot theory.Jones attended the University of Geneva's school of mathematics (Ph.D., 1979) and became a professor at the University of California, Berkeley, U.S., in 1985. He was awarded the Fields Medal at the International Congress of Mathematicians in Kyoto, Japan, in 1990.In his study of von Neumann algebras (algebras of bounded operators acting on a Hilbert space), Jones came across polynomials that were invariant for knots and links—simple closed curves in three-dimensional space. I...
</Question>
<Choice>Jones, Vaughan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician whose work on substitution groups (permutation groups) and the theory of equations first brought full understanding of the importance of the theories of the eminent mathematician Évariste Galois, who had died in 1832.Jordan's early research was in geometry. His Traité des substitutions et des équations algébriques (1870; “Treatise on Substitutions and Algebraic Equations”), which brought him the Poncelet Prize of the French Academy of Sciences, both gave a comprehensive account of Galois's theory of substitution groups and applied these groups to algebraic equations and to...
</Question>
<Choice>Jordan, Camille</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
mathematician and engineer who held an official position in Baghdad (c. 1010–1015), perhaps culminating in the position of vizier, during which time he wrote his three main works, al-Fakhri fi?l-jabr wa'l-muqabala (“Glorious on algebra”), al-Badi‘ fi'l-hisab (“Wonderful on calculation”), and al-Kafi fi'l-hisab (“Sufficient on calculation”). A now lost work of his contained the first description of what later became known as Pascal's triangle (see binomial theorem).Al-Karaji combined tradition and novelty in his mathematical exposition. Like his Arabic predecessors he did not use symbolism—even...
</Question>
<Choice>Karaji, al-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American crystallographer who, along with Herbert A. Hauptman, was awarded the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1985 for their development of mathematical methods for deducing the molecular structure of chemical compounds from the patterns formed when X rays are diffracted by their crystals.Karle was a classmate of Hauptman's at City College in New York, from which they both graduated in 1937. Karle went on to earn his Ph.D. degree in physical chemistry at the University of Michigan in 1943. After working on the Manhattan Project in 1943–44, he joined the Naval Research Laboratory in 1944, becomin...
</Question>
<Choice>Karle, Jerome</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hungarian-born American research engineer best known for his pioneering work in the use of mathematics and the basic sciences in aeronautics and astronautics. His laboratory at the California Institute of Technology later became the National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA) Jet Propulsion Laboratory.
</Question>
<Choice>Karman, Theodore von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
ranks among the greatest mathematicians and astronomers in the Islamic world.
</Question>
<Choice>Kashi, al-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish engineer, mathematician, and physicist, who profoundly influenced the scientific thought of his generation.Thomson, who was knighted and raised to the peerage in recognition of his work in engineering and physics, was foremost among the small group of British scientists who helped to lay the foundations of modern physics. His contributions to science included a major role in the development of the second law of thermodynamics; the absolute temperature scale (measured in kelvins); the dynamical theory of heat; the mathematical analysis of electricity and magnetism, including the basic...
</Question>
<Choice>Kelvin, William Thomson, Baron</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. electrical engineer who made innovations in analytic methods in electronics, particularly the definitive application of complex-number theory to alternating-current (ac) circuits.After working as an office boy for a London engineering society, as an electrician, and on a cable-engineering ship, in 1887 Kennelly joined Thomas Edison's staff at West Orange, N.J., where he was chief assistant until 1894. Then, with Edwin J. Houston, he formed the consulting firm of Houston and Kennelly in Philadelphia.The mathematical analysis of direct-current circuits was a simple matter, but the analysis...
</Question>
<Choice>Kennelly, Arthur Edwin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
New Zealand mathematician who solved (1963) Einstein's field equations of general relativity to describe rotating black holes, thus providing a major contribution to the field of astrophysics.Kerr received an M.S. (1954) from New Zealand University (now dissolved) and his Ph.D. (1960) from Cambridge University. He served on the faculty of the University of Texas at Austin (1963–72) and, returning to New Zealand, then became a professor of mathematics at the University of Canterbury, Christchurch, in 1972.Kerr worked in the tradition of Karl Schwarzschild, who in 1916, shortly after the appeara...
</Question>
<Choice>Kerr, Roy P.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Muslim mathematician and astronomer whose major works introduced Hindu-Arabic numerals and the concepts of algebra into European mathematics. Latinized versions of his name and of his most famous book title live on in the terms algorithm and algebra.Al-Khwarizmi lived in Baghdad, where he worked at the “House of Wisdom” (Dar al-?ikma) under the caliphate of al-Ma?mun. (The House of Wisdom acquired and translated scientific and philosophic treatises, particularly Greek, as well as publishing original research.) Al-Kwarizmi's work on elementary algebra, al-Kitab al-mukhta?ar fi ?isab al-jabr wa?...
</Question>
<Choice>Khwarizmi, al-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Babylonian astronomer who may have been responsible for what modern scholars call System B, a Babylonian theory that described the speed of the Moon's motion around the zodiac as increasing gradually and then decreasing gradually in the course of a month, following a regular sawtooth pattern. In this very successful theory, the Sun also varied its speed in a sawtooth pattern. The Babylonian lunar theory included a scheme for the motion of the Sun, since the Sun figures in the prediction of lunar phenomena such as phases and eclipses. In the simpler and probably older System A for the behaviour...
</Question>
<Choice>Kidinnu</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jesuit priest and scholar, sometimes called the last Renaissance man, important for his prodigious activity in disseminating knowledge.Kircher learned Greek and Hebrew at the Jesuit school in Fulda, pursued scientific and humanistic studies at Paderborn, Cologne, and Koblenz, and in 1628 was ordained at Mainz. He fled the increasing factional and dynastic fighting in Germany (part of the Thirty Years' War) and, after occupying various academic positions at Avignon, settled in 1634 in Rome. There he remained for most of his life, functioning as a kind of one-man intellectual clearinghouse for c...
</Question>
<Choice>Kircher, Athanasius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American mathematician and logician whose work on recursion theory helped lay the foundations of theoretical computer science.Kleene was educated at Amherst College (A.B., 1930) and earned a Ph.D. in mathematics at Princeton University in 1934. After teaching briefly at Princeton, he joined the University of Wisconsin at Madison as an instructor in 1935 and became a full professor there in 1948. He retired in 1979.Kleene's research was devoted to the theory of algorithms and recursive functions (i.e., functions defined in a finite sequence of combinatorial steps). Kleene, together with Alonzo...
</Question>
<Choice>Kleene, Stephen Cole</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German mathematician whose unified view of geometry as the study of the properties of a space that are invariant under a given group of transformations, known as the Erlanger Programm, profoundly influenced mathematical developments.As a student at the University of Bonn (Ph.D., 1868), Klein worked closely with the physicist and geometer Julius Plücker (1801–68). After Plücker's death, he worked with the geometer Alfred Clebsch (1833–72), who headed the mathematics department at the University of Göttingen. On Clebsch's recommendation, Klein was appointed professor of mathematics at the Univer...
</Question>
<Choice>Klein, Felix</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese mathematician who was awarded the Fields Medal in 1954 for his work in algebraic geometry and complex analysis.Kodaira attended the University of Tokyo (Ph.D., 1949). His dissertation attracted the attention of Hermann Weyl, who invited Kodaira to join him at the Institute for Advanced Study, Princeton, New Jersey, U.S., where he remained until 1961. After appointments at Harvard University (Cambridge, Massachusetts), Johns Hopkins University (Baltimore, Maryland), and Stanford University (California), he returned to the University of Tokyo in 1967. He retired in 1985.Kodaira was awar...
</Question>
<Choice>Kodaira Kunihiko</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian mathematician whose work influenced many branches of modern mathematics, especially harmonic analysis, probability, set theory, information theory, and number theory. A man of broad culture, with interests in technology, history, and education, he played an active role in the reform of education in the Soviet Union. He is best remembered for a brilliant series of papers on the theory of probability.
</Question>
<Choice>Kolmogorov, Andrey Nikolayevich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian mathematician who won the Fields Medal in 1998 for his work in algebraic geometry and algebraic topology.Kontsevich studied mathematics at Moscow State University from 1980 to 1985 before receiving his doctorate (1992) from the University of Bonn. He held positions in Germany at the University of Bonn; in the United States at Harvard University, Princeton University, the University of California at Berkeley, and Rutgers University; and in France at the Institute of Advanced Scientific Studies, Bures-sur-Yvette.His first success was to prove a conjecture of fellow Fields Medalist Edward...
</Question>
<Choice>Kontsevich, Maxim</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
mathematician and writer who made a valuable contribution to the theory of partial differential equations. She was the first woman in modern Europe to gain a doctorate in mathematics, the first to join the editorial board of a scientific journal, and the first to be appointed professor of mathematics.In 1868 Kovalevskaya entered into a marriage of convenience with a young paleontologist, Vladimir Kovalevsky, in order to leave Russia and continue her studies. The pair traveled together to Austria and then to Germany, where in 1869 she studied at the University of Heidelberg under the mathematic...
</Question>
<Choice>Kovalevskaya, Sofya Vasilyevna</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German mathematician whose primary contributions were in the theory of equations and higher algebra.Kronecker acquired a passion for number theory from Ernst Kummer, his instructor in mathematics at the Liegnitz Gymnasium, and earned his doctor's degree at the University of Berlin with a dissertation (1845) on those special complex units that appear in certain algebraic number fields. He managed the family mercantile and land business until age 30, when he was financially able to retire. While in business he pursued mathematics as a recreation. From 1861 to 1883 Kronecker lectured at the Unive...
</Question>
<Choice>Kronecker, Leopold</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German mathematician whose introduction of ideal numbers, which are defined as a special subgroup of a ring, extended the fundamental theorem of arithmetic (unique factorization of every integer into a product of primes) to complex number fields.After teaching in Gymnasium 1 year at Sorau and 10 years at Liegnitz, Kummer became professor of mathematics at the University of Breslau (now Wroclaw, Poland) in 1842. In 1855 he succeeded Peter Gustav Lejeune Dirichlet as professor of mathematics at the University of Berlin, at the same time also becoming a professor at the Berlin War College.In 1843...
</Question>
<Choice>Kummer, Ernst Eduard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician who won the Fields Medal in 2002 for his work connecting number theory and analysis.Lafforgue attended the École Normale Supérieure (1986–90) in Paris before receiving a Ph.D. in algebraic geometry from the University of Paris in 1994. In 2001 he became a permanent professor at the Institute of Advanced Scientific Studies, Bures-sur-Yvette, France.Lafforgue was awarded the Fields Medal at the International Congress of Mathematicians in Beijing in 2002. Building on work by the 1990 Fields Medalist, Russian Vladimir Drinfeld, Lafforgue established one important case of the L...
</Question>
<Choice>Lafforgue, Laurent</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian French mathematician who made great contributions to number theory and to analytic and celestial mechanics. His most important book, Mécanique analytique (1788; “Analytic Mechanics”), was the basis for all later work in this field.Lagrange was from a well-to-do family of French origin on his father's side. His father was treasurer to the king of Sardinia and lost his fortune in speculation. Lagrange later said, “If I had been rich, I probably would not have devoted myself to mathematics.” His interest in mathematics was aroused by the chance reading of a memoir by the English astronome...
</Question>
<Choice>Lagrange, Joseph-Louis, comte de l'Empire</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss German mathematician, astronomer, physicist, and philosopher who provided the first rigorous proof that p (the ratio of a circle's circumference to its diameter) is irrational, meaning that it cannot be expressed as the quotient of two integers.Lambert, the son of a tailor, was largely self-educated and early in his life began geometric and astronomical investigations by means of instruments he designed and built himself. He worked for a time as a bookkeeper, secretary, and editor. As a private tutor in 1748, he gained access to a good library, which he used for self-improvement until 17...
</Question>
<Choice>Lambert, Johann Heinrich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician, astronomer, and physicist who is best known for his investigations into the stability of the solar system.Laplace successfully accounted for all the observed deviations of the planets from their theoretical orbits by applying Sir Isaac Newton's theory of gravitation to the solar system, and he developed a conceptual view of evolutionary change in the structure of the solar system. He also demonstrated the usefulness of probability for interpreting scientific data.Laplace was the son of a peasant farmer. Little is known of his early life except that he quickly showed his m...
</Question>
<Choice>Laplace, Pierre-Simon, marquis de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician whose generalization of the Riemann integral revolutionized the field of integration.Lebesgue was maître de conférences (lecture master) at the University of Rennes from 1902 until 1906, when he went to Poitiers, first as chargé de cours (assistant lecturer) of the faculty of sciences and later as professor. In 1910 he went to the Sorbonne in Paris as maître de conférences in mathematical analysis, and in 1921 he became a professor at the Collège de France. In 1917 he was awarded the Prix Saintour, and in 1922 he was elected to the French Academy of Sciences. He was made a...
</Question>
<Choice>Lebesgue, Henri-Leon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician whose distinguished work on elliptic integrals provided basic analytic tools for mathematical physics.Little is known about Legendre's early life except that his family wealth allowed him to study physics and mathematics, beginning in 1770, at the Collège Mazarin (Collège des Quatre-Nations) in Paris and that, at least until the French Revolution, he did not have to work. Nevertheless, Legendre taught mathematics at the École Militaire in Paris from 1775 to 1780. In 1782 he won a prize offered by the Berlin Academy of Sciences for his effort to “determine the curve describ...
</Question>
<Choice>Legendre, Adrien-Marie</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German philosopher, mathematician, and political adviser, important both as a metaphysician and as a logician and distinguished also for his independent invention of the differential and integral calculus.
</Question>
<Choice>Leibniz, Gottfried Wilhelm</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
medieval Italian mathematician who wrote Liber abaci (1202; “Book of the Abacus”), the first European work on Indian and Arabian mathematics.
</Question>
<Choice>Leonardo Pisano</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polish logician and mathematician who was a co-founder and leading representative of the Warsaw school of logic.
</Question>
<Choice>Lesniewski, Stanislaw</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French Jewish mathematician, philosopher, astronomer, and Talmudic scholar.In 1321 Levi wrote his first work, Sefer ha-mispar (“Book of the Number”), dealing with arithmetical operations, including extraction of roots. In De sinibus, chordis et arcubus (1342; “On Sines, Chords, and Arcs”) he presented an original derivation of the sine theorem for plane triangles and tables of sines calculated to five decimal places. On the request of Philip of Vitry, bishop of Meaux, he composed a book on geometry, preserved only in Latin translation, De numeris harmonicis (1343; “The Harmony of Numbers”), co...
</Question>
<Choice>Levi ben Gershom</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian mathematician known for his work in differential calculus and relativity theory. At the University of Padua (1891–95), he studied under Gregorio Ricci Curbastro, with whom he later collaborated in founding the absolute differential calculus (now known as tensor analysis). Levi-Civita became an instructor there in 1898 and a professor of rational mechanics in 1902. He taught at the University of Rome from 1918 until 1938, when he was removed because of his Jewish origins.With Ricci, Levi-Civita wrote the pioneering work on the calculus of tensors, Méthodes de calcul differéntiel absolu...
</Question>
<Choice>Levi-Civita, Tullio</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mining engineer and mathematician noted for his work in the theory of probability.After serving as a professor at the École des Mines de Saint-Étienne, Paris, from 1910 to 1913, Lévy joined the faculty (1914–51) of the École Nationale Supérieure des Mines, Paris. He also taught from 1920 to 1959 at the École Polytechnique in Paris.Lévy contributed to the theory of probability, functional analysis, and other analysis problems, principally partial differential equations and series. He also studied geometry. Among his major works are Leçons d'analyse fonctionnelle (1922, 2nd ed., 1951; “Le...
</Question>
<Choice>Levy, Paul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese mathematician and astronomer.Li was the son of a widely educated state official. He was given a position in the Imperial Astronomical Bureau in 627, following his critique of the Wuyin calendar, which had been introduced in 619. Later he submitted a report concerning the outdated astronomical instruments used in the bureau and was ordered to make a new armillary sphere; it was accomplished in 633 according to his design, which added a third ring to the traditional two-ring structure.Li became the deputy director of the Imperial Astronomical Bureau about 641. He participated in the comp...
</Question>
<Choice>Li Chunfeng</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese mathematician and astronomer who made notable contributions to the revival of traditional Chinese mathematics and astronomy and to the development of the theory of equations.Having failed the Chinese civil service examinations several times, Li Rui could obtain no official position, and he had to make a poor living as an assistant to various mandarin scholar-officials. From about 1800 he began to study the works of the 13th-century mathematicians Li Ye and Qin Jiushao. From these works, he found that the traditional Chinese method of solving higher-degree equations had several advantag...
</Question>
<Choice>Li Rui</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese mathematician who was instrumental in combining Western mathematical and scientific knowledge and methods with traditional Chinese methods.Li was educated by Chen Huan (1786–1863), a famous philologist, and from an early age demonstrated a remarkable talent for mathematics. In particular, Li mastered both traditional Chinese and available Western mathematical treatises at a precocious age. However, during this period in China, mathematics was not held in high esteem, and he had to find various other employments, such as tutoring. Almost all the treatises that he wrote in this period we...
</Question>
<Choice>Li Shanlan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese mathematician and scholar-official who contributed to the solution of polynomial equations in one variable.Li passed the mandarinjinshi examination (the highest scholar-official title in imperial China) in prose literature at the late age of 38. He was appointed to the administrative position of prefect but fled when the Mongols invaded his district in 1233. Wandering homeless in Shanxi, Shandong, and Henan provinces, Li perfected his literary, mathematical, and astronomical skills and composed several writings. It was during this period that he composed his main work, Ceyuan haijing (...
</Question>
<Choice>Li Ye</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese mathematician, astronomer, and geographer whose translations of European scientific books greatly contributed to the spread of Western science in China.Originally from a military family, Li was made a jinshi (the highest scholar-official title in imperial China) in 1598. In 1601 he met the Italian Jesuit Matteo Ricci, who was one of the first Westerners allowed into the interior of China. To gain acceptance, Ricci had first learned the Chinese language and culture, which in turn enabled him to spread knowledge of Western science and religion. Li was greatly attracted by Ricci's teachin...
</Question>
<Choice>Li Zhizao</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Norwegian mathematician who founded the theory of continuous groups and their applications to the theory of differential equations. His investigations led to one of the major branches of 20th-century mathematics, the theory of Lie groups and Lie algebras.Lie attended a broad range of science and mathematics courses at the University of Kristiania (now Oslo) from 1859 to 1865 without deciding on a subject for graduate study. He supported himself for the following few years by giving private lessons while studying astronomy, mechanics, and mathematics on his own. His interest in geometry deepene...
</Question>
<Choice>Lie, Marius Sophus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German mathematician who is mainly remembered for having proved that the number p is transcendental—i.e., it does not satisfy any algebraic equation with rational coefficients. This proof established that the classical Greek construction problem of squaring the circle (constructing a square with an area equal to that of a given circle) by compass and straightedge is insoluble.Beginning in 1870 Lindemann studied at the University of Göttingen, the University of Munich, and the University of Erlangen, where he received his doctorate in 1873. Following postgraduate studies he taught at the Univer...
</Question>
<Choice>Lindemann, Carl Louis Ferdinand von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician who was awarded the Fields Medal in 1994 for his work on partial differential equations.Lions earned a doctorate from the University of Paris VI in 1979. He joined the faculty of the University of Paris IX in 1981 and, from 1993, also held an appointment at the École Polytechnique, Palaiseau.The work for which Lions was awarded the Fields Medal at the International Congress of Mathematicians in Zürich, Switz., in 1994 lies largely in classical analysis—mainly nonlinear partial differential equations. In 1983, in work with Michael G. Crandall, he introduced “viscosity solut...
</Question>
<Choice>Lions, Pierre-Louis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician known for his work in analysis, differential geometry, and number theory and for his discovery of transcendental numbers—i.e., numbers that are not the roots of algebraic equations having rational coefficients. He was also influential as a journal editor and teacher.Liouville, the son of an army captain, was educated in Paris at the École Polytechnique from 1825 to 1827 and then at the École Nationale des Ponts et Chaussées (“National School of Bridges and Roads”) until 1830. At the École Polytechnique, Liouville was taught by André-Marie Ampère, who recognized his talent...
</Question>
<Choice>Liouville, Joseph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian mathematician and founder of non-Euclidean geometry, which he developed independently of János Bolyai and Carl Gauss. (Lobachevsky's first publication on this subject was in 1829, Bolyai's in 1832; Gauss never published his ideas on non-Euclidean geometry.)
</Question>
<Choice>Lobachevsky, Nikolay Ivanovich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British geophysicist and mathematician who discovered a major type of seismic wave that was subsequently named for him.Love held the Sedleian professorship of natural philosophy at the University of Oxford from 1899 to 1940. In his analysis of earthquake waves, Love made the assumption that the Earth consists of concentric layers that differ in density and postulated the occurrence of a seismic wave confined to the surface layer, or crust, of the Earth. This wave would be propagated as a result of the difference in density between the crust and underlying mantle. His prediction was confirmed b...
</Question>
<Choice>Love, Augustus Edward Hough</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English mathematician, an associate of Charles Babbage, for whose prototype of a digital computer she created a program. She has been called the first computer programmer.She was the daughter of famed poet Lord Byron and Annabella Milbanke Byron, who legally separated two months after her birth. Her father then left Britain forever, and his daughter never knew him personally. She was educated privately by tutors and then self-educated but was helped in her advanced studies by mathematician-logician Augustus De Morgan, the first professor of mathematics at the University of London. On July 8, 1...
</Question>
<Choice>
Lovelace, Ada King, countess of Ada King, countess of Lovelace
</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American mathematician who was a cocreator of category theory, an architect of homological algebra, and an advocate of categorical foundations for mathematics.Mac Lane graduated from Yale University in 1930 and then began graduate work at the University of Chicago. He soon moved to Germany, where he, with a dissertation on mathematical logic, received a doctorate degree in 1933 from the University of Göttingen. While in Germany, he stayed in the homes of Hermann Weyl and Richard Courant, and he saw his dissertation adviser Paul Bernays barred from teaching by the Nazis. Mac Lane returned home...
</Question>
<Choice>Mac Lane, Saunders</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish mathematician who developed and extended Sir Isaac Newton's work in calculus, geometry, and gravitation.A child prodigy, he entered the University of Glasgow at age 11. At the age of 19 he was elected a professor of mathematics at Marischal College, Aberdeen, and two years later he became a fellow of the Royal Society of London. At this time he became acquainted with Newton. In his first work, Geometrica Organica; Sive Descriptio Linearum Curvarum Universalis (1720; “Organic Geometry, with the Description of the Universal Linear Curves”), Maclaurin developed several theorems similar t...
</Question>
<Choice>Maclaurin, Colin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian mathematician who made significant contributions to the development of algebra.All that is known about Mahavira's life is that he was a Jain (he perhaps took his name to honour the great Jainism reformer Mahavira [c. 599–527 BCE]) and that he wrote Ganitasarasangraha (“Compendium of the Essence of Mathematics”) during the reign of Amoghavarsha (c. 814–878) of the Rashtrakuta dynasty. The work comprises more than 1,130 versified rules and examples divided in nine chapters: the first chapter for “terminology” and the rest for “mathematical procedures” such as basic operations, reductions...
</Question>
<Choice>Mahavira</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian mathematician who was awarded the Fields Medal in 1978 for his contributions to the theory of Lie groups. Margulis attended Moscow State University (Ph.D., 1970).In 1978 Margulis was awarded the Fields Medal at the International Congress of Mathematicians in Helsinki, Fin., but was not allowed by the Soviet government to travel to Finland to receive the award. In 1990 Margulis immigrated to the United States. After brief appointments at Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass., and the Institute for Advanced Study, Princeton, N.J., he was appointed to a position at Yale University, New Hav...
</Question>
<Choice>Margulis, Gregori Aleksandrovich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian mathematician who helped to develop the theory of stochastic processes, especially those called Markov chains. Based on the study of the probability of mutually dependent events, his work has been developed and widely applied in the biological and social sciences.As a child Markov had health problems and used crutches until he was 10 years old. In 1874 he enrolled at the University of St. Petersburg (now St. Petersburg State University), where he earned a bachelor's degree (1878), a master's degree (1880), and a doctorate (1884). In 1883, as his station in life improved, he married his...
</Question>
<Choice>Markov, Andrey Andreyevich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American mathematical physicist, educator, and science administrator.Mason completed his undergraduate work at the University of Wisconsin (1898) and received his Ph.D. degree from the University of Göttingen in 1903. His first position, as an instructor in mathematics at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge (1903–04), ended with an appointment as an assistant professor of mathematics at the Sheffield Scientific School at Yale (1904–08). Mason then returned to his alma mater as professor of mathematical physics (1908–25). During World War I he invented several devices for subma...
</Question>
<Choice>Mason, Max</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French astronomer and mathematician who worked particularly on the determination of the distances of the stars.After a brief period as an engineer, Mathieu became an astronomer at the Observatoire de Paris and at the Bureau des Longitudes in 1817. He later served as professor of astronomy at the Collège de France, Paris, and from 1829 was professor of analysis at the École Polytechnique, Paris. He represented Macon in the Chamber of Deputies (1834–48). For many years he edited the work on population statistics, L'Annuaire du Bureau des Longitudes, and published L'Histoire de l'astronomie au XV...
</Question>
<Choice>Mathieu, Claude-Louis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician, biologist, and astronomer who helped popularize Newtonian mechanics.Maupertuis became a member of the Academy of Sciences in Paris in 1731 and soon became the foremost French proponent of the Newtonian theory of gravitation. In 1736 he led an expedition to Lapland to measure the length of a degree along the meridian. His measurement verified the Newtonian view that the Earth is an oblate spheroid (a sphere flattened at the poles). The success of his expedition gained him favour with Frederick the Great, who called him to Berlin. He became a member of the Berlin Academy of...
</Question>
<Choice>Maupertuis, Pierre-Louis Moreau de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American mathematician who won the Fields Medal in 1998 for his work in dynamics.McMullen studied mathematics at Williams College and received his doctorate (1985) from Harvard University. Afterward he taught at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Princeton University, the University of California at Berkeley, and Harvard.McMullen first used the methods of dynamical systems theory to show that generally convergent algorithms for solving polynomial equations exist only for polynomials of degree 3 or less. He then studied one-dimensional complex dynamics and went on to apply similar ideas...
</Question>
<Choice>McMullen, Curtis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese court official, mathematician, and astronomer.Mei Juecheng learned mathematics from his grandfather Mei Wending (1633–1721), a renowned mathematician and astronomer. In 1712 Mei Juecheng became a court mathematician and the following year joined the Mengyangzhai (an imperial bureau created to synthesize Western and Chinese scientific knowledge) as one of the chief editors of Lüli yuanyuan (c. 1723; “Source of Mathematical Harmonics and Astronomy”), a compendium on music, mathematics, and astronomy. Unlike earlier such endeavours, this was purely a work of Chinese authorship; Jesuits we...
</Question>
<Choice>Mei Juecheng</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese writer on astronomy and mathematics whose work represented an association of Chinese and Western knowledge.In 1645 China adopted a new, controversial calendar that had been prepared under the direction of the Jesuit Adam Schall von Bell. Together with his three younger brothers, Mei studied calendar design under the Daoist Ni Guanghu. A member of a loyalist family, Mei remained independent rather than join the “foreign” Manchu administration, but his fame spread far beyond the boundaries of his province. The Kangxi emperor was interested in Mei's work, the Lixue yiwen (c. 1701; “Inquir...
</Question>
<Choice>Mei Wending</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek mathematician and friend of Plato who is credited with discovering the conic sections.Menaechmus's credit for discovering that the ellipse, parabola, and hyperbola are sections of a cone—produced by the intersection of a plane with the surface of a cone—derives from an epigram of Eratosthenes of Cyrene (c. 276–194 BC) that refers to cutting the cone “in the triads of Menaechmus.” Eutocius of Ascalon (fl. AD 520) recounts two of Menaechmus's solutions to the problem of constructing a cube with double the volume of a given cube of side a. Menaechmus's solutions use properties of the parabo...
</Question>
<Choice>Menaechmus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek mathematician and astronomer who first conceived and defined a spherical triangle (a triangle formed by three arcs of great circles on the surface of a sphere).Menelaus's most important work is Sphaerica, on the geometry of the sphere, extant only in an Arabic translation. In Book I he established the basis for a mathematical treatment of spherical triangles analogous to Euclid's treatment of plane triangles. Furthermore, he originated the use of arcs of great circles instead of arcs of parallel circles on the sphere, a major turning point in the development of spherical trigonometry. Bo...
</Question>
<Choice>Menelaus of Alexandria</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French theologian, natural philosopher, and mathematician. While best remembered by mathematicians for his search for a formula to generate prime numbers based on what are now known as “Mersenne numbers,” his wider significance stems from his role as correspondent, publicizing and disseminating the work of some of the greatest thinkers of his age.Mersenne was educated at the Jesuit college of La Flèche soon after its founding in 1604. He left La Flèche about 1609 to study theology in Paris at both the Sorbonne and the Collège de France. In 1611 he entered the austere Roman Catholic Order of Mi...
</Question>
<Choice>Mersenne, Marin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English astrophysicist and cosmologist best known for his development of kinematic relativity.Milne was educated at the University of Cambridge and served as assistant director of the Solar Physics Observatory at Cambridge from 1920 to 1924. He then became a professor of applied mathematics at the University of Manchester, and from 1929 until his death he was a professor of mathematics at the University of Oxford.Collaborating with Sir Ralph H. Fowler, Milne became known in the 1920s for their formulation of a reliable surface-temperature scale for stars of any spectral type. His theoretical s...
</Question>
<Choice>Milne, Edward Arthur</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American mathematician who was awarded the Fields Medal in 1962 for his work in differential topology.Milnor attended Princeton University (A.B., 1951; Ph.D., 1954), in New Jersey. He held an appointment at Princeton from 1954 to 1967 and, after several years at other institutions, joined the faculty at the Institute for Advanced Study, Princeton, in 1970. In 1989 he became director of the Institute for Mathematical Sciences at the State University of New York, Stony Brook.Milnor was awarded the Fields Medal at the International Congress of Mathematicians in Stockholm in 1962. His work was par...
</Question>
<Choice>Milnor, John Willard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese astronomer and mathematician who studied the power series expansions of trigonometric functions. See the .Minggantu was a Mongolian of the Plain White Banner (one of the administrative units used by the Manchu; seeBanner system). His name first appeared in official Chinese records in 1712, among the Kangxi emperor's retinue, as a shengyuan (state-subsidized student) of the Imperial Astronomical Bureau. He spent his whole career there, at a time when Jesuit missionaries were in charge of calendar reforms. In 1713 Minggantu was appointed to the newly created Office of Mathematics, where...
</Question>
<Choice>Minggantu</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German mathematician who developed the geometrical theory of numbers and who made numerous contributions to number theory, mathematical physics, and the theory of relativity. His idea of combining the three dimensions of physical space with that of time into a four-dimensional “Minkowski space”—space-time—laid the mathematical foundations for Albert Einstein's special theory of relativity.The son of German parents living in Russia, Minkowski returned to Germany with them in 1872 and spent his youth in the royal Prussian city of Königsberg. A gifted prodigy, he began his studies at the Universi...
</Question>
<Choice>Minkowski, Hermann</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American mathematician and computer scientist, one of the most famous practitioners of the science of artificial intelligence (AI). Minsky won the 1969 A.M. Turing Award, the highest honour in computer science, for his pioneering work in AI.Following service in the U.S. Navy from 1944 to 1945, Minsky enrolled in 1946 at Harvard University to explore his many intellectual interests. After completing research in physics, neurophysiology, and psychology, Minsky graduated with honours in mathematics in 1950. In 1951 he entered Princeton University, and in that same year he built the first neural n...
</Question>
<Choice>Minsky, Marvin Lee</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian-born American mathematician, engineer, and positivist philosopher who notably advanced statistics and probability theory.Von Mises's early work centred on geometry and mechanics, especially the theory of turbines. In 1913, during his appointment at the University of Strassburg (1909–18; now the French University of Strasbourg), he gave the first German university course on aviation, and he contributed to the theory of airfoil design. In 1915–16 he constructed a 600-horsepower airplane for the Austrian army on which he served as a test pilot.Von Mises had to leave Strasbourg after the...
</Question>
<Choice>Mises, Richard von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish mathematician who founded the international mathematical journal Acta Mathematica and whose contributions to mathematical research helped advance the Scandinavian school of mathematics.Mittag-Leffler studied in Paris under Charles Hermite and in Berlin under Karl Weierstrass, and in 1872 he became a lecturer in mathematics at the University of Uppsala, Sweden. Five years later he was appointed a professor of mathematics at the University of Helsinki, Finland. In 1881 he became a professor of mathematics at the University of Stockholm. With the financial patronage of King Oscar II of Sw...
</Question>
<Choice>Mittag-Leffler, Magnus Gosta</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German mathematician and theoretical astronomer who is best known for his work in analytic geometry and in topology. In the latter field he is especially remembered as one of the discoverers of the Möbius strip.Möbius entered the University of Leipzig in 1809 and soon decided to concentrate on mathematics, astronomy, and physics. From 1813 to 1814 he studied theoretical astronomy under Carl Friedrich Gauss at the University of Göttingen. He then studied mathematics at the University of Halle before he obtained a position as a professor of astronomy at Leipzig in 1816. From 1818 to 1821 Möbius...
</Question>
<Choice>Mobius, August Ferdinand</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician who was a pioneer in the development of analytic trigonometry and in the theory of probability.A French Huguenot, de Moivre was jailed as a Protestant upon the revocation of the Edict of Nantes in 1685. When he was released shortly thereafter, he fled to England. In London he became a close friend of Sir Isaac Newton and the astronomer Edmond Halley. De Moivre was elected to the Royal Society of London in 1697 and later to the Berlin and Paris academies. Despite his distinction as a mathematician, he never succeeded in securing a permanent position but eked out a precariou...
</Question>
<Choice>Moivre, Abraham de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician who invented descriptive geometry, the study of the mathematical principles of representing three-dimensional objects in a two-dimensional plane; no longer an active discipline in mathematics, the subject is part of mechanical and architectural drawing. He was a prominent figure during the French Revolution, helping to establish the metric system and the École Polytechnique. He was made a count in 1808 by Napoleon I.Monge was educated at the Oratorian schools at Beaune and at Lyon, where for a time at age 16 he was a physics teacher. He made a large-scale plan of Beaune du...
</Question>
<Choice>Monge, Gaspard, comte de Peluse</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese mathematician who was awarded the Fields Medal in 1990 for his work in algebraic geometry.Mori attended Kyoto University (B.A., 1973; M.A., 1975; Ph.D., 1978) and held an appointment there until 1980, when he went to Nagoya University. In 1990 he joined the faculty of the Research Institute for Mathematical Sciences at Kyoto.Mori was awarded the Fields Medal at the International Congress of Mathematicians in Kyoto in 1990. In 1979 Mori proved Hartshorne's conjecture, an unsolved problem in algebraic geometry. His most important work focused on the problem of classification of algebrai...
</Question>
<Choice>Mori Shigefumi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British-born mathematician who was awarded the Fields Medal in 1974 for his work in algebraic geometry.Mumford attended Harvard University, Cambridge, Massachusetts, U.S. (B.A., 1957; Ph.D., 1961), staying on to join the faculty upon graduation. He served as vice president (1991–94) and president (1995–98) of the International Mathematical Union. Mumford was awarded the Fields Medal at the International Congress of Mathematicians in Vancouver, British Columbia, Canada, in 1974. As with a number of Fields Medalists, Mumford's prizewinning work was in algebraic geometry. In some of his early wor...
</Question>
<Choice>Mumford, David Bryant</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish mathematician and theological writer who originated the concept of logarithms as a mathematical device to aid in calculations.
</Question>
<Choice>Napier, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American mathematician who was awarded the 1994 Nobel Prize for Economics for his landmark work, first begun in the 1950s, on the mathematics of game theory. He shared the Nobel Prize with the Hungarian American economist John C. Harsanyi and German mathematician Reinhard Selten.In 1948 Nash received bachelor's and master's degrees in mathematics from the Carnegie Institute of Technology (now Carnegie-Mellon University) in Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania. Two years later, at age 22, he completed his doctorate at Princeton University, publishing his influential thesis “Non-cooperative Games” in the jo...
</Question>
<Choice>Nash, John F., Jr.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Canadian-born American astronomer and mathematician who prepared ephemerides—tables of computed places of celestial bodies over a period of time—and tables of astronomical constants.
</Question>
<Choice>Newcomb, Simon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physicist and mathematician, who was the culminating figure of the scientific revolution of the 17th century. In optics, his discovery of the composition of white light integrated the phenomena of colours into the science of light and laid the foundation for modern physical optics. In mechanics, his three laws of motion, the basic principles of modern physics, resulted in the formulation of the law of universal gravitation. In mathematics, he was the original discoverer of the infinitesimal calculus. Newton's Philosophiae Naturalis Principia Mathematica (Mathematical Principles of Natu...
</Question>
<Choice>Newton, Sir Isaac</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polish mathematician and statistician who, working in Russian, Polish, and then English, helped to establish the statistical theory of hypothesis testing. Neyman was a principal founder of modern theoretical statistics. In 1969 he was awarded the prestigious National Medal of Science by U.S. Pres. Lyndon Johnson.Neyman was born into a Polish-speaking family and was raised in Bessarabia, the Crimea, and Ukraine under the Russian Empire. After serving as a lecturer at the Institute of Technology, Kharkov, in Ukraine, from 1917 to 1921, Neyman was appointed statistician of the Institute of Agricu...
</Question>
<Choice>Neyman, Jerzy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
cardinal, mathematician, scholar, experimental scientist, and influential philosopher who stressed the incomplete nature of man's knowledge of God and of the universe. At the Council of Basel in 1432, he gained recognition for his opposition to the candidate put forward by Pope Eugenius IV for the archbishopric of Trier. To his colleagues at the council he dedicated De concordantia catholica (1433; “On Catholic Concordance”), in which he expressed support for the supremacy of the general councils of the church over the authority of the papacy. In the same work he discussed the harmony of the c...
</Question>
<Choice>Nicholas of Cusa</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician and explorer.Nicollet showed promise in mathematics and astronomy early; he became a teacher of mathematics at the age of 19. In 1817 he began working with the scientist Pierre-Simon Laplace at the Paris Observatory, and in the 1820s he became a professor of mathematics at the Collège Louis-le-Grand in Paris.In 1832 Nicollet immigrated to the United States after financial reverses in France. He lived first in New Orleans, La., and then settled in St. Louis, Mo. With support from the wealthy Chouteau family of St. Louis, Nicollet in 1836–37 led an expedition that surveyed t...
</Question>
<Choice>Nicollet, Joseph Nicolas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Neo-Pythagorean philosopher and mathematician who wrote Arithmetike eisagoge (Introduction to Arithmetic), an influential treatise on number theory. Considered a standard authority for 1,000 years, the book sets out the elementary theory and properties of numbers and contains the earliest-known Greek multiplication table.Nicomachus was interested in philosophical questions dealing with whole numbers, the classification of even and odd numbers and their ratios, and wondrous or curious properties of numbers. For example, he was interested in the notion of “perfect numbers,” such as 6, which equa...
</Question>
<Choice>Nicomachus of Gerasa</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German mathematician whose innovations in higher algebra gained her recognition as the most creative abstract algebraist of modern times.Noether received a Ph.D. degree from the University of Erlangen in 1907, with a dissertation on algebraic invariants. From 1913 she lectured occasionally at Erlangen, substituting for her father, Max Noether (1844–1921). In 1915 she went to the University of Göttingen and was persuaded by the eminent mathematicians David Hilbert and Felix Klein to remain there over the objections of some faculty members; she won formal admission as an academic lecturer in 191...
</Question>
<Choice>Noether, Emmy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian mathematician who was awarded the Fields Medal in 1970 for his work in topology.Novikov graduated from Moscow State University in 1960 and received Ph.D. (1964) and Doctor of Science (1965) degrees from the V.A. Steklov Institute of Mathematics in Moscow. He joined the faculty at Moscow in 1964 and became head of the mathematics department at the L.D. Landau Institute of Theoretical Physics in 1975. In 1983 he became head of the mathematics department at the Steklov Institute.Novikov was awarded the Fields Medal at the International Congress of Mathematicians in Nice, France, in 1970....
</Question>
<Choice>Novikov, Sergey Petrovich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German scientist who is considered to be one of the founders of modern astronautics.The son of a prosperous physician, Oberth studied medicine in Munich, but his education was interrupted by service in the Austro-Hungarian army during World War I. After being wounded in the war, he found time to pursue his studies in astronautics. He performed experiments to simulate weightlessness and worked out a design for a long-range, liquid-propellant rocket that his commanding officer sent to the War Ministry. The design was rejected as a fantasy. After the war Oberth sought a Ph.D. degree at the Univer...
</Question>
<Choice>Oberth, Hermann Julius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Persian mathematician, astronomer, and poet, renowned in his own country and time for his scientific achievements but chiefly known to English-speaking readers through the translation of a collection of his roba?iyat (“quatrains”) in The Rubáiyát of Omar Khayyám (1859), by the English writer Edward FitzGerald.His name Khayyam (“Tentmaker”) may have been derived from his father's trade. He received a good education in the sciences and philosophy in his native Neyshabur before traveling to Samarkand (now in Uzbekistan), where he completed the algebra treatise, Risalah fi?l-barahin ?ala masa?il a...
</Question>
<Choice>Omar Khayyam</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French Roman Catholic bishop, scholastic philosopher, economist, and mathematician whose work provided some basis for the development of modern mathematics and science and of French prose, particularly its scientific vocabulary.It is known that Oresme was of Norman origin, although the exact place and year of his birth are uncertain. Similarly, the details of his early education are unknown. In 1348 his name appears on a list of graduate scholarship holders in theology at the College of Navarre at the University of Paris. As Oresme became grand master of the college in 1356, he must have compl...
</Question>
<Choice>Oresme, Nicholas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English mathematician and Anglican minister who invented the earliest form of the slide rule, two identical linear or circular logarithmic scales held together and adjusted by hand. Improvements involving the familiar inner sliding rule came later.Oughtred was educated at Eton College and at King's College, Cambridge, where he received his bachelor's degree (1596) and master's degree (1600). Before his ordainment as an Anglican priest in 1603 and appointment as vicar of Shalford in 1604, Oughtred had already designed (or improved upon) several instruments and composed various works that would...
</Question>
<Choice>Oughtred, William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French politician, mathematician, and patron of aviation who was prime minister at a crucial period of World War I and again during the 1925 financial crisis.Educated at the École Normale Supérieure (now part of the Universities of Paris), Painlevé completed his thesis on a problem in complex function theory at the University of Göttingen in Germany. He presented his thesis in Paris in 1887 and the same year became a professor at Lille. In 1892 he moved to Paris, where he taught at the École Polytechnique and the Collège de France (1896). He was a distinguished mathematician, and among his awa...
</Question>
<Choice>Painleve, Paul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the most important mathematical author writing in Greek during the later Roman Empire, known for his Synagoge (“Collection”), a voluminous account of the most important work done in ancient Greek mathematics. Other than that he was born at Alexandria in Egypt and that his career coincided with the first three decades of the 4th century AD, little is known about his life. Judging by the style of his writings, he was primarily a teacher of mathematics. Pappus seldom claimed to present original discoveries, but he had an eye for interesting material in his predecessors' writings, many of which ha...
</Question>
<Choice>Pappus of Alexandria</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician, physicist, religious philosopher, and master of prose. He laid the foundation for the modern theory of probabilities, formulated what came to be known as Pascal's law of pressure, and propagated a religious doctrine that taught the experience of God through the heart rather than through reason. The establishment of his principle of intuitionism had an impact on such later philosophers as Jean-Jacques Rousseau and Henri Bergson and also on the Existentialists.
</Question>
<Choice>Pascal, Blaise</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian mathematician and a founder of symbolic logic whose interests centred on the foundations of mathematics and on the development of a formal logical language.Peano became a lecturer of infinitesimal calculus at the University of Turin in 1884 and a professor in 1890. He also held the post of professor at the Accademia Militare in Turin from 1886 to 1901. Peano made several important discoveries, including a continuous mapping of a line onto every point of a square, that were highly counterintuitive and convinced him that mathematics should be developed formally if mistakes were to be avo...
</Question>
<Choice>Peano, Giuseppe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British statistician, leading founder of the modern field of statistics, prominent proponent of eugenics, and influential interpreter of the philosophy and social role of science.Pearson was descended on both sides of his family from Yorkshire Quakers, and, although he was brought up in the Church of England and as an adult adhered to agnosticism or “freethought,” he always identified with his Quaker ancestry. Until about age 24 it seemed that he would follow his father, a barrister who rose to Queen's Counsel, into the law, but he was tempted by many possible careers. In 1875 Pearson won a sc...
</Question>
<Choice>Pearson, Karl</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American mathematician, astronomer, and educator who computed the general perturbations of the planets Uranus and Neptune.Peirce graduated from Harvard University in 1829 and accepted a teaching position with George Bancroft at his Round Hill School in Northampton, Massachusetts. Two years later Peirce was asked to join the faculty at Harvard as a tutor in mathematics. Much of his reputation was based on two of his early works. The first was his solution to a mathematical problem proposed in the journal Mathematical Diary, in which he proved that there is no odd perfect number (a number that i...
</Question>
<Choice>Peirce, Benjamin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British mathematician and relativist who in the 1960s calculated many of the basic features of black holes.After obtaining a Ph.D. in algebraic geometry from the University of Cambridge in 1957, Penrose held temporary posts at a number of universities in both England and America. From 1964 to 1973 he served as reader and eventually professor of applied mathematics at Birkbeck College, London. From 1973 he held the Rouse-Ball chair of mathematics at the University of Oxford. He was knighted for his services to science in 1994.In 1969, with Stephen Hawking, Penrose proved that all matter within...
</Question>
<Choice>Penrose, Sir Roger</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian mathematician and astronomer instrumental in the European revival of the technical understanding of the astronomical ideas of Ptolemy (fl. c. AD 140) and the early use of sines in Europe.Nothing is known of Peuerbach's life before 1446, when he entered the University of Vienna (B.A., 1448). Between 1448 and 1451 he traveled, notably in northern Italy, where he lectured on astronomy in Padua. Returning to Vienna, he became a master of arts in 1453 and lectured on Latin poetry at the university. His own literary aspirations appear in Latin love poems addressed to a young Carthusian novi...
</Question>
<Choice>Peuerbach, Georg von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician whose theories did much to advance research in analysis, algebraic geometry, and mechanics.Picard became a lecturer at the University of Paris in 1878 and a professor at the University of Toulouse the following year. From 1881 to 1898 he held various posts with the University of Toulouse and the École Normale Supérieure (now part of the Universities of Paris), and in 1898 he was appointed a professor at the University of Paris. In 1917 he was elected permanent secretary for the mathematical sciences in the French Academy of Sciences. After World War I he led a decade-long...
</Question>
<Choice>Picard, Charles-Emile</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek Orthodox humanities scholar, anthologist, and theological polemicist in the controversy between Byzantium and Rome. His Greek translations of works in classical Latin philosophy and literature and in Arabic mathematics publicized these areas of learning throughout the Greek Byzantine cultural world.After entering political life in Constantinople, Planudes retired to a monastery in 1283 because of factional strife. He later returned to Constantinople, where he established a monastery for laymen and opened a school by the imperial library. Drawing students from the royal family and nobilit...
</Question>
<Choice>Planudes, Maximus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German mathematician and physicist who made fundamental contributions to analytic and projective geometry as well as experimental physics.Plücker attended the universities in Heidelberg, Bonn, Berlin, and Paris. In 1829, after four years as an unsalaried lecturer, he became a professor at the University of Bonn, where he wrote Analytisch-geometrische Entwicklungen, 2 vol. (1828–31; “The Development of Analytic Geometry”). This work introduced abridged notation (a flexible type of mathematical “shorthand”) and exploited the possibility of taking lines rather than points as the fundamental geome...
</Question>
<Choice>Plucker, Julius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician, one of the greatest mathematicians and mathematical physicists at the end of 19th century. He made a series of profound innovations in geometry, the theory of differential equations, electromagnetism, topology, and the philosophy of mathematics.Poincaré grew up in Nancy and studied mathematics from 1873 to 1875 at the École Polytechnique in Paris. He continued his studies at the Mining School in Caen before receiving his doctorate from the École Polytechnique in 1879. While a student, he discovered new types of complex functions that solved a wide variety of differential...
</Question>
<Choice>Poincare, Henri</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician known for his work on definite integrals, electromagnetic theory, and probability.Poisson's family had intended him for a medical career, but he showed little interest or aptitude and in 1798 began studying mathematics at the École Polytechnique in Paris under the mathematicians Pierre-Simon Laplace and Joseph-Louis Lagrange, who became his lifelong friends. He became a professor at the École Polytechnique in 1802. In 1808 he was made an astronomer at the Bureau of Longitudes, and, when the Faculty of Sciences was instituted in 1809, he was appointed a professor of pure ma...
</Question>
<Choice>Poisson, Simeon-Denis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician and engineer who was one of the founders of modern projective geometry.As a lieutenant of engineers in 1812, he took part in Napoleon's Russian campaign, in which he was abandoned as dead at Krasnoy and imprisoned at Saratov; he returned to France in 1814. During his imprisonment Poncelet studied projective geometry and wrote Applications d'analyse et de géométrie, 2 vol. (1862–64; “Applications of Analysis and Geometry”). This work was originally planned as an introduction to his celebrated Traité des propriétés projectives des figures (1822; “Treatise on the Projective P...
</Question>
<Choice>Poncelet, Jean-Victor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian mathematician, noted for contributions to topology, algebra, and dynamical systems.Pontryagin lost his eyesight as the result of an explosion when he was about 14 years old. His mother became his tutor, describing mathematical symbols as they appeared to her, since she did not know their meaning or names. Entering Moscow State University in 1925, he soon became friends with Pavel Aleksandrov, who was developing point-set and combinatorial topology. Under Aleksandrov's influence, Pontryagin spent most of the 1930s and '40s investigating topology; his papers were collected and published...
</Question>
<Choice>Pontryagin, Lev Semyonovich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British mathematician and chemist who, with Walter Kohn, received the 1998 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for work on computational methodology in quantum chemistry. Pople's share of the prize recognized his development of computer-based methods of studying the quantum mechanics of molecules.Pople was educated at the University of Cambridge and received a Ph.D. in mathematics from that institution in 1951. He was a fellow at Trinity College, Cambridge, from 1951 to 1958 and a lecturer in mathematics there from 1954 to 1958. He then headed the Basic Physics Division of the National Physical Laborato...
</Question>
<Choice>Pople, Sir John A.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
an Egyptian astronomer, mathematician, and geographer of Greek descent who flourished in Alexandria during the 2nd century AD. In several fields his writings represent the culminating achievement of Greco-Roman science, particularly his geocentric (Earth-centred) model of the universe now known as the Ptolemaic system.Virtually nothing is known about Ptolemy's life except what can be inferred from his writings. His first major astronomical work, the Almagest, was completed about AD 150 and contains reports of astronomical observations that Ptolemy had made over the preceding quarter of a centu...
</Question>
<Choice>Ptolemy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek philosopher, mathematician, and founder of the Pythagorean brotherhood that, although religious in nature, formulated principles that influenced the thought of Plato and Aristotle and contributed to the development of mathematics and Western rational philosophy (seePythagoreanism).Pythagoras migrated to southern Italy about 532 BC, apparently to escape Samos's tyrannical rule, and established his ethico-political academy at Croton (now Crotone, Italy).It is difficult to distinguish Pythagoras's teachings from those of his disciples. None of his writings have survived, and Pythagoreans in...
</Question>
<Choice>Pythagoras</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese mathematician who developed a method of solving simultaneous linear congruences.In 1219 Qin joined the army as captain of a territorial volunteer unit and helped quash a local rebellion. In 1224–25 Qin studied astronomy and mathematics in the capital Lin'an (modern Hangzhou) with functionaries of the Imperial Astronomical Bureau and with an unidentified hermit. In 1233 Qin began his official mandarin (government) service. He interrupted his government career for three years beginning in 1244 because of his mother's death; during the mourning period he wrote his only mathematical book,...
</Question>
<Choice>Qin Jiushao</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Belgian mathematician, astronomer, statistician, and sociologist known for his application of statistics and probability theory to social phenomena.From 1819 Quetelet lectured at the Brussels Athenaeum, military college, and museum. In 1823 he went to Paris to study astronomy, meteorology, and the management of an astronomical observatory. While there he learned probability from Joseph Fourier and, conceivably, from Pierre-Simon Laplace. Quetelet founded (1828) and directed the Royal Observatory in Brussels, served as perpetual secretary of the Belgian Royal Academy (1834–74), and organized th...
</Question>
<Choice>Quetelet, Adolphe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American mathematician who was awarded the Fields Medal in 1978 for contributions to algebraic K-theory.Quillen attended Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass. (Ph.D., 1969), and held appointments at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (1973–88) and the Mathematical Institute of Oxford (Eng.) University (1988– ).Quillen was awarded the Fields Medal at the International Congress of Mathematicians in Helsinki, Fin., in 1978. In addition to Quillen's application of geometric and topological techniques to the study of algebraic K-theory, he made contributions in topology to the cobordism theor...
</Question>
<Choice>Quillen, Daniel Gray</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian mathematician whose contributions to the theory of numbers include pioneering discoveries of the properties of the partition function.When he was 15 years old, he obtained a copy of George Shoobridge Carr's Synopsis of Elementary Results in Pure and Applied Mathematics, 2 vol. (1880–86). This collection of some 6,000 theorems (none of the material was newer than 1860) aroused his genius. Having verified the results in Carr's book, Ramanujan went beyond it, developing his own theorems and ideas. In 1903 he secured a scholarship to the University of Madras but lost it the following year b...
</Question>
<Choice>Ramanujan, Srinivasa</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
physician, mathematician, and author of introductory mathematics textbooks.
</Question>
<Choice>Recorde, Robert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the foremost mathematician and astronomer of 15th-century Europe, a sought-after astrologer, and one of the first printers.Königsberg means “King's Mountain,” which is what the Latinized version of his name, Joannes de Regio monte or Regiomontanus, also means. A miller's son, he entered the University of Leipzig at the age of 11 and in 1450 went to the University of Vienna. Regiomontanus was awarded a baccalaureate in 1452, but university regulations forced him to wait until he turned 21 to receive his master's degree. He eventually collaborated with his teacher, the mathematician-astronomer G...
</Question>
<Choice>Regiomontanus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian-born astronomer and mathematician who was among the first to adopt and spread the heliocentric theory of Nicolaus Copernicus.In 1536 Rheticus was appointed to a chair of mathematics and astronomy at the University of Wittenberg. Intrigued by the news of the Copernican theory that Earth revolves around the Sun, he went to Frauenburg (now Frombork, Pol.) in 1539, where he studied for two years with Copernicus. Rheticus published the first account of the new views in his De libris revolutionum…Nic. Copernici…narratio prima… (1540; “The First Account of the Book on the Revolutions by Nico...
</Question>
<Choice>Rheticus, Georg Joachim</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian mathematician instrumental in the development of absolute differential calculus, formerly also called the Ricci calculus but now known as tensor analysis.Ricci was a professor at the University of Padua from 1880 to 1925. His earliest work was in mathematical physics, notably on the laws of electric circuits, and in differential equations. Ricci created the systematic theory of tensor analysis in 1887–96, with significant extensions later contributed by his pupil Tullio Levi-Civita.Tensor analysis concerns relations that are covariant—i.e., relations that remain valid when changed from...
</Question>
<Choice>Ricci-Curbastro, Gregorio</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physicist and psychologist who was the first to apply mathematical techniques to predict the weather accurately.Richardson made major contributions to methods of solving certain types of problems in physics, and from 1913 to 1922 he applied his ideas to meteorology. His work, published in Weather Prediction by Numerical Process (1922), was not entirely successful at first. The main drawback to his mathematical technique for systematically forecasting the weather was the time necessary to produce such a forecast. It generally took him three months to predict the weather for the next 24...
</Question>
<Choice>Richardson, Lewis Fry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German mathematician whose profound and novel approaches to the study of geometry laid the mathematical foundation for Albert Einstein's theory of relativity. He also made important contributions to the theory of functions, complex analysis, and number theory.Riemann was born into a poor Lutheran pastor's family, and all his life he was a shy and introverted person. He was fortunate to have a schoolteacher who recognized his rare mathematical ability and lent him advanced books to read, including Adrien-Marie Legendre's Number Theory (1830). Riemann read the book in a week and then claimed to...
</Question>
<Choice>Riemann, Bernhard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hungarian mathematician and pioneer of functional analysis, which has found important applications to mathematical physics.Riesz taught mathematics at the University of Kolozsvár (Cluj) from 1911 and in 1922 became editor of the newly founded Acta Scientiarum Mathematicarum, which quickly found a position of distinction among the mathematical journals of the world. He was appointed professor of mathematics at the University of Budapest in 1945.Many of Riesz's fundamental findings in functional analysis were incorporated with those of Stefan Banach of Poland. The Riesz-Fischer theorem of 1907,...
</Question>
<Choice>Riesz, Frigyes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician who made important advances in the geometry of curves.In 1632 Roberval became professor of mathematics at the Collège de France, Paris, a position he held until his death. He studied the methods of determination of surface area and volume of solids, developing and improving the method of indivisibles used by the Italian mathematician Bonaventura Cavalieri for computing some of the simpler cases. He discovered a general method of drawing tangents, by treating a curve as the result of the motion of a moving point and by resolving the motion of the point into two simpler comp...
</Question>
<Choice>Roberval, Gilles Personne de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British mathematician and military engineer who laid the groundwork for modern ordnance (field-artillery) theory and practice with his New Principles of Gunnery (1742), which invalidated old suppositions about the nature and action of gunpowder and the flight of projectiles and formed the basis of all later scientific studies in these fields. His invention of the ballistic pendulum, a device allowing the determination of the momentum of a projectile suddenly halted in its flight, enabled gunners for the first time to measure with considerable exactness the muzzle velocities of projectiles deli...
</Question>
<Choice>Robins, Benjamin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician and physicist who contributed to the development of the French atomic bomb and to the understanding of such diverse fields of research as semiconductors, seismology, and radio astronomy.Rocard received doctorates in mathematics (1927) and physical science (1928) from the École Normale Supérieure (ENS) in Paris and took a job in the electronics industry. During World War II he worked with the resistance and supplied British scientific intelligence with vital information, including details on a new radio navigational beam station. For this assistance he was made a Commander...
</Question>
<Choice>Rocard, Yves-Andre</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-born British mathematician who was awarded the Fields Medal in 1958 for his work in number theory.Roth attended Peterhouse College, Cambridge, Eng. (B.A., 1945), and the University of London (M.Sc., 1948; Ph.D., 1950). From 1948 to 1966 he held an appointment at University College, London, then became professor of pure mathematics at Imperial College of Science, Technology and Medicine, London, a position he held until 1988.Roth was awarded the Fields Medal at the International Congress of Mathematicians in Edinburgh in 1958. His major work has been in number theory, particularly the an...
</Question>
<Choice>Roth, Klaus Friedrich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian mathematician and physician who made studies of equations that anticipated the algebraic theory of groups. He is regarded as the first to make a significant attempt to show that there is no algebraic solution to the general quintic equation (an equation whose highest-degree term is raised to the fifth power).When Ruffini was still a teenager, his family moved to Reggio, near Modena, Italy. He entered the University of Modena in 1783 and while still a student taught a course there in the foundations of analysis for the 1787–88 academic year. Ruffini received degrees in philosophy, medic...
</Question>
<Choice>Ruffini, Paolo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British philosopher, logician, and social reformer, founding figure in the analytic movement in Anglo-American philosophy, and recipient of the Nobel Prize for Literature in 1950. Russell's contributions to logic, epistemology, and the philosophy of mathematics established him as one of the foremost philosophers of the 20th century. To the general public, however, he was best known as a campaigner for peace and as a popular writer on social, political, and moral subjects. During a long, productive, and often turbulent life, he published more than 70 books and about 2,000 articles, married four...
</Question>
<Choice>Russell, Bertrand</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician who was awarded the Fields Medal in 1950 for his work in functional analysis.Schwartz received his early education at the École Normale Supérieure (now part of the Universities of Paris) and the Faculty of Science, both located in Paris. He received his doctorate in mathematical sciences in Paris, after which he became a professor at the University of Nancy (1945–52). He joined the Faculty of Science (1953–83) and also served as a professor of analysis at the École Polytechnique, Palaiseau (1959–60, 1963–83).Schwartz was awarded the Fields Medal at the International Congre...
</Question>
<Choice>Schwartz, Laurent</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist and mathematician who in 1751 introduced the concept of the surface tension of liquids, likening it to a stretched membrane. His view that minute and imperceptible attractive forces maintain surface tension laid the foundation for the subsequent development of surface tension theory.Segner taught physics and mathematics at the universities of Jena, Göttingen, and Halle. In 1750 he developed a simple-reaction waterwheel. The study of this machine by the mathematician Leonhard Euler led to the development of a crude turbine. Segner also studied the theory of the spinning top and...
</Question>
<Choice>Segner, Johann Andreas von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the most important figure of the wasan (“Japanese calculation”) tradition (seemathematics, East Asian: Japan in the 17th century) that flourished from the early 17th century until the opening of Japan to the West in the mid-19th century. Seki was instrumental in recovering neglected and forgotten mathematical knowledge from ancient Chinese sources and then extending and generalizing the main problems.Little is known about Seki's life and intellectual formation. He was the second son of Nagaakira Uchiyama, a samurai; he was adopted at an early age by Seki Gorozaemon, a samurai official with the...
</Question>
<Choice>Seki Takakazu</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Norwegian-born American mathematician who was awarded the Fields Medal in 1950 for his work in number theory. In 1986 he shared (with Samuel Eilenberg) the Wolf Prize.Selberg attended the University of Oslo (Ph.D., 1943) and remained there as a research fellow until 1947. He then became a fellow at the Institute for Advanced Study, Princeton, N.J., and a member of the faculty from 1949 until his retirement in 1987. In the 1990s he became a U.S. citizen.Selberg was awarded the Fields Medal at the International Congress of Mathematicians in Cambridge, Mass., in 1950. His work in analytic number...
</Question>
<Choice>Selberg, Atle</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German mathematician who shared the 1994 Nobel Prize for Economics with John F. Nash and John C. Harsanyi for their development of game theory, a branch of mathematics that examines rivalries among competitors with mixed interests.The son of a bookseller, Selten studied mathematics at the University of Frankfurt and graduated in 1957. He became interested in game theory in the late 1940s when he read an article about the subject in the magazine Fortune. Refining the research of Nash, Selten in 1965 proposed theories that distinguished between reasonable and unreasonable decisions in predicting...
</Question>
<Choice>Selten, Reinhard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician who was awarded the Fields Medal in 1954 for his work in algebraic topology. In 2003 he was awarded the first Abel Prize by the Norwegian Academy of Science and Letters.Serre attended the École Normale Supérieure (1945–48) and the Sorbonne (Ph.D.; 1951), both now part of the Universities of Paris. Between 1948 and 1954 he was at the National Centre for Scientific Research in Paris, and after two years at the University of Nancy he returned to Paris for a position at the Collège de France. He retired in 1994. Between 1983 and 1986 Serre served as vice president of the Inter...
</Question>
<Choice>Serre, Jean-Pierre</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American educator, noted for the improvements she made in the curriculum of Wellesley College both as mathematics chair and as school president.Shafer graduated in 1863 from Oberlin (Ohio) College. After two years of teaching in New Jersey she joined the faculty of St. Louis (Missouri) High School, where her work as a teacher of mathematics attracted the favourable notice of the superintendent of St. Louis schools, William Torrey Harris, later U.S. commissioner of education. In 1877 she was given the chair of mathematics at the two-year-old Wellesley College. Her work in establishing high stan...
</Question>
<Choice>Shafer, Helen Almira</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American mathematician and electrical engineer who laid the theoretical foundations for digital circuits and information theory, a mathematical communication model.After graduating from the University of Michigan in 1936 with bachelor's degrees in mathematics and electrical engineering, Shannon obtained a research assistant's position at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT). There, among other duties, he worked with the noted researcher Vannevar Bush, helping to set up differential equations on Bush's differential analyzer. A summer internship at American Telephone and Telegraph's B...
</Question>
<Choice>Shannon, Claude</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese philosopher who greatly influenced the development of the idealist school of Neo-Confucianism (seeConfucianism). Shao Yong's mathematical ideas also influenced the 18th-century European philosopher Gottfried Wilhelm Leibniz in the development of a binary arithmetical system—i.e., one based on only two digits.Originally a Daoist, Shao refused all offers of government office, preferring to while away the hours in a humble hermitage outside Luoyang, conversing with friends and engaging in mystical speculation. He became interested in Confucianism through his study of the great Confucian C...
</Question>
<Choice>Shao Yung</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese astronomer, mathematician, and high official whose famous work Mengxi bitan (“Brush Talks from Dream Brook” [Dream Brook was the name of his estate in Jingkou]) contains the first reference to the magnetic compass, the first description of movable type, and a fairly accurate explanation of the origin of fossils. The Mengxi bitan also contains Shen's observations on such varied subjects as mathematics, astronomy, atmospheric phenomena, cartography, optics, and medicine. Shen produced a number of works, including commentaries on the Confucian Classics, atlases, diplomatic reports, and a...
</Question>
<Choice>Shen Kua</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
highly esteemed Hindu mathematician who wrote several treatises on the two major fields of Indian mathematics, pati-ganita (“mathematics of procedures,” or algorithms) and bija-ganita (“mathematics of seeds,” or equations).Very little is known about Shridhara's life. Some scholars believe that he was born in Bengal, while others believe that he was born in South India. All three of Shridhara's extant works—the partially preserved Patiganita, Ganitasara (“Essence of Mathematics”), and Ganitapanchavimashi (“Mathematics in 25 Verses”)—belong to pati-ganita, but, according to Bhaskara II (1114–c....
</Question>
<Choice>Shridhara</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian astronomer-astrologer and mathematician whose astrological writings were particularly influential.Shripati wrote various works in the first two of the three branches of astral science (jyotihshastra)—namely, mathematics (including astronomy), horoscopic astrology, and natural astrology (divination). For the first branch, he wrote Ganitatilaka (“The Ornament of Mathematics”) and the astronomical works Siddhantashekhara (“The Crest of Established Doctrines”), Dhikotidakarana (“Procedure Giving Intellectual Climax”), and Dhruvamanasa (“Permanent Mind”). Siddhantashekhara is modeled on Brah...
</Question>
<Choice>Shripati</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch mathematician, astronomer, and cosmologist who developed theoretical models of the universe based on Albert Einstein's general theory of relativity.De Sitter studied mathematics at the State University of Groningen and then joined the astronomical laboratory there, where under J.C. Kapteyn's guidance he developed a liking for astronomy. He spent the years 1897–99 at the Cape Observatory in South Africa and devoted himself to astronomy thereafter. In 1908 de Sitter became professor of astronomy at the University of Leiden, and in 1919 he became director of the Leiden Observatory.In his ea...
</Question>
<Choice>Sitter, Willem de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American mathematician, who was awarded the Fields Medal in 1966 for his work on topology in higher dimensions.Smale grew up in a rural area near Flint. From 1948 to 1956 he attended the University of Michigan, obtaining B.S., M.S., and Ph.D. degrees in mathematics. As an instructor at the University of Chicago from 1956 to 1958, Smale achieved notoriety by proving that there exists an eversion of the sphere (meaning, in a precise theoretical sense, that it is possible to turn a sphere inside out).In 1960 Smale obtained his two most famous mathematical results. First he constructed a function,...
</Question>
<Choice>Smale, Stephen</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek astronomer and mathematician, probably from Alexandria, employed by Julius Caesar to devise the Julian calendar. He is sometimes confused with Sosigenes the Peripatetic (fl. 2nd century AD), the tutor of the Greek philosopher Alexander of Aphrodisias.At the conclusion of the Roman civil war (49–45 BC), Caesar set out to replace the multitude of inaccurate and diverse calendars of the Roman commonwealth with a single official calendar. At the suggestion of Sosigenes, he adopted a modification of the 365-day Egyptian solar calendar but with an extra day every fourth year (leap year). (The...
</Question>
<Choice>Sosigenes of Alexandria</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German mathematician who developed the first purely synthetic theory of imaginary points, lines, and planes in projective geometry. Later geometers, especially Felix Klein (1849–1925), Moritz Pasch (1843–1930), and David Hilbert (1862–1943), exploited these possibilities for bridging the gap between synthetic and analytic methods in geometry.Staudt studied mathematics and astronomy under Carl Gauss from 1818 to 1822 at the University of Göttingen. Under Gauss's supervision he published research on ephemerides and the orbits of asteroids. After taking his doctorate at the University of Erlangen...
</Question>
<Choice>Staudt, Karl George Christian von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss mathematician who was one of the founders of modern synthetic and projective geometry.As the son of a small farmer, Steiner had no early schooling and did not learn to write until he was 14. Against the wishes of his parents, at 18 he entered the Pestalozzi School at Yverdon, Switzerland, where his extraordinary geometric intuition was discovered. Later he went to the University of Heidelberg and the University of Berlin to study, supporting himself precariously as a tutor. By 1824 he had studied the geometric transformations that led him to the theory of inversive geometry, but he did n...
</Question>
<Choice>Steiner, Jakob</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-born American electrical engineer whose ideas on alternating current systems helped inaugurate the electrical era in the United States.At birth Steinmetz was afflicted with a physical deformity, hunchback, and as a youth he showed an unusual capability in mathematics, physics, and classical literature. On graduating from the gymnasium with honours, he entered the University of Breslau in 1883. There he joined a student socialist club, which was banned by the government after becoming affiliated with the German Social Democrats. When some of his fellow party members were arrested, Steinm...
</Question>
<Choice>Steinmetz, Charles Proteus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Flemish mathematician who helped standardize the use of decimal fractions and aided in refuting Aristotle's doctrine that heavy bodies fall faster than light ones.Stevin was a merchant's clerk in Antwerp for a time and eventually rose to become commissioner of public works and quartermaster general of the army under Prince Maurice of Nassau. He engineered a system of sluices to flood certain areas and drive off any enemy, an important defense of Holland. He also invented a 26-passenger carriage with sails for use along the seashore.In De Beghinselen der Weeghconst (1586; “Statics and Hydrostat...
</Question>
<Choice>Stevin, Simon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
philosopher and major exponent of the Scottish “common sense” school of philosophy.Educated at the University of Edinburgh, where his father was professor of mathematics, Stewart began teaching there when he was 19. In 1775 he took over his father's chair and 10 years later was appointed professor of moral philosophy, a position he held until 1820.As a student, Stewart had come under the influence of the works of the Scottish realist Thomas Reid, particularly An Inquiry into the Human Mind on the Principles of Common Sense (1764). Stewart, like Reid, held that philosophy should be a scientific...
</Question>
<Choice>Stewart, Dugald</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch-born French mathematician who made notable contributions to the theory of infinite series. He is remembered as “the father of the analytic theory of continued fractions.”Stieltjes was the son of a civil engineer and enrolled in 1873 at the École Polytechnique in Delft. However, he was more interested in reading mathematical monographs in the school's library than in attending classes and failed his exams that year, as well as subsequent exams in 1875 and 1876. In 1877 his father got him a position as an assistant at the Leiden Observatory. After six years of work at the observatory, duri...
</Question>
<Choice>Stieltjes, Thomas Jan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish mathematician who contributed important advances to the theory of infinite series and infinitesimal calculus.No absolutely reliable information about Stirling's undergraduate education in Scotland is known. According to one source, he was educated at the University of Glasgow, while another source indicates that he attended his father's alma mater, the University of Edinburgh. Beginning in 1711, Stirling matriculated at Balliol College, Oxford, England, on various graduate scholarships for which he was initially exempted as a Jacobite (a supporter of the exiled Stuart king, James II)...
</Question>
<Choice>Stirling, James</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physicist and mathematician noted for his studies of the behaviour of viscous fluids, particularly for his law of viscosity, which describes the motion of a solid sphere in a fluid, and for Stokes's theorem, a basic theorem of vector analysis.Stokes, who was appointed Lucasian Professor of Mathematics at Cambridge University in 1849, earlier had published his first papers on fluid motion and the steady motion of incompressible fluids (1842 and 1843) and his work on the friction of fluids in motion and the equilibrium and motion of elastic solids (1845). He worked on fluorescence (he or...
</Question>
<Choice>Stokes, Sir George Gabriel, 1st Baronet</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
geophysicist and mathematician who developed a mathematical theory of auroral phenomena.Professor of pure mathematics at the University of Christiania (Oslo, after 1924) from 1903 to 1946, Størmer began his mathematical work with studies of series, function theory, and number theory. He produced a number of papers on pure mathematics, and many of his results are of considerable importance. In 1895 he demonstrated that there are only four nontrivial solutions for the equation m tan-1(1/x) + n tan-1(1/y) = kp/4, in which m, n, k, x, and y are integers.In 1903 Størmer became interested in Kristia...
</Question>
<Choice>Stormer, Fredrik Carl Mulertz</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician whose work resulted in Sturm's theorem, an important contribution to the theory of equations.As tutor of the de Broglie family in Paris (1823–24), Sturm met many of the leading French scientists and mathematicians. In 1826, with the Swiss engineer Daniel Colladon, he made the first accurate determination of the velocity of sound in water, and a year later he wrote a prizewinning essay on compressible fluids.Sturm's theorem first appeared in Mémoire sur la résolution des équations numériques (1829; “Treatise on Numerical Equations”) and provided a complete solution to the p...
</Question>
<Choice>Sturm, Charles-Francois</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French head of the Roman Catholic church (999–1003), renowned for his scholarly achievements, his advances in education, and his shrewd political judgment. He was the first Frenchman to become pope.
</Question>
<Choice>Sylvester II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British mathematician who, with Arthur Cayley, was a cofounder of invariant theory, the study of properties that are unchanged (invariant) under some transformation, such as rotating or translating the coordinate axes. He also made significant contributions to number theory and elliptic functions.In 1837 Sylvester came second in the mathematical tripos at the University of Cambridge but, as a Jew, was prevented from taking his degree or securing an appointment there. In 1838 he became a professor of natural philosophy at University College, London (the only nonsectarian British university). In...
</Question>
<Choice>Sylvester, James Joseph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish physicist and mathematician who helped develop quaternions, an advanced algebra that gave rise to vector analysis and was instrumental in the development of modern mathematical physics.After serving from 1852 to 1854 as a fellow and lecturer at Peterhouse College, Cambridge, England, Tait took a professorship in mathematics at Queen's College, Belfast, Ireland. There he joined the noted Irish chemist Thomas Andrews in research on the density of ozone and the effect of electric discharges on oxygen and other gases. From 1860 he was a professor of natural philosophy at the University of...
</Question>
<Choice>Tait, Peter Guthrie</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese mathematician of the wasan (“Japanese calculation”) tradition (seemathematics, East Asian: Japan in the 17th century) who extended and disseminated the mathematical research of his teacher Seki Takakazu (c. 1640–1708).Takebe's career was one of the most prestigious that a wasan mathematician ever experienced. He served successively two shoguns, Tokugawa Ienobu (reigned 1709–12; seeTokugawa period), initially lord of Kofu, whom he escorted all along his rise to the supreme position, and Tokugawa Yoshimune (reigned 1716–45), an enlightened sovereign who gave a significant impulse to sci...
</Question>
<Choice>Takebe Katahiro</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polish-born American mathematician and logician who made important studies of general algebra, measure theory, mathematical logic, set theory, and metamathematics.Tarski completed his education at the University of Warsaw (Ph.D., 1923). He taught in Warsaw until 1939, when he moved to the United States (becoming a naturalized citizen in 1945). He joined the staff of the University of California at Berkeley in 1942, was appointed professor of mathematics (1949), and was research professor of the Miller Institute of Basic Research in Science there (1958–60). In succeeding years he was responsibl...
</Question>
<Choice>Tarski, Alfred</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian mathematician who originated the science of ballistics.During the French sack of Brescia (1512), his jaws and palate were cleft by a sabre. The resulting speech difficulty earned him the nickname Tartaglia (“Stammerer”), which he adopted. He settled in Venice in 1534 as a teacher of mathematics.Tartaglia's Nova Scientia (1537; “A New Science”), a treatise on gunnery, is an important pioneering effort to establish the laws of falling bodies. Soon after the publication of this work, Tartaglia was asked by Girolamo Cardano, physician and lecturer in Milan, to publish his solution to the c...
</Question>
<Choice>Tartaglia, Niccolo Fontana</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British mathematician, a proponent of Newtonian mechanics and noted for his contributions to the development of calculus.Taylor was born into a prosperous and educated family who encouraged the development of his musical and artistic talents, both of which found mathematical expression in his later life. He was tutored at home before he entered St. John's College, Cambridge, in 1701 to study law. He completed his LL.B. in 1709 and his doctorate in 1714, but it is doubtful that he ever practiced as a lawyer.Taylor's first important mathematical paper, which provided a solution to the problem of...
</Question>
<Choice>Taylor, Brook</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German psychologist, mathematician, economist, educator, and empiricist philosopher who strongly influenced the work of Immanuel Kant.Tetens became professor of physics at Bützow University in 1760 and five years later was made director of the Pädagogium (“Academy”) there. In 1776 he was appointed professor of philosophy at the University of Kiel, where he later held the chair of mathematics. He gave up teaching in 1789 to enter public service, becoming assessor and then councillor of state and deputy in the Danish Ministry of Finance in Copenhagen.Tetens' major work, Philosophische Versuche ü...
</Question>
<Choice>Tetens, Johannes Nikolaus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Arab mathematician, astronomer, physician, and philosopher, a representative of the flourishing Arab-Islamic culture of the 9th century.Thabit was a scion of a prominent family settled in ?arran, a city noted as the seat of a Hellenized Semitic astronomical cult of which Thabit was a member. By calling themselves Sabians, after a group mentioned in the Qur'an, the cult members established themselves as “People of the Book” and hence were freed from the requirement of conversion to Islam. Some sources describe Thabit as a money changer in ?arran, and, although the sources give two different acc...
</Question>
<Choice>Thabit ibn Qurra</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Athenian mathematician who had a significant influence on the development of Greek geometry.Theaetetus was a disciple of Socrates and studied with Theodorus of Cyrene. He taught at some time in Heraclea (located in present-day southern Italy). Plato made Theaetetus the chief subject of two dialogues—Theaetetos (Theaetetus) and Sophistes (Sophist)—the former being the major source of information about Theaetetus's life, including his death in a battle between Athens and Corinth in 369 BC.Theaetetus made important contributions to the mathematics that Euclid (fl. c. 300 BC) eventually collected...
</Question>
<Choice>Theaetetus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician who was awarded the Fields Medal in 1958 for his work in topology.Thom graduated from the École Normale Supérieure (now part of the Universities of Paris) in 1946, spent four years at the nearby National Centre for Scientific Research, and in 1951 was awarded a doctorate by the University of Paris. He held appointments at the University of Grenoble (1953–54) and the University of Strasbourg (1954–63). In 1964 he became a professor at the Institute of Advanced Scientific Studies, Bures-sur-Yvette.Thom was awarded the Fields Medal at the International Congress of Mathematici...
</Question>
<Choice>Thom, Rene Frederic</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American mathematician who was awarded the Fields Medal in 1970 for his work in group theory. In 2008 the Norwegian Academy of Science and Letters awarded Thompson and Jacques Tits of France the Abel Prize for their “profound achievements in algebra and in particular for shaping modern group theory.”Thompson earned a B.A. from Yale University in 1955 and a Ph.D. from the University of Chicago in 1959. After a year at Harvard University (1961–62), he returned to the University of Chicago (1962–68), and he subsequently moved to Churchill College, Cambridge, England.Thompson was awarded the Field...
</Question>
<Choice>Thompson, John Griggs</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American mathematician who won the 1982 Fields Medal for his work in topology.Thurston was educated at New College, Sarasota, Florida (B.A., 1967), and the University of California, Berkeley (Ph.D., 1972). After a year at the Institute for Advanced Study, Princeton, New Jersey, he joined the faculty of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (1973–74) and then moved to Princeton University, where he remained until 1991. In 1992 he became director of the Mathematical Sciences Research Institute at Berkeley. In 1996 he moved to the University of California, Davis.Thurston received the Fields M...
</Question>
<Choice>Thurston, William Paul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English mathematician whose contributions to analysis placed him at the forefront of his profession.Titchmarsh graduated from the University of Oxford in 1922 and undertook research under the supervision of Godfrey Hardy, who became the main influence on his mathematical career. In 1923 Titchmarsh was appointed lecturer at University College, London, and in 1929 he was elected professor of pure mathematics at the University of Liverpool. Two years later he returned to Oxford as the Savilian Professor of Geometry. He devoted his early research to the theory of Fourier integrals and series and a...
</Question>
<Choice>Titchmarsh, Edward Charles</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian physicist and mathematician who invented the barometer and whose work in geometry aided in the eventual development of integral calculus. Inspired by Galileo's writings, he wrote a treatise on mechanics, De Motu (“Concerning Movement”), which impressed Galileo. In 1641 Torricelli was invited to Florence, where he served the elderly astronomer as secretary and assistant during the last three months of Galileo's life. Torricelli was then appointed to succeed him as professor of mathematics at the Florentine Academy.Two years later, pursuing a suggestion by Galileo, he filled a glass tube...
</Question>
<Choice>Torricelli, Evangelista</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British mathematician and logician, who made major contributions to mathematics, cryptanalysis, logic, philosophy, and biology and to the new areas later named computer science, cognitive science, artificial intelligence, and artificial life.
</Question>
<Choice>Turing, Alan M.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
outstanding Persian philosopher, scientist, and mathematician.Educated first in ?us, where his father was a jurist in the Twelfth Imam school, the main sect of Shi?ite Muslims, al-?usi finished his education in Neyshabur, about 75 kilometres (50 miles) to the west. This was no doubt a prudent move as Genghis Khan (d. 1227), having conquered Beijing in 1215, turned his attention to the Islamic world and reached the region around ?us by 1220. In about 1227 the Isma?ilite governor Na?ir al-Din ?Abd al-Ra?im offered al-?usi sanctuary in his mountain fortresses in Khorasan. Al-?usi in turn dedicate...
</Question>
<Choice>Tusi, Nasir al-Din al-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
mathematician who played a major role in the development of the hydrogen bomb at Los Alamos, New Mexico, U.S.Ulam received a doctoral degree (1933) at the Polytechnic Institute in Lvov (now Lviv). At the invitation of John von Neumann, he worked at the Institute for Advanced Study, Princeton, New Jersey, U.S., in 1936. He lectured at Harvard University in 1939–40 and taught at the University of Wisconsin at Madison from 1941 to 1943. In 1943 he became a U.S. citizen and was recruited to work at Los Alamos on the development of the atomic bomb. He remained at Los Alamos until 1965 and taught at...
</Question>
<Choice>Ulam, Stanislaw Marcin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American mathematician and physicist who, as assistant to Thomas Edison, contributed to the development of the American electric industry.Upton studied at Bowdoin College, Brunswick, Maine; Princeton University; and—with Hermann von Helmholtz—Berlin University. In 1878 he joined Edison at his laboratory in Menlo Park, N.J. There he worked out mathematical problems arising during the development of such devices as the incandescent lamp, the watt-hour meter, and large dynamos. He was a partner and general manager of the Edison Lamp Works, established in 1880.Upton also helped Edison publicize hi...
</Question>
<Choice>Upton, Francis Robbins</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist and mathematician who shared the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1977 with Philip W. Anderson and Sir Nevill F. Mott. The prize honoured Van Vleck's contributions to the understanding of the behaviour of electrons in magnetic, noncrystalline solid materials.Educated at the University of Wisconsin, Madison, and at Harvard University, where he received his Ph.D. in 1922, Van Vleck joined the faculty of the University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, in 1924. He taught at Wisconsin from 1928 to 1934, and he then went to Harvard, where he eventually served as chairman of the physics depart...
</Question>
<Choice>Van Vleck, John H.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian philosopher, astronomer, and mathematician, author of the Pañca-siddhantika (“Five Treatises”), a compendium of Greek, Egyptian, Roman, and Indian astronomy.Varahamihira's knowledge of Western astronomy was thorough. In five sections, his monumental work progresses through native Indian astronomy and culminates in two treatises on Western astronomy, showing calculations based on Greek and Alexandrian reckoning and even giving complete Ptolemaic mathematical charts and tables.Although Varahamihira's writings give a comprehensive picture of 6th-century India, his real interest lay in astr...
</Question>
<Choice>Varahamihira</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American mathematician who made important contributions to differential geometry and the early development of topology. Many of his contributions found application in atomic physics and the theory of relativity.Veblen graduated from the University of Iowa in 1898. He spent a year at Harvard University before moving to the University of Chicago (Ph.D., 1903). He taught mathematics at Princeton University (1905–32) and was appointed a professor at the Institute for Advanced Study, Princeton, New Jersey, when it opened in 1932. Veblen played a key role in the formation and research direction of t...
</Question>
<Choice>Veblen, Oswald</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician and government official who is best remembered for his invention of the vernier caliper, an instrument for making accurate linear measurements. Taught by his scientist-father, Claude Vernier, he developed an early interest in measuring instruments. During his adult years, however, science was for him primarily an avocation. He held various positions with the government of Spain and then became commandant of the Castle of Ornans in France and later director general of the treasury in Bourgogne. In La Construction, l'usage, et les propriétés du quadrant nouveau de mathématiq...
</Question>
<Choice>Vernier, Pierre</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
mathematician who introduced the first systematic algebraic notation and contributed to the theory of equations.Viète, a Huguenot sympathizer, solved a complex cipher of more than 500 characters used by King Philip II of Spain in his war to defend Roman Catholicism from the Huguenots. When Philip, assuming that the cipher could not be broken, discovered that the French were aware of his military plans, he complained to the pope that black magic was being employed against his country.Viète's Canon mathematicus seu ad triangula (1579; “Mathematical Laws Applied to Triangles”) is probably the fir...
</Question>
<Choice>Viete, Francois, seigneur de la Bigotiere</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian mathematician known for his contributions to analytic number theory, especially his partial solution of the Goldbach conjecture (proposed in 1742), that every integer greater than two can be expressed as the sum of three prime numbers.In 1914 Vinogradov graduated from the University of St. Petersburg (renamed the Leningrad State University in 1924 and the St. Petersburg State University in 1991). From 1918 to 1920 he taught at Perm State University—founded in 1916, originally as a branch of the University of St. Petersburg—and was then appointed professor of mathematics at St. Petersbu...
</Question>
<Choice>Vinogradov, Ivan Matveyevich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian mathematician who won the Fields Medal in 2002 for having made one of the most outstanding advances in algebraic geometry in several decades.Voevodsky attended Moscow State University (1983–89) before earning a Ph.D. from Harvard University in 1992. He then held visiting positions at Harvard (1993–96) and at Northwestern University, Evanston, Illinois (1996–98), before becoming a permanent professor in 1998 at the Institute for Advanced Study, Princeton, New Jersey.Voevodsky was awarded the Fields Medal at the International Congress of Mathematicians in Beijing in 2002. In an area of m...
</Question>
<Choice>Voevodsky, Vladimir</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian mathematician who strongly influenced the modern development of calculus.Volterra's later work in analysis and mathematical physics was influenced by Enrico Betti while the former attended the University of Pisa (1878–82). Volterra was appointed professor of rational mechanics at Pisa in 1883, the year he began devising a general theory of functionals (functions that depend on a continuous set of values of another function). This concept led to the development of new fields of analysis, including important applications to the solution of integral and differential equations. The importa...
</Question>
<Choice>Volterra, Vito</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hungarian-born American mathematician. As an adult, he appended von to his surname; the hereditary title had been granted his father in 1913. Von Neumann grew from child prodigy to one of the world's foremost mathematicians by his mid-twenties. Important work in set theory inaugurated a career that touched nearly every major branch of mathematics. Von Neumann's gift for applied mathematics took his work in directions that influenced quantum theory, automata theory, economics, and defense planning. Von Neumann pioneered game theory and, along with Alan Turing and Claude Shannon, was one of the...
</Question>
<Choice>von Neumann, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English mathematician who contributed substantially to the origins of the calculus and was the most influential English mathematician before Isaac Newton.Wallis learned Latin, Greek, Hebrew, logic, and arithmetic during his early school years. In 1632 he entered the University of Cambridge, where he received B.A. and M.A. degrees in 1637 and 1640, respectively. He was ordained a priest in 1640 and shortly afterward exhibited his skill in mathematics by deciphering a number of cryptic messages from Royalist partisans that had fallen into the hands of the Parliamentarians. In 1645, the year of h...
</Question>
<Choice>Wallis, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese mathematician who made important advances in the solution of problems involving cubic equations.During the reign of Li Yuan (618–626), Wang was a suanxue boshi (arithmetic officer). In 626 he took part in the revision of the Wuying calendar (618), which had erroneously predicted eclipses in 620.About 630 Wang finished his Jigu suanjing (“Continuation of Ancient Mathematics”), of which he was so proud that, in his dedication to the emperor Li Shimin, son and successor of Li Yuan, he promised to award 1,000 taels of silver to whoever could find a single mistake in it. All 20 problems in...
</Question>
<Choice>Wang Xiaotong</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish instrument maker and inventor whose steam engine contributed substantially to the Industrial Revolution. He was elected fellow of the Royal Society of London in 1785.
</Question>
<Choice>Watt, James</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German mathematician, one of the founders of the modern theory of functions.His domineering father sent him to the University of Bonn at age 19 to study law and finance in preparation for a position in the Prussian civil service. Weierstrass pursued four years of intensive fencing and drinking and returned home with no degree. He then entered the Academy of Münster in 1839 to prepare for a career as a secondary school teacher. At Münster he came under the influence of Cristof Gudermann, professor of mathematics, who was particularly interested in the theory of elliptic functions. Gudermann cul...
</Question>
<Choice>Weierstrass, Karl Theodor Wilhelm</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician who was one of the most influential figures in mathematics during the 20th century, particularly in number theory and algebraic geometry.André was the brother of the philosopher and mystic Simone Weil. He studied at the École Normale Supérieure (now part of the Universities of Paris) and at the Universities of Rome and Göttingen, receiving his doctorate from the University of Paris in 1928. His teaching career was even more international; he was professor of mathematics at the Aligarh Muslim University, India (1930–32), and thereafter taught at the University of Strasbourg...
</Question>
<Choice>Weil, Andre</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German American mathematician who, through his widely varied contributions in mathematics, served as a link between pure mathematics and theoretical physics, in particular adding enormously to quantum mechanics and the theory of relativity.As a student at the University of Göttingen (graduated 1908), Weyl came under the influence of David Hilbert. In 1913 he became professor of mathematics at the Technische Hochschule, Zürich, where he was a colleague of Albert Einstein. The outstanding characteristic of Weyl's work was his ability to unite previously unrelated subjects. In Die Idee der Rieman...
</Question>
<Choice>Weyl, Hermann</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Anglican priest and mathematician who sought to harmonize religion and science, and who is remembered for reviving in England the heretical views of Arianism.Ordained in 1693, Whiston served from 1694 to 1698 as chaplain to John Moore, Anglican bishop of Norwich. During this period he wrote A New Theory of the Earth (1696), in which he claimed that the biblical stories of the creation, flood, and final conflagration could be explained scientifically as accounts of events with historical bases. After three years as vicar of Lowestoft (1698–1701), he returned to Cambridge, his alma mater, as ass...
</Question>
<Choice>Whiston, William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English mathematician and philosopher, who collaborated with Bertrand Russell on Principia Mathematica (1910–13) and, from the mid-1920s, taught at Harvard University and developed a comprehensive metaphysical theory.
</Question>
<Choice>Whitehead, Alfred North</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English mathematician who made pioneering contributions to the area of special functions, which is of particular interest in mathematical physics.Whittaker became a fellow of Trinity College, Cambridge, in 1896. After being elected a fellow of the Royal Society of London in 1905, he was appointed the following year professor of astronomy at the University of Dublin and astronomer royal of Ireland. He served as professor of mathematics at the University of Edinburgh from 1912 until his retirement in 1946. He was knighted in 1945.Whittaker excelled not only in mathematics but also as a historian...
</Question>
<Choice>Whittaker, Sir Edmund Taylor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American mathematician who established the science of cybernetics. He attained international renown by formulating some of the most important contributions to mathematics in the 20th century.Wiener, a child prodigy whose education was controlled by his father, a professor of Slavonic languages and literature at Harvard University, graduated in mathematics from Tufts College (now Tufts University, Medford, Massachusetts) in 1909 at the age of 14. He spent a year at Harvard as a graduate student in zoology but left after he found that he was inept at laboratory work. At his father's suggestion,...
</Question>
<Choice>Wiener, Norbert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British mathematician who proved Fermat's last theorem; in recognition he was awarded a special silver plaque—he was beyond the traditional age limit of 40 years for receiving the gold Fields Medal—by the International Mathematical Union in 1998.Wiles was educated at Merton College, Oxford (B.A., 1974), and Clare College, Cambridge (Ph.D., 1980). Following a junior research fellowship at Cambridge (1977–80), Wiles held an appointment at Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass., U.S., and in 1982 moved to Princeton (N.J.) University. Wiles worked on a number of outstanding problems in number theory...
</Question>
<Choice>Wiles, Andrew John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
philosopher, mathematician, and scientist who worked in many subjects but who is best known as the German spokesman of the Enlightenment, the 18th-century philosophical movement characterized by Rationalism.Wolff was educated at the universities of Breslau, Jena, and Leipzig and was a pupil of the philosopher and mathematician Gottfried Wilhelm Leibniz. On the recommendation of Leibniz he was appointed professor of mathematics at the University of Halle in 1707, but he was banished in 1723 as a result of theological disputes with Pietists, who were followers of the German movement for an incre...
</Question>
<Choice>Wolff, Christian, Freiherr von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
mathematician active in the great flowering of Chinese mathematics during the Southern Song dynasty.Although practically nothing is known about the life of Yang, his books are among the few contemporary Chinese mathematics works to survive. A remark in the preface to one of his treatises indicates that he was a mandarin (scholar-official).Yang's works are mentioned in the Wenyan ge shumu (1441; “Catalogue of the Books of the Ming Imperial Library”) but were long thought to be irreparably lost. Ruan Yuan, compiler of Chou ren zhuan (1799; “Biographies of Mathematicians and Astronomers”), first...
</Question>
<Choice>Yang Hui</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese-born mathematician who won the 1982 Fields Medal for his work in differential geometry.Yau received a Ph.D. from the University of California, Berkeley, in 1971. Between 1971 and 1987 he held appointments at a number of institutions, including Stanford (Calif.) University (1974–79), the Institute for Advanced Study, Princeton, N.J. (1979–84), and the University of California, San Diego (1984–87). In 1987 he became a professor at Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass.Yau received the Fields Medal at the International Congress of Mathematicians in Warsaw in 1983 for his work in global diff...
</Question>
<Choice>Yau, Shing-Tung</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician who was awarded the Fields Medal in 1994 for his work in dynamical systems.Yoccoz was educated at the École Normale Supérieure, Paris, and the École Polytechnique, Palaiseau (Ph.D., 1985). He then became a professor at the University of Paris at Orsay.Yoccoz was awarded the Fields Medal at the International Congress of Mathematicians in Zürich, Switz., in 1994. His area of interest was dynamical systems, an area developed by Henri Poincaré about the turn of the 20th century to study the stability of the solar system. The techniques are applied to problems in biology, chemi...
</Question>
<Choice>Yoccoz, Jean-Christophe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian mathematician who was awarded the Fields Medal in 1994 for his work in group theory.Zelmanov was educated at Novosibirsk State University (Ph.D., 1980) and Leningrad (now St. Petersburg) State University (D.Sc., 1985). He worked at the Institute of Mathematics of the Academy of Sciences of the U.S.S.R. in Novosibirsk until 1987. He then left the Soviet Union, eventually settling at the University of Wisconsin, Madison (U.S.), in 1990. He moved to the University of Chicago in 1994 and on to Yale University, New Haven, Conn., in 1995.Zelmanov was awarded the Fields Medal at the Internati...
</Question>
<Choice>Zelmanov, Efim Isaakovich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek philosopher and mathematician, whom Aristotle called the inventor of dialectic. Zeno is especially known for his paradoxes that contributed to the development of logical and mathematical rigour and that were insoluble until the development of precise concepts of continuity and infinity.Zeno was famous for the paradoxes whereby, in order to recommend the Parmenidean doctrine of the existence of “the one” (i.e., indivisible reality), he sought to controvert the commonsense belief in the existence of “the many” (i.e., distinguishable qualities and things capable of motion). Zeno was the son...
</Question>
<Choice>Zeno of Elea</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese astronomer, mathematician, and Daoist who calculated the value of p, constructed astronomical instruments, conducted experiments with a camera obscura, and compiled an influential astronomical compendium.Zhao was one of the patriarchs of the northern branch of the Quanzhen (“Complete Perfection”) sect of Daoism. His astronomical treatise Gexiang xinshu (“New Writing on the Symbol of Alteration”) presents his cosmological theory featuring a flat Earth inside a spherical Heaven, his explanation of the lunar and solar eclipses, and his experiments with a camera obscura to establish the re...
</Question>
<Choice>Zhao Youqin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese mathematician who stood at the pinnacle of traditional Chinese mathematics. Zhu is also known for having unified the southern and northern Chinese mathematical traditions.Little is known of Zhu's life except that he was probably a native of the present Beijing area and that he traveled throughout the country as an itinerant teacher during the last 30 years of the 13th century.Zhu's fame rests primarily on two publications, Suanxue qimeng (1299; “Introduction to Mathematical Science”) and Siyuan yujian (1303; “Precious Mirror of Four Elements”). The former is an introductory mathematics...
</Question>
<Choice>Zhu Shijie</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese government official, mathematician, astronomer, and son of Zu Chongzhi (429–500).Beginning in 504, Zu Geng actively advocated his father's calendar (the Daming calendar) and finally succeeded in getting it officially adopted in 510. His astronomical observations with gnomons allowed him to measure the angular distance between Polaris and the celestial north pole. Although none of his complete mathematical writings is extant, some scholars suggest that the mathematical treatise Zhuishu (meaning of the title now uncertain), conventionally credited to his father and lost by the 11th centu...
</Question>
<Choice>Zu Gengzhi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polish-born mathematician who exerted a major influence on 20th-century mathematics, particularly in harmonic analysis, a field utilized in science and technology for the formulation of descriptions of periodic phenomena such as waves, vibrations, and regularly repeating structures.Zygmund graduated from the University of Warsaw (Ph.D. 1923) and taught there (1926–29) and at the Polytechnical School in Warsaw (1922–29). After a year in England on a Rockefeller fellowship, he became professor of mathematics at the University of Wilno (later Vilnius, Lithuania). In 1940, following a period of se...
</Question>
<Choice>Zygmund, Antoni</Choice>
</item>
</topics>