<topics>
<item>
<Question>
meteorologist who pioneered in the foundation and growth of the U.S. Weather Bureau, later renamed the National Weather Service.Trained as an astronomer, he was appointed director of the Cincinnati (Ohio) Observatory in 1868. His interest gradually turned to meteorology, however, and he inaugurated a public weather service that served as a model for the national weather service, which was organized shortly thereafter as a branch of the Signal Service. In 1871 he was appointed chief meteorologist of the branch (which in 1891 was reorganized under civilian control as the U.S. Weather Bureau) and...
</Question>
<Choice>Abbe, Cleveland</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish physicist and meteorologist who, through a series of experiments and observations in which he used apparatus of his own design, elucidated the crucial role that microscopic particles, now called Aitken nuclei, play in the condensation of atmospheric water vapour in clouds and fogs. Ill health prevented Aitken from holding any official position; he worked instead in the laboratory in his home in Falkirk. Much of his work was published in the journals of the Royal Society of Edinburgh, of which he was a member.
</Question>
<Choice>Aitken, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish meteorologist best known for his work on cloud physics.He was educated at the universities of Stockholm and Oslo, from the latter of which he received his Ph.D. in 1928. He taught at the University of Stockholm (1935–45) and the University of Uppsala, Swed. (1946–60). From 1918 to 1921 he was a student and co-worker of the pioneering meteorologist Vilhelm Bjerknes and was actively engaged in the development of new methods of weather forecasting.Bergeron was noted for his studies in the analysis of air masses and the formation of warm and cold fronts. He was also the first meteorologist...
</Question>
<Choice>Bergeron, Tor Harold Percival</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Norwegian American meteorologist whose discovery that cyclones (low-pressure centres) originate as waves associated with sloping weather fronts that separate different air masses proved to be a major contribution to modern weather forecasting.The work of his father, the Norwegian physicist and meteorologist Vilhelm F.K. Bjerknes, influenced Bjerknes in his choice of meteorology as a career. During World War I he assisted his father in establishing a network of weather observation stations throughout Norway. Data gathered by these stations gave rise to their theory of polar fronts, essential to...
</Question>
<Choice>Bjerknes, Jacob Aall Bonnevie</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Norwegian meteorologist and physicist, one of the founders of the modern science of weather forecasting.As a youth Bjerknes assisted his father, a professor of mathematics at Christiania, with research in hydrodynamics. In 1890 he went to Germany and became an assistant to and scientific collaborator with the German physicist Heinrich Hertz. Bjerknes made a comprehensive study of electrical resonance that was decisive in the development of radio.After two years as lecturer at the Högskola (School of Engineering), Stockholm, Bjerknes in 1895 became professor of applied mechanics and mathematica...
</Question>
<Choice>Bjerknes, Vilhelm Friman Koren</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
eminent British meteorologist who first noticed what became known as Buchan spells—departures from the normally expected temperature occurring during certain seasons. They are now believed by meteorologists to be more or less random. Buchan is credited with establishing the weather map as the basis of weather forecasting as a result of his tracing, in 1868, the path of a storm across North America and the Atlantic into northern Europe.Buchan took up teaching as a profession and botany as a hobby. In December 1860 he was appointed secretary of the Scottish Meteorological Society and edited and...
</Question>
<Choice>Buchan, Alexander</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch meteorologist particularly remembered for his observation in 1857 that the wind tends to blow at right angles to the atmospheric pressure gradient. Although he was not the first to make this discovery, his name remains attached to it as Buys Ballot's law (q.v.).Buys Ballot studied and taught at the University of Utrecht, attaining the rank of professor in 1867. He also served as the director of the Royal Netherlands Meteorological Institute, which he founded in 1854.
</Question>
<Choice>Buys Ballot, Christophorus Henricus Didericus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American meteorologist who contributed to the development of numerical weather prediction and to increased understanding of the general circulation of the atmosphere by devising a series of increasingly sophisticated mathematical models of the atmosphere.Shortly after receiving his Ph.D. from the University of California, Los Angeles, Charney joined the Institute for Advanced Study in Princeton, N.J., and participated in the first efforts to apply digital computers to the problem of weather prediction. The recipient of numerous awards, he became professor of meteorology at Massachusetts Instit...
</Question>
<Choice>Charney, Jule Gregory</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English meteorologist and chemist, a pioneer in the development of modern atomic theory.
</Question>
<Choice>Dalton, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British chemist and meteorologist who invented the Daniell cell, which was a great improvement over the voltaic cell used in the early days of battery development.In 1820 Daniell invented a dew-point hygrometer (a device that indicates atmospheric humidity), which came into widespread use. In his Meteorological Essays and Observations (1823), Daniell revealed his findings on the behaviour of the atmosphere and on trade winds, in addition to giving details of improved meteorological equipment. In a later edition he also discussed the meteorological effects of solar radiation and the cooling of...
</Question>
<Choice>Daniell, John Frederic</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. geographer, geologist, and meteorologist who founded the science of geomorphology, the study of landforms.In 1870 he began three years of service as a meteorologist with the Argentine Meteorological Observatory, Córdoba. In 1876 he obtained a position with Harvard University, where he taught until 1912. His meteorological studies gave rise to Elementary Meteorology (1894), which was used as a college text for more than 30 years.In the 1870s his interest turned to the study of landforms, and the publication of “The Rivers and Valleys of Pennsylvania” (1889) laid the foundation for the Davi...
</Question>
<Choice>Davis, William Morris</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss-born British geologist and meteorologist whose theoretical work was influential on 19th-century writing about meteorology.Deluc was educated in mathematics and the natural sciences. He engaged in business, and on his business travels around Europe he collected mineral and plant specimens.Deluc suffered business reverses in 1773 and left Geneva for England. He devoted himself to his scientific interests and was made a fellow of the Royal Society. He became a reader to Queen Charlotte, which allowed him much time and the means to travel on the European continent. He studied the effects of...
</Question>
<Choice>Deluc, Jean Andre</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British meteorologist who invented instruments to measure atmospheric properties.The son of a meteorologist, Dines was graduated from Corpus Christi College, Cambridge, with honours. He became interested in wind speed and invented a pressure-tube anemometer, the first device to measure both the velocity and direction of wind. Dines pioneered in the use of kites and balloons for upper-air measurement and designed a remarkable meteorograph for upper-air soundings weighing only about 2 ounces (60 g). This became for years the standard British instrument for upper-atmosphere soundings and provided...
</Question>
<Choice>Dines, William Henry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. botanist, physician, and meteorologist who is known primarily for his botanical monographs, especially one on the cactus and also A Monography of North American Cuscutinae (1842).Engelmann studied at the universities of Heidelberg and Berlin and received his M.D. degree from the University of Würzburg in 1831. His illustrated thesis, De Antholysi Prodromus, was an important study of the morphology of monstrosities. He went to the United States in 1833, and in 1835 he settled in St. Louis, where he became a leading physician. Continuing his studies in biology, he pointed out the adaptation...
</Question>
<Choice>Engelmann, George</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American meteorologist who apparently gave the first essentially correct explanation of the thermodynamics of cloud formation and growth. He was also one of the first to use the telegraph for collecting meteorological observations.Espy served as a meteorologist with the U.S. War Department and the U.S. Navy until 1852, when he continued his work at the Smithsonian Institution, Washington, D.C. He presented his theory of clouds and his more general (though incorrect) theory of storms before scientific audiences in the United States and Europe and in his Philosophy of Storms (1841).
</Question>
<Choice>Espy, James Pollard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American meteorologist known for his description of the deflection of air currents on the rotating Earth.Ferrel taught school and in 1857 joined the staff of The American Ephemeris and Nautical Almanac in Cambridge, Mass. He served as a member of the U.S. Coast and Geodetic Survey from 1867 until 1882, when he became a member of the Signal Service; he retired in 1886.Ferrel did research on tides, currents, and storms and invented a machine to predict tidal maxima and minima. He wrote Meteorological Researches, 3 vol. (1877–82), Popular Essays on the Movements of the Atmosphere (1882), Temperat...
</Question>
<Choice>Ferrel, William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian mathematician and physical scientist.After graduating from the University of St. Petersburg in 1910, Friedmann joined the Pavlovsk Aerological Observatory and, during World War I, did aerological work for the Russian army. After the war he was on the staff of the University of Perm (1918–20) and then on the staffs of the Main Physical Observatory and other institutions until his death in 1925.In 1922–24 Friedmann used Einstein'sgeneral theory of relativity to formulate the mathematics of a dynamic (time-dependent) universe. (Einstein and Dutch mathematician Willem de Sitter had earlier...
</Question>
<Choice>Friedmann, Aleksandr Aleksandrovich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese-American meteorologist who created the Fujita Scale, or F-Scale, a system of classifying tornado intensity based on damage to structures and vegetation. He also discovered macrobursts and microbursts, weather phenomena that are associated with severe thunderstorms and are hazards to aviation.Fujita earned a bachelor's degree in mechanical engineering in 1943 from Meiji College of Technology, Tokyo, Japan, where he became an assistant professor in the physics department in 1944. Upon completion of a doctoral degree from Tokyo University in 1953, he moved to the United States and joined...
</Question>
<Choice>Fujita, Tetsuya Theodore</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French chemist and physicist who pioneered investigations into the behaviour of gases, established new techniques for analysis, and made notable advances in applied chemistry.
</Question>
<Choice>Gay-Lussac, Joseph-Louis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German meteorologist, one of the founders of microclimatology, the study of the climatic conditions within a few metres of the ground surface. His observations, made above grassy fields or areas of crops and below forest canopies, elucidated the complex and subtle interactions between vegetation and the heat, radiation, and water balances of the air and soil.Geiger taught and conducted his research at several institutions in Germany and was director of the Meteorological Research Institute in the Bavarian Forest Service and of the Meteorological Institute of the University of Munich. He was th...
</Question>
<Choice>Geiger, Rudolf Oskar Robert Williams</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss-born American geologist, geographer, and educator whose extensive meteorological observations led to the founding of the U.S. Weather Bureau. The guyot, a flat-topped volcanic peak rising from the ocean floor, is named after him.He studied at the College of Neuchâtel and in Germany, taught at Paris from 1835 to 1840, and became professor of history and physical geography at the Neuchâtel Academy in 1839. In 1838, under the influence of the famed naturalist-geologist Louis Agassiz, he took up the study of the structure and motion of glaciers.In 1848 Guyot settled in Cambridge, Mass., and...
</Question>
<Choice>Guyot, Arnold Henry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physicist and meteorologist who first formulated an accurate theory describing the trade winds and the associated meridional (north-south) circulation pattern now known as the Hadley cell.Though educated in law, Hadley preferred physics to legal work. For about seven years he was in charge of the meteorological observations prepared for the Royal Society of London. Having made the first adequate study of the trade-wind currents, he explained their relation to the Earth's daily rotation and discussed the relevant atmospheric motions and their causes. He presented his ideas in a paper, “...
</Question>
<Choice>Hadley, George</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German naturalist and explorer who was a major figure in the classical period of physical geography and biogeography—areas of science now included in the earth sciences and ecology. With his book Kosmos he made a valuable contribution to the popularization of science. The Humboldt Current off the west coast of South America was named after him.
</Question>
<Choice>Humboldt, Alexander von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German meteorologist and climatologist best known for his delineation and mapping of the climatic regions of the world. He played a major role in the advancement of climatology and meteorology for more than 70 years. His achievements, practical and theoretical, profoundly influenced the development of atmospheric science.Köppen remained in Russia until he was 20. His grandfather was one of the German physicians invited to Russia by the empress Catherine the Great to improve sanitation in the provinces. He later became personal physician to the tsar. His father, Peter von Köppen (1793–1864), wo...
</Question>
<Choice>Koppen, Wladimir Peter</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astrophysicist and aeronautical pioneer who developed new instruments with which to study the Sun and built the first powered heavier-than-air machine of significant size to achieve sustained flight.Following his education at the Boston Latin School, Langley worked as an engineer and architectural draftsman before traveling to Europe in 1864. Following his return in 1866, he was appointed an assistant professor of mathematics at the U.S. Naval Academy in Annapolis, Md. The next year he accepted a position as a professor of physics and astronomy at the Western University of Pennsylvani...
</Question>
<Choice>Langley, Samuel Pierpont</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist and meteorologist, the first to propose the use of a ring pendulum for measuring absolute gravity.Mendenhall was a professor at Ohio State University, Columbus, in 1873–78 and from 1881 until he was named professor emeritus in 1884, when he became a professor for the U.S. Signal Corps. In 1878–81 he was a visiting professor at the Tokyo Imperial University, where he helped develop the Japanese government's meteorological system, and in 1889 he was appointed superintendent of the U.S. Coast and Geodetic Survey; he served as president of the Worcester (Mass.) Polytechnic Insti...
</Question>
<Choice>Mendenhall, Thomas Corwin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-born American physicist who established the speed of light as a fundamental constant and pursued other spectroscopic and metrological investigations. He received the 1907 Nobel Prize for Physics.Michelson came to the United States with his parents when he was two years old. From New York City, the family made its way to Virginia City, Nev., and San Francisco, where the elder Michelson prospered as a merchant. At 17, Michelson entered the United States Naval Academy at Annapolis, Md., where he did well in science but was rather below average in seamanship. He graduated in 1873, then serv...
</Question>
<Choice>Michelson, A. A.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British geographer and meteorologist who exercised a great influence in the reform of geography teaching and on the development of meteorology.Mill was educated at Edinburgh University, graduating in chemistry (1883) and specializing in the chemistry of seawater for his doctorate (1886). Love of the sea and of boats led to his famous pioneer survey, The English Lakes (1895). Indifferent health and physique—he became totally blind in later life—prevented his becoming an explorer, but from 1892 (when he was appointed librarian of the Royal Geographical Society and settled in London), he became a...
</Question>
<Choice>Mill, Hugh Robert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Croatian meteorologist and geophysicist who discovered the boundary between the Earth's crust and mantle—a boundary subsequently named the Mohorovicic discontinuity.The son of a shipyard carpenter, he was a precocious youth and by the age of 15 spoke not only Croatian but English, French, and Italian, to which he later added Latin and Greek as well as Czech and German. He studied under the physicist and philosopher Ernst Mach at the University of Prague and was graduated in mathematics and physics (1875). After teaching in a secondary school for seven years, he received an appointment to the R...
</Question>
<Choice>Mohorovicic, Andrija</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physicist and psychologist who was the first to apply mathematical techniques to predict the weather accurately.Richardson made major contributions to methods of solving certain types of problems in physics, and from 1913 to 1922 he applied his ideas to meteorology. His work, published in Weather Prediction by Numerical Process (1922), was not entirely successful at first. The main drawback to his mathematical technique for systematically forecasting the weather was the time necessary to produce such a forecast. It generally took him three months to predict the weather for the next 24...
</Question>
<Choice>Richardson, Lewis Fry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish American meteorologist whose innovations in the study of large-scale air movement and introduction of the equations describing atmospheric motion were largely responsible for the rapid development of meteorology as a science.Rossby moved to the United States in 1926, where he worked in Washington, D.C., as a fellow of the American-Scandinavian Foundation for Research at the U.S. Weather Bureau. In 1928 he became professor and head of the department of meteorology (the first in the United States) at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge. There he made important contributi...
</Question>
<Choice>Rossby, Carl-Gustaf Arvid</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American research chemist and meteorologist, who in 1946 carried out the first systematic series of experiments to investigate the physics of precipitation. From an aircraft over Massachusetts he seeded clouds with pellets of Dry Ice (solid carbon dioxide) and succeeded in producing snow, initiating the science of experimental meteorology and weather control.Schaefer attended classes at Union College in New York and graduated in 1928 from the Davey Institute of Tree Surgery. From 1933 to 1954 he worked in research at General Electric Laboratories, where his efforts during the war were directed...
</Question>
<Choice>Schaefer, Vincent Joseph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English meteorologist whose introduction of the millibar, a unit of measurement of air pressure, and the tephigram, a graphical representation of the first law of thermodynamics as applied to Earth's atmosphere, contributed to the development of modern meteorology.Shaw taught physics at the University of Cambridge from 1877 to 1906. He was elected to the Royal Society in 1891 and in 1900 became secretary of the Meteorological Council, the governing body of the Meteorological Office. He instigated the reorganization of this office and served as director from 1905 to 1920. He was knighted in 191...
</Question>
<Choice>Shaw, Sir William Napier</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British meteorologist who, as the chief weather forecaster to General Dwight D. Eisenhower, gave crucial advice on weather conditions for the Normandy Invasion during World War II.Stagg, a graduate of the University of Edinburgh, became an assistant in Britain's Meteorological Office in 1924. He led the British Polar Year Expedition to the Canadian Arctic in 1932–33, and he served as superintendent of the Kew Gardens Observatory in 1939. In 1943 he was given the rank of group captain and appointed the chief meteorological adviser to Eisenhower, the supreme commander of the projected Allied inv...
</Question>
<Choice>Stagg, James Martin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish meteorologist and geophysicist noted for his studies of terrestrial magnetism and radiant heat.Stewart pursued a mercantile career for 10 years before becoming an assistant at Kew Observatory and later an assistant to James Forbes at Edinburgh University, where Stewart conducted his research on radiant heat. In 1859 he became director of Kew Observatory, and in 1870 he became professor of natural philosophy at Owens College, Manchester.In his work on radiant heat, Stewart was the first to discover that bodies radiate and absorb energy of the same wavelength; his work in this field was...
</Question>
<Choice>Stewart, Balfour</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American oceanographer and meteorologist.Stommel became internationally known during the 1950s for his theories on circulation patterns in the AtlanticOcean. He suggested that the Earth's rotation is responsible for the Gulf Stream along the coast of North America, and he theorized that its northward flow must be balanced by a stream of cold water moving southward beneath it. He proposed a global circulation in which surface water sinks in the far north to feed the deep, south-flowing current, while water rises in the Antarctic region to supply a northward flow along the eastern coasts of Nort...
</Question>
<Choice>Stommel, Henry Melson</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Norwegian meteorologist and oceanographer known for his studies of the physics, chemistry, and biology of the oceans. He explained the equatorial countercurrents and helped develop the method of predicting surf and breakers. A unit of water flow in the oceans was named after him by the oceanographic research community: 1 sverdrup (Sv) is equal to the transport of 1 million cubic metres of water per second.Sverdrup was in charge of the scientific work on the Maud Expedition to the Arctic from 1917 until 1925 and was a research associate at the Carnegie Institution, Washington, D.C., from 1928 u...
</Question>
<Choice>Sverdrup, H. U.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British meteorologist who strove to provide reliable observational data by imposing standards of accuracy and uniformity on meteorological measurements and by substantially increasing the number of reporting stations.Symons was elected a member of the British Meteorological Society (later the Royal Meteorological Society) in 1856, when he was only 18 years old. He concentrated his attention on the collection of rainfall statistics and, in 1860, issued the first of his annual rainfall reports. In that year results from 168 stations were compiled in the report, but by 1899, the year before his d...
</Question>
<Choice>Symons, George James</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French meteorologist who discovered the stratosphere, thus paving the way for further study of the upper atmosphere.In 1880 Teisserenc began his career in the meteorological department of the Administrative Centre of National Meteorology in Paris. He journeyed to Africa in 1883, 1885, and 1887 to study geology and terrestrial magnetism, and in 1892 he became chief meteorologist to the centre. Four years later he resigned and set up his own private meteorological observatory at Trappes, near Versailles. One of the pioneers in the use of unmanned, instrumented balloons, he sent them up to study...
</Question>
<Choice>Teisserenc de Bort, Leon-Philippe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Finnish meteorologist and astronomer noted for developing meteorological measuring methods and instruments.After receiving his Ph.D. in 1922, Väisälä joined the faculty of the Geodetic Institute of Turku University (1925) and worked as an astronomer and surveyor, completing a magnetic survey of the Earth and inventing the light-interference system for measuring long paths (on the order of 100 metres) for use as baselines in geodetic surveys (1927). Later in his career, Väisälä turned to meteorology and developed, among other things, a new method of radio direction finding (1951). In 1952 he he...
</Question>
<Choice>Vaisala, Yrjo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German meteorologist and geophysicist who formulated the first complete statement of the continental drift hypothesis.The son of an orphanage director, Wegener earned a Ph.D. degree in astronomy from the University of Berlin in 1905. He had meanwhile become interested in paleoclimatology, and in 1906–08 he took part in an expedition to Greenland to study polar air circulation. He made three more expeditions to Greenland, in 1912–13, 1929, and 1930. He taught meteorology at Marburg and Hamburg and was a professor of meteorology and geophysics at the University of Graz from 1924 to 1930. He died...
</Question>
<Choice>Wegener, Alfred Lothar</Choice>
</item>
</topics>