<topics>
<item>
<Question>
physicist whose theoretical and technical innovations in optical theory led to great improvements in microscope design (such as the use of a condenser to provide strong, even illumination, introduced in 1870) and clearer understanding of magnification limits. He discovered the optical formula now called the Abbe sine condition, one of the requirements that a lens must satisfy if it is to form a sharp image, free from the blurring or distortion caused by coma and spherical aberration.In 1863 he joined the University of Jena, rising to professor of physics and mathematics (1870) and director of...
</Question>
<Choice>Abbe, Ernst</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian physicist, who won the Nobel Prize for Physics in 2003 for his pioneering contribution to the theory of superconductivity. He shared the award with Vitaly L. Ginzburg of Russia and Anthony J. Leggett of Great Britain.Abrikosov received doctorates in physics from the Institute for Physical Problems (now the P.L. Kapitsa Institute) in Moscow in 1951 and 1955. In the following decades he worked at scientific institutions and universities in the U.S.S.R. In 1991 he joined Argonne National Laboratory in Illinois and became a distinguished scientist in its materials science division.Abrikoso...
</Question>
<Choice>Abrikosov, Alexey A.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
physicist who discovered (1756) pyroelectricity in the mineral tourmaline and published (1759) the first mathematical theory of electric and magnetic phenomena.Aepinus studied medicine and briefly taught mathematics at the University of Rostock, where his father was a professor of theology. In 1755 he became director of the astronomical observatory in Berlin and a member of the Berlin Academy of Sciences. In 1757 he moved to Russia, where he was appointed a full member of the Imperial Academy of Sciences (now the Russian Academy of Sciences) in St. Petersburg. After retiring in 1798, he settle...
</Question>
<Choice>Aepinus, Franz Maria Ulrich Theodor Hoch</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English scientist who was astronomer royal from 1835 to 1881.Airy graduated from Trinity College, Cambridge, in 1823. He became Lucasian professor of mathematics at Cambridge in 1826 and Plumian professor of astronomy and director of the Cambridge observatory in 1828. In 1835 he was appointed the seventh astronomer royal, i.e., director of the Royal Greenwich Observatory, a post he would hold for more than 45 years.Airy completely reorganized the Greenwich observatory, installing new apparatus and rescuing thousands of lunar observations from oblivion. Most importantly, he modernized the obser...
</Question>
<Choice>Airy, Sir George Biddell</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish physicist and meteorologist who, through a series of experiments and observations in which he used apparatus of his own design, elucidated the crucial role that microscopic particles, now called Aitken nuclei, play in the condensation of atmospheric water vapour in clouds and fogs. Ill health prevented Aitken from holding any official position; he worked instead in the laboratory in his home in Falkirk. Much of his work was published in the journals of the Royal Society of Edinburgh, of which he was a member.
</Question>
<Choice>Aitken, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German scholastic philosopher especially noted for his investigations into physics.He studied at Prague and then at the University of Paris, where he was a master of arts from 1351 to 1362 and rector in 1353. Most probably he is to be identified with the Albert of Ricmestorp, or Rückmersdorf, who was rector of the University of Vienna in 1365 and bishop of Halberstadt from 1366 until his death there in 1390.Albert based his logic on William Ockham, his physical theory on Jean Buridan, his mathematics on Thomas Bradwardine, and his ethics on Walter Burley (rejecting Buridan's psychological dete...
</Question>
<Choice>Albert of Saxony</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Soviet physicist who, with Herbert Kroemer and Jack S. Kilby, was awarded the Nobel Prize for Physics in 2000 for their work that laid the foundation for the modern era of computers and information technology.Alferov received a doctorate in physics and mathematics from the A.F. Ioffe Physico-Technical Institute (1970); he became director of the institute in 1987. In the 1950s he began work to develop fast optoelectronic and microelectronic components made from semiconductor heterostructures. (While most computer chips and other semiconductor components were made from one kind of material, such...
</Question>
<Choice>Alferov, Zhores</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
astrophysicist and winner, with Louis Néel of France, of the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1970 for his essential contributions in founding plasma physics—the study of plasmas (ionized gases).Alfvén was educated at Uppsala University and in 1940 joined the staff of the Royal Institute of Technology, Stockholm. During the late 1930s and early '40s he made remarkable contributions to space physics, including the theorem of frozen-in flux, according to which under certain conditions a plasma is bound to the magnetic lines of flux that pass through it. Alfvén later used the concept to explain the ori...
</Question>
<Choice>Alfven, Hannes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American experimental physicist who was awarded the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1968 for work that included the discovery of many resonance particles (subatomic particles having extremely short lifetimes and occurring only in high-energy nuclear collisions).Alvarez studied physics at the University of Chicago (B.S., 1932; M.S., 1934; Ph.D., 1936). He joined the faculty of the University of California, Berkeley, in 1936, becoming professor of physics in 1945 and professor emeritus in 1978. In 1938 Alvarez discovered that some radioactive elements decay by orbital-electron capture; i.e., an orbit...
</Question>
<Choice>Alvarez, Luis W.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physicist and inventor of scientific instruments, best known for his work on friction and temperature measurement.Amontons is often credited with having discovered the laws of friction (1699), though in fact his work dealt solely with static friction—i.e., the friction of objects at rest. It was only after the English physicist Sir Isaac Newton formulated his laws of motion that the friction of moving bodies was analyzed.Amontons also developed an air-pressure thermometer (1702) and published two notable papers on thermometry (1702–03). He devised a method of measuring a change in tempe...
</Question>
<Choice>Amontons, Guillaume</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physicist who founded and named the science of electrodynamics, now known as electromagnetism. His name endures in everyday life in the ampere, the unit for measuring electric current.
</Question>
<Choice>Ampere, Andre-Marie</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist who, with Victor Francis Hess of Austria, won the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1936 for his discovery of the positron, or positive electron, the first known particle of antimatter.Anderson received his Ph.D. in 1930 from the California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, where he worked with physicist Robert Andrews Millikan. Having studied X-ray photoelectrons (electrons ejected from atoms by interaction with high-energy photons) since 1927, he began research in 1930 on gamma rays and cosmic rays. While studying cloud-chamber photographs of cosmic rays, Anderson found a number...
</Question>
<Choice>Anderson, Carl David</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist who played a pivotal role in developing the field of health physics.Anderson's affinity for numbers and her general intellectual gifts were apparent from girlhood. After graduating from Ripon College (B.S., 1922) in Ripon, Wisconsin, she earned (1924) a master's degree in physics from the University of Wisconsin. Her doctorate in physics from the same institution was granted in 1941. In the interim she taught physics and chemistry at schools in Iowa and Wisconsin. In 1941–42 she took a sabbatical leave from Milwaukee-Downer College, where she was chairman of the physics depa...
</Question>
<Choice>Anderson, Elda Emma</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist and corecipient, with John H. Van Vleck and Sir Nevill F. Mott, of the 1977 Nobel Prize for Physics for his research on semiconductors, superconductivity, and magnetism.Educated at Harvard University, Anderson received his doctorate in 1949. From 1949 to 1984 he worked at Bell Telephone Laboratories in Murray Hill, New Jersey. From 1967 to 1975 he was professor of theoretical physics at the University of Cambridge, and from 1975 he taught at Princeton University. His research in solid-state physics made possible the development of inexpensive electronic switching and memory...
</Question>
<Choice>Anderson, Philip W.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
chemist and physicist who established the concepts of critical temperature and pressure and showed that a gas will pass into the liquid state, and vice versa, without any discontinuity, or abrupt change in physical properties. He also proved that ozone is a form of oxygen.Following studies in Britain and Paris, he received a medical degree from the University of Edinburgh (1835). He was appointed vice president of Northern College in Belfast in 1845 and helped to prepare it for its reorganization as Queen's College, Belfast (1849). He was professor of chemistry there from 1849 to 1879.
</Question>
<Choice>Andrews, Thomas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish physicist, a founder of spectroscopy for whom the angstrom, a unit of length equal to 10-10 metre, was named.Educated at the University of Uppsala, Ångström became privatdocent (lecturer) there in 1839 and succeeded to the chairmanship of the physics department in 1858. In 1843 he became observer at Uppsala Observatory.Ångström's most important work concerned heat conduction and spectroscopy. He devised a method of measuring thermal conductivity, showing it to be proportional to electrical conductivity. In 1853 he pointed out that the electric spark yields two superposed spectra, one f...
</Question>
<Choice>Angstrom, Anders Jonas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
physicist and pioneer in the teaching of electrical engineering in the United States.After studying at Brown (Providence, R.I.) and Yale universities, Anthony taught physics and chemistry at Antioch College, Yellow Springs, Ohio (1867–69); Iowa State Agricultural College, Ames (1869–72); Cornell University, Ithaca, N.Y. (1872–87); and Cooper Union, New York City (1894–1908). While at Cornell he originated and developed one of the first courses in electrical engineering in the United States (1883).Anthony also designed and built improved dynamos, including the one used for the first underground...
</Question>
<Choice>Anthony, William Arnold</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British winner of the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1947 for his discovery of the so-called Appleton layer of the ionosphere, which is a dependable reflector of radio waves and as such is useful in communication. Other ionospheric layers reflect radio waves sporadically, depending upon temperature and time of day.Educated at St. John's College, Cambridge, Appleton worked at the Cavendish Laboratory from 1920 until he was appointed Wheatstone professor of physics at King's College, University of London, in 1924. There he attained international repute with his research into the propagation of elect...
</Question>
<Choice>Appleton, Sir Edward Victor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physicist who discovered the principle of the production of magnetism by rotation of a nonmagnetic conductor. He also devised an experiment that proved the wave theory of light and engaged with others in research that led to the discovery of the laws of light polarization.Arago was educated in Perpignan and at the École Polytechnique, Paris, where, at the age of 23, he succeeded Gaspard Monge in the chair of analytic geometry. Subsequently he was director of the Paris Observatory and permanent secretary of the Academy of Sciences. He was also active as a republican in French politics. A...
</Question>
<Choice>Arago, Francois</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist whose research led to the development of long-distance telephony and radio communication.Arnold studied at Wesleyan University in Middletown, Connecticut, where he received a Ph.B. (1906) and a M.S. (1907), and in 1911 he earned a doctorate at the University of Chicago. While working for the Western Electric Company, he developed and designed the manufacturing methods for reliable high-vacuum triodes (thermionic tubes) used to provide the amplification needed for transcontinental telephony (1914) and intercontinental radio telephony (1915). Arnold also contributed to the dev...
</Question>
<Choice>Arnold, Harold DeForest</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physicist who won the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1922 for his development of the mass spectrograph, a device that separates atoms or molecular fragments of different mass and measures those masses with remarkable accuracy. Aston used the mass spectograph to discover a large number of nuclides, or nuclear species that differ in mass. The mass spectrograph is widely used in geology, chemistry, biology, and nuclear physics.Aston was trained as a chemist, but, upon the rebirth of physics following the discovery of X-rays in 1895 and of radioactivity in 1896, he began in 1903 to study the...
</Question>
<Choice>Aston, Francis William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
physicist known for research on long-range radio transmissions. He was educated at Middlebury College, Vermont, and the University of Strasbourg, Germany. In 1904 he began work on radio transmissions for the U.S. Bureau of Standards. In 1908 Austin became head of a naval radiotelegraphy laboratory at the bureau (later to become the Naval Research Laboratory) and from 1923 until 1932 was chief of the bureau's laboratory for special radio transmission research.Austin's work involved long-range transmission experiments, most notably a study, conducted in 1910, that tested radio contact between sh...
</Question>
<Choice>Austin, Louis Winslow</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist who was cowinner of the Nobel Prize for Physics in both 1956 and 1972. He shared the 1956 prize with William B. Shockley and Walter H. Brattain for their joint invention of the transistor. With Leon N. Cooper and John R. Schrieffer he was awarded the 1972 prize for development of the theory of superconductivity.Bardeen earned bachelor's and master's degrees in electrical engineering from the University of Wisconsin (Madison) and obtained his doctorate in 1936 in mathematical physics from Princeton University. A staff member of the University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, from 1...
</Question>
<Choice>Bardeen, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist who discovered the Barkhausen effect, a principle concerning changes in the magnetic properties of metal.Barkhausen attended the universities of Munich and Berlin before earning his doctorate in 1907 from Göttingen. After working for the Siemens &amp; Halske laboratories in Berlin, he accepted the world's first professorship in the communications branch of electrical engineering, at the Technical Academy in Dresden (1911). There he worked on theories of spontaneous oscillation and nonlinear switching elements and formulated electron-tube coefficients that are still in use. He...
</Question>
<Choice>Barkhausen, Heinrich Georg</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physicist who was awarded the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1917 for his work on X-ray scattering, which occurs when X rays pass through a material and are deflected by the atomic electrons. This technique proved to be particularly useful in the study of atomic structures.Educated at Trinity and King's colleges, Cambridge, he joined the faculty of Liverpool University in 1902, moved to the University of London in 1909, and became professor of natural philosophy at the University of Edinburgh in 1913.In 1906 Barkla and C.A. Sadler used X-ray scattering to determine the number of electrons...
</Question>
<Choice>Barkla, Charles Glover</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Danish physician, mathematician, and physicist who discovered the optical phenomenon of double refraction.While professor of medicine (1657–98) at the University of Copenhagen, Bartholin observed that images seen through Icelandic feldspar (calcite) were doubled and that, when the crystal was rotated, one image remained stationary while the other rotated with the crystal. Perceiving that light passing through calcite was split into two rays, he called the stationary image the “ordinary beam” and the moving image the “extraordinary beam.” Although Bartholin himself was unable to explain double...
</Question>
<Choice>Bartholin, Erasmus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Soviet physicist, one of the founders of quantum electronics, and a corecipient of the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1964, with Aleksandr Mikhaylovich Prokhorov of the Soviet Union and Charles H. Townes of the United States, for research leading to the development of both the maser and the laser.Basov served in the military during World War II and in 1945 became a physics student at the Moscow Engineering Physics Institute. Upon graduation in 1950, he worked in Moscow at the P.N. Lebedev Physical Institute. In 1953 he received his doctorate (Russian kandidat nauk) degree from the Moscow Engineeri...
</Question>
<Choice>Basov, Nikolay Gennadiyevich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physicist who discovered radioactivity through his investigations of uranium and other substances. In 1903 he shared the Nobel Prize for Physics with Pierre and Marie Curie.He was a member of a scientific family extending through several generations, the most notable being his grandfather Antoine-César Becquerel (1788–1878), his father, Alexandre-Edmond Becquerel (1820–91), and his son Jean Becquerel (1878–1953).
</Question>
<Choice>Becquerel, Henri</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist who, along with Karl Alex Müller (q.v.), was awarded the 1987 Nobel Prize for Physics for their joint discovery of superconductivity in certain substances at temperatures higher than had previously been thought attainable.Bednorz graduated from the University of Münster in 1976 and earned his doctorate at the Swiss Federal Institute of Technology at Zürich in 1982. That same year he joined the IBM Zürich Research Laboratory, where he was recruited by Müller into the latter's studies of superconductivity.In 1983 the two men began systematically testing newly developed ceramic m...
</Question>
<Choice>Bednorz, J. Georg</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist and physiologist who received the 1961 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for his discovery of the physical means by which sound is analyzed and communicated in the cochlea, a portion of the inner ear.As director of the Hungarian Telephone System Research Laboratory (1923–46), Békésy worked on problems of long-distance communication and became interested in the mechanics of human hearing. At the telephone laboratory, the University of Budapest (1939–46), the Karolinska Institute, Stockholm (1946–47), and Harvard University (1947–66) he conducted intensive research that l...
</Question>
<Choice>Bekesy, Georg von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist who discovered (1934) the pinch effect, an electromagnetic process that may offer a way to magnetically confine a plasma at temperatures high enough for controlled nuclear fusion reactions to occur.Bennett attended the University of Wisconsin (M.Sc., 1926) and Ohio State University in Columbus (Ph.D., 1928). In 1930 he joined the faculty of Ohio State but left in 1938 to become director of research of the Electronic Research Corporation. As a U.S. Army officer (1941–45), he worked on aircraft equipment development, and he served as chief (1946–50) of the physical electronics...
</Question>
<Choice>Bennett, Willard Harrison</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish meteorologist best known for his work on cloud physics.He was educated at the universities of Stockholm and Oslo, from the latter of which he received his Ph.D. in 1928. He taught at the University of Stockholm (1935–45) and the University of Uppsala, Swed. (1946–60). From 1918 to 1921 he was a student and co-worker of the pioneering meteorologist Vilhelm Bjerknes and was actively engaged in the development of new methods of weather forecasting.Bergeron was noted for his studies in the analysis of air masses and the formation of warm and cold fronts. He was also the first meteorologist...
</Question>
<Choice>Bergeron, Tor Harold Percival</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist and engineer who first measured the extent, including height and density, of the ionosphere (ionized layers of the Earth's atmosphere), leading to a better understanding of radio wave propagation. He later turned his attention to investigating the origin and development of the Earth's atmosphere. In 1950 the need for data on a worldwide scale led him to propose the International Geophysical Year, a cooperative study of the Earth, which was carried out by the International Council of Scientific Unions while he was president in 1957–59.In 1963 Berkner, with L.C. Marshall, adva...
</Question>
<Choice>Berkner, Lloyd Viel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
physicist known for his studies of the atomic structure of solid compounds, during which he made major contributions to X-ray crystallography.Following graduation from the University of Cambridge (1922), Bernal did research under William Bragg at the Davy-Faraday Laboratory in London before moving back to Cambridge in 1927. At Cambridge, Bernal initiated a research program of X-ray investigations into the structure of complex biological molecules that resulted in Nobel-level discoveries by his students and coworkers Rosalind Franklin, Dorothy Hodgkin, Aaron Klug, and Max Perutz. Bernal spent t...
</Question>
<Choice>Bernal, John Desmond</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist, educator, and writer widely known for the clarity of his writing for the lay reader on the major issues of modern physics.After graduation from Harvard University (Ph.D., 1955), Bernstein worked at Harvard and at the Institute of Advanced Studies at Princeton, N.J. In 1962 he became an associate professor of physics at New York University. He became a professor of physics at Stevens Institute of Technology in Hoboken, N.J., in 1967, a position he continued to hold. He was also on the staff of The New Yorker magazine and held a variety of appointments throughout the United S...
</Question>
<Choice>Bernstein, Jeremy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-born American theoretical physicist who helped shape quantum physics and increased the understanding of the atomic processes responsible for the properties of matter and of the forces governing the structures of atomic nuclei. He received the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1967 for his work on the production of energy in stars. Moreover, he was a leader in emphasizing the social responsibility of science.
</Question>
<Choice>Bethe, Hans</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-born physicist who shared with Heinrich Rohrer (q.v.) half of the 1986 Nobel Prize for Physics for their invention of the scanning tunneling microscope. (Ernst Ruska won the other half of the prize.)Binnig graduated from Johann Wolfgang Goethe University in Frankfurt and received a doctorate from the University of Frankfurt in 1978. He then joined the IBM Research Laboratory in Zürich, where he and Rohrer designed and built the first scanning tunneling microscope (STM). This instrument produces images of the surfaces of conducting or semiconducting materials in such fine detail that ind...
</Question>
<Choice>Binnig, Gerd</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physicist who helped formulate the Biot-Savart law, which concerns magnetic fields, and laid the basis for saccharimetry, a useful technique of analyzing sugar solutions.Educated at the École Polytechnique, Biot was appointed professor of mathematics at the University of Beauvais in 1797, became professor of mathematical physics at the Collège de France in 1800, and was elected a member of the French Academy of Sciences in 1803. He accompanied J.-L. Gay-Lussac in 1804 on the first balloon flight undertaken for scientific purposes. The men showed that the Earth's magnetic field does not...
</Question>
<Choice>Biot, Jean-Baptiste</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Persian scholar and scientist, one of the most learned men of his age and an outstanding intellectual figure.Possessing a profound and original mind of encyclopaedic scope, al-Biruni had varying degrees of proficiency in a number of languages, including Khwarezmian (an eastern Middle Iranian language), Persian, Sanskrit, Hebrew, and Syriac, in addition to the Arabic in which he wrote. He applied his talents in many fields of knowledge, excelling particularly in astronomy, mathematics, chronology, physics, medicine, and history. He corresponded with the great philosopher Ibn Sina (Avicenna). So...
</Question>
<Choice>Biruni, al-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Norwegian meteorologist and physicist, one of the founders of the modern science of weather forecasting.As a youth Bjerknes assisted his father, a professor of mathematics at Christiania, with research in hydrodynamics. In 1890 he went to Germany and became an assistant to and scientific collaborator with the German physicist Heinrich Hertz. Bjerknes made a comprehensive study of electrical resonance that was decisive in the development of radio.After two years as lecturer at the Högskola (School of Engineering), Stockholm, Bjerknes in 1895 became professor of applied mechanics and mathematica...
</Question>
<Choice>Bjerknes, Vilhelm Friman Koren</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British chemist and physicist best known for the rediscovery of “fixed air” (carbon dioxide), the concept of latent heat, and the discovery of the bicarbonates (such as bicarbonate of soda). Black lived and worked within the context of the Scottish Enlightenment, a remarkable flourishing of intellectual life in Edinburgh, Glasgow, and Aberdeen during the latter half of the 18th century. He could count the philosopher David Hume, economist Adam Smith, and geologist James Hutton among his friends.
</Question>
<Choice>Black, Joseph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
winner of the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1948 for his discoveries in the field of cosmic radiation, which he accomplished primarily with cloud-chamber photographs that revealed the way in which a stable atomic nucleus can be disintegrated by bombarding it with alpha particles (helium nuclei). Although such nuclear disintegration had been observed previously, his data explained this phenomenon for the first time and were useful in explaining disintegration by other means.After graduating from Cambridge University in 1921, Blackett spent 10 years as a research worker in the Cavendish Laboratory....
</Question>
<Choice>Blackett, Patrick M. S., Baron Blackett of Chelsea</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss-born American physicist who shared (with E.M. Purcell) the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1952 for developing the nuclear magnetic resonance method of measuring the magnetic field of atomic nuclei.Bloch's doctoral dissertation (University of Leipzig, 1928) promulgated a quantum theory of solids that provided the basis for understanding electrical conduction. Bloch taught at the University of Leipzig until 1933; when Adolf Hitler came to power he emigrated to the United States and was naturalized in 1939. After joining the faculty of Stanford University, Palo Alto, Calif., in 1934, he propose...
</Question>
<Choice>Bloch, Felix</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch-born American physicist, corecipient with Arthur Leonard Schawlow of the United States and Kai Manne Börje Siegbahn of Sweden (qq.v.) of the 1981 Nobel Prize for Physics for their revolutionary spectroscopic studies of the interaction of electromagnetic radiation with matter. Bloembergen made a pioneering use of lasers in these investigations.Bloembergen received undergraduate (1941) and graduate (1943) degrees from the University of Utrecht. In 1946 he entered Harvard University, where with Edward Purcell and Robert Pound he did fundamental research on nuclear magnetic resonance. After...
</Question>
<Choice>Bloembergen, Nicolaas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physicist known for his invention of the oscillograph and for his development of a system of photometric units of measurement.Blondel became a professor of electrotechnology at the School of Bridges and Highways and the School of Mines in Paris. In 1893 he invented the electromagnetic oscillograph, a device that allowed electrical researchers to observe the intensity of alternating currents. In 1894 he proposed the lumen and other new measurement units for use in photometry, based on the metre and the Violle candle. His system was endorsed in 1896 by the International Electrical Congres...
</Question>
<Choice>Blondel, Andre-Eugene</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Danish physicist who shared the 1975 Nobel Prize for Physics with Ben R. Mottelson and James Rainwater for their work in determining the asymmetrical shapes of certain atomic nuclei.Bohr was educated at the University of Copenhagen, where he received a doctorate in 1954. During the 1940s he worked as assistant to his father, Niels Bohr (1922 Nobel physics laureate), on the development of the atomic bomb at Los Alamos, N.M. From 1946 he was associated with the Niels Bohr Institute of Theoretical Physics, founded in Copenhagen by his father, whom he succeeded as director from 1963 to 1970. From...
</Question>
<Choice>Bohr, Aage N.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Danish physicist who is generally regarded as one of the foremost physicists of the 20th century. He was the first to apply the quantum concept, which restricts the energy of a system to certain discrete values, to the problem of atomic and molecular structure. For this work he received the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1922. His manifold roles in the origins and development of quantum physics may be his most important contribution, but through his long career his involvements were substantially broader, both inside and outside the world of physics.
</Question>
<Choice>Bohr, Niels</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American chemist and physicist whose work on the radioactive decay of uranium and thorium was important in the development of the theory of isotopes.Boltwood was a member of the Yale faculty from 1897 until 1900, when he established a consulting firm of mining engineers and chemists in partnership with the American chemist Joseph Hyde Pratt. Boltwood grew interested in radioactivity and, in 1904, showed that many of the radioactive elements decay into other radioactive elements. He discovered ionium, now called thorium-230. In 1905 he proposed that lead is the final decay product of uranium an...
</Question>
<Choice>Boltwood, Bertram Borden</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
physicist whose greatest achievement was in the development of statistical mechanics, which explains and predicts how the properties of atoms (such as mass, charge, and structure) determine the visible properties of matter (such as viscosity, thermal conductivity, and diffusion).After receiving his doctorate from the University of Vienna in 1866, Boltzmann held professorships in mathematics and physics at Vienna, Graz, Munich, and Leipzig.In the 1870s Boltzmann published a series of papers in which he showed that the second law of thermodynamics, which concerns energy exchange, could be explai...
</Question>
<Choice>Boltzmann, Ludwig Eduard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian physiologist and physicist who was the first to explain muscular movement and other body functions according to the laws of statics and dynamics.He was appointed professor of mathematics at Messina in 1649 and at Pisa in 1656. In 1667 he returned to Messina and in 1674 went to Rome, where he lived under the protection of Christina, former queen of Sweden. His best-known work is De Motu Animalium (1680–81; “On the Movement of Animals”), in which he sought to explain the movements of the animal body on mechanical principles; he thus ranks as the founder of the iatrophysical school.Borell...
</Question>
<Choice>Borelli, Giovanni Alfonso</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist who shared the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1954 with Walther Bothe for his probabilistic interpretation of quantum mechanics.Born came from an upper-middle-class, assimilated, Jewish family. At first he was considered too frail to attend public school, so he was tutored at home before being allowed to attend the König Wilhelm Gymnasium in Breslau. Thereafter he continued his studies in physics and mathematics at universities in Breslau, Heidelberg, Zürich, and Göttingen. At the University of Göttingen he wrote his dissertation (1906), on the stability of elastic wires and tapes...
</Question>
<Choice>Born, Max</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian mathematician and physicist noted for his collaboration with Albert Einstein in developing a theory regarding the gaslike qualities of electromagnetic radiation (seeBose-Einstein statistics).Bose, a graduate of the University of Calcutta, taught at the University of Dacca (1921–45) and then at Calcutta (1945–56). Bose's numerous scientific papers (published from 1918 to 1956) contributed to statistical mechanics, the electromagnetic properties of the ionosphere, the theories of X-ray crystallography and thermoluminescence, and unified field theory. Bose's Planck's Law and the Hypothesis...
</Question>
<Choice>Bose, Satyendra Nath</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian plant physiologist and physicist whose invention of highly sensitive instruments for the detection of minute responses by living organisms to external stimuli enabled him to anticipate the parallelism between animal and plant tissues noted by later biophysicists. Bose's experiments on the quasi-optical properties of very short radio waves (1895) led him to make improvements on the coherer, an early form of radio detector, which have contributed to the development of solid-state physics.With a degree from the University of Cambridge (1884), Bose became professor of physical science at Pr...
</Question>
<Choice>Bose, Sir Jagadis Chandra</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist who shared the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1954 with Max Born for his invention of a new method of detecting subatomic particles and for other resulting discoveries.Bothe taught at the universities of Berlin (1920–31), Giessen (1931–34), and Heidelberg (1934–57). In 1925 he and Hans Geiger used two Geiger counters to gather data on the Compton effect—the dependence of the increase in the wavelength of a beam of X rays upon the angle through which the beam is scattered as a result of collision with electrons. Their experiments, which simultaneously measured the energies and dire...
</Question>
<Choice>Bothe, Walther</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physicist and inventor of sensitive instruments, known particularly for his utilization of the torsion of quartz fibres in the measurement of minute forces. This technique was applied in connection with his radiomicrometer (1888) for measuring radiant heat and also in connection with his elaboration (1895) of Henry Cavendish's experiment relating to the Newtonian constant of gravitation.Boys had earlier constructed an integraph (1881) for mechanically drawing the graph of an antiderivative of a given mathematical function. Among his inventions were an improved automatic recording calor...
</Question>
<Choice>Boys, Sir Charles Vernon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Australian-born British physicist and X-ray crystallographer, discoverer (1912) of the Bragg law of X-ray diffraction, which is basic for the determination of crystal structure. He was joint winner (with his father, Sir William Bragg) of the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1915. He was knighted in 1941.Bragg was the eldest child of Sir William Bragg. His maternal grandfather, Sir Charles Todd, was postmaster general and government astronomer of South Australia. Educated at St. Peter's College, Adelaide, and then at Adelaide University, Bragg gained high honours in mathematics at an age when most bo...
</Question>
<Choice>Bragg, Sir Lawrence</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
pioneer British scientist in solid-state physics who was a joint winner (with his son Sir Lawrence Bragg) of the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1915 for his research on the determination of crystal structures. He was knighted in 1920.William Bragg came on his father's side from a family without academic traditions, mainly yeoman farmers and merchant seamen. His mother was the daughter of the local vicar. Upon her death, when he was barely seven, he went to live with two paternal uncles who had set up a pharmacy and grocery shop in Market Harborough, Leicestershire. There he attended an old school...
</Question>
<Choice>Bragg, Sir William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American scientist who, along with John Bardeen and William B. Shockley, won the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1956 for his investigation of the properties of semiconductors—materials of which transistors are made—and for the development of the transistor. The transistor replaced the bulkier vacuum tube for many uses and was the forerunner of microminiature electronic parts.Brattain earned a Ph.D. from the University of Minnesota, and in 1929 he became a research physicist for Bell Telephone Laboratories. His chief field of research involved the surface properties of solids, particularly the atom...
</Question>
<Choice>Brattain, Walter Houser</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist who shared the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1909 with Guglielmo Marconi for the development of wireless telegraphy.Braun received his doctorate from the University of Berlin in 1872. After appointments at Würzburg, Leipzig, Marburg, Karlsruhe, and Tübingen, he became director of the Physical Institute and professor of physics at the University of Strasbourg in 1895.Braun was recognized by the Nobel committee for his improvement of Marconi's transmitting system. In early wireless transmission, the antenna was directly in the power circuit and broadcasting was limited to a range o...
</Question>
<Choice>Braun, Karl Ferdinand</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physicist best remembered for his work on the lattice theory of crystals; Bravais lattices are named for him.Bravais completed his classical education at the Collège Stanislas, Paris, and received his doctorate from Lyon in 1837. His interest in exploration prompted him to join the Navy, and he began teaching astronomy at the Faculté des Sciences at Lyon in 1841. In 1844 he was elected to the Académie Royal des Sciences, Belles-Lettres et Arts de Lyon. In 1845 he was appointed professor of physics at the École Polytechnique, Paris, and in 1854 was admitted to the geography and navigatio...
</Question>
<Choice>Bravais, Auguste</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish physicist noted for his experimental work in optics and polarized light—i.e., light in which all waves lie in the same plane. When light strikes a reflective surface at a certain angle (called the polarizing angle), the reflected light becomes completely polarized. Brewster discovered a simple mathematical relationship between the polarizing angle and the refractive index of the reflective substance. This law is useful in determining the refractive index of materials that are opaque or available only in small samples.Brewster was educated for the ministry at the University of Edinburg...
</Question>
<Choice>Brewster, Sir David</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American experimental physicist noted for his studies of materials at high temperatures and pressures. For his work he was awarded the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1946.Bridgman was the son of a journalist. He entered Harvard University in 1900, receiving his M.A. in 1905 and his Ph.D. in 1908. His experimental work on static high pressures was begun in 1908. It was at first confined to pressures of about 6,500 atmospheres, but he gradually extended the range to more than 100,000 atmospheres and ultimately reached about 400,000 atmospheres. In this unexplored field, he had to invent much of the...
</Question>
<Choice>Bridgman, Percy Williams</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Canadian physicist who shared the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1994 with American physicist Clifford G. Shull for their separate but concurrent development of neutron-scattering techniques.Brockhouse was educated at the University of British Columbia (B.A., 1947) and at the University of Toronto (M.A., 1948; Ph.D., 1950). He conducted his award-winning work from 1950 to 1962 at the Chalk River Nuclear Laboratory, a facility operated by Atomic Energy of Canada. Brockhouse was a professor at McMaster University (Hamilton, Ontario) from 1962 until his retirement in 1984.In neutron-scattering techni...
</Question>
<Choice>Brockhouse, Bertram N.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physicist who made many contributions to the study of X rays.After graduating from the École Navale (Naval School), he served as a naval officer for nine years. He turned to the physical sciences about 1904 and founded his own well-equipped laboratory at the family mansion in Paris, where he and other physicists collaborated in experimentation, especially relating to atomic structure. He improved the accuracy of X-ray spectrography by introducing the rotating crystal method and used X-ray techniques to measure the forces binding various groups of electrons to the atomic nucleus. He was...
</Question>
<Choice>Broglie, Louis-Cesar-Victor-Maurice, 6e duc de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physicist best known for his research on quantum theory and for his discovery of the wave nature of electrons. He was awarded the 1929 Nobel Prize for Physics.
</Question>
<Choice>Broglie, Louis-Victor, 7e duc de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Aristotelian philosopher, logician, and scientific theorist in optics and mechanics.After studies in philosophy at the University of Paris under the nominalist thinker William of Ockham, Buridan was appointed professor of philosophy there. He served as university rector in 1328 and in 1340, the year in which he condemned Ockham's views, an act that is sometimes called the first seed of theological skepticism. Buridan's own works were condemned and placed on the Index of Forbidden Books from 1474 to 1481 by partisans of Ockham.A defender of the principle of causality, Buridan asserted a modifie...
</Question>
<Choice>Buridan, Jean</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physicist and ironmaster, noted for his work on the liquefaction of gases.As a youth, Cailletet worked in his father's ironworks and later was in charge of the works. He was also active in scientific research. On Dec. 2, 1877, Cailletet became the first to liquefy oxygen. Shortly afterward he also succeeded in liquefying nitrogen, hydrogen, nitrogen dioxide, carbon monoxide, and acetylene for the first time. This work was carried on independently of the work on liquefaction by the Swiss physician Raoul-Pierre Pictet (1846–1929), and there was considerable discussion as to which of the t...
</Question>
<Choice>Cailletet, Louis-Paul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physicist who made notable contributions to thermometry, calorimetry, and knowledge of the thermodynamic properties of steam. Callendar in 1886 described a precise thermometer based on the electrical resistivity of platinum; since then, platinum resistance thermometers have been prescribed for the determination of temperatures between the defined points of internationally recognized temperature scales. Later he developed the electrical continuous-flow calorimeter, which measures the heat-carrying properties of liquids. In 1915 he published TheCallendar Steam Tables and in 1920 Properti...
</Question>
<Choice>Callendar, H. L.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physicist and teacher.The son of a weaver, Canton became the clerk to the master of a school in London in 1737; he succeeded the master as teacher in 1745 and ran the school himself until his death in 1772. Canton's invention of a new way to make artificial magnets helped procure him the Copley Medal (1751) and a fellowship in the Royal Society. He was the first in England to experimentally verify Benjamin Franklin's hypothesis of the identity of lightning and electricity (1752). He then made several important discoveries about electrostatic induction. He was the first to refute the Fl...
</Question>
<Choice>Canton, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist who was the inventor of xerography, an electrostatic dry-copying process that found applications ranging from office copying to reproducing out-of-print books.By the age of 14 Carlson was supporting his invalid parents, yet he managed to earn a college degree from the California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, in 1930. After a short time spent with the Bell Telephone Company, he obtained a position with the patent department of P.R. Mallory Company, a New York electronics firm.Plagued by the difficulty of getting copies of patent drawings and specifications, Carlson began...
</Question>
<Choice>Carlson, Chester F.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
natural philosopher, the greatest experimental and theoretical English chemist and physicist of his age. Cavendish was distinguished for great accuracy and precision in researches into the composition of atmospheric air, the properties of different gases, the synthesis of water, the law governing electrical attraction and repulsion, a mechanical theory of heat, and calculations of the density (and hence the weight) of the Earth. His experiment to weigh the Earth has come to be known as the Cavendish experiment.
</Question>
<Choice>Cavendish, Henry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physicist who received the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1935 for the discovery of the neutron.Educated at the universities of Manchester and Cambridge, Chadwick also studied under Hans Geiger at the Technische Hochschule, Berlin. From 1923 he worked with Ernest Rutherford in the Cavendish Laboratory, Cambridge, where they studied the transmutation of elements by bombarding them with alpha particles and investigated the nature of the atomic nucleus, identifying the proton, the nucleus of the hydrogen atom, as a constituent of the nuclei of other atoms.In 1932 Chadwick observed that beryll...
</Question>
<Choice>Chadwick, Sir James</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist, who shared the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1959 with Emilio Segrè for their discovery of the antiproton. This previously postulated subatomic particle was the second antiparticle to be discovered and led directly to the discovery of many additional antiparticles.Chamberlain attended Dartmouth College (B.A., 1941) and the University of California at Berkeley before working on the Manhattan Project, a U.S. research project that produced the first atom bombs. Later, while completing a Ph.D. (1948) at the University of Chicago, he worked at Argonne National Laboratory in Illinoi...
</Question>
<Choice>Chamberlain, Owen</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian-born American astrophysicist who, with William A. Fowler, won the 1983 Nobel Prize for Physics for key discoveries that led to the currently accepted theory on the later evolutionary stages of massive stars.Chandrasekhar was the nephew of Sir Chandrasekhara Venkata Raman, who won the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1930. Chandrasekhar was educated at Presidency College, at the University of Madras, and at Trinity College, Cambridge. From 1933 to 1936 he held a position at Trinity.By the early 1930s, scientists had concluded that, after converting all of their hydrogen to helium, stars lose e...
</Question>
<Choice>Chandrasekhar, Subrahmanyan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English mathematician and physicist noted for his research in geophysics.Chapman was educated at Victorian University of Manchester and at Trinity College, Cambridge. One of his earliest scientific contributions was to modify Maxwell's kinetic theory of gases, thereby predicting the phenomenon of thermal diffusion and later confirming it experimentally (1912–17). His interest in geophysics was aroused while he served as chief assistant (1910–14, 1916–19) to Sir Frank W. Dyson, the Astronomer Royal at Greenwich, where he helped design a new magnetic observatory. This involvement led him to stud...
</Question>
<Choice>Chapman, Sydney</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician, physicist, and inventor who, with Nicolas Robert, was the first to ascend in a hydrogen balloon (1783). About 1787 he developed Charles's law (q.v.) concerning the thermal expansion of gases.From clerking in the finance ministry Charles turned to science and experimented with electricity. He developed several inventions, including a hydrometer and reflecting goniometer, and improved the Gravesand heliostat and Fahrenheit's aerometer. With the Robert brothers, Nicolas and Anne-Jean, he built one of the first hydrogen balloons (1783). In several flights he rose more than a...
</Question>
<Choice>Charles, Jacques-Alexandre-Cesar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polish-born French physicist, winner of the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1992 for his invention of subatomic particle detectors, in particular the multiwire proportional chamber.Charpak's family moved from Poland to Paris when he was seven years old. During World War II Charpak served in the resistance and was imprisoned by Vichy authorities in 1943. In 1944 he was deported to the Nazi concentration camp at Dachau, where he remained until the camp was liberated in 1945. Charpak became a French citizen in 1946. He received his doctorate in 1955 from the Collège de France, Paris, where he worked i...
</Question>
<Choice>Charpak, Georges</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician and physicist who was the mistress of Voltaire.She was married at 19 to the Marquis Florent du Châtelet, governor of Semur-en-Auxois, with whom she had three children. The marquis then took up a military career and thereafter saw his wife only infrequently. Mme du Châtelet returned to Paris and its dazzling social life in 1730 and had several lovers before entering into an affair and intellectual alliance with Voltaire in 1733. She was able to extricate the intemperate Voltaire from many personal and political difficulties, such as those that followed the publication of hi...
</Question>
<Choice>
Chatelet, Gabrielle-Emilie Le Tonnelier de Breteuil, Marquise du
</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Soviet physicist who shared the 1958 Nobel Prize for Physics with fellow Soviet scientists Igor Y. Tamm and Ilya M. Frank for the discovery and theoretical interpretation of the phenomenon of Cherenkov radiation.A peasant's son, Cherenkov graduated from Voronezh State University in 1928; he later became a research student at the P.N. Lebedev Physical Institute. In 1934, working on his dissertation under the guidance of and in collaboration with Sergei Ivanovich Vavilov, he observed that electrons produce a faint blue glow when passing through a transparent liquid at high velocity. This Cherenk...
</Question>
<Choice>Cherenkov, Pavel Alekseyevich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist who, with Claude Cohen-Tannoudji and William D. Phillips, was awarded the 1997 Nobel Prize for Physics for their independent, pioneering research in cooling and trapping atoms using laser light. He later served as secretary of energy (2009– ) in the administration of Pres. Barack Obama.Chu graduated from the University of Rochester, N.Y., in 1970 with a B.S. in physics and an A.B. in math. He received his doctorate in physics in 1976 from the University of California, Berkeley, where he was a postdoctoral fellow from 1976 to 1978. He joined the staff at Bell Laboratories, Mu...
</Question>
<Choice>Chu, Steven</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German mathematical physicist who formulated the second law of thermodynamics and is credited with making thermodynamics a science.Clausius was appointed professor of physics at the Artillery and Engineering School at Berlin in 1850, the same year in which he presented a paper stating the second law of thermodynamics in the well-known form: “Heat cannot of itself pass from a colder to a hotter body.” He applied his results to an exhaustive development of the theory of the steam engine, stressing the concept of entropy (dissipation of available energy). He became professor of physics at Zürich...
</Question>
<Choice>Clausius, Rudolf Julius Emanuel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist and astronomer whose work lay primarily in infrared spectroscopy. Coblentz developed more accurate infrared spectrometers and extended their measurements to longer wavelengths. In 1905 he published a lengthy study of the infrared emission and absorption spectra of numerous elements and compounds. In 1914–16 he published improved values for the Stefan-Boltzmann constant of blackbody radiation and helped to confirm Planck's radiation law. He turned then to astrophysics and measured the infrared radiation from stars, planets, and nebulae. From 1905 until 1945 Coblentz was chief...
</Question>
<Choice>Coblentz, William W.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physicist, joint winner, with Ernest T.S. Walton of Ireland, of the 1951 Nobel Prize for Physics for pioneering the use of particle accelerators in studying the atomic nucleus.Educated at the University of Manchester and St. John's College, Cambridge, Cockcroft was Jacksonian professor of natural philosophy at the University of Cambridge from 1939 to 1946. In 1932 he and Walton designed the Cockcroft-Walton generator and used it to disintegrate lithium atoms by bombarding them with protons. This type of accelerator proved to be one of the most useful in the world's laboratories. They c...
</Question>
<Choice>Cockcroft, Sir John Douglas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physicist who shared the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1997 with Steven Chu and William D. Phillips. They received the award for their development of techniques that use laser light to cool atoms to extremely low temperatures. At such temperatures the atoms move slowly enough to be examined in detail.Cohen-Tannoudji was educated at the École Normale Supérieure (ENS), Paris, receiving his doctorate in 1962. After graduating he continued to work as a research scientist in the department of physics at ENS, while also teaching at the University of Paris VI from 1964 to 1973 and at the College...
</Question>
<Choice>Cohen-Tannoudji, Claude</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist and joint winner, with C.T.R. Wilson of England, of the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1927 for his discovery and explanation of the change in the wavelength of X rays when they collide with electrons in metals. This so-called Compton effect (q.v.) is caused by the transfer of energy from a photon to an electron. Its discovery in 1922 confirmed the dual nature of electromagnetic radiation as both a wave and a particle.Compton, a younger brother of the physicist Karl T. Compton, received his doctorate from Princeton University in 1916 and became head of the department of physics...
</Question>
<Choice>Compton, Arthur Holly</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American educator and physicist who was closely associated with development of the atomic bomb.After obtaining his Ph.D. from Princeton University in 1912, Compton (an older brother of the Nobel prizewinner Arthur Holly Compton) joined the faculty of Reed College, Portland, Ore., as a physics instructor. He later became assistant professor of physics at Princeton University. World War I interrupted his teaching and research, but he returned to Princeton, conducting research in fundamental problems in atomic physics and promoting development of the graduate program. In 1930 he was chosen presid...
</Question>
<Choice>Compton, Karl Taylor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist for whom the Franck–Condon principle was named and who applied quantum mechanics to an understanding of the atom and its nucleus.During World War II Condon made valuable contributions to the development of both atomic energy and radar. In 1943 he helped J. Robert Oppenheimer recruit the group that made the first atomic bombs at Los Alamos, N.M. In 1946 he was a consultant to the committee of the Senate that drafted the legislation that created the Atomic Energy Commission; in the aftermath of the struggle to put atomic energy under civilian control he was attacked by the Hou...
</Question>
<Choice>Condon, Edward U.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist and winner of the 1972 Nobel Prize for Physics, along with John Bardeen and John Robert Schrieffer, for his role in developing the BCS (for their initials) theory of superconductivity. The concept of Cooper electron pairs was named after him.Cooper was educated at Columbia University, receiving his Ph.D. in 1954. He taught at Ohio State University in Columbus before joining (1958) the faculty at Brown University, Providence, R.I., where he was appointed Henry Ledyard Goddard university professor in 1966 and Thomas J. Watson, Sr., professor of science in 1974.His principal co...
</Question>
<Choice>Cooper, Leon N.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
South African-born American physicist who, with Godfrey Hounsfield, was awarded the 1979 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for his work in developing the powerful new diagnostic technique of computerized axial tomography (CAT). Cormack was unusual in the field of Nobel laureates because he never earned a doctorate degree in medicine or any other field of science.After graduating from the University of Cape Town in 1944 Cormack pursued advanced studies there and at the University of Cambridge. He was a lecturer at Cape Town from 1950 to 1956 and then, after a year's research fellowship at...
</Question>
<Choice>Cormack, Allan MacLeod</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist who, with Carl E. Wieman and Wolfgang Ketterle, won the Nobel Prize for Physics in 2001 for creating a new ultracold state of matter, the so-called Bose-Einstein condensate (BEC).After studying at Stanford University (B.S., 1985), Cornell earned a Ph.D. from the Massachusetts Institute of Technology in 1990. In 1992 he joined the faculty of the University of Colorado. That year he also became a senior scientist at the National Institute of Standards and Technology.In the early 1990s Cornell began searching for the Bose-Einstein condensate, which had been predicted some 70 ye...
</Question>
<Choice>Cornell, Eric A.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physicist best known for the formulation of Coulomb's law, which states that the force between two electrical charges is proportional to the product of the charges and inversely proportional to the square of the distance between them. Coulombic force is one of the principal forces involved in atomic reactions.Coulomb spent nine years in the West Indies as a military engineer and returned to France with impaired health. Upon the outbreak of the French Revolution, he retired to a small estate at Blois and devoted himself to scientific research. In 1802 he was appointed an inspector of pub...
</Question>
<Choice>Coulomb, Charles-Augustin de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American particle physicist, corecipient with Val Logsdon Fitch (q.v.) of the 1980 Nobel Prize for Physics for an experiment that implied that reversing the direction of time would not precisely reverse the course of certain reactions of subatomic particles.Cronin graduated from Southern Methodist University at Dallas, Texas, in 1951 and received his Ph.D. from the University of Chicago in 1955. He then joined the staff of the Brookhaven National Laboratory, Upton, N.Y., and in 1958 became a professor at Princeton University.Cronin and his colleague Fitch played a role in modifying the long-he...
</Question>
<Choice>Cronin, James Watson</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British chemist and physicist noted for his discovery of the element thallium and for his cathode-ray studies, fundamental in the development of atomic physics.After studying at the Royal College of Chemistry, London, Crookes became superintendent of the meteorological department at Radcliffe Observatory, Oxford, in 1854, and the following year gained a post at the College of Science in Chester, Cheshire. Having inherited a large fortune from his father, he devoted himself from 1856 entirely to scientific work of various kinds at his private laboratory in London. His researches on electrical d...
</Question>
<Choice>Crookes, Sir William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek physicist and inventor, the first great figure of the ancient engineering tradition of Alexandria, Egypt.Ctesibius was the son of a barber. The discovery of the elasticity of air is attributed to Ctesibius, as is the invention of several devices using compressed air, including force pumps and an air-powered catapult. His most famous invention, however, was an improvement of the clepsydra, or water clock, in which water dripping at a constant rate raised a float that held a pointer to mark the passage of the hours. Another notable invention was a hydraulis, or water organ, in which air wa...
</Question>
<Choice>Ctesibius of Alexandria</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polish-born French physicist, famous for her work on radioactivity and twice a winner of the Nobel Prize. With Henri Becquerel and her husband, Pierre Curie, she was awarded the 1903 Nobel Prize for Physics. She was the sole winner of the 1911 Nobel Prize for Chemistry. She was the first woman to win a Nobel Prize, and she is the only woman to win the award in two different fields.From childhood she was remarkable for her prodigious memory, and at the age of 16 she won a gold medal on completion of her secondary education at the Russian lycée. Because her father, a teacher of mathematics and p...
</Question>
<Choice>Curie, Marie</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physical chemist, cowinner of the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1903. He and his wife, Marie Curie, discovered radium and polonium in their investigation of radioactivity. An exceptional physicist, he was one of the main founders of modern physics.Educated by his father, a doctor, Curie developed a passion for mathematics at the age of 14 and showed a particular aptitude for spatial geometry, which was later to help him in his work on crystallography. Matriculating at the age of 16 and obtaining his licence ès sciences at 18, he was in 1878 taken on as laboratory assistant at the Sorbonne....
</Question>
<Choice>Curie, Pierre</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French painter and physicist who invented the first practical process of photography, known as the daguerreotype. Though the first permanent photograph from nature was made in 1826/27 by Nicéphore Niépce of France, it was of poor quality and required about eight hours' exposure time. The process that Daguerre developed required only 20 to 30 minutes.Daguerre was at first an inland revenue officer and then a scene painter for the opera. In 1822 at Paris he opened the Diorama, an exhibition of pictorial views, with various effects induced by changes in the lighting. A similar establishment that...
</Question>
<Choice>Daguerre, Louis-Jacques-Mande</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish engineer who won the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1912 for his invention of the automatic sun valve, or Solventil, which regulates a gaslight source by the action of sunlight, turning it off at dawn and on at dusk or at other periods of darkness. It rapidly came into worldwide use for buoys and unmanned lighthouses.In 1906 Dalén became chief engineer of the Gas Accumulator Company, which marketed acetylene gas. He became managing director of the company in 1909 and then invented Agamassan, a substance that absorbs acetylene, making it possible to concentrate the gas with no danger of exp...
</Question>
<Choice>Dalen, Nils</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English meteorologist and chemist, a pioneer in the development of modern atomic theory.
</Question>
<Choice>Dalton, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist who, with Koshiba Masatoshi, won the Nobel Prize for Physics in 2002 for detecting neutrinos. Riccardo Giacconi also won a share of the award for his work on X-rays.Davis received a Ph.D. from Yale University in 1942. After military service during World War II, he joined Brookhaven National Laboratory in Upton, N.Y., in 1948. He remained there until his retirement in 1984. In 1985 Davis took a post as a research professor with the University of Pennsylvania.Davis's prizewinning work focused on neutrinos, subatomic particles that had long baffled scientists. Since the 1920s i...
</Question>
<Choice>Davis, Raymond, Jr.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American experimental physicist who shared the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1937 with George P. Thomson of England for discovering that electrons can be diffracted like light waves, thus verifying the thesis of Louis de Broglie that electrons behave both as waves and as particles.Davisson received his doctorate from Princeton University and spent most of his career at the Bell Telephone Laboratories. He began his research there on the emissions of electrons from a metal in the presence of heat and later helped develop the electron microscope.Then, in 1927, Davisson and Lester H. Germer found tha...
</Question>
<Choice>Davisson, Clinton Joseph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-born American physicist who shared one-half of the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1989 with the German physicist Wolfgang Paul. (The other half of the prize was awarded to the American physicist Norman F. Ramsey.) Dehmelt received his share of the prize for his development of the Penning trap, an electromagnetic device that can hold small numbers of ions (electrically charged atoms) and electrons for periods of time long enough to allow their properties to be studied with unprecedented accuracy.Dehmelt served in the German army from 1940 until he was captured by U.S. forces in 1945. Having...
</Question>
<Choice>Dehmelt, Hans Georg</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist who built the first mass spectrometer, a device used to separate and measure the quantities of different charged particles, such as atomic nuclei or molecular fragments.Dempster was educated at the University of Toronto (A.B., 1909; M.A., 1910) and then studied in Germany. He went to the United States in 1914 and obtained his doctorate in physics at the University of Chicago in 1916. He built his first mass spectrometer in 1918, and he began teaching at the University of Chicago in 1919. In 1936, with Kenneth T. Bainbridge of the United States and J.H.E. Mattauch of Austria,...
</Question>
<Choice>Dempster, Arthur Jeffrey</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physicist and astrophysicist who in 1894 invented a spectroheliograph, an instrument that photographs the Sun in monochromatic light. (About a year earlier George E. Hale had independently invented a spectroheliograph in the United States.)After graduating from the École Polytechnique (“Polytechnic School”) in 1874 and spending seven years in the army, Deslandres worked in the laboratories of the École Polytechnique and the Sorbonne. From 1886 to 1891 he studied the spectra of radiation emitted by molecules. Joining the Paris Observatory in 1889, he turned his energies to astrophysics,...
</Question>
<Choice>Deslandres, Henri-Alexandre</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British chemist and physicist whose study of low-temperature phenomena entailed the use of a double-walled vacuum flask of his own design which has been named for him.Educated at the University of Edinburgh, Dewar became a professor at the University of Cambridge (1875) and at the Royal Institution of Great Britain, London (1877), holding both posts throughout his life.Dewar developed structural formulas for benzene (1867), did research in spectroscopy for more than 25 years, and by 1891 had constructed a machine for producing liquid oxygen in quantity. About 1892 he conceived the idea of usin...
</Question>
<Choice>Dewar, Sir James</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist noted for his theoretical work in cosmology and investigations centring on the general theory of relativity. He also made a number of significant contributions to radar technology and to the field of atomic physics.Dicke received a bachelor's degree from Princeton University (1939) and a doctorate from the University of Rochester (1941). In 1941 he became a staff scientist at the radiation laboratory of MIT. Dicke joined the Princeton faculty in 1946; in 1975 he was appointed Albert Einstein professor of science, becoming emeritus professor in 1984.During the early 1940s Dic...
</Question>
<Choice>Dicke, Robert H.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English theoretical physicist who was one of the founders of quantum mechanics and quantum electrodynamics. Dirac is most famous for his 1928 relativistic quantum theory of the electron and his prediction of the existence of antiparticles. In 1933 he shared the Nobel Prize for Physics with the Austrian physicist Erwin Schrödinger.Dirac's mother was British and his father was Swiss. Dirac's childhood was not happy—his father intimidated the children, both at home and at school where he taught French, by meticulous and oppressive discipline. Dirac grew up an introvert, spoke only when spoken to,...
</Question>
<Choice>Dirac, P. A. M.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian physicist who first described how the observed frequency of light and sound waves is affected by the relative motion of the source and the detector. This phenomenon became known as the Doppler effect.Educated at the Polytechnical Institute in Vienna, Doppler became director of the Physical Institute and professor of experimental physics of the University of Vienna in 1850. His earliest writings were on mathematics, but in 1842 he published Über das farbige Licht der Doppelsterne (“Concerning the Coloured Light of Double Stars”), which contained his first statement of the Doppler effec...
</Question>
<Choice>Doppler, Christian</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. physicist and deputy administrator of the National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA) for seven years.Educated at Johns Hopkins University (Baltimore) in 1920, Dryden was named chief of the aerodynamics section of the National Bureau of Standards, Washington. He made pioneering studies in the aerodynamics of high speed and some of the earliest studies of air flow around wing surfaces at the speed of sound. In 1934 he became chief of the mechanics and sound division. During World War II he headed the Washington Project of the National Defense Research Committee, which developed th...
</Question>
<Choice>Dryden, Hugh L.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physicist and inventor who in 1869 developed the so-called trichrome process of colour photography, a key 19th-century contribution to photography.The son of a tax collector, Ducos du Hauron began experimenting in his 20s and on March 1, 1864, patented (but did not build) a device for taking and projecting motion pictures. Four years later, on Nov. 23, 1868, he was granted a patent on a process for making colour photographs. He photographed each scene through green, orange, and violet filters, then printed his three negatives on thin sheets of bichromated gelatin containing carbon pigme...
</Question>
<Choice>Ducos du Hauron, Louis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physicist, mathematician, and philosopher of science who emphasized a history of modern science based on evolutionary metaphysical concepts. He maintained that the role of theory in science is to systematize relationships rather than to interpret new phenomena.Duhem studied at the Collège Stanislas and École Normale Supérieure before teaching at Lille and Rennes. As professor of theoretical physics at the University of Bordeaux (1894), he was also known for work in thermodynamics and hydrodynamics. Among his voluminous writings are Études sur Léonard de Vinci (1906–13; “Studies on Leona...
</Question>
<Choice>Duhem, Pierre-Maurice-Marie</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
chemist and physicist who helped formulate the Dulong–Petit law of specific heats (1819), which proved useful in determining atomic weights.He was an assistant to Claude-Louis Berthollet, eventually became a professor of physics at the Polytechnical School, Paris (1820), and was appointed its director (1830). While working in chemistry he impoverished himself purchasing equipment. During investigations of the highly explosive nitrogen trichloride, which he discovered in 1813, he lost the sight in one eye and nearly lost a hand. His important research in physics was carried out with Alexis-Thér...
</Question>
<Choice>Dulong, Pierre-Louis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American nuclear physicist whose experiments in nuclear fission helped lay the groundwork for the development of the atomic bomb.Dunning graduated from Nebraska Wesleyan University in 1929 and earned a Ph.D. in physics from Columbia University, New York City, in 1934. About the time he received his doctoral degree, he also became an instructor at Columbia. Dunning spent the years 1935–36 in Europe meeting with prominent nuclear physicists before he returned to Columbia University to direct the construction of Columbia's first cyclotron. In 1939 Dunning led the American research team that verif...
</Question>
<Choice>Dunning, John R.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physicist who pioneered in the development of radio communication.He received his doctorate from the Royal College of Science, London, in 1901, and then taught at South Western Polytechnic, London (1902–16), and, succeeding Silvanus Thompson, at City and Guilds Technical College, London (1916–26).Eccles was an early proponent of Oliver Heaviside's theory that an upper layer of the atmosphere reflects radio waves, thus enabling their transmission over long distances. He also suggested in 1912 that solar radiation accounted for the differences in wave propagation during the day and night...
</Question>
<Choice>Eccles, William Henry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English astronomer, physicist, and mathematician who did his greatest work in astrophysics, investigating the motion, internal structure, and evolution of stars. He also was the first expositor of the theory of relativity in the English language.
</Question>
<Choice>Eddington, Sir Arthur Stanley</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist who was corecipient, with R.G.W. Norrish and George Porter, of the 1967 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for work on extremely rapid chemical reactions.Eigen was educated in physics and chemistry at the University of Göttingen (Ph.D., 1951). He worked at the university's Institute of Physical Chemistry from 1951 to 1953, when he joined the Max Planck Institute for Biophysical Chemistry, Göttingen, where he became director in 1964 and later chairman.Eigen was able to study many extremely fast chemical reactions by a variety of methods that he introduced and which are called relaxation...
</Question>
<Choice>Eigen, Manfred</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-born physicist who developed the special and general theories of relativity and won the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1921 for his explanation of the photoelectric effect. Einstein is generally considered the most influential physicist of the 20th century.
</Question>
<Choice>Einstein, Albert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-born American physicist notable for a variety of contributions to science.Elsasser received the Ph.D. from the University of Göttingen in 1927, then accepted teaching appointments at Frankfurt, Paris, and the California Institute of Technology. He became a U.S. citizen in 1940 and engaged in research for the U.S. Army Signal Corps and the Radio Corporation of America before returning to academic life, holding successive positions at the universities of Pennsylvania, Utah, and California; the Scripps Institution of Oceanography; and Princeton, Maryland, and Johns Hopkins universities.Whi...
</Question>
<Choice>Elsasser, Walter M.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
physicist and astrophysicist who developed a theory of expansion and compression of gas spheres and applied it to stellar structure.In 1889 Emden was appointed to the Technical University of Munich, where he became professor of physics and meteorology in 1907. His famous book Gaskugeln (1907; “Gas Spheres”) was a very important early work on the theory of stellar structure; it develops the physical theory of a gas sphere acted upon by its own gravity. He also devised a hypothesis, no longer taken seriously, to explain sunspots.In 1924 Emden became honorary professor of astrophysics at the Univ...
</Question>
<Choice>Emden, Robert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(German),Hungarian physicist who introduced the concept of molecular surface tension. His study of the Earth's gravitational field—which led to his development of the Eötvös torsion balance, long unsurpassed in precision—resulted in proof that inertial mass and gravitational mass are equivalent, later a major principle of Albert Einstein's general theory of relativity.Eötvös, the son of Baron József Eötvös, was minister of public instruction in the Cabinet of Sandor Wekerle, resigning in 1895 to devote himself to teaching physics at the University of Budapest.
</Question>
<Choice>Eotvos, Roland, Baron von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese solid-state physicist and researcher in superconductivity who shared the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1973 with Ivar Giaever and Brian Josephson.Esaki was a 1947 graduate in physics from Tokyo University and immediately joined the Kobe Kogyo company. In 1956 he became chief physicist of the Sony Corporation, where he conducted the experimentation that led to the Nobel Prize. In 1959 he received his Ph.D. from Tokyo University.Esaki's work at Sony was in the field of quantum mechanics and concentrated on the phenomenon of tunneling, in which the wavelike character of matter enables elect...
</Question>
<Choice>Esaki, Leo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist and crystallographer whose theory of X-ray interference by crystals was the first detailed, rigorous theoretical explanation of the diffraction effects first observed in 1912 by his fellow physicist Max von Laue.Ewald received his doctorate from the University of Munich, where his thesis problem, the passage of light waves through a crystal lattice, led Laue to surmise that interference effects would be produced as the wavelength of the incident radiation approached the interatomic spacing of the crystal. Ewald remained in the forefront of developments in X-ray crystallography...
</Question>
<Choice>Ewald, Paul Peter</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British philosopher and educator and an advocate of a Neo-Realist school of thought; he is noted for his proposals toward a general theory of personal and normative ethics (as against the purely descriptive). He proposed a theory of the intuitive knowledge of good and duty (“deontological”) that dispensed with the necessity for an essential concept or definition of the good. His principal writings include Kant's Treatment of Causality (1924); Reason and Intuition (1941); The Fundamental Questions of Philosophy (1951); Ethics (1953); and Non-Linguistic Philosophy (1968). His essays in philosoph...
</Question>
<Choice>Ewing, A. C.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physicist who discovered and named hysteresis, the resistance of magnetic materials to change in magnetic force.Ewing was professor of mechanical engineering at the University of Tokyo (1878–83) and professor of mechanism and applied mechanics at King's College, Cambridge (1890–1903). In his work on the magnetic properties of iron, steel, and other metals, he succeeded in modifying Wilhelm E. Weber's theory of induced magnetism and constructed a hypothetical model to fit his own theory. In 1890 he observed that in electromagnets using alternating current, the magnetization of the metal...
</Question>
<Choice>Ewing, Sir James Alfred</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physicist who discovered in the upper atmosphere the ozone layer that acts as a screen protecting life on the surface of Earth from most of the harmful effects of ultraviolet radiation from the Sun.Fabry joined the staff of Marseilles University in 1894. His early studies centred on light interference, in which a primary research instrument was the Fabry–Pérot interferometer, invented in 1896 in collaboration with Alfred Pérot. This instrument was widely used for the measurement of the wavelengths of light and related studies. While applying it to study the light spectra of the Sun and...
</Question>
<Choice>Fabry, Charles</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist and maker of scientific instruments. He is best known for inventing the alcohol thermometer (1709) and mercury thermometer (1714) and for developing the Fahrenheit temperature scale; this scale is still commonly used in the United States.Fahrenheit spent most of his life in the Netherlands, where he devoted himself to the study of physics and the manufacture of precision meteorological instruments. He discovered, among other things, that water can remain liquid below its freezing point and that the boiling point of liquids varies with atmospheric pressure.
</Question>
<Choice>Fahrenheit, Daniel Gabriel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physicist and chemist whose many experiments contributed greatly to the understanding of electromagnetism.Faraday, who became one of the greatest scientists of the 19th century, began his career as a chemist. He wrote a manual of practical chemistry that reveals his mastery of the technical aspects of his art, discovered a number of new organic compounds, among them benzene, and was the first to liquefy a “permanent” gas (i.e., one that was believed to be incapable of liquefaction). His major contribution, however, was in the field of electricity and magnetism. He was the first to prod...
</Question>
<Choice>Faraday, Michael</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian-born American scientist who was one of the chief architects of the nuclear age. He developed the mathematical statistics required to clarify a large class of subatomic phenomena, explored nuclear transformations caused by neutrons, and directed the first controlled chain reaction involving nuclear fission. He was awarded the 1938 Nobel Prize for Physics, and the Enrico Fermi Award of the U.S. Department of Energy is given in his honour. Fermilab, the National Accelerator Laboratory, in Illinois, is named for him, as is fermium, element number 100.
</Question>
<Choice>Fermi, Enrico</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian physicist who established the basic principle of the induction motor, which is now the principal device for the conversion of electrical power to mechanical power.Ferraris was the son of a pharmacist and the nephew of a Turin physician, to whom he was sent at age 10 and who supervised his education in the classics and the sciences. He was a graduate of the University of Turin and the Scuola d'Applicazione of Turin. While teaching physics he conducted research into light and optics, and the study of optical phase differences in light waves led him to look into similar phenomena in other...
</Question>
<Choice>Ferraris, Galileo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American theoretical physicist who was widely regarded as the most brilliant, influential, and iconoclastic figure in his field in the post-World War II era.Feynman remade quantum electrodynamics—the theory of the interaction between light and matter—and thus altered the way science understands the nature of waves and particles. He was co-awarded the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1965 for this work, which tied together in an experimentally perfect package all the varied phenomena at work in light, radio, electricity, and magnetism. The other cowinners of the Nobel Prize, Julian S. Schwinger of th...
</Question>
<Choice>Feynman, Richard P.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American particle physicist who was corecipient with James Watson Cronin of the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1980 for an experiment conducted in 1964 that disproved the long-held theory that particle interaction should be indifferent to the direction of time.Fitch's early interest in chemistry shifted to physics in the mid-1940s when, as a member of the U.S. Army, he was sent to Los Alamos, N.M., to work on the Manhattan Project. He graduated from McGill University in Montreal with a bachelor's degree in electrical engineering in 1948 and was awarded a Ph.D. in physics by Columbia University in...
</Question>
<Choice>Fitch, Val Logsdon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
physicist who first suggested a method of producing radio waves, thus helping to lay the basis of wireless telegraphy. He also developed a theory, now known as the Lorentz–FitzGerald contraction, which Einstein used in his own special theory of relativity.FitzGerald became a tutor at Trinity College in Dublin in 1877 and professor of natural and experimental philosophy in 1881. From his studies of radiation he concluded that an oscillating electric current would produce electromagnetic waves. This finding was later verified experimentally by Heinrich R. Hertz of Germany and used in the develop...
</Question>
<Choice>FitzGerald, George Francis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physicist noted for his experimental determination of the speed of light.Fizeau worked with Jean-Bernard-Léon Foucault on investigations of the infrared portion of the solar spectrum and made other observations of heat and light. Unaware of Christian Doppler's publication (1842), Fizeau in 1848 gave an explanation of the shift in wavelength in light coming from a star and showed how it could be used to measure the relative velocities of stars that lie in the same line of sight. In 1849 Fizeau found the first reasonably accurate value of the velocity of light obtained in a nonastronomica...
</Question>
<Choice>Fizeau, Armand-Hippolyte-Louis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. physicist, a leading authority in the fields of psychoacoustics and acoustical engineering.Fletcher graduated from Brigham Young University in Provo, Utah, in 1907 and received a Ph.D. in physics from the University of Chicago in 1911. In 1916 he joined the staff of Bell Telephone Laboratories, where he worked for 33 years, primarily in the fields of speech, music, and hearing. Much of his work on the fundamentals of psychoacoustics is described in his book Speech and Hearing (1922).Fletcher's research group developed and demonstrated two separate but related methods for reproducing sound...
</Question>
<Choice>Fletcher, Harvey</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish physicist noted for his research on heat conduction and glaciers.Educated at the University of Edinburgh, Forbes became a professor there in 1833. Between 1836 and 1844 he published four series of “Researches on Heat” in which he described the polarization (alignment of waves to vibrate in a plane) of radiant infrared heat by the mineral tourmaline, by transmission through a bundle of thin mica plates, and by reflection from the surfaces of a pile of mica plates. In 1846 he began experiments on the temperature of the Earth at different depths and in different soils near Edinburgh. Lat...
</Question>
<Choice>Forbes, James David</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physicist who introduced and helped develop a technique of measuring the absolute velocity of light with extreme accuracy. He provided experimental proof that the Earth rotates on its axis.Foucault was educated for the medical profession, but his interests turned to experimental physics. With Armand Fizeau, he began a series of investigations of light and heat. By 1850 he established that light travels slower in water than in air. In the same year he measured the velocity of light, finding a value that is within 1 percent of the true figure.In 1851, by interpreting the motion of a heavy...
</Question>
<Choice>Foucault, Jean</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician, known also as an Egyptologist and administrator, who exerted strong influence on mathematical physics through his Théorie analytique de la chaleur (1822; The Analytical Theory of Heat). He showed how the conduction of heat in solid bodies may be analyzed in terms of infinite mathematical series now called by his name, the Fourier series. Far transcending the particular subject of heat conduction, his work stimulated research in mathematical physics, which has since been often identified with the solution of boundary-value problems, encompassing many natural occurrences su...
</Question>
<Choice>Fourier, Jean-Baptiste-Joseph, Baron</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American nuclear astrophysicist who, with Subrahmanyan Chandrasekhar, won the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1983 for his role in formulating a widely accepted theory of element generation.Fowler studied at Ohio State University (B.S., 1933) and at the California Institute of Technology (Ph.D., 1936), where he became a professor in 1939. His theory of element generation, which he developed with Sir Fred Hoyle, Margaret Burbidge, and Geoffrey Burbidge in the 1950s, suggests that in stellar evolution elements are synthesized progressively from light elements to heavy ones, in nuclear reactions that...
</Question>
<Choice>Fowler, William A.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-born American physicist who shared the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1925 with Gustav Hertz for research on the excitation and ionization of atoms by electron bombardment that verified the quantized nature of energy transfer.Franck studied at the universities of Heidelberg and Berlin, received his doctorate from the latter in 1906, and served in the German army during World War I. He and Hertz performed their prizewinning work at the University of Berlin in 1912–14. They bombarded mercury atoms with electrons and traced the energy changes that resulted from the collisions. They found that...
</Question>
<Choice>Franck, James</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Soviet winner of the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1958 jointly with Pavel A. Cherenkov and Igor Y. Tamm, also of the Soviet Union. He received the award for explaining the phenomenon of Cherenkov radiation.After graduating from Moscow State University in 1930, Frank worked at the Leningrad Optical Institute. He returned to Moscow to work at the P.N. Lebedev Physical Institute (1934–70) and from 1940 was a professor at Moscow State University.In 1937 Frank and Tamm provided the theoretical explanation of Cherenkov radiation, an effect discovered by Cherenkov in 1934 in which light is emitted when...
</Question>
<Choice>Frank, Ilya Mikhaylovich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist who first studied the dark lines of the Sun'sspectrum, now known as Fraunhofer lines. He also was the first to use extensively the diffraction grating, a device that disperses light more effectively than a prism does. His work set the stage for the development of spectroscopy.Fraunhofer worked as an optician at the Untzschneider Optical Institute at Benedictbeuern, near Munich, of which he became manager in 1818. While measuring the light-bending properties of various kinds of glass, he noticed dark lines in the light spectrum of a sodium flame, and he continued looking for su...
</Question>
<Choice>Fraunhofer, Joseph von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physicist who pioneered in optics and did much to establish the wave theory of light advanced by Thomas Young.Fresnel served as an engineer in various departments of France but lost his post temporarily during the period following Napoleon's return from Elba (1814). About that time he seems to have begun his researches in optics. He studied the aberration of light, created various devices for producing interference fringes, and, by applying mathematical analysis to his work, removed a number of objections to the wave theory.With François Arago he studied the laws of the interference of...
</Question>
<Choice>Fresnel, Augustin-Jean</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist who, together with Richard E. Taylor and Henry W. Kendall, received the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1990 for their joint experimental confirmation of the fundamental particles known as quarks.Friedman was educated at the University of Chicago, from which he received his Ph.D. degree in 1956. After conducting research there and at Stanford University, where he met Taylor and Kendall, he began teaching at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology in 1960. He became a full professor there in 1967 and head of the physics department in 1983.Friedman conducted his prizewinning rese...
</Question>
<Choice>Friedman, Jerome Isaac</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
physicist who, with his aunt Lise Meitner, described the division of neutron-bombarded uranium into lighter elements and named the process fission (1939). At the time, Meitner was working in Stockholm and Frisch at Copenhagen under Niels Bohr, who brought their observation to the attention of Albert Einstein and others in the United States.After receiving his doctorate at Vienna (1926), Frisch, with Otto Stern and Immanuel Estermann, measured the magnetic moment of the proton (1933). During World War II he was engaged in atomic research at Los Alamos, N.M. From 1947 he taught at Cambridge and...
</Question>
<Choice>Frisch, Otto Robert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian mathematician, astronomer, and physicist who is best known for his work in hydraulics. His most significant contributions to science, however, were in the compilation, interpretation, and dissemination of the work of other scientists.Frisi was a member of the Barnabite religious order, a professor at the University of Milan, and a member of most of the major scientific societies of his time. He was held in such esteem by his contemporaries that plans for nearly all the major hydraulic works constructed in northern Italy during his adult life were first shown to him for his inspection....
</Question>
<Choice>Frisi, Paolo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hungarian-born electrical engineer who won the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1971 for his invention of holography, a system of lensless, three-dimensional photography that has many applications.A research engineer for the firm of Siemens and Halske in Berlin from 1927, Gabor fled Nazi Germany in 1933 and worked with the Thomson-Houston Company in England, later becoming a British subject. In 1947 he conceived the idea of holography and, by employing conventional filtered-light sources, developed the basic technique. Because conventional light sources generally provided either too little light or...
</Question>
<Choice>Gabor, Dennis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian natural philosopher, astronomer, and mathematician who made fundamental contributions to the sciences of motion, astronomy, and strength of materials and to the development of the scientific method. His formulation of (circular) inertia, the law of falling bodies, and parabolic trajectories marked the beginning of a fundamental change in the study of motion. His insistence that the book of nature was written in the language of mathematics changed natural philosophy from a verbal, qualitative account to a mathematical one in which experimentation became a recognized method for discoveri...
</Question>
<Choice>Galileo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian physician and physicist who investigated the nature and effects of what he conceived to be electricity in animal tissue. His discoveries led to the invention of the voltaic pile, a kind of battery that makes possible a constant source of current electricity.
</Question>
<Choice>Galvani, Luigi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian-born American nuclear physicist and cosmologist who was one of the foremost advocates of the big-bang theory, according to which the universe was formed in a colossal explosion that took place billions of years ago. In addition, his work on deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) made a basic contribution to modern genetic theory.Gamow attended Leningrad (now St. Petersburg) University, where he studied briefly with A.A. Friedmann, a mathematician and cosmologist who suggested that the universe should be expanding. At that time Gamow did not pursue Friedmann's suggestion, preferring instead to del...
</Question>
<Choice>Gamow, George</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German mathematician, generally regarded as one of the greatest mathematicians of all time for his contributions to number theory, geometry, probability theory, geodesy, planetary astronomy, the theory of functions, and potential theory (including electromagnetism).Gauss was the only child of poor parents. He was rare among mathematicians in that he was a calculating prodigy, and he retained the ability to do elaborate calculations in his head most of his life. Impressed by this ability and by his gift for languages, his teachers and his devoted mother recommended him to the duke of Brunswick...
</Question>
<Choice>Gauss, Carl Friedrich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French chemist and physicist who pioneered investigations into the behaviour of gases, established new techniques for analysis, and made notable advances in applied chemistry.
</Question>
<Choice>Gay-Lussac, Joseph-Louis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist who introduced the first successful detector (the Geiger counter) of individual alpha particles and other ionizing radiations.Geiger was awarded the Ph.D. by the University of Erlangen in 1906 and shortly thereafter joined the staff of the University of Manchester, where he became one of the most valuable collaborators of Ernest Rutherford. At Manchester, Geiger built the first version of his particle counter and used it and other radiation detectors in experiments that led to the identification of the alpha particle as the nucleus of the helium atom and to Rutherford's correc...
</Question>
<Choice>Geiger, Hans</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist, winner of the Nobel Prize for Physics for 1969 for his work pertaining to the classification of subatomic particles and their interactions.Having entered Yale University at age 15, Gell-Mann received his B.S. in physics in 1948 and his Ph.D. at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology in 1951. His doctoral research on subatomic particles was influential in the later work of the Nobel laureate (1963) Eugene P. Wigner. In 1952 Gell-Mann joined the Institute for Nuclear Studies at the University of Chicago. The following year he introduced the concept of “strangeness,” a quan...
</Question>
<Choice>Gell-Mann, Murray</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physicist, who was awarded the 1991 Nobel Prize for Physics for his discoveries about the ordering of molecules in liquid crystals and polymers.The son of a physician, Gennes studied at the École Normale Supérieure. He was employed as an engineer at the French Atomic Energy Commission (1955–61) and then was a professor with the Orsay Liquid Crystals Group of the University of Paris (1961–71). He later taught at the Collège de France (1971–76) and served as director of the École Supérieure de Physique et de Chimie Industrielles (1976–2002).Gennes investigated how extremely complex forms...
</Question>
<Choice>Gennes, Pierre-Gilles de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist noted especially for his work with Otto Stern on the deflections of atoms in a nonhomogeneous magnetic field.Educated at the University of Tübingen, he became a lecturer there in 1916; after periods at Göttingen and Frankfurt, he returned to Tübingen as professor of physics in 1925 and from 1929 to 1957 was professor of physics at Munich. He was best known for his part in the Stern-Gerlach experiment (q.v.), but he also made contributions in the fields of radiation, spectroscopy, and quantum theory. His books include Grundlagen der Quantentheorie (1921), Magnetismus (1931), Hu...
</Question>
<Choice>Gerlach, Walther</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist who, with his colleague Clinton Joseph Davisson, conducted an experiment (1927) that first demonstrated the wave properties of the electron. This experiment confirmed the hypothesis of Louis-Victor de Broglie, a founder of wave mechanics, that the electron should show the properties of an electromagnetic wave as well as those of a particle.Germer was a graduate student at Columbia University, working under Davisson's supervision at the Bell Telephone Laboratories in New York City, when they bombarded a single crystal of nickel with an electron beam and observed that the dist...
</Question>
<Choice>Germer, Lester Halbert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian-born physicist who won the Nobel Prize for Physics in 2002 for his seminal discoveries of cosmic sources of X rays, which helped lay the foundations for the field of X-ray astronomy. Raymond Davis, Jr., and Koshiba Masatoshi also won a share of the award for their research on neutrinos.Giacconi received a Ph.D. from the University of Milan in 1954. In 1959 he joined the research firm American Science and Engineering, and in 1973 he moved to the Harvard-Smithsonian Center for Astrophysics. He later directed the Space Telescope Science Institute (1981–93) and the European Southern Observ...
</Question>
<Choice>Giacconi, Riccardo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Norwegian-born American physicist who shared the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1973 with Leo Esaki and Brian Josephson for work in solid-state physics.Giaever received an engineering degree at the Norwegian Institute of Technology in Trondheim in 1952 and became a patent examiner for the Norwegian government. In 1954 he migrated to Canada, where he worked as a mechanical engineer with the General Electric Company in Ontario. In 1956 he was transferred to General Electric's Development Center in Schenectady, N.Y. There he shifted his interest to physics and did graduate work at the Rensselaer Poly...
</Question>
<Choice>Giaever, Ivar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
theoretical physicist and chemist who was one of the greatest scientists in the United States in the 19th century. His application of thermodynamic theory converted a large part of physical chemistry from an empirical into a deductive science.Gibbs was the fourth child and only son of Josiah Willard Gibbs, Sr., professor of sacred literature at Yale University. There were college presidents among his ancestors and scientific ability in his mother's family. Facially and mentally, Gibbs resembled his mother. He was a friendly youth but was also withdrawn and intellectually absorbed. This circums...
</Question>
<Choice>Gibbs, J. Willard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian physicist and astrophysicist, who won the Nobel Prize for Physics in 2003 for his pioneering work on superconductivity. He shared the award with Alexey A. Abrikosov of Russia and Anthony J. Leggett of Great Britain. Ginzburg was also noted for his work on theories of radio wave propagation, radio astronomy, and the origin of cosmic rays. He was a member of the team that developed the Soviet thermonuclear bomb.After graduating from Moscow State University (1938), Ginzburg was appointed to the P.N. Lebedev Physical Institute of the U.S.S.R. Academy of Sciences in 1940, and from 1971 to 1...
</Question>
<Choice>Ginzburg, Vitaly Lazarevich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian physicist who proposed a widely used system for the definition of electrical, magnetic, and mechanical units of measurement.Giorgi studied civil engineering at the Institute of Technology in Rome and from 1906 to 1923 directed the Technology Office of Rome. He taught (1913–39) at the University of Rome and also held appointments at the universities of Cagliari and Palermo and at the Royal Institute for Higher Mathematics. He is best known for developing the Giorgi International System of Measurement (also known as the MKSA system) in 1901. This system proposed as units of scientific me...
</Question>
<Choice>Giorgi, Giovanni</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist and recipient of the 1960 Nobel Prize for Physics for his invention and development of the bubble chamber, a research instrument used to observe the behaviour of subatomic particles.After graduating from Case Institute of Technology, Cleveland, in 1946, Glaser attended the California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, where he received a Ph.D. in physics in 1949, then began teaching at the University of Michigan, where he was a professor of physics until 1959. There he conceived the idea for the bubble chamber, which has become a widely used instrument because it allows prec...
</Question>
<Choice>Glaser, Donald A.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American theoretical physicist who, with Steven Weinberg and Abdus Salam, received the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1979 for their complementary efforts in formulating the electroweak theory, which explains the unity of electromagnetism and the weak force.Glashow was the son of Jewish immigrants from Russia. He and Weinberg were members of the same classes at the Bronx High School of Science, New York City (1950), and Cornell University (1954). Glashow received his Ph.D. in physics from Harvard University in 1959. He joined the faculty of the University of California at Berkeley in 1961 and retu...
</Question>
<Choice>Glashow, Sheldon Lee</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist, who won one-half of the Nobel Prize for Physics in 2005 for contributions to the field of optics, the branch of physics that deals with the physical properties of light and its interactions with matter. (The other half of the award was shared by John L. Hall and Theodor W. Hänsch.)Glauber received a Ph.D. in physics from Harvard University in 1949. He then conducted research at the Institute for Advanced Studies in Princeton, N.J., and at the California Institute of Technology. In 1952 he returned to Harvard, where he continued to teach into the early 21st century.Glauber's...
</Question>
<Choice>Glauber, Roy J.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American professor and inventor generally acknowledged to be the father of modern rocketry. He published his classic treatise, A Method of Reaching Extreme Altitudes, in 1919.
</Question>
<Choice>Goddard, Robert Hutchings</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. physicist whose contributions to nuclear physics include the discovery that the nucleus of the deuterium atom consists of a proton and a neutron.While studying at Cambridge University, Goldhaber, in collaboration with James Chadwick, discovered (1934) the nuclear photoelectric effect (the disintegration of a nucleus by high-energy X-rays or gamma rays). This discovery later provided evidence that the neutron is heavier than the proton. While studying slow neutrons, they discovered the neutron-induced disintegrations of the nuclei of lithium, boron, and nitrogen. Goldhaber also showed the...
</Question>
<Choice>Goldhaber, Maurice</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist known for his work on electrical phenomena in gases and on cathode rays; he is also credited with discovering canal rays.Goldstein studied at the University of Breslau (now in Wroclaw, Pol.), where he received his doctorate in 1881. His career was spent at the Potsdam Observatory. He was primarily interested in electrical discharges in moderate to high vacuums. In 1886 he discovered what he termed Kanalstrahlen, or canal rays, also called positive rays; these are positively charged ions that are accelerated toward and through a perforated cathode in an evacuated tube. He also...
</Question>
<Choice>Goldstein, Eugen</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian physicist known for his work on methods of earthquake observations and on the construction of seismographs.Golitsyn was educated in the naval school and naval academy. In 1887 he left active service for scientific studies and went to Strasbourg. In 1891 he was appointed Privatdozent at the University of Moscow and in 1893 professor of physics at Dorpat. The same year he was elected fellow, and in 1908 a member, of the Academy of Sciences in St. Petersburg. His early research was in spectroscopy.He invented the first effective electromagnetic seismograph in 1906. Five years later he mod...
</Question>
<Choice>Golitsyn, Boris Borisovich, Knyaz</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch-born U.S. physicist who, with George E. Uhlenbeck (q.v.), a fellow graduate student at the University of Leiden, Neth., formulated (1925) the concept of electron spin, leading to major changes in atomic theory and quantum mechanics. Of this work Isidor I. Rabi, a Nobelist in physics, remarked, “Physics must be forever in debt to those two men for discovering the spin.” Later it was recognized that spin is a fundamental property of neutrons, protons, and other elementary particles.A faculty member of the University of Michigan (1927–46) and Northwestern University, Ill. (1946–48), Goudsmi...
</Question>
<Choice>Goudsmit, Samuel Abraham</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist who, with H. David Politzer and Frank Wilczek, was awarded the Nobel Prize for Physics in 2004 for discoveries regarding the strong force—the nuclear force that binds together quarks (the smallest building blocks of matter) and holds together the nucleus of the atom.Gross graduated from Hebrew University in Jerusalem in 1962 and received a Ph.D. in physics from the University of California, Berkeley, in 1966. In 1969 he joined the faculty at Princeton University, where he began working with Wilczek, then a graduate student. In 1997 Gross became director of the Kavli Institut...
</Question>
<Choice>Gross, David J.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physicist and a justice of Britain's high court (from 1880), who first offered proof of the thermal dissociation of atoms within a molecule. He showed that steam in contact with a strongly heated platinum wire is decomposed into hydrogen and oxygen in a reversible reaction. Grove also developed the two-fluid electric cell, consisting of amalgamated zinc in dilute sulfuric acid and a platinum cathode in concentrated nitric acid, the liquids being separated by a porous container.Grove was educated by private tutors and then at Brasenose College, Oxford, and also studied law at Lincoln's...
</Question>
<Choice>Grove, Sir William Robert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist, engineer, and natural philosopher who invented the first air pump and used it to study the phenomenon of vacuum and the role of air in combustion and respiration.Guericke was educated at the University of Leipzig and studied law at the University of Jena in 1621 and mathematics and mechanics at the University of Leyden in 1623. In 1631 he became an engineer in the army of Gustavus II Adolphus of Sweden, and from 1646 to 1681 he was bürgermeister (mayor) of Magdeburg and magistrate for Brandenburg.In 1650 Guericke invented the air pump, which he used to create a partial vacuum...
</Question>
<Choice>Guericke, Otto von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physicist whose exhaustive studies of ferronickel alloys culminated in the discovery of invar (a nickel–steel alloy) and gained him the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1920.In 1883 Guillaume joined the International Bureau of Weights and Measures, Sèvres, and from 1915 served as its director. His early studies there included exhaustive investigations of the mercury thermometer and of the volume of the litre, which he found to be 1,000.028 cubic centimetres, not 1,000.000 cubic centimetres as had been accepted. From 1890 he focused his attention on alloys and developed invar and elinvar. Inva...
</Question>
<Choice>Guillaume, Charles Edouard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physicist and meteorologist who first formulated an accurate theory describing the trade winds and the associated meridional (north-south) circulation pattern now known as the Hadley cell.Though educated in law, Hadley preferred physics to legal work. For about seven years he was in charge of the meteorological observations prepared for the Royal Society of London. Having made the first adequate study of the trade-wind currents, he explained their relation to the Earth's daily rotation and discussed the relevant atmospheric motions and their causes. He presented his ideas in a paper, “...
</Question>
<Choice>Hadley, George</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist, who shared one-half of the 2005 Nobel Prize for Physics with Theodor W. Hänsch for their contributions to the development of laser spectroscopy, the use of lasers to determine the frequency (colour) of light emitted by atoms and molecules. (The other half of the prize went to Roy J. Glauber.)Hall studied at the Carnegie Institute of Technology (B.S., 1956; M.S., 1958; Ph.D., 1961) in Pittsburgh. In 1961 he joined the Joint Institute for Laboratory Astrophysics (now known as JILA), a research institute operated by the National Bureau of Standards (later called the National I...
</Question>
<Choice>Hall, John L.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish geologist and physicist who founded experimental geology by artificially producing various rock types in the laboratory.Hall succeeded to his father's baronetcy in 1776 and thereafter studied at Christ's College, Cambridge, and the University of Edinburgh. He later became president of the Royal Society of Edinburgh.For many years he rejected the belief of his friend, the noted Scottish geologist James Hutton, that many rocks have an igneous origin, but eventually he came to believe that Hutton's views might be subject to experimental testing. By melting minerals and cooling them at a...
</Question>
<Choice>Hall, Sir James, 4th Baronet</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Irish mathematician who contributed to the development of optics, dynamics, and algebra—in particular, discovering the algebra of quaternions. His work proved significant for the development of quantum mechanics.Hamilton was the son of a solicitor. He was educated by his uncle, James Hamilton, an Anglican priest with whom he lived from before the age of three until he entered college. An aptitude for languages was soon apparent: at five he was already making progress with Latin, Greek, and Hebrew, broadening his studies to include Arabic, Sanskrit, Persian, Syriac, French, and Italian before h...
</Question>
<Choice>Hamilton, Sir William Rowan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist, who shared one-half of the 2005 Nobel Prize for Physics with John L. Hall for their contributions to the development of laser spectroscopy, the use of lasers to determine the frequency (colour) of light emitted by atoms and molecules. (The other half of the award went to Roy J. Glauber.)Hänsch received a Ph.D. in physics from the University of Heidelberg in 1969. The following year he moved to the United States and began teaching at Stanford University. In 1986 he returned to Germany, where he later became director of the Max Planck Institute for Quantum Optics and joined the...
</Question>
<Choice>Hansch, Theodore W.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist who contributed to the development of radar and is regarded as the founder of microwave technology.After earning a Ph.D. at Stanford University in 1933, Hansen began teaching there the next year. His early pioneering work in 1937 on microwave resonant cavities was key to the development of microwave technology just before World War II. At that time he also began work, with the brothers Russell and Sigurd Varian, on the problem of detecting aircraft. Using the technology of resonant cavities, Hansen developed the basis for a new microwave vacuum tube called the klystron ampli...
</Question>
<Choice>Hansen, William Webster</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Norwegian astronomer and physicist noted for his research in geomagnetism.At the beginning of the 19th century, measurements of geomagnetic intensity had just begun. Hansteen continued the task, taking measurements in London, Paris, Finland, and (1828–30) Siberia. In 1826 he published the first reliable chart of magnetic intensities. Hansteen's theories of geomagnetism were less successful than his measurements, however, and were ultimately disproved by Carl Friedrich Gauss in 1839.Hansteen, who joined the faculty of the University of Christiania in 1814, established the first astronomical obs...
</Question>
<Choice>Hansteen, Christopher</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physicist who built a primitive internal-combustion engine.Born of poor parents, Hautefeuille was reared by the Duchess of Bouillon and eventually took holy orders and became an abbé. He spent all his time in mechanical pursuits. He published works on acoustics, optics, tidal phenomena, and watch mechanisms. He also invented the micrometer microscope to measure the size of minute objects.Hautefeuille's internal-combustion engine was intended to operate a pump. The piston was first actuated by the ignition of a small charge of gunpowder and then returned to its initial position when the...
</Question>
<Choice>Hautefeuille, Jean de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English theoretical physicist whose theory of exploding black holes drew upon both relativity theory and quantum mechanics. He also worked with space-time singularities.Hawking studied mathematics and physics at University College, Oxford (B.A., 1962), and Trinity Hall, Cambridge (Ph.D., 1966). He was elected a research fellow at Gonville and Caius College at Cambridge. In the early 1960s Hawking contracted amyotrophic lateral sclerosis, an incurable degenerative neuromuscular disease. He continued to work despite the disease's progressively disabling effects.Hawking worked primarily in the fi...
</Question>
<Choice>Hawking, Stephen W.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American electrical engineer and physicist who invented the neutrodyne circuit, which made radio commercially possible.Hazeltine attended Stevens Institute of Technology, Hoboken, N.J., and, after working a year (1906–07) in the laboratory of the General Electric Company in Schenectady, N.Y., he returned to Stevens to begin a long career in teaching. He became a full professor and head of the department of electrical engineering in 1917.Experimental work in radio telegraphy and telephony, including a period as consultant to the U.S. Navy during World War I, led Hazeltine to invent the neutrody...
</Question>
<Choice>Hazeltine, Alan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
physicist who predicted the existence of the ionosphere, an electrically conductive layer in the upper atmosphere that reflects radio waves. In 1870 he became a telegrapher, but increasing deafness forced him to retire in 1874. He then devoted himself to investigations of electricity. In Electrical Papers (1892), he dealt with theoretical aspects of problems in telegraphy and electrical transmission, making use of an unusual calculatory method called operational calculus, now better known as the method of Laplace transforms, to study transient currents in networks. His work on the theory of th...
</Question>
<Choice>Heaviside, Oliver</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist and philosopher who discovered (1925) a way to formulate quantum mechanics in terms of matrices. For that discovery, he was awarded the Nobel Prize for Physics for 1932. In 1927 he published his uncertainty principle, upon which he built his philosophy and for which he is best known. He also made important contributions to the theories of the hydrodynamics of turbulent flows, the atomic nucleus, ferromagnetism, cosmic rays, and subatomic particles, and he was instrumental in planning the first West German nuclear reactor at Karlsruhe, together with a research reactor in Munich...
</Question>
<Choice>Heisenberg, Werner</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German scientist and philosopher who made fundamental contributions to physiology, optics, electrodynamics, mathematics, and meteorology. He is best known for his statement of the law of the conservation of energy. He brought to his laboratory research the ability to analyze the philosophical assumptions on which much of 19th-century science was based, and he did so with clarity and precision.
</Question>
<Choice>Helmholtz, Hermann von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Flemish physician, philosopher, mystic, and chemist who recognized the existence of discrete gases and identified carbon dioxide.
</Question>
<Choice>Helmont, Jan Baptista van</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist who, with James Franck, received the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1925 for the Franck-Hertz experiment, which confirmed the quantum theory that energy can be absorbed by an atom only in definite amounts and provided an important confirmation of the Bohr atomic model.A nephew of the noted physicist Heinrich Hertz, he studied at the universities of Göttingen, Munich, and Berlin, and was appointed an assistant in physics at the University of Berlin in 1913, where he began to work with Franck. Their experiments showed that when an electron strikes an atom of mercury vapour, the elec...
</Question>
<Choice>Hertz, Gustav</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist who was the first to broadcast and receive radio waves.He received his Ph.D. magna cum laude from the University of Berlin in 1880, where he studied under Hermann von Helmholtz. In 1883 he began his studies of the electromagnetic theory of James Clerk Maxwell. Between 1885 and 1889, while he was professor of physics at the Karlsruhe Polytechnic, he produced electromagnetic waves in the laboratory and measured their length and velocity. He showed that the nature of their vibration and their susceptibility to reflection and refraction were the same as those of light and heat wav...
</Question>
<Choice>Hertz, Heinrich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Canadian physicist and winner of the 1971 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for his work in determining the electronic structure and geometry of molecules, especially free radicals—groups of atoms that contain odd numbers of electrons. His work provided the foundation for molecular spectroscopy.Herzberg became Privatdozent (unsalaried lecturer) at the Darmstadt Institute of Technology in 1930 but fled Nazi Germany in 1935 and obtained a position with the University of Saskatchewan. From 1945 to 1948 he worked at the University of Chicago's Yerkes Observatory in Williams Bay, Wisconsin, after which he...
</Question>
<Choice>Herzberg, Gerhard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian-born physicist who was a joint recipient, with Carl D. Anderson of the United States, of the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1936 for his discovery of cosmic rays—high-energy radiation originating in outer space.Educated at the University of Graz, Hess received his Ph.D. from the University of Vienna in 1906. His research dealt chiefly with radioactivity and atmospheric electricity. For many years scientists had been unable to explain the source of an ionizing background radiation in the atmosphere that penetrated electroscopes sent aloft in balloons. It was assumed that the radiation must...
</Question>
<Choice>Hess, Victor Francis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British astrophysicist who won the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1974 for his discovery of pulsars (cosmic objects that emit extremely regular pulses of radio waves).Hewish was educated at the University of Cambridge and in 1946 joined the radio astronomy group there led by Sir Martin Ryle. While directing a research project at the Mullard Radio Astronomy Observatory at Cambridge in 1967, Hewish recognized the significance of an observation made by a graduate assistant, Jocelyn Bell. He determined that the regularly patterned radio signals, or pulses, that Bell had detected were not caused by ear...
</Question>
<Choice>Hewish, Antony</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German mathematician who reduced geometry to a series of axioms and contributed substantially to the establishment of the formalistic foundations of mathematics. His work in 1909 on integral equations led to 20th-century research in functional analysis.The first steps of Hilbert's career occurred at the University of Königsberg, at which, in 1884, he finished his Inaugurel-dissertation (Ph.D.); he remained at Königsberg as a Privatdozent (lecturer, or assistant professor) in 1886–92, as an Extraordinarius (associate professor) in 1892–93, and as an Ordinarius in 1893–95. In 1892 he married Kät...
</Question>
<Choice>Hilbert, David</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist who first computed the electricity-carrying capacity of charged atoms and molecules (ions), an important factor in understanding electrochemical reactions.Hittorf's early investigations were on the allotropes (different physical forms) of phosphorus and selenium. Between 1853 and 1859 his most important work was on ion movement caused by electric current. He measured the changes in the concentration of electrolyzed solutions, computed from these the transport numbers (relative carrying capacities) of many ions, and, in 1869, published his laws governing the migration of ions....
</Question>
<Choice>Hittorf, Johann Wilhelm</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American scientist who was a joint recipient of the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1961 for his investigations of protons and neutrons, which revealed the hitherto unknown structure of these particles. He shared the prize with Rudolf Ludwig Mössbauer of Germany.Hofstadter was educated at Princeton University, where he earned a Ph.D. in 1938. As a physicist at the National Bureau of Standards during World War II, he was instrumental in developing the proximity fuse, which was used to detonate anti-aircraft and other artillery shells. He joined the faculty of Princeton in 1946, where his principal s...
</Question>
<Choice>Hofstadter, Robert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch physicist, corecipient with Martinus J.G. Veltman of the 1999 Nobel Prize for Physics for their development of a mathematical model that enabled scientists to predict the properties of both the subatomic particles that constitute the universe and the fundamental forces through which they interact. Their work facilitated the finding of a new subatomic particle, the top quark.In 1972 't Hooft earned his doctorate in physics at the University of Utrecht and five years later became a professor there. He also was a visiting professor at numerous other institutions, including Duke and Boston u...
</Question>
<Choice>Hooft, Gerardus 't</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physicist who discovered the law of elasticity, known as Hooke's law, and who did research in a remarkable variety of fields.In 1655 Hooke was employed by Robert Boyle to construct the Boylean air pump. Five years later, Hooke discovered his law of elasticity, which states that the stretching of a solid body (e.g., metal, wood) is proportional to the force applied to it. The law laid the basis for studies of stress and strain and for understanding of elastic materials. He applied these studies in his designs for the balance springs of watches. In 1662 he was appointed curator of experi...
</Question>
<Choice>Hooke, Robert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British engineer and physicist who invented the three-wire system for electricity distribution and improved the design and efficiency of electric generators. In 1872 he became engineering manager of Chance Brothers and Company, a glass manufacturer in Birmingham, where he studied the problems of lighthouse illumination and advocated the use of flashing groups of lights for more efficient lighthouse operation.He also studied electrostatic storage capacity, the phenomenon of residual charge, and other problems arising from the electromagnetic theory of James Clerk Maxwell.Hopkinson set up a succ...
</Question>
<Choice>Hopkinson, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist who independently discovered the powder method of X-ray analysis of crystals, which permits the study of crystalline materials in a finely divided microcrystalline, or powder, state. He also invented a number of electron tubes that have found wide application as components in electronic circuits.After he received his Ph.D. from Yale University (1909) and had taught for a few years, Hull began work as a research physicist for General Electric Company (1914) and served (1928–50) as assistant director of its research laboratory in Schenectady.Hull devised the powder method in 1...
</Question>
<Choice>Hull, Albert Wallace</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist who in 1993 shared the Nobel Prize for Physics with his former teacher, the astrophysicist Joseph H. Taylor, Jr., for their joint discovery of the first binary pulsar.Hulse studied at Cooper Union College in New York City (B.S., 1970) and earned a Ph.D. degree in physics (1975) from the University of Massachusetts at Amherst, where he was a graduate student under Taylor. Using the large radio telescope at Arecibo, Puerto Rico, they discovered dozens of pulsars, which are rapidly spinning neutron stars that emit rapid, regular bursts of radio waves. Irregularities in the radi...
</Question>
<Choice>Hulse, Russell Alan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American atmospheric physicist who applied basic physical laws to explain the optical, electrical, acoustical, and thermal properties and phenomena of the atmosphere.Humphreys received his Ph.D. from Johns Hopkins University and, in 1905, after holding a number of teaching and research positions, began the affiliation with the U.S. Weather Bureau that lasted until his death. Much of his work, and indeed most of classical physical meteorology, is summarized in his Physics of the Air (1920).
</Question>
<Choice>Humphreys, William Jackson</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist known for his work on the electronic structure of atoms and molecules. He helped introduce the method of using molecular orbitals to determine the electronic structure of molecules and chemical bond formation.Hund taught and did research at German universities (Rostock, Leipzig, Jena, Frankfurt am Main, and Göttingen) exclusively, except for one year spent as a visiting lecturer at Harvard University. His publications include Einführung in die theoretische Physik, 5 vol. (1945–50; “Introduction to Theoretical Physics”), Theoretische Physik, 3 vol. (1956–63), Theorie des Aufbau...
</Question>
<Choice>Hund, Friedrich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch mathematician, astronomer, and physicist, who founded the wave theory of light, discovered the true shape of the rings of Saturn, and made original contributions to the science of dynamics—the study of the action of forces on bodies.Huygens was from a wealthy and distinguished middle-class family. His father, Constantijn Huygens, a diplomat, Latinist, and poet, was the friend and correspondent of many outstanding intellectual figures of the day, including the scientist and philosopher René Descartes. From an early age, Huygens showed a marked mechanical bent and a talent for drawing and...
</Question>
<Choice>Huygens, Christiaan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physicist and mathematician who was the first to propose that matter is continuously created throughout the universe. He made other innovations in astronomical theory but is perhaps best known as a writer of popular books about astronomy.Jeans taught at the University of Cambridge (1904–05, 1910–12) and at Princeton University (1905–09). In 1923 he became a research associate at Mt. Wilson Observatory, Pasadena, Calif., where he remained until 1944. In 1928, the year he was knighted, he proposed his continuous-creation theory.His work included investigations of spiral nebulae, the sour...
</Question>
<Choice>Jeans, Sir James</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist who shared half of the 1963 Nobel Prize for Physics with Maria Goeppert Mayer for their proposal of the shell nuclear model. (The other half of the prize was awarded to Eugene P. Wigner for unrelated work.)After obtaining his Ph.D. at the University of Hamburg in 1932, Jensen served on the faculties of Hamburg, the Institute of Technology in Hannover, and the University of Heidelberg. He and Mayer proposed the shell model independently of each other in 1949. The shell nuclear model holds that an atomic nucleus should be thought of not as a random aggregation of neutrons and pr...
</Question>
<Choice>Jensen, J. Hans D.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Irish geologist and physicist who, soon after 1898, estimated the age of the Earth at 100,000,000 years. He also developed a method for extracting radium (1914) and pioneered its use in cancer treatment.Joly was educated at Trinity College, Dublin, where he became professor of geology and mineralogy (1897) after having served as demonstrator in civil engineering (1883) and physics (1893). He first sought to estimate the age of the Earth from the salt content of the oceans, then from rocks containing radioactive zircon and alanite. He also tried to explain the formation of the Earth's crust by...
</Question>
<Choice>Joly, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German theoretical physicist who was one of the founders of quantum mechanics and quantum field theory.Jordan received a doctorate (1924) from the University of Göttingen, working with German physicists Max Born and James Franck on the problems of quantum theory. In 1925 Jordan published two seminal papers, one in collaboration with Born and German physicist Werner Heisenberg and one with just Born, that developed Heisenberg's initial idea of noncommutative variables into a formulation of quantum theory in terms of matrix mechanics—the first working version of quantum mechanics. In the followi...
</Question>
<Choice>Jordan, Pascual</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physicist whose discovery of the Josephson effect while a 22-year-old graduate student won him a share (with Leo Esaki and Ivar Giaever) of the 1973 Nobel Prize for Physics.He entered Trinity College, Cambridge, in pursuit of an education in physics and received his bachelor's (1960) and master's and Ph.D. degrees (1964) there, publishing his first work while still an undergraduate; it dealt with certain aspects of the special theory of relativity and the Mossbauer effect. He was elected a fellow of Trinity College in 1962. He was a brilliant and assured student; one former lecturer re...
</Question>
<Choice>Josephson, Brian D.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physicist who established that the various forms of energy—mechanical, electrical, and heat—are basically the same and can be changed, one into another. Thus he formed the basis of the law of conservation of energy, the first law of thermodynamics.Joule studied with the noted English chemist John Dalton at the University of Manchester in 1835. Describing “Joule's law” in a paper, On the Production of Heat by Voltaic Electricity (1840), he stated that the heat produced in a wire by an electric current is proportional to the product of the resistance of the wire and the square of the cur...
</Question>
<Choice>Joule, James Prescott</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch winner of the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1913 for his work on low-temperature physics and his production of liquid helium. He discovered superconductivity, the almost total lack of electrical resistance in certain materials when cooled to a temperature near absolute zero.From 1871 until 1873 Kamerlingh Onnes studied and worked at Heidelberg University, notably with the German physicists Robert Bunsen and Gustav Kirchhoff. Awarded a doctorate by the University of Groningen (1879), he taught at the Polytechnic School in Delft (1878–1882). From 1882 to 1923 he served as professor of experim...
</Question>
<Choice>Kamerlingh Onnes, Heike</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Soviet physicist who invented new machines for liquefaction of gases and in 1937 discovered the superfluidity of liquid helium. He was a corecipient of the 1978 Nobel Prize for Physics for his basic inventions and discoveries in the area of low-temperature physics.After a short military service in World War I, Kapitsa resumed his engineering education at the Petrograd Polytechnical Institute, turning to physics in the seminar of Abram Joffe. Before graduation in 1919, he started work at the Petrograd Physico-Technical Institute, a new research institution organized by Joffe after the Russian R...
</Question>
<Choice>Kapitsa, Pyotr Leonidovich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physicist who won the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1966 for his discovery and development of methods for observing Hertzian resonances within atoms.In 1920 Kastler went to Paris to study at the École Normale Supérieure. After serving on the science faculties at Bordeaux and Clermont-Ferrand in France and Leuven (Louvain) in Belgium, he returned to the École Normale Supérieure to teach (1941–68). He was professor and codirector of the laboratory of physics there at the time of the Nobel award. During his long and fruitful teaching career he trained an entire generation of French physicists...
</Question>
<Choice>Kastler, Alfred</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist who discovered the presence of helium in the Earth's atmosphere.Kayser's early research work was on the properties of sound. In collaboration with the physicist and mathematician Carl D.T. Runge, Kayser carefully mapped the spectra of a large number of elements and discovered the existence of series, or closely grouped spectral lines, the spacing and intensity of which vary in a regular manner. In 1883 they developed a mathematical formula that showed the relationship between these lines. About the same time, the Swedish physicist Johannes R. Rydberg used the data of other res...
</Question>
<Choice>Kayser, Heinrich Gustav Johannes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch physicist who specialized in cryogenics and was the first to solidify helium.Having taken his doctorate from the University of Amsterdam in 1904, Keesom worked under Heike Kamerlingh Onnes at the University of Leiden and then in 1917 joined the faculty of the Utrecht veterinary school. Six years later he returned to Leiden as professor of experimental physics. At the Onnes laboratory there in 1926, he successfully solidified helium. In 1932 he achieved the temperature of -457.6° F (-272° C), just two degrees Fahrenheit above absolute zero. His book Helium appeared in 1942.
</Question>
<Choice>Keesom, Willem Hendrik</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish engineer, mathematician, and physicist, who profoundly influenced the scientific thought of his generation.Thomson, who was knighted and raised to the peerage in recognition of his work in engineering and physics, was foremost among the small group of British scientists who helped to lay the foundations of modern physics. His contributions to science included a major role in the development of the second law of thermodynamics; the absolute temperature scale (measured in kelvins); the dynamical theory of heat; the mathematical analysis of electricity and magnetism, including the basic...
</Question>
<Choice>Kelvin, William Thomson, Baron</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American nuclear physicist who shared the 1990 Nobel Prize for Physics with Jerome Isaac Friedman and Richard E. Taylor for obtaining experimental evidence for the existence of the subatomic particles known as quarks.Kendall received his B.A. from Amherst College in 1950 and his Ph.D. from the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) in 1955. After serving as a U.S. National Science Foundation Fellow at MIT, he taught and pursued research at Stanford University (1956–61). In 1961 he joined the faculty of MIT, becoming a full professor in 1967.Kendall and his colleagues were cited by the Nob...
</Question>
<Choice>Kendall, Henry Way</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-born physicist who, with Eric A. Cornell and Carl E. Wieman, won the Nobel Prize for Physics in 2001 for creating a new ultracold state of matter, the so-called Bose-Einstein condensate (BEC).In 1986 Ketterle received a Ph.D. from the University of Munich and the Max Planck Institute for Quantum Optics in Garching, Germany. After postdoctoral work he joined the faculty at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) in 1993. He also served as a principal investigator with the Center for Ultracold Atoms, a joint research institution sponsored by MIT, Harvard University, and the Nation...
</Question>
<Choice>Ketterle, Wolfgang</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American engineer and one of the inventors of the integrated circuit, a system of interconnected transistors on a single microchip. In 2000 Kilby was a corecipient, with Herbert Kroemer and Zhores Alferov, of the Nobel Prize for Physics.
</Question>
<Choice>Kilby, Jack</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist who, with the chemist Robert Bunsen, firmly established the theory of spectrum analysis (a technique for chemical analysis by analyzing the light emitted by a heated material), which Kirchhoff applied to determine the composition of the Sun.In 1845 Kirchhoff first announced Kirchhoff's laws, which allow calculation of the currents, voltages, and resistances of electrical networks. Extending the theory of the German physicist Georg Simon Ohm, he generalized the equations describing current flow to the case of electrical conductors in three dimensions. In further studies he demo...
</Question>
<Choice>Kirchhoff, Gustav Robert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist who was awarded the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1985 for his discovery that under appropriate conditions the resistance offered by an electrical conductor is quantized; that is, it varies by discrete steps rather than smoothly and continuously.At the end of World War II, Klitzing was taken by his parents to live in West Germany. He attended the Technical University of Brunswick, graduating in 1969, and then earned a doctorate in physics at the University of Würzburg in 1972. In 1980 he became a professor at the Technical University of Munich, and in 1985 he became director of t...
</Question>
<Choice>Klitzing, Klaus von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist who investigated the properties of electrolytes (substances that conduct electricity in solutions by transfer of ions) and contributed to the understanding of their behaviour.Kohlrausch was a professor of physics at the universities of Göttingen (1866–70) and Darmstadt (1871–75), among other schools. In 1874 he demonstrated that an electrolyte has a definite and constant amount of electrical resistance. By observing the dependence of conductivity upon dilution, he could determine the transfer velocities of the ions (charged atoms or molecules) in solution. He later served as p...
</Question>
<Choice>Kohlrausch, Friedrich Wilhelm Georg</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian-born American physicist who, with John A. Pople, received the 1998 Nobel Prize in Chemistry. The award recognized their individual work on computations in quantum chemistry. Kohn's share of the prize acknowledged his development of the density-functional theory, which made it possible to apply the complicated mathematics of quantum mechanics to the description and analysis of the chemical bonding between atoms.Having emigrated from his native Austria, Kohn received a master's degree from the University of Toronto (Ontario, Canada) in 1946. He earned a Ph.D. in physics from Harvard Uni...
</Question>
<Choice>Kohn, Walter</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese physicist who, with Raymond Davis, Jr., won the Nobel Prize for Physics in 2002 for their detection of neutrinos. Riccardo Giacconi also won a share of the award for his work on the cosmic sources of X rays.Koshiba earned a Ph.D. from the University of Rochester in New York in 1955. He then joined the University of Tokyo, where he became professor in 1960 and emeritus professor in 1987. From 1987 to 1997 Koshiba taught at Tokai University.Koshiba's award-winning work centred on neutrinos, subatomic particles that had long perplexed scientists. Since the 1920s it had been suspected tha...
</Question>
<Choice>Koshiba Masatoshi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch physicist who, with Ralph de Laer Kronig, derived important equations relating the absorption to the dispersion of light. He also predicted (1924) the existence of the Raman effect, an inelastic scattering of light, and showed (1927) that the complex form of the mathematical functions in dispersion theory, concerning collisions of subatomic particles, results from the inability of a signal to be propagated faster than the speed of light.Kramers' research on X rays resulted in his development of equations to determine the efficiency and intensity of X-ray production.
</Question>
<Choice>Kramers, Hendrik Anthony</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-born physicist who, with Zhores Alferov and Jack S. Kilby, was awarded the 2000 Nobel Prize for Physics for their work that laid the foundation for the modern era of microchips, computers, and information technology.After receiving a Ph.D. (1952) from Georg August University in Göttingen, Germany, Kroemer worked in the United States at RCA Laboratories (1954–57) in Princeton, New Jersey, and at Varian Associates (1959–66) in Palo Alto, California. In 1968 he became professor of electrical engineering at the University of Colorado at Boulder, and in 1976 he joined the faculty of the Univ...
</Question>
<Choice>Kroemer, Herbert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist who developed a method for determining the velocity of sound in gases and solids.Kundt studied at the University of Leipzig but afterward went to the University of Berlin. In 1867 he became an instructor at Berlin, and in the following year he became professor of physics at the Zürich Polytechnic. In 1872 he was called to Strasbourg, where he was one of the founders of that city's Physical Institute. In 1888 he succeeded to the chair of experimental physics and the directorship of the Berlin Physical Institute. In his experiments on sound, Kundt dusted the interior of a tube w...
</Question>
<Choice>Kundt, August Adolph Eduard Eberhard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Soviet nuclear physicist who guided the development of his country's first atomic bomb, first practical thermonuclear bomb, and first nuclear reactor.Kurchatov's father was a surveyor and his mother a teacher. In 1912 the family moved to Simferopol in the Crimea. In 1920 Kurchatov entered Simferopol State University, from which he graduated three years later with a degree in physics. In 1925 he was invited to join A.F. Ioffe's Physico-Technical Institute of the Soviet Academy of Sciences in Leningrad (now St. Petersburg). Kurchatov's initial studies concerned what is now called ferroelectricit...
</Question>
<Choice>Kurchatov, Igor Vasilyevich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-American physicist who, with Willis E. Lamb, Jr., was awarded the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1955 for his accurate determination that the magnetic moment of the electron is greater than its theoretical value, thus leading to reconsideration of and innovations in quantum electrodynamics.Kusch was brought to the United States in 1912 and became a citizen in 1922. In 1937, at Columbia University, he worked with the physicist Isidor I. Rabi on studies of the effects of magnetic fields on beams of atoms. He spent the wartime years in research on radar and returned to Columbia in 1946 as prof...
</Question>
<Choice>Kusch, Polykarp</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss physicist who was one of the founders of the electrochemical theory of batteries.La Rive was elected to the chair of natural philosophy at the Academy of Geneva in 1823, and for the next seven years he conducted studies on the specific heat of various gases and the temperature of the Earth's crust. His experiments in 1836 on the voltaic cell, an early type of battery, furthered the development of electrical theory. He shared the view of the English physicist Michael Faraday that voltaic electricity was caused by chemical action. In 1840 he invented the process for electroplating gold ont...
</Question>
<Choice>La Rive, Auguste-Arthur de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist and corecipient, with Polykarp Kusch, of the 1955 Nobel Prize for Physics for experimental work that spurred refinements in the quantum theories of electromagnetic phenomena.Lamb joined the faculty of Columbia University, New York City, in 1938 and worked in the Radiation Laboratory there during World War II. Though the quantum mechanics of P.A.M. Dirac had predicted the hyperfine structure of the lines that appear in the spectrum (dispersed light, as by a prism), Lamb applied new methods to measure the lines and in 1947 found their positions to be slightly different from wh...
</Question>
<Choice>Lamb, Willis Eugene, Jr.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss German mathematician, astronomer, physicist, and philosopher who provided the first rigorous proof that p (the ratio of a circle's circumference to its diameter) is irrational, meaning that it cannot be expressed as the quotient of two integers.Lambert, the son of a tailor, was largely self-educated and early in his life began geometric and astronomical investigations by means of instruments he designed and built himself. He worked for a time as a bookkeeper, secretary, and editor. As a private tutor in 1748, he gained access to a good library, which he used for self-improvement until 17...
</Question>
<Choice>Lambert, Johann Heinrich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American inventor and physicist whose one-step process for developing and printing photographs culminated in a revolution in photography unparalleled since the advent of roll film.While a student at Harvard University, Land became interested in polarized light, i.e., light in which all rays are aligned in the same plane. He took a leave of absence, and, after intensive study and experimentation, succeeded (1932) in aligning submicroscopic crystals of iodoquinine sulfate and embedding them in a sheet of plastic. The resulting polarizer, for which he envisioned numerous uses and which he dubbed...
</Question>
<Choice>Land, Edwin Herbert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Soviet theoretical physicist, one of the founders of the quantum theory of condensed matter whose pioneering research in this field was recognized with the 1962 Nobel Prize for Physics.Landau was a mathematical prodigy and enfant terrible. His schooling reflected the zigzags of radical educational reforms during the turbulent period following the Russian Revolution of 1917. Like many scientists of the first Soviet generation, Landau did not formally complete some educational stages, such as high school. He never wrote a doctoral thesis either, as academic degrees had been abolished and were no...
</Question>
<Choice>Landau, Lev Davidovich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astrophysicist and aeronautical pioneer who developed new instruments with which to study the Sun and built the first powered heavier-than-air machine of significant size to achieve sustained flight.Following his education at the Boston Latin School, Langley worked as an engineer and architectural draftsman before traveling to Europe in 1864. Following his return in 1866, he was appointed an assistant professor of mathematics at the U.S. Naval Academy in Annapolis, Md. The next year he accepted a position as a professor of physics and astronomy at the Western University of Pennsylvani...
</Question>
<Choice>Langley, Samuel Pierpont</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician, astronomer, and physicist who is best known for his investigations into the stability of the solar system.Laplace successfully accounted for all the observed deviations of the planets from their theoretical orbits by applying Sir Isaac Newton's theory of gravitation to the solar system, and he developed a conceptual view of evolutionary change in the structure of the solar system. He also demonstrated the usefulness of probability for interpreting scientific data.Laplace was the son of a peasant farmer. Little is known of his early life except that he quickly showed his m...
</Question>
<Choice>Laplace, Pierre-Simon, marquis de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Irish physicist, the first to calculate the rate at which energy is radiated by an accelerated electron, and the first to explain the splitting of spectrum lines by a magnetic field. His theories were based on the belief that matter consists entirely of electric particles moving in the ether.Educated in Belfast and at Cambridge, Larmor taught at Queen's College, Galway (1880–85), and at Cambridge (1885–1932). Knighted in 1909, he represented his university in the British Parliament from 1911 to 1922.
</Question>
<Choice>Larmor, Sir Joseph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Brazilian physicist who, with American physicist Eugene Gardner at the University of California, Berkeley, in 1948 confirmed the existence of heavy and light mesons formed during the bombardment of carbon nuclei with alpha particles.Lattes studied at the University of São Paulo with Giuseppe Occhialini in the 1940s and accompanied him in 1946 to the University of Bristol, where with Cecil Frank Powell they demonstrated that the two types of mesons could be identified by tracks left on photographic plates exposed to cosmic rays atop a mountain in the Bolivian Andes. Lattes became a full profess...
</Question>
<Choice>Lattes, C. M. G.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German recipient of the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1914 for his discovery of the diffraction of X rays in crystals. This enabled scientists to study the structure of crystals and hence marked the origin of solid-state physics, an important field in the development of modern electronics.Laue became professor of physics at the University of Zürich in 1912. Laue was the first to suggest the use of a crystal to act as a grating for the diffraction of X rays, showing that if a beam of X rays passed through a crystal, diffraction would take place and a pattern would be formed on a photographic plate...
</Question>
<Choice>Laue, Max von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist who, with Daniel C. Tsui and Horst Störmer, received the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1998 for the discovery that electrons in an extremely powerful magnetic field can form a quantum fluid in which “portions” of electrons can be identified. This effect is known as the fractional quantum Hall effect.Laughlin graduated from the University of California at Berkeley in 1972 and earned a Ph.D. in physics from the Massachusetts Institute of Technology in 1979. He conducted research at Bell Laboratories, Murray Hill, New Jersey (1979–81) and at the Lawrence Livermore National Laborat...
</Question>
<Choice>Laughlin, Robert B.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist, winner of the 1939 Nobel Prize for Physics for his invention of the cyclotron, the first particle accelerator to achieve high energies.Lawrence earned his Ph.D. at Yale University in 1925. An assistant professor of physics at Yale (1927–28), he went to the University of California, Berkeley, as an associate professor and became full professor there in 1930.Lawrence first conceived the idea for the cyclotron in 1929. One of his students, M. Stanley Livingston, undertook the project and succeeded in building a device that accelerated hydrogen ions (protons) to an energy of 13...
</Question>
<Choice>Lawrence, Ernest Orlando</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Soviet physicist and biophysicist known for his physicochemical theory of the movement of ions and the consequent theory of excitation in living matter, which attempts to explain sensation, muscular contraction, and the functions of the central nervous system.Educated in medicine, mathematics, and physics at the University of Moscow (1903), Lazarev did scientific research at Strasbourg and in 1907 was appointed privatdocent (unsalaried lecturer) in physics and assistant to Pyotr N. Lebedev at the University of Moscow. In 1912 he became professor at the Moscow Imperial Technical School and from...
</Question>
<Choice>Lazarev, Pyotr Petrovich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian physicist who experimentally proved that light exerts a mechanical pressure on material bodies.Lebedev received his doctorate (1891) from the University of Strasburg in Germany. The next year he began teaching physics at Moscow State University and was appointed a professor there in 1900, after defending a dissertation for the Russian advanced doctorate. In 1895 he generated electromagnetic radiation with a wavelength of a few millimetres. In a virtuoso experiment of 1899, Lebedev managed to register directly the pressure of light radiation upon a metallic foil, confirming a prediction...
</Question>
<Choice>Lebedev, Pyotr Nikolayevich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist who, along with Melvin Schwartz and Jack Steinberger, received the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1988 for their joint research on neutrinos.Lederman was educated at the City College of New York (B.S., 1943) and received his Ph.D. in physics from Columbia University, New York City, in 1951. He joined the faculty at Columbia that same year and became a full professor there in 1958. He was director of the Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory in Batavia, Ill., from 1979 to 1989.From 1960 to 1962, Lederman, together with his fellow Columbia University researchers Schwartz and Stein...
</Question>
<Choice>Lederman, Leon Max</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist who, with Robert C. Richardson and Douglas D. Osheroff, was awarded the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1996 for their joint discovery of superfluidity in the isotope helium-3.Lee received a bachelor's degree from Harvard University in 1952 and a Ph.D. in physics from Yale University in 1959. He joined the faculty of Cornell University (Ithaca, N.Y.) in 1959, becoming a full professor there in 1968. Lee and Richardson built a special cooling apparatus for their research in the low-temperature laboratory at Cornell. They discovered superfluidity in helium-3 by accident in 1972. Th...
</Question>
<Choice>Lee, David M.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese-born American physicist who, with Chen Ning Yang, received the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1957 for work in discovering violations of the principle of parity conservation (the quality of space reflection symmetry of subatomic particle interactions), thus bringing about major refinements in particle physics theory.In 1946 Lee was awarded a scholarship to study in the United States, and, although he had no undergraduate degree, he entered the graduate school in physics at the University of Chicago, where Enrico Fermi selected him as a doctoral student. After working briefly at the Univers...
</Question>
<Choice>Lee, Tsung-Dao</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physicist, who won the Nobel Prize for Physics in 2003 for his seminal work on superfluidity. He shared the award with the Russian physicists Alexey A. Abrikosov and Vitaly L. Ginzburg.Leggett received a Ph.D. in physics from the University of Oxford in 1964. In 1967 he joined the faculty of the University of Sussex, where he served until 1983, when he moved to the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign.Leggett conducted his pioneering research on superfluidity, a phenomenon in which certain extremely cold liquid substances flow without internal resistance, or viscosity. Superfluid...
</Question>
<Choice>Leggett, Anthony J.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist and recipient of the 1905 Nobel Prize for Physics for his research on cathode rays and the discovery of many of their properties. His results had important implications for the development of electronics and nuclear physics.After working as a lecturer and as an assistant to Heinrich Hertz at the University of Bonn in 1893, Lenard became a professor of physics successively at the universities of Breslau (1894), Aachen (1895), Heidelberg (1896), and Kiel (1898). In 1907 he returned to teach at the University of Heidelberg, where he stayed until his retirement in 1931.Applying th...
</Question>
<Choice>Lenard, Philipp</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist, satirist, and writer of aphorisms, best known for his ridicule of metaphysical and romantic excesses.Lichtenberg was the 17th child of a Protestant pastor, who taught him mathematics and natural sciences. In 1763 he entered Göttingen University, where in 1770 he became assistant professor of physics and in 1775 professor. This post he held until his death. Lichtenberg did research in a wide variety of fields—including geophysics, volcanology, meteorology, chemistry, astronomy, and mathematics—but most important were his investigations into physics. Notably, he constructed a h...
</Question>
<Choice>Lichtenberg, Georg Christoph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physicist who received the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1908 for producing the first colour photographic plate. He was known for the innovations that resulted from his search for a direct colour-sensitive medium in photography.Though born of French parents in Luxembourg, Lippmann grew up in Paris and was a bright but unruly student. Despite the fact that he never received his teacher's certificate, he was appointed professor of mathematical physics at the Sorbonne in 1883. He later was appointed head of the Sorbonne's Laboratories of Physical Research (1886).Lippmann's scientific talents...
</Question>
<Choice>Lippmann, Gabriel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physicist who perfected the coherer, a radio-wave detector and the heart of the early radiotelegraph receiver.Lodge became assistant professor of applied mathematics at University College, London, in 1879 and was appointed to the chair of physics at University College, Liverpool, in 1881. During his tenure in Liverpool, he conducted experiments in the propagation and reception of electromagnetic waves. In 1890 a French physicist, Édouard Branly, showed that loose iron filings in a glass tube coalesce, or “cohere,” under the influence of radiated electric waves. To this basic design Lod...
</Question>
<Choice>Lodge, Sir Oliver Joseph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian poet, scientist, and grammarian who is often considered the first great Russian linguistic reformer. He also made substantial contributions to the natural sciences, reorganized the St. Petersburg Imperial Academy of Sciences, established in Moscow the university that today bears his name, and created the first coloured glass mosaics in Russia.Lomonosov was the son of a poor fisherman. At the age of 10 he too took up that line of work. When the few books he was able to obtain could no longer satisfy his growing thirst for knowledge, in December 1730, he left his native village, penniles...
</Question>
<Choice>Lomonosov, Mikhail Vasilyevich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German American physicist who did pioneering work in quantum chemistry and on macroscopic quantum phenomena of superconductivity and superfluidity.London received his doctorate in philosophy (1921) from the University of Munich before switching in 1925 to study theoretical physics with Arnold Sommerfeld. He subsequently worked with Erwin Schrödinger at the University of Zürich and at the University of Berlin, where, as a Jew, he was dismissed from lecturing after the Nazis came to power in 1933. After several years at the University of Oxford in England and the Institut Henri Poincaré in Paris...
</Question>
<Choice>London, Fritz Wolfgang</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch physicist and joint winner (with Pieter Zeeman) of the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1902 for his theory of electromagnetic radiation, which, confirmed by findings of Zeeman, gave rise to Albert Einstein's special theory of relativity.In his doctoral thesis at the University of Leiden (1875), Lorentz refined the electromagnetic theory of James C. Maxwell of England so that it more satisfactorily explained the reflection and refraction of light. He was appointed professor of mathematical physics at Leiden in 1878. His work in physics was wide in scope, but his central aim was to construct a...
</Question>
<Choice>Lorentz, Hendrik Antoon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian physicist and philosopher who established important principles of optics, mechanics, and wave dynamics and who supported the view that all knowledge is a conceptual organization of the data of sensory experience (or observation).Mach was educated at home until the age of 14, then went briefly to gymnasium (high school) before entering the University of Vienna at 17. He received his doctorate in physics in 1860 and taught mechanics and physics in Vienna until 1864, when he became professor of mathematics at the University of Graz. Mach's interests had already begun to turn to the psych...
</Question>
<Choice>Mach, Ernst</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist, who constructed the first laser, a device that produces monochromatic coherent light, or light in which the rays are all of the same wavelength and phase. The laser has found numerous practical uses, ranging from delicate surgery to measuring the distance between the Earth and the Moon.After receiving a Ph.D. from Stanford University in 1955, Maiman accepted a position with the Hughes Research Laboratories (now HRL Laboratories, LLC), where he became interested in a device developed and built by Charles H. Townes and colleagues and known as a maser (acronym for “microwave [...
</Question>
<Choice>Maiman, Theodore H.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physicist who discovered that light, when reflected, becomes partially plane polarized; i.e., its rays vibrate in the same plane. His observation led to a better understanding of the propagation of light.A member of the corps of engineers, Malus accompanied Napoleon's invasion of Egypt in 1798 and remained in the Near East until 1801. After he returned, he held official posts at Antwerp, Strasbourg, and Paris and did research in optics. He published a paper in 1809 on his discovery of the polarization of light by reflection and a memoir in 1810 on the theory of double refraction (bendin...
</Question>
<Choice>Malus, Etienne-Louis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physicist who, with American chemist Paul Lauterbur, won the 2003 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for the development of magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), a computerized scanning technology that produces images of internal body structures, especially those comprising soft tissues.Mansfield received a Ph.D. in physics from the University of London in 1962. Following two years as a research associate in the United States, he joined the faculty of the University of Nottingham, where he became professor in 1979. Mansfield was knighted in 1993.Mansfield's prize-winning work expanded...
</Question>
<Choice>Mansfield, Sir Peter</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian physicist and inventor of a successful wireless telegraph (1896). In 1909 he received the Nobel Prize for Physics, which he shared with German physicist Ferdinand Braun. He later worked on the development of shortwave wireless communication, which constitutes the basis of nearly all modern long-distance radio.
</Question>
<Choice>Marconi, Guglielmo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physicist and plant physiologist who, independent of Robert Boyle, discovered the law that states that the volume of a gas varies inversely with its pressure. Although widely known as Boyle's law, this basic tenet of physics and chemistry is called Mariotte's law in France.Mariotte, a Roman Catholic priest and prior of Saint-Martin-sous-Beaune, was in 1666 one of the founding members of the Academy of Sciences, in Paris. In his Discours de la nature de l'air (1676; “Discourse on the Nature of Air”), in which he coined the word barometer, Mariotte stated Boyle's law and went further by n...
</Question>
<Choice>Mariotte, Edme</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist and engineer, coinventor in 1946, with John P. Eckert, of the Electronic Numerical Integrator and Computer (ENIAC), the first general-purpose electronic computer.After completing his education, Mauchly entered the teaching profession, eventually becoming an associate professor of electrical engineering at the University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia. During World War II Mauchly and Eckert, a graduate engineer, were asked to devise ways to accelerate the recomputation of artillery firing tables for the U.S. Army. They accordingly proposed the construction of a general-purpose...
</Question>
<Choice>Mauchly, John W.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish physicist best known for his formulation of electromagnetic theory. He is regarded by most modern physicists as the scientist of the 19th century who had the greatest influence on 20th-century physics, and he is ranked with Sir Isaac Newton and Albert Einstein for the fundamental nature of his contributions. In 1931, on the 100th anniversary of Maxwell's birth, Einstein described the change in the conception of reality in physics that resulted from Maxwell's work as “the most profound and the most fruitful that physics has experienced since the time of Newton.”The concept of electroma...
</Question>
<Choice>Maxwell, James Clerk</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-born American physicist who shared one-half of the 1963 Nobel Prize for Physics with J. Hans D. Jensen of West Germany for their proposal of the shell nuclear model. (The other half of the prize was awarded to Eugene P. Wigner of the United States for unrelated work.)Maria Goeppert studied physics at the University of Göttingen (Ph.D., 1930) under a committee of three Nobel Prize winners. In 1930 she married the American chemical physicist Joseph E. Mayer, and a short time later she accompanied him to Johns Hopkins University in Baltimore, Maryland. Over the next nine years she was asso...
</Question>
<Choice>Mayer, Maria Goeppert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American nuclear physicist who shared the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1951 with Glenn T. Seaborg for his discovery of element 93, neptunium, the first element heavier than uranium, thus called a transuranium element.McMillan was educated at the California Institute of Technology and at Princeton University, where he earned a Ph.D. in 1932. He then joined the faculty of the University of California, Berkeley, and became a full professor in 1946 and director of the Lawrence Radiation Laboratory in 1958. He retired in 1973.While studying nuclear fission, McMillan discovered neptunium, a decay pr...
</Question>
<Choice>McMillan, Edwin Mattison</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch physical engineer who in 1984, with Carlo Rubbia, received the Nobel Prize for Physics for his contribution to the discovery of the massive, short-lived subatomic particles designated W and Z that were crucial to the unified electroweak theory posited in the 1970s by Steven Weinberg, Abdus Salam, and Sheldon Glashow.After receiving a degree in physical engineering from the Higher Technical School in Delft, Neth., in 1952, van der Meer worked for the Philips Company. In 1956 he joined the staff of CERN (the European Organization for Nuclear Research), near Geneva, where he remained until...
</Question>
<Choice>Meer, Simon van der</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian-born physicist who shared the Enrico Fermi Award (1966) with the chemists Otto Hahn and Fritz Strassmann for their joint research that led to the discovery of uranium fission.After receiving her doctorate at the University of Vienna (1906), Meitner attended Max Planck's lectures at Berlin in 1907 and joined Hahn in research on radioactivity. During three decades of association, she and Hahn were among the first to isolate the isotope protactinium-231 (which they called protactinium), studied nuclear isomerism and beta decay, and in the 1930s (along with Strassmann) investigated the pr...
</Question>
<Choice>Meitner, Lise</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist and meteorologist, the first to propose the use of a ring pendulum for measuring absolute gravity.Mendenhall was a professor at Ohio State University, Columbus, in 1873–78 and from 1881 until he was named professor emeritus in 1884, when he became a professor for the U.S. Signal Corps. In 1878–81 he was a visiting professor at the Tokyo Imperial University, where he helped develop the Japanese government's meteorological system, and in 1889 he was appointed superintendent of the U.S. Coast and Geodetic Survey; he served as president of the Worcester (Mass.) Polytechnic Insti...
</Question>
<Choice>Mendenhall, Thomas Corwin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-born American physicist who established the speed of light as a fundamental constant and pursued other spectroscopic and metrological investigations. He received the 1907 Nobel Prize for Physics.Michelson came to the United States with his parents when he was two years old. From New York City, the family made its way to Virginia City, Nev., and San Francisco, where the elder Michelson prospered as a merchant. At 17, Michelson entered the United States Naval Academy at Annapolis, Md., where he did well in science but was rather below average in seamanship. He graduated in 1873, then serv...
</Question>
<Choice>Michelson, A. A.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist honoured with the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1923 for his study of the elementary electronic charge and the photoelectric effect.Millikan graduated from Oberlin College (Oberlin, Ohio) in 1891 and obtained his doctorate at Columbia University in 1895. In 1896 he became an assistant at the University of Chicago, where he became a full professor in 1910.In 1909 Millikan began a series of experiments to determine the electric charge carried by a single electron. He began by measuring the course of charged water droplets in an electrical field. The results suggested that the cha...
</Question>
<Choice>Millikan, Robert Andrews</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Flemish astronomer and solar physicist who pioneered in solar spectrophotometry and showed how such a technique could reveal much about the structure of the Sun's outer layers.Minnaert was first a botanist, but his desire to understand more fully the effect of light on plants led him to study physics at the University of Leiden, in The Netherlands. Exiled from Belgium for his support of the nationalist Flemish movement before and during World War I, he became a staff member of the solar observatory at Utrecht in 1921.After the invention of the microphotometer about 1920, Minnaert undertook the...
</Question>
<Choice>Minnaert, Marcel Gilles Jozef</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician who invented descriptive geometry, the study of the mathematical principles of representing three-dimensional objects in a two-dimensional plane; no longer an active discipline in mathematics, the subject is part of mechanical and architectural drawing. He was a prominent figure during the French Revolution, helping to establish the metric system and the École Polytechnique. He was made a count in 1808 by Napoleon I.Monge was educated at the Oratorian schools at Beaune and at Lyon, where for a time at age 16 he was a physics teacher. He made a large-scale plan of Beaune du...
</Question>
<Choice>Monge, Gaspard, comte de Peluse</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physicist who experimentally demonstrated that the major properties of an element are determined by the atomic number, not by the atomic weight, and firmly established the relationship between atomic number and the charge of the atomic nucleus.Educated at Trinity College, Oxford, Moseley in 1910 was appointed lecturer in physics at Ernest (later Lord) Rutherford's laboratory at the University of Manchester, where he worked until the outbreak of World War I, when he entered the army. His first researches were concerned with radioactivity and beta radiation in radium. He then turned to t...
</Question>
<Choice>Moseley, Henry Gwyn Jeffreys</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist and winner, with Robert Hofstadter of the United States, of the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1961 for his discovery of the Mössbauer effect.Mössbauer discovered the effect in 1957, one year before he received his doctorate from the Technical Academy of Munich. Under normal conditions, atomic nuclei recoil when they emit gamma rays, and the wavelength of the emission varies with the amount of recoil. Mössbauer found that at a low temperature, a nucleus can be embedded in a crystal lattice that absorbs its recoil. The discovery of the Mössbauer effect made it possible to produce g...
</Question>
<Choice>Mossbauer, Rudolf Ludwig</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physicist who shared (with P.W. Anderson and J.H. Van Vleck of the United States) the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1977 for his independent researches on the magnetic and electrical properties of noncrystalline, or amorphous, semiconductors.Mott earned bachelor's (1927) and master's (1930) degrees at the University of Cambridge. He became a professor of theoretical physics at the University of Bristol in 1933. At Bristol his work in solid-state physics included studies of metals and metal alloys, semiconductors, and photographic emulsions. In 1938 Mott devised the theoretical description...
</Question>
<Choice>Mott, Sir Nevill F.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American-Danish physicist who shared the 1975 Nobel Prize for Physics with Aage N. Bohr and James Rainwater for his work in determining the asymmetrical shapes of certain atomic nuclei and the reasons behind such asymmetries.Having taken his doctorate in theoretical physics at Harvard University in 1950, Mottelson accepted a fellowship at the Niels Bohr Institute of Theoretical Physics in Copenhagen and then joined the faculty of the Nordic Institute for Theoretical Nuclear Physics there; he subsequently became a naturalized Danish citizen.From experiments conducted in collaboration with Bohr...
</Question>
<Choice>Mottelson, Ben R.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-U.S. physicist who originated field emission microscopy. Besides working on solid surface phenomena and gas discharge, Müller studied field electron and field ion emissions, inventing the field emission microscope (1937) and the field ion microscope (1956) which for the first time made it possible to take pictures of individual atoms.A research physicist for certain German firms (1935–45), he joined the Kaiser Wilhelm Institute for Physical Chemistry in Göttingen and then the Free University of Berlin. He finally (1951) went to the United States, becoming professor of physics at Pennsyl...
</Question>
<Choice>Muller, Erwin Wilhelm</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss physicist who, along with J. Georg Bednorz, was awarded the 1987 Nobel Prize for Physics for their joint discovery of superconductivity in certain substances at higher temperatures than had previously been thought attainable.Müller received his doctorate from the Swiss Federal Institute of Technology in 1958, and beginning in 1963 he performed research in solid-state physics at the IBM Zürich Research Laboratory, heading the physics department there for several years and becoming an IBM fellow in 1982.A specialist in the ceramic compounds known as oxides, Müller in the early 1980s began...
</Question>
<Choice>Muller, Karl Alex</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American chemist and physicist who received the 1966 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for “fundamental work concerning chemical bonds and the electronic structure of molecules.”A graduate of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Mulliken worked, during World War I and for a few years afterward, in government chemical research. He then studied under the physicist Robert A. Millikan at the University of Chicago, receiving his Ph.D. in 1921. He taught at New York University (1926–28) and then joined the faculty of the University of Chicago (1928–85).Mulliken began working on his theory of molecular...
</Question>
<Choice>Mulliken, Robert Sanderson</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physicist who was corecipient, with the Swedish astrophysicist Hannes Alfvén, of the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1970 for his pioneering studies of the magnetic properties of solids. His contributions to solid-state physics have found numerous useful applications, particularly in the development of improved computer memory units.Néel attended the École Normale Supérieure in Paris and the University of Strasbourg (Ph.D., 1932), where he studied under Pierre-Ernest Weiss and first began researching magnetism. He was a professor at the universities of Strasbourg (1937–45) and Grenoble (1945...
</Question>
<Choice>Neel, Louis-Eugene-Felix</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist, winner with Bert Sakmann in 1991 of the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for their research into basic cell function and for the development of the patch-clamp technique, a laboratory method that can detect the very small electrical currents produced by the passage of ions through the cell membrane.Neher earned a degree in physics from the Technical University of Munich and then attended the University of Wisconsin at Madison, where he obtained a master of science degree in 1967. From 1968 to 1972 Neher did graduate work and postdoctoral work at the Max Planck Institute...
</Question>
<Choice>Neher, Erwin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physicist and mathematician, who was the culminating figure of the scientific revolution of the 17th century. In optics, his discovery of the composition of white light integrated the phenomena of colours into the science of light and laid the foundation for modern physical optics. In mechanics, his three laws of motion, the basic principles of modern physics, resulted in the formulation of the law of universal gravitation. In mathematics, he was the original discoverer of the infinitesimal calculus. Newton's Philosophiae Naturalis Principia Mathematica (Mathematical Principles of Natu...
</Question>
<Choice>Newton, Sir Isaac</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish physicist and gunnery expert, considered a founder of the science of ballistics. His pioneering research on fired gunpowder, often in conjunction with the British chemist Frederick Abel, contributed greatly to the progress of gunnery.Noble was educated at Edinburgh Academy and the Royal Military Academy, Woolwich, London, and then entered the Royal Artillery in 1849. During the 1850s, in a study of the relative merits of smoothbore and rifled cannon, he devised a method of comparing their accuracy of fire. He became assistant inspector of artillery in 1859 but later left the service t...
</Question>
<Choice>Noble, Sir Andrew, 1st Baronet</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist and electrical and communications engineer, a prolific inventor who made fundamental theoretical and practical contributions to telecommunications.Nyquist moved to the United States in 1907. He earned a B.S. (1914) and an M.S. (1915) in electrical engineering from the University of North Dakota. In 1917, after earning a Ph.D. in physics from Yale University, he joined the American Telephone and Telegraph Company (AT&amp;T). There he remained until his retirement in 1954, working in the research department and then (from 1934) at Bell Laboratories. Nyquist continued to serve...
</Question>
<Choice>Nyquist, Harry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist who discovered the law, named after him, which states that the current flow through a conductor is directly proportional to the potential difference (voltage) and inversely proportional to the resistance.Ohm became professor of mathematics at the Jesuits' College at Cologne in 1817. The most important aspect of Ohm's law is summarized in his pamphlet Die galvanische Kette, mathematisch bearbeitet (1827; The Galvanic Circuit Investigated Mathematically). While his work greatly influenced the theory and applications of current electricity, it was so coldly received that Ohm resi...
</Question>
<Choice>Ohm, Georg Simon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Australian physicist (b. Oct. 8, 1901, Adelaide, Australia—d. July 14, 2000, Canberra, Australia), was an esteemed specialist in high-energy physics at the University of Cambridge's Cavendish Laboratory, where he had won a scholarship in 1927. Oliphant was also Poynting Professor of Physics at the University of Birmingham, Eng. (1937–50), and a co-discoverer (1934) of tritium with Ernest Rutherford and Paul Harteck, and he directed the team (1939) that developed the cavity magnetron used in advanced microwave radar. Having been a member of the British team that split the atom in 1932, he went...
</Question>
<Choice>Oliphant, Sir Mark</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist who invented the colliding-beam storage ring and was a leading advocate of space colonization.Having studied physics at Swarthmore College in Pennsylvania (A.B., 1950) and at Cornell University in New York state (Ph.D., 1954), O'Neill joined the faculty of Princeton University and soon began experimenting with ways to increase the energy output of particle accelerators. His solution, the colliding-beam storage ring, utilized beams of particles moving through a ring-shaped chamber in opposite directions. With Wolfgang Panofsky of Stanford University in California, he construc...
</Question>
<Choice>O'Neill, Gerard K.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American theoretical physicist and science administrator, noted as director of the Los Alamos laboratory during development of the atomic bomb (1943–45) and as director of the Institute for Advanced Study, Princeton (1947–66). Accusations of disloyalty led to a government hearing that resulted in the loss of his security clearance and of his position as adviser to the highest echelons of the U.S. government. The case became a cause célèbre in the world of science because of its implications concerning political and moral issues relating to the role of scientists in government.Oppenheimer was t...
</Question>
<Choice>Oppenheimer, J. Robert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Danish physicist and chemist who discovered that electric current in a wire can deflect a magnetized compass needle, a phenomenon the importance of which was rapidly recognized and which inspired the development of electromagnetic theory.In 1806 Ørsted became a professor at the University of Copenhagen, where his first physical researches dealt with electric currents and acoustics. During an evening lecture in April 1820, Ørsted discovered that a magnetic needle aligns itself perpendicularly to a current-carrying wire, definite experimental evidence of the relationship between electricity and...
</Question>
<Choice>Orsted, Hans Christian</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist who, along with David Lee and Robert Richardson, was the corecipient of the 1996 Nobel Prize for Physics for their discovery of superfluidity in the isotope helium-3.Osheroff received a bachelor's degree (1967) from the California Institute of Technology and a doctorate (1973) from Cornell University in Ithaca, N.Y. He was a graduate student working with Lee and Richardson in the low-temperature laboratory at Cornell when the team made its discovery in 1972. The team was investigating the properties of helium-3 under temperatures of just a few thousandths of a degree above a...
</Question>
<Choice>Osheroff, Douglas D.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist known as the “father” of U.S. radar.Page changed his major from theology to physics in his senior year at Hamline University in St. Paul, Minnesota. After graduating in 1927, he moved to Washington, D.C., where he joined the U.S. Naval Research Laboratory (NRL) and attended George Washington University (M.A., 1932). In 1934 he began work on developing pulse radar. In spite of its receiving low priority and limited support from the U.S. Navy administration, he successfully demonstrated a radar in 1936 and tested it at sea in 1937. By the time the United States entered World W...
</Question>
<Choice>Page, Robert Morris</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French-born British physicist who invented the pressure cooker and suggested the first cylinder and piston steam engine. Though his design was not practical, it was improved by others and led to the development of the steam engine, a major contribution to the Industrial Revolution.Papin assisted the Dutch physicist Christiaan Huygens with his air-pump experiments and went to London in 1675 to work with the English physicist Robert Boyle. In 1679 Papin invented his steam digester (pressure cooker), a closed vessel with a tightly fitting lid that confines the steam until a high pressure is gener...
</Question>
<Choice>Papin, Denis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist who shared one-half of the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1989 with the German-born American physicist Hans G. Dehmelt. (The other half of the prize was awarded to the American physicist Norman F. Ramsey.) Paul received his share of the prize for his development of the Paul trap—an electromagnetic device that captures ions (electrically charged atoms) and holds them long enough for their properties to be accurately measured.Paul studied at technological institutes in Munich and Berlin and received a doctoral degree in physics from the Technical University in Berlin in 1939. He bec...
</Question>
<Choice>Paul, Wolfgang</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian-born physicist and recipient of the 1945 Nobel Prize for Physics for his discovery in 1925 of the Pauli exclusion principle, which states that in an atom no two electrons can occupy the same quantum state simultaneously. Pauli made major contributions to quantum mechanics, quantum field theory, and solid-state physics, and he successfully hypothesized the existence of the neutrino.In addition to his original work, he wrote masterful syntheses of several areas of physical theory that are considered classics of scientific literature. An even deeper influence was left by his personal int...
</Question>
<Choice>Pauli, Wolfgang</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physicist who discovered (1834) that at the junction of two dissimilar metals an electric current will produce heat or cold, depending on the direction of current flow. The effect, known by his name, is used in devices for measuring temperature and, with the discovery of new conducting materials, in refrigeration units.A clockmaker, Peltier retired when he was 30 years old to devote his time to scientific investigations. In 1840 he introduced the concept of electrostatic induction, a method of charging a conductor by closely juxtaposing another charged object to attract all charges of o...
</Question>
<Choice>Peltier, Jean-Charles-Athanase</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-American astrophysicist who shared one-half of the 1978 Nobel Prize for Physics with Robert Woodrow Wilson for their discovery of a faint electromagnetic radiation throughout the universe. Their detection of this radiation lent strong support to the big-bang model of cosmic evolution. (The other half of the Nobel Prize was awarded to the Soviet physicist Pyotr Leonidovich Kapitsa for unrelated work.)Educated at City College of New York in New York City and Columbia University, where he received his doctorate in 1962, Penzias joined Bell Telephone Laboratories in Holmdel, N.J. In collabo...
</Question>
<Choice>Penzias, Arno</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist who received the 1995 Nobel Prize for Physics for discovering a subatomic particle that he named the tau, a massive lepton with a negative charge. The tau, which he found in the mid-1970s, was the first evidence of a third “generation” of fundamental particles, the existence of which proved essential for completing the so-called standard model of particle physics. Perl was jointly awarded the Nobel Prize with physicist Frederick Reines (q.v.), who discovered another subatomic particle, the neutrino, in the 1950s.In 1948 Perl graduated from the Brooklyn Polytechnic Institute...
</Question>
<Choice>Perl, Martin Lewis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physicist who, in his studies of the Brownian motion of minute particles suspended in liquids, verified Albert Einstein's explanation of this phenomenon and thereby confirmed the atomic nature of matter. For this achievement he was honoured with the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1926.Educated at the École Normale Supérieure, Paris, Perrin joined the faculty of the University of Paris (1898) where he became professor of physical chemistry (1910–40). In 1895 he established that cathode rays are negatively charged particles (electrons). His attempt to determine the mass of these particles was...
</Question>
<Choice>Perrin, Jean</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist whose experiments using laser light to cool and trap atoms earned him the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1997. He shared the award with Steven Chu and Claude Cohen-Tannoudji, who also developed methods of laser cooling and atom trapping.Phillips received his doctorate in physics (1976) and completed his postdoctoral research at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. In 1978 he joined the staff of the National Bureau of Standards (now the National Institute of Standards and Technology) in Gaithersburg, Md., and it was there that he conducted his award-winning research. Buildi...
</Question>
<Choice>Phillips, William D.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss-born Belgian physicist notable for his exploration of both the upper stratosphere and the depths of the sea in ships of his own design. In 1930 he built a balloon to study cosmic rays. In 1932 he developed a new cabin design for balloon flights, and in the same year he ascended to 17,008 metres (55,800 feet). He completed a bathyscaphe in 1948 and later made several dives with his son Jacques.Piccard was born into a family of Swiss scholars. His father, Jules Piccard, was a professor of chemistry at the University of Basel. Auguste and his twin brother, Jean, enrolled together at the Swi...
</Question>
<Choice>Piccard, Auguste</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss oceanic engineer, economist, and physicist, who helped his father, Auguste Piccard, build the bathyscaphe for deep-sea exploration and who also invented the mesoscaphe, an undersea vessel for exploring middle depths.He was born in Brussels while his Swiss-born father was a professor at the University of Brussels. After graduating from the École Nouvelle de Suisse Romande in Lausanne, Switz., in 1943, he studied at the University of Geneva, taking a year off in 1944–45 in order to serve with the French First Army. Upon receiving his licentiate in 1946, he taught at the university for two...
</Question>
<Choice>Piccard, Jacques-Ernest-Jean</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. physicist and astronomer who introduced the use of the meridian photometer to measure the magnitude of stars and established the Harvard Photometry (1884), the first great photometric catalog.In 1867 Pickering became professor of physics at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, where he established the first U.S. laboratory in which students were required to use laboratory instruments to make measurements. In 1876 he was appointed professor of astronomy and director of the Harvard College Observatory.He invented the meridian photometer, which utilized a calcite prism to ju...
</Question>
<Choice>Pickering, Edward Charles</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
New Zealand-born American engineer, physicist, and head of the team that developed Explorer 1, the first U.S. satellite. He played a leading role in the development of the U.S. space program.Pickering attended Canterbury University in New Zealand before moving to the United States in 1929; he became a U.S. citizen in 1941. He studied at the California Institute of Technology in Pasadena (B.S. 1932, M.S. 1933, Ph.D. 1936) and joined the staff of the institute in 1936. Working under the American physicist Robert A. Millikan, Pickering developed cosmic-radiation-detection gear for high-altitude b...
</Question>
<Choice>Pickering, William Hayward</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
theoretical physicist who originated quantum theory, which won him the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1918.Planck made many contributions to theoretical physics, but his fame rests primarily on his role as originator of the quantum theory. This theory revolutionized our understanding of atomic and subatomic processes, just as Albert Einstein's theory of relativity revolutionized our understanding of space and time. Together they constitute the fundamental theories of 20th-century physics. Both have forced man to revise some of his most cherished philosophical beliefs, and both have led to industri...
</Question>
<Choice>Planck, Max</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physicist who produced the first electric storage battery, or accumulator, in 1859; in improved form, his invention is widely used in automobiles.Planté followed an academic career, beginning in Paris as a lecture assistant in physics at the Conservatory of Arts and Crafts in 1854 and, six years later, rising to the post of professor of physics at the Polytechnic Association for the Development of Popular Instruction.In 1859 Planté began experiments that resulted in construction of a battery for the storage of electrical energy; his first model contained two sheets of lead, separated by...
</Question>
<Choice>Plante, Gaston</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German mathematician and physicist who made fundamental contributions to analytic and projective geometry as well as experimental physics.Plücker attended the universities in Heidelberg, Bonn, Berlin, and Paris. In 1829, after four years as an unsalaried lecturer, he became a professor at the University of Bonn, where he wrote Analytisch-geometrische Entwicklungen, 2 vol. (1828–31; “The Development of Analytic Geometry”). This work introduced abridged notation (a flexible type of mathematical “shorthand”) and exploited the possibility of taking lines rather than points as the fundamental geome...
</Question>
<Choice>Plucker, Julius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician known for his work on definite integrals, electromagnetic theory, and probability.Poisson's family had intended him for a medical career, but he showed little interest or aptitude and in 1798 began studying mathematics at the École Polytechnique in Paris under the mathematicians Pierre-Simon Laplace and Joseph-Louis Lagrange, who became his lifelong friends. He became a professor at the École Polytechnique in 1802. In 1808 he was made an astronomer at the Bureau of Longitudes, and, when the Faculty of Sciences was instituted in 1809, he was appointed a professor of pure ma...
</Question>
<Choice>Poisson, Simeon-Denis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist who, with David J. Gross and Frank Wilczek, was awarded the Nobel Prize for Physics in 2004 for discoveries regarding the strong force—the nuclear force that binds together quarks (the smallest building blocks of matter) and holds together the nucleus of the atom.Politzer studied physics at the University of Michigan (B.S., 1969) and Harvard University (Ph.D., 1974). In 1975 he began teaching at the California Institute of Technology, and from 1986 to 1988 he served as head of the school's physics department.In the early 1970s Politzer—along with Gross and Wilczek, who were...
</Question>
<Choice>Politzer, H. David</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
physicist and electrical engineer acclaimed in Russia as the inventor of radio. Evidently he built his first primitive radio receiver, a lightning detector (1895), without knowledge of the contemporary work of the Italian inventor Guglielmo Marconi. The genuineness and the value of Popov's successful experiments are not seriously doubted, but Marconi's priority is usually conceded.Popov was the son of a village priest. He received his early education in an ecclesiastical seminary school and planned to enter the priesthood. But in 1877 his interests changed to mathematics, and he entered the Un...
</Question>
<Choice>Popov, Aleksandr</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physicist and winner of the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1950 for his development of the photographic method of studying nuclear processes and for the resulting discovery of the pion (pi-meson), a heavy subatomic particle. The pion proved to be the hypothetical particle proposed in 1935 by Yukawa Hideki of Japan in his theory of nuclear physics.In 1928 Powell was appointed research assistant at the Henry Herbert Wills Physical Laboratory at the University of Bristol. He became professor of physics at Bristol in 1948 and director of the Wills Laboratory in 1964. Between 1939 and 1945 he d...
</Question>
<Choice>Powell, Cecil Frank</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physicist who introduced a theorem that assigns a value to the rate of flow of electromagnetic energy known as the Poynting vector.He was a professor of physics at Mason Science College (later the University of Birmingham) from 1880 until his death. In papers published in 1884–85, he showed that the flow of energy at a point can be expressed by a simple formula in terms of the electric and magnetic forces at that point. This is Poynting's theorem. He also wrote papers on radiation and the pressure of light. After 12 years of experiments he determined in 1891 the mean density of the Ear...
</Question>
<Choice>Poynting, John Henry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist who is considered to be the father of aerodynamics.In 1901 Prandtl became professor of mechanics at the Technical Institute of Hannover, where he continued his earlier efforts to provide a sound theoretical basis for fluid mechanics. From 1904 to 1953, he served as professor of applied mechanics at the University of Göttingen, where he established a school of aerodynamics and hydrodynamics that achieved world renown. In 1925 he became director of the Kaiser Wilhelm (later the Max Planck) Institute for Fluid Mechanics. His discovery (1904) of the boundary layer, which adjoins t...
</Question>
<Choice>Prandtl, Ludwig</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Soviet physicist who, with Nikolay G. Basov and Charles H. Townes, won the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1964 for fundamental research in quantum electronics that led to the development of the maser and laser.Prokhorov's father was involved in revolutionary activities that eventually forced the family to leave Russia. In 1911 they settled in Australia, where Prokhorov was born. Following the overthrow of the tsar (1917), the family returned to Russia in 1923. In 1951 Prokhorov received a doctorate from Leningrad State University and later joined the P.N. Lebedev Physical Institute, Moscow, as a s...
</Question>
<Choice>Prokhorov, Aleksandr Mikhaylovich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Serbian American physicist who devised a means of greatly extending the range of long-distance telephone communication by placing loading coils (of wire) at predetermined intervals along the transmitting wire.Pupin's family was of Serbian origin, and his parents, who were illiterate, encouraged his education. He immigrated to the United States in 1874 and held a series of odd jobs before attending Columbia College (now Columbia University), where he earned a B.A. in 1883; that year he also became a U.S. citizen. Pupin subsequently studied at Cambridge University and the University of Berlin (P...
</Question>
<Choice>Pupin, Michael Idvorsky</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist who shared, with Felix Bloch of the United States, the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1952 for his independent discovery (1946) of nuclear magnetic resonance in liquids and in solids. Nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) has become widely used to study the molecular structure of pure materials and the composition of mixtures.During World War II Purcell headed a group studying radar problems at the Radiation Laboratory of the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge. In 1946 he developed his NMR detection method, which was extremely accurate and a major improvement over the a...
</Question>
<Choice>Purcell, E. M.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist who was awarded the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1944 for his invention (in 1937) of the atomic and molecular beam magnetic resonance method of observing atomic spectra.Rabi's parents settled in New York City in 1899. After earning a bachelor's degree in chemistry at Cornell University in 1919, Rabi switched to physics and received his Ph.D. from Columbia University in 1927. He did postgraduate work in Europe and then joined the faculty of Columbia University in 1929, becoming professor of physics in 1937. From 1940 to 1945 Rabi was a leader of the group of scientists at the M...
</Question>
<Choice>Rabi, Isidor Isaac</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist who won a share of the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1975 for his part in determining the asymmetrical shapes of certain atomic nuclei.Educated at the California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, and Columbia University, where he received his doctorate in 1946, Rainwater worked on the Manhattan Project to develop the atomic bomb during World War II. In 1949 he began formulating a theory that not all atomic nuclei are spherical, as was then generally believed. The theory was tested experimentally and confirmed by Danish physicists Aage N. Bohr and Ben R. Mottelson. For their wo...
</Question>
<Choice>Rainwater, James</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian physicist whose work was influential in the growth of science in India. He was the recipient of the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1930 for the discovery that when light traverses a transparent material, some of the light that is deflected changes in wavelength. This phenomenon is now called Raman scattering and is the result of the Raman effect.After earning a master's degree in physics at Presidency College, University of Madras, in 1907, Raman became an accountant in the finance department of the Indian government. He became professor of physics at the University of Calcutta in 1917. Stu...
</Question>
<Choice>Raman, Sir Chandrasekhara Venkata</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist who received one-half of the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1989 for his development of a technique to induce atoms to shift from one specific energy level to another. (The other half of the prize was awarded to Wolfgang Paul and Hans Georg Dehmelt.) Ramsey's innovation, called the separated oscillatory fields method, found application in the precise measurement of time and frequency.Ramsey studied physics at Columbia University, N.Y., and received a Ph.D. degree there in 1940. He also earned a D.Sc. degree from the University of Cambridge in 1954. After teaching at various Amer...
</Question>
<Choice>Ramsey, Norman Foster</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish engineer and physicist and one of the founders of the science of thermodynamics, particularly in reference to steam-engine theory.Trained as a civil engineer under Sir John Benjamin MacNeill, Rankine was appointed to the Queen Victoria chair of civil engineering and mechanics at the University of Glasgow (1855). One of Rankine's first scientific works, a paper on fatigue in metals of railway axles (1843), led to new methods of construction. His Manual of Applied Mechanics (1858) was of considerable help to designing engineers and architects. His classic Manual of the Steam Engine and...
</Question>
<Choice>Rankine, William John Macquorn</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physical scientist who made fundamental discoveries in the fields of acoustics and optics that are basic to the theory of wave propagation in fluids. He received the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1904 for his successful isolation of argon, an inert atmospheric gas.Strutt suffered from poor health throughout his childhood and youth, and it was necessary for him to be withdrawn from both Eton and Harrow. In 1857 he began four years of private study under a tutor. In 1861 Strutt entered Trinity College, Cambridge, from which he was graduated with a B.A. in 1865. He early developed an absorbi...
</Question>
<Choice>
Rayleigh of Terling Place, John William Strutt, 3rd Baron
</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French chemist and physicist noted for his work on the properties of gases.After studying with Justus von Liebig, in Giessen, Regnault became professor of chemistry successively at the University of Lyon, the École Polytechnique (1840), and the Collège de France (1841). His four-volume work on chemistry appeared in 1847. While director of the porcelain factory at Sèvres (from 1854), he continued his work in science. During the Franco-German War (1870–71) his laboratory there was destroyed, and his son Henri, the painter, was killed.Regnault designed apparatus for a large number of physical mea...
</Question>
<Choice>Regnault, Henri-Victor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist who was awarded the 1995 Nobel Prize for Physics for his discovery 40 years earlier, together with his colleague Clyde L. Cowan, Jr., of the subatomic particle called the neutrino, a tiny lepton with little or no mass and a neutral charge. Reines shared the Nobel Prize with physicist Martin Lewis Perl, who also discovered a fundamental particle, the tau.Reines was educated at Stevens Institute of Technology, Hoboken, N.J. (B.S., 1939; M.A., 1941), and at New York University (Ph.D., 1944). From 1944 to 1959 he conducted research in particle physics and nuclear weaponry at the...
</Question>
<Choice>Reines, Frederick</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist who constructed a precursor of the electric telephone.Reis was educated at Frankfurt am Main, became a merchant for a few years, and in 1858 began teaching in Friedrichsdorf. While there he experimented with electricity and worked on the development of hearing aids. This research led to his interest in the electrical transmission of sound, and by 1861 he had designed several transmitters and receivers.In Reis's instruments, a contact in an electrical circuit was established between a metal point and a metal strip resting on a membrane in the transmitter. It was Reis's theory t...
</Question>
<Choice>Reis, Johann Philipp</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British engineer, physicist, and educator best known for his work in hydraulics and hydrodynamics.Reynolds was born into a family of Anglican clerics. He gained early workshop experience by apprenticing with a mechanical engineer, and he graduated at Queens' College, Cambridge, in mathematics in 1867. In 1868 he became the first professor of engineering at Owens College, Manchester, a position he held until his retirement in 1905. He became a fellow of the Royal Society in 1877 and received a Royal Medal in 1888.Though his earliest professional research dealt with such properties as magnetism,...
</Question>
<Choice>Reynolds, Osborne</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physicist and psychologist who was the first to apply mathematical techniques to predict the weather accurately.Richardson made major contributions to methods of solving certain types of problems in physics, and from 1913 to 1922 he applied his ideas to meteorology. His work, published in Weather Prediction by Numerical Process (1922), was not entirely successful at first. The main drawback to his mathematical technique for systematically forecasting the weather was the time necessary to produce such a forecast. It generally took him three months to predict the weather for the next 24...
</Question>
<Choice>Richardson, Lewis Fry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist who was the corecipient, along with Douglas Osheroff and David Lee, of the 1996 Nobel Prize for Physics for their discovery of superfluidity in the isotope helium-3 (3He).Richardson received his Ph.D. in physics from Duke University (Durham., N.C.) in 1966 and joined the faculty of Cornell University (Ithaca, N.Y.) in 1967. He became director of the laboratory of atomic and solid-state physics there in 1990.At the time of their discovery in 1972, Richardson and Lee were senior researchers in the low-temperature laboratory at Cornell and were investigating the properties of t...
</Question>
<Choice>Richardson, Robert C.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physicist and recipient of the 1928 Nobel Prize for Physics for his work on electron emission by hot metals, the basic principle used in vacuum tubes.Richardson, a graduate (1900) of Trinity College, Cambridge, and a student of J.J. Thomson at the Cavendish Laboratory, was appointed professor of physics at Princeton University (1906–13). In 1911 he proved that electrons are emitted from hot metal and not from the surrounding air, as some had thought. That same year he proposed a mathematical equation that relates the rate of electron emission to the absolute temperature of the metal. T...
</Question>
<Choice>Richardson, Sir Owen Willans</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist who was jointly awarded the 1976 Nobel Prize for Physics with Samuel C.C. Ting for the discovery of a new subatomic particle, the J/psi particle.Richter studied at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, where he received his doctorate in 1956. That same year he became a research associate at Stanford University, Stanford, Calif., becoming a full professor in 1967. He immediately undertook experiments that confirmed the validity of quantum electrodynamics at very short distances. In collaboration with David Ritson and with financial support from the Atomic Ener...
</Question>
<Choice>Richter, Burton</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist and seismologist who developed the Richter scale for measuring earthquake magnitude.Born on an Ohio farm, Richter moved with his mother to Los Angeles in 1916. He attended the University of Southern California (1916–17) and then studied physics at Stanford University (A.B., 1920) and the California Institute of Technology (Ph.D., 1928). Richter was on the staff of the Seismological Laboratory of the Carnegie Institution of Washington, Pasadena, California (1927–36), and then taught both physics and seismology at Caltech (1937–70) and worked at its Seismological Laboratory (f...
</Question>
<Choice>Richter, Charles F.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German mathematician whose profound and novel approaches to the study of geometry laid the mathematical foundation for Albert Einstein's theory of relativity. He also made important contributions to the theory of functions, complex analysis, and number theory.Riemann was born into a poor Lutheran pastor's family, and all his life he was a shy and introverted person. He was fortunate to have a schoolteacher who recognized his rare mathematical ability and lent him advanced books to read, including Adrien-Marie Legendre's Number Theory (1830). Riemann read the book in a week and then claimed to...
</Question>
<Choice>Riemann, Bernhard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist who discovered the ultraviolet region of the spectrum and thus helped broaden man's view beyond the narrow region of visible light to encompass the entire electromagnetic spectrum from the shortest gamma rays to the longest radio waves.A pharmacist in Liegnitz, Silesia, from 1791 to 1795, Ritter studied medicine at the University of Jena, where he taught until he gained the patronage of the duke of Saxe–Gotha. In 1800, only months after the English chemist William Nicholson succeeded in decomposing water into hydrogen and oxygen by electrolysis, Ritter duplicated the experimen...
</Question>
<Choice>Ritter, Johann Wilhelm</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French mathematician and physicist who contributed to the development of the French atomic bomb and to the understanding of such diverse fields of research as semiconductors, seismology, and radio astronomy.Rocard received doctorates in mathematics (1927) and physical science (1928) from the École Normale Supérieure (ENS) in Paris and took a job in the electronics industry. During World War II he worked with the resistance and supplied British scientific intelligence with vital information, including details on a new radio navigational beam station. For this assistance he was made a Commander...
</Question>
<Choice>Rocard, Yves-Andre</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss physicist who, with Gerd Binnig, received half of the 1986 Nobel Prize for Physics for their joint invention of the scanning tunneling microscope. (Ernst Ruska received the other half of the prize.)Rohrer was educated at the Swiss Federal Institute of Technology in Zürich and received his Ph.D. there in 1960. In 1963 he joined the IBM Research Laboratory in Zürich, where he remained. Binnig also joined the laboratory, and it was there that the two men designed and built the first scanning tunneling microscope. This instrument is equipped with a tiny tungsten probe whose tip, only about o...
</Question>
<Choice>Rohrer, Heinrich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist who was a recipient of the first Nobel Prize for Physics, in 1901, for his discovery of X-rays, which heralded the age of modern physics and revolutionized diagnostic medicine.Röntgen studied at the Polytechnic in Zürich and then was professor of physics at the universities of Strasbourg (1876–79), Giessen (1879–88), Würzburg (1888–1900), and Munich (1900–20). His research also included work on elasticity, capillary action of fluids, specific heats of gases, conduction of heat in crystals, absorption of heat by gases, and piezoelectricity.In 1895, while experimenting with elec...
</Question>
<Choice>Rontgen, Wilhelm Conrad</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polish-born British physicist who became a leading critic of nuclear weaponry. He was a founding member (1957), secretary-general (1957–73), and president (1988–97) of the Pugwash Conferences on Science and World Affairs, a London-based worldwide organization of scholars that seeks solutions to problems of national development and international security. In 1995 Rotblat and his organization were jointly awarded the Nobel Prize for Peace for their long-standing promotion of nuclear disarmament, most notably by sponsoring discussions between scientists from the United States and the Soviet Union...
</Question>
<Choice>Rotblat, Sir Joseph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist who invented the concave diffraction grating, which replaced prisms and plane gratings in many applications, and revolutionized spectrum analysis—the resolution of a beam of light into components that differ in wavelength.In 1872 Rowland became an instructor of physics at Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, Troy, N.Y., and four years later he was elected to the chair of physics in the newly founded Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore. In 1876 he succeeded in proving that a moving electric charge has the same magnetic action as an electric current. Three years later, with impro...
</Question>
<Choice>Rowland, Henry Augustus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian physicist who in 1984 shared with Simon van der Meer the Nobel Prize for Physics for the discovery of the massive, short-lived subatomic W particle and Z particle. These particles are the carriers of the so-called weak force involved in the radioactive decay of atomic nuclei. Their existence strongly confirms the validity of the electroweak theory, proposed in the 1970s, that the weak force and electromagnetism are different manifestations of a single basic kind of physical interaction.Rubbia was educated at the Normal School of Pisa and the University of Pisa, earning a doctorate from...
</Question>
<Choice>Rubbia, Carlo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German electrical engineer who invented the electron microscope. He was awarded half of the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1986 (the other half was divided between Heinrich Rohrer and Gerd Binnig).Ruska studied at the Technical University of Munich during 1925–27 and then enrolled at the Technical University in Berlin. Around this time he began the studies that led to his invention of the electron microscope. The extent to which an optical microscope could resolve the detail of a highly magnified object was limited by the wavelengths of the light beams used to view the object. Since it had been es...
</Question>
<Choice>Ruska, Ernst</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
New Zealand-born British physicist considered the greatest experimentalist since Michael Faraday (1791–1867). Rutherford was the central figure in the study of radioactivity, and with his concept of the nuclear atom he led the exploration of nuclear physics. He won the Nobel Prize for Chemistry in 1908, was president of the Royal Society (1925–30) and the British Association for the Advancement of Science (1923), was conferred the Order of Merit in 1925, and was raised to the peerage as Lord Rutherford of Nelson in 1931.
</Question>
<Choice>
Rutherford, Ernest, Baron Rutherford of Nelson, of Cambridge
</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish physicist for whom the Rydberg constant in spectroscopy is named.Educated at the University of Lund, Rydberg received his bachelor's degree in 1875 and his doctorate in mathematics in 1879. He became lecturer in physics there in 1882 and assistant at the Physics Institute in 1892. He was permanent professor of physics from 1901 until his retirement in 1919.Rydberg is best known for his theoretical studies of spectral series. Using wave numbers instead of wavelengths in his calculations, he was able to arrive at a relatively simple expression that related the various lines in the spectr...
</Question>
<Choice>Rydberg, Johannes Robert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British radio astronomer who developed revolutionary radio telescope systems and used them for accurate location of weak radio sources. With improved equipment, he observed the most distant known galaxies of the universe. Ryle and Antony Hewish shared the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1974, the first Nobel prize awarded in recognition of astronomical research.Ryle was the nephew of the philosopher Gilbert Ryle. After earning a degree in physics at the University of Oxford in 1939, he worked with the Telecommunications Research Establishment on the design of radar equipment during World War II. Af...
</Question>
<Choice>Ryle, Sir Martin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. physicist who founded the science of architectural acoustics.After graduating from Ohio State University in 1886, Sabine did graduate work at Harvard University, where he later joined the faculty. A brilliant researcher, he enjoyed teaching and never bothered to get his doctorate; his papers were modest in number but exceptional in content. When Harvard opened the Fogg Art Museum in 1895, its auditorium revealed seriously defective acoustics caused by excessive reverberation. Sabine was asked to find a remedy. His discovery that the product of the reverberation time multiplied by the tota...
</Question>
<Choice>Sabine, Wallace Clement Ware</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pakistani nuclear physicist who was the corecipient with Steven Weinberg and Sheldon Lee Glashow of the 1979 Nobel Prize for Physics for their work in formulating the electroweak theory, which explains the unity of the weak nuclear force and electromagnetism.Salam attended the Government College at Lahore, and in 1952 he received his Ph.D. in theoretical physics from the University of Cambridge. He returned to Pakistan as a professor of mathematics in 1951–54 and then went back to Cambridge as a lecturer in mathematics. He became professor of theoretical physics at the Imperial College of Scie...
</Question>
<Choice>Salam, Abdus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss physicist, geologist, and early Alpine explorer who developed an improved hygrometer to measure atmospheric humidity.Saussure became professor of physics and philosophy at the Academy of Geneva in 1762 and in 1766 developed what was probably the first electrometer, used to measure electric potential. The word geology was introduced into scientific nomenclature by Saussure with the publication of the first volume of his Voyages dans les Alpes (1779–96; “Travels in the Alps”), a work that contains the results of more than 30 years of geologic studies. In 1783 Saussure built the first hygro...
</Question>
<Choice>Saussure, Horace Benedict de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist and corecipient, with Nicolaas Bloembergen of the United States and Kai Manne Börje Siegbahn of Sweden, of the 1981 Nobel Prize for Physics for his work in developing the laser and in laser spectroscopy.As a child, Schawlow moved with his family to Canada. He attended the University of Toronto, receiving his Ph.D. in 1949. In that year he went to Columbia University, where he began collaborating with Charles Townes on the development of the maser (a device that produces and amplifies electromagnetic radiation mainly in the microwave region of the spectrum), the laser (a devi...
</Question>
<Choice>Schawlow, Arthur L.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss physicist who collaborated with Peter Debye in the development of a method of X-ray diffraction analysis. The Debye–Scherrer method is widely used to identify materials that do not readily form large, perfect crystals.Scherrer spent most of his life in Zürich, where he was professor of physics (1916–60) and director (1920–60) of the Physics Institute of the University of Zürich. In recognition of his contributions to solid-state, quantum, and nuclear physics, he was appointed president of the Swiss Atomic Energy Commission in 1946.
</Question>
<Choice>Scherrer, Paul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist whose research in solid-state physics and electronics yielded many devices that now bear his name.Schottky obtained doctorates in engineering, technology, and natural sciences from the University of Berlin, where he conducted research under Max Planck. He taught at the universities of Würzburg (1920–22) and Rostock (1923–27) and then worked as an industrial researcher at Siemens AG from 1927 until shortly before his death at age 90.In 1914 Schottky discovered an irregularity in the emission of thermions in a vacuum tube, now known as the Schottky effect. He invented the screen...
</Question>
<Choice>Schottky, Walter</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist and winner, with John Bardeen and Leon N. Cooper, of the 1972 Nobel Prize for Physics for developing the BCS theory (for their initials), the first successful microscopic theory of superconductivity.Schrieffer was educated at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge, and the University of Illinois, Urbana-Champaign, where he received his Ph.D. in 1957. He was a young graduate student working under Bardeen at the University of Illinois when he helped explain why metals lose their electrical resistance at very low temperatures.Schrieffer taught at the University of...
</Question>
<Choice>Schrieffer, John Robert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian theoretical physicist who contributed to the wave theory of matter and to other fundamentals of quantum mechanics. He shared the 1933 Nobel Prize for Physics with the British physicist P.A.M. Dirac.Schrödinger entered the University of Vienna in 1906 and obtained his doctorate in 1910, upon which he accepted a research post at the university's Second Physics Institute. He saw military service in World War I and then went to the University of Zürich in 1921, where he remained for the next six years. There, in a six-month period in 1926, at the age of 39, a remarkably late age for origi...
</Question>
<Choice>Schrodinger, Erwin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist and entrepreneur who, along with Leon M. Lederman and Jack Steinberger, received the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1988 for their research concerning neutrinos (subatomic particles that have no electric charge and virtually no mass).Schwartz studied physics at Columbia University, New York City, and received a Ph.D. there in 1958. He taught at Columbia from 1958 to 1966 and then was a professor of physics at Stanford University, Calif., from 1966 to 1983. In 1970 he founded Digital Pathways, Inc., a company that designed computer-security systems. Schwartz later served as an as...
</Question>
<Choice>Schwartz, Melvin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German astronomer whose contributions, both practical and theoretical, were of primary importance in the development of 20th-century astronomy.Schwarzschild's exceptional ability in science became evident at the age of 16, when his paper on the theory of celestial orbits was published. In 1901 he became professor and director of the observatory at the University of Göttingen, and eight years later he was appointed director of the Astrophysical Observatory at Potsdam.While at Göttingen, Schwarzschild introduced precise methods in photographic photometry. The results of his studies clearly demon...
</Question>
<Choice>Schwarzschild, Karl</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist and joint winner, with Richard P. Feynman and Tomonaga Shin'ichiro, of the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1965 for introducing new ideas and methods into quantum electrodynamics.Schwinger was a child prodigy, publishing his first physics paper at age 16. He earned a bachelor's degree (1937) and a doctorate (1939) from Columbia University in New York City, before engaging in postdoctoral studies at the University of California at Berkeley with physicist J. Robert Oppenheimer. Schwinger left Berkeley in the summer of 1941 to accept an instructorship at Purdue University, West Lafa...
</Question>
<Choice>Schwinger, Julian Seymour</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist who discovered (1821) that an electric current flows between different conductive materials that are kept at different temperatures, known as the Seebeck effect.Seebeck studied medicine at Berlin and at the University of Gottingen, where he acquired an M.D. in 1802. However, he abandoned medical practice for scientific research. He was chosen (1814) as a member of the Berlin Academy and was awarded (1816) the academy's annual prize for his investigation of polarization in stressed glass.In numerous experiments on the magnetizability of various metals, he observed the anomalous...
</Question>
<Choice>Seebeck, Thomas Johann</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist and mathematician who in 1751 introduced the concept of the surface tension of liquids, likening it to a stretched membrane. His view that minute and imperceptible attractive forces maintain surface tension laid the foundation for the subsequent development of surface tension theory.Segner taught physics and mathematics at the universities of Jena, Göttingen, and Halle. In 1750 he developed a simple-reaction waterwheel. The study of this machine by the mathematician Leonhard Euler led to the development of a crude turbine. Segner also studied the theory of the spinning top and...
</Question>
<Choice>Segner, Johann Andreas von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian-born American physicist who was cowinner, with Owen Chamberlain of the United States, of the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1959 for the discovery of the antiproton, an antiparticle having the same mass as a proton but opposite in electrical charge.Segrè initially began studies in engineering at the University of Rome in 1922 but later studied under Enrico Fermi and received his doctorate in physics in 1928. In 1932 Segrè was appointed assistant professor of physics at the University of Rome, and two years later he participated in neutron experiments directed by Fermi, in which many elemen...
</Question>
<Choice>Segre, Emilio</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American engineer and teacher, cowinner (with John Bardeen and Walter H. Brattain) of the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1956 for their development of the transistor, a device that largely replaced the bulkier and less-efficient vacuum tube and ushered in the age of microminiature electronics.Shockley studied physics at the California Institute of Technology (B.S., 1932) and at Harvard University (Ph.D., 1936). He joined the technical staff of the Bell Telephone Laboratories in 1936 and there began experiments with semiconductors that ultimately led to the invention and development of the transist...
</Question>
<Choice>Shockley, William B.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist who was corecipient of the 1994 Nobel Prize for Physics for his development of neutron-scattering techniques—in particular, neutron diffraction, a process that enabled scientists to better explore the atomic structure of matter. He shared the prize with Canadian physicist Bertram N. Brockhouse, who conducted separate but concurrent work in the field.Shull was educated at the Carnegie Institute of Technology (B.S., 1937) and New York University (Ph.D., 1941) and began a career as a research physicist. His award-winning work was completed at the Oak Ridge National Laboratories...
</Question>
<Choice>Shull, Clifford G.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish physicist, corecipient with Nicolaas Bloembergen and Arthur Leonard Schawlow of the 1981 Nobel Prize for Physics for their revolutionary work in spectroscopy, particularly the spectroscopic analysis of the interaction of electromagnetic radiation with matter.Siegbahn was the son of Karl Manne Siegbahn, who received the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1924 for his discoveries relating to X-ray spectroscopy. Kai was awarded his Ph.D. in physics by the University of Stockholm in 1944. In 1951 he was appointed professor at the Royal Institute of Technology in Stockholm, and in 1954 he moved to...
</Question>
<Choice>Siegbahn, Kai Manne Borje</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish physicist who was awarded the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1924 for his discoveries and investigations in X-ray spectroscopy.Siegbahn was educated at the University of Lund and obtained his doctorate there in 1911. At Lund he became a research assistant to Johannes Rydberg and succeeded Rydberg as professor of physics in 1920. In 1916 Siegbahn discovered a new group of wavelengths, the M series, in X-ray emission spectra. He developed equipment and techniques that allowed him and subsequent researchers to determine accurately the wavelengths of X rays. A year after he became professor of...
</Question>
<Choice>Siegbahn, Karl Manne Georg</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American chemist and physicist, who shared the 1996 Nobel Prize for Chemistry with Robert F. Curl, Jr., and Sir Harold W. Kroto for their joint discovery of carbon-60 (C60, or buckminsterfullerene) and the fullerenes.Smalley received a Ph.D. from Princeton University in 1973. After postdoctoral work at the University of Chicago, he began his teaching career at Rice University (Houston, Texas) in 1976. He was named Gene and Norman Hackerman Professor of Chemistry there in 1982 and became a professor of physics in 1990.It was at Rice University that Smalley and his colleagues discovered fulleren...
</Question>
<Choice>Smalley, Richard E.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British novelist, scientist, and government administrator.Snow was graduated from Leicester University and earned a doctorate in physics at the University of Cambridge, where, at the age of 25, he became a fellow of Christ's College. After working at Cambridge in molecular physics for some 20 years, he became a university administrator, and, with the outbreak of World War II, he became a scientific adviser to the British government. He was knighted in 1957 and made a life peer in 1964. In 1950 he married the British novelist Pamela Hansford Johnson.In the 1930s Snow began the 11-volume novel s...
</Question>
<Choice>Snow, C. P.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist whose atomic model permitted the explanation of fine-structure spectral lines.After studying mathematics and science at Königsberg University, Sommerfeld became an assistant at the University of Göttingen and then taught mathematics at Clausthal (1897) and Aachen (1900).As professor of theoretical physics at Munich (1906–31), he did his most important work. His investigations of atomic spectra led him to suggest that, in the Bohr model of the atom, the electrons move in elliptical orbits as well as circular ones. From this idea he postulated the azimuthal quantum number. He la...
</Question>
<Choice>Sommerfeld, Arnold Johannes Wilhelm</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist who won the 1919 Nobel Prize for Physics for his discovery in 1913 that an electric field would cause splitting of the lines in the spectrum of light emitted by a luminous substance; the phenomenon is called the Stark effect.Stark became a lecturer at the University of Göttingen in 1900, and from 1917 until he retired in 1922, he was a professor of physics at the University of Greifswald and, later, at the University of Würzburg. A supporter of Adolf Hitler and an anti-Semitic racial theorist, Stark was president of the Reich Physical-Technical Institute from 1933 to 1939. In...
</Question>
<Choice>Stark, Johannes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian physicist who in 1879 formulated a law which states that the radiant energy of a blackbody—a theoretical object that absorbs all radiation that falls on it—is proportional to the fourth power of its temperature. His law was one of the first important steps toward the understanding of blackbody radiation, from which sprang the quantum idea of radiation.At the University of Vienna, Stefan rose from lecturer in mathematical physics in 1858 to professor ordinarius of physics in 1863 and to director of the Physical Institute in 1866. Five years after he derived his law empirically, it was...
</Question>
<Choice>Stefan, Josef</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
philosopher and physicist, who combined scientific ideas with German Idealist metaphysics.Steffens spent his early years at Copenhagen, where he attended the university. He later studied at Kiel, Jena, and Berlin and by 1799 was an established figure in German literary and philosophical circles and on friendly terms with Schelling, Goethe, and Friedrich Schleiermacher. After publishing Beiträge zur innern Naturgeschichte der Erde (1801; “Contributions to the Internal Natural History of the Earth”), he took up an academic career, beginning as a lecturer at Copenhagen in 1802 and becoming profes...
</Question>
<Choice>Steffens, Henrik</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-born American physicist who, along with Leon M. Lederman and Melvin Schwartz, was awarded the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1988 for their joint discoveries concerning neutrinos.Steinberger immigrated to the United States in 1934. He studied physics at the University of Chicago, receiving his Ph.D. there in 1948. He was a professor of physics at Columbia University, New York City, from 1950 to 1971, and from 1968 he was a physicist at the European Organization for Nuclear Research (CERN) in Geneva, Switz.In the early 1960s Steinberger, along with his Columbia University colleagues Lederman...
</Question>
<Choice>Steinberger, Jack</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-born scientist and winner of the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1943 for his development of the molecular beam as a tool for studying the characteristics of molecules and for his measurement of the magnetic moment of the proton.Stern's early scientific work was theoretical studies of statistical thermodynamics. In 1914 he became a lecturer in theoretical physics at the University of Frankfurt and in 1923 a professor of physical chemistry at the University of Hamburg. Stern and Walther Gerlach performed their historic molecular-beam experiment at Hamburg in the early 1920s. By shooting a bea...
</Question>
<Choice>Stern, Otto</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physicist and mathematician noted for his studies of the behaviour of viscous fluids, particularly for his law of viscosity, which describes the motion of a solid sphere in a fluid, and for Stokes's theorem, a basic theorem of vector analysis.Stokes, who was appointed Lucasian Professor of Mathematics at Cambridge University in 1849, earlier had published his first papers on fluid motion and the steady motion of incompressible fluids (1842 and 1843) and his work on the friction of fluids in motion and the equilibrium and motion of elastic solids (1845). He worked on fluorescence (he or...
</Question>
<Choice>Stokes, Sir George Gabriel, 1st Baronet</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
physicist who introduced the term electron for the fundamental unit of electricity.In 1848 Stoney became assistant to the astronomer William Parsons Rosse, who secured for him a professorship in natural philosophy (natural science) at Queen's College, Galway (1852). In 1857 he became secretary of the Queen's University, Dublin.From his work on molecular physics and kinetic theory of gases, he estimated the number of molecules in a volume of gas under standard conditions. Though his method for estimating the value of the electronic charge was sound (1874), his result was incorrect because of an...
</Question>
<Choice>Stoney, George Johnstone</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-born American physicist who, with Daniel C. Tsui and Robert B. Laughlin, was coawarded the 1998 Nobel Prize in Physics for the discovery and explanation of the fractional quantum Hall effect.Störmer graduated from the University of Frankfurt, Germany, in 1970 and earned a Ph.D. in physics at the University of Stuttgart, Germany, in 1977. Moving to the United States, he joined the research staff of Bell Laboratories (Murray Hill, New Jersey) in 1978. There he and his coworker Tsui made their discovery in 1982. Störmer was head of the Physical Research Laboratory at Bell Labs from 1992 to...
</Question>
<Choice>Stormer, Horst L.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physicist and chemist who produced an early electric light bulb and invented the dry photographic plate, an important improvement in photography and a step in the development of modern photographic film.After serving his apprenticeship with a druggist in his native town, Swan became first assistant and later partner in a firm of manufacturing chemists in Newcastle. Working with wet photographic plates, he noticed that heat increased the sensitivity of the silver bromide emulsion. By 1871 he had devised a method of drying the wet plates, initiating the age of convenience in photography....
</Question>
<Choice>Swan, Sir Joseph Wilson</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hungarian-born American physicist who helped conduct the first sustained nuclear chain reaction and was instrumental in initiating the Manhattan Project for the development of the atomic bomb.In 1922 Szilard received his Ph.D. from the University of Berlin and joined the staff of the Institute of Theoretical Physics there. When the Nazis came into power in 1933, he went to Vienna and, in 1934, to London, where he joined the physics staff of the medical college of St. Bartholomew's Hospital. There, with the British physicist T.A. Chalmers, Szilard developed the first method of separating isotop...
</Question>
<Choice>Szilard, Leo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish physicist and mathematician who helped develop quaternions, an advanced algebra that gave rise to vector analysis and was instrumental in the development of modern mathematical physics.After serving from 1852 to 1854 as a fellow and lecturer at Peterhouse College, Cambridge, England, Tait took a professorship in mathematics at Queen's College, Belfast, Ireland. There he joined the noted Irish chemist Thomas Andrews in research on the density of ozone and the effect of electric discharges on oxygen and other gases. From 1860 he was a professor of natural philosophy at the University of...
</Question>
<Choice>Tait, Peter Guthrie</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Soviet physicist who shared the 1958 Nobel Prize for Physics with Pavel A. Cherenkov and Ilya M. Frank for his efforts in explaining Cherenkov radiation. Tamm was one of the theoretical physicists who contributed to the construction of the first Soviet thermonuclear bomb.Tamm's father was an engineer in the city of Yelizavetgrad (now Kirovohrad, Ukr.), where he was responsible for building and managing electric power stations and water systems. Tamm graduated from the gymnasium there in 1913 and went abroad to study at the University of Edinburgh. The following year he returned to Moscow State...
</Question>
<Choice>Tamm, Igor Yevgenyevich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American radio astronomer and physicist who, with Russell A. Hulse, was the corecipient of the 1993 Nobel Prize for Physics for their joint discovery of the first binary pulsar.Taylor studied at Haverford College, Pa. (B.A., 1963), and earned a Ph.D. in astronomy at Harvard University in 1968. He taught at the University of Massachusetts, Amherst, from 1969 to 1981 and then joined the faculty at Princeton University, where he became the James S. McDonnell professor of physics in 1986.Taylor and Hulse conducted their prizewinning research on pulsars while Taylor was a professor at Amherst and H...
</Question>
<Choice>Taylor, Joseph H., Jr.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Canadian physicist who in 1990 shared the Nobel Prize for Physics with Jerome Friedman and Henry Kendall for his collaboration in proving the existence of quarks, which are now generally accepted as being among the basic building blocks of matter.Taylor attended the University of Alberta, where he received his bachelor's degree (1950) and his master's degree (1952). He received his doctorate from Stanford University in 1962. He worked for a year at the University of California's Lawrence Berkeley Laboratory, and from 1962 to 1968 he was a staff member at the Stanford Linear Accelerator Center...
</Question>
<Choice>Taylor, Richard E.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hungarian-born American nuclear physicist who participated in the production of the first atomic bomb (1945) and who led the development of the world's first thermonuclear weapon, the hydrogen bomb.Teller was from a family of prosperous Hungarian Jews. After attending schools in Budapest, he earned a degree in chemical engineering at the Institute of Technology in Karlsruhe, Germany. He then went to Munich and Leipzig to earn a Ph.D. in physical chemistry (1930). His doctoral thesis, on the hydrogen molecular ion, helped lay the foundation for a theory of molecular orbitals that remains widely...
</Question>
<Choice>Teller, Edward</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physicist and historian of science known for contributions in electrical machinery, optics, and X rays.He received both a B.A. (1869) and a D.Sc. (1878) from the University of London and was a popular teacher at University College, Bristol (1876–85), and at the City and Guilds Technical College, Finsbury (1885–1916). While teaching, Thompson contributed to the development of electric dynamo machines and radiotelegraphy.Thompson was a prolific lecturer and writer on a wide range of scientific and technical subjects. Among his many works were Elementary Lessons in Electricity and Magneti...
</Question>
<Choice>Thompson, Silvanus Phillips</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American-born British physicist, government administrator, and a founder of the Royal Institution of Great Britain, London. His investigations of heat overturned the theory that heat is a liquid form of matter and established the beginnings of the modern theory that heat is a form of motion.In 1772 Thompson married a wealthy widow, Sarah Walker, and lived in Rumford (now Concord), N.H. Loyal to the British crown, he served as a spy after the outbreak of the American Revolution, but in 1776 he was forced to flee to London, leaving his wife and daughter behind. There he served for a time as a go...
</Question>
<Choice>Thompson, Sir Benjamin, Graf von Rumford</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physicist who was the joint recipient, with Clinton J. Davisson of the United States, of the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1937 for demonstrating that electrons undergo diffraction, a behaviour peculiar to waves that is widely exploited in determining the atomic structure of solids and liquids.The only son of the noted physicist Sir J.J. Thomson, he worked in the Cavendish Laboratory at Cambridge University after World War I. In 1922 he was appointed professor of natural philosophy at the University of Aberdeen, Scot., where he conducted experiments demonstrating that a beam of electrons...
</Question>
<Choice>Thomson, Sir George Paget</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physicist who helped revolutionize the knowledge of atomic structure by his discovery of the electron (1897). He received the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1906 and was knighted in 1908.
</Question>
<Choice>Thomson, Sir J. J.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist who shared in the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1976 for his discovery of a new subatomic particle, the J/psi particle.The son of a Chinese college professor who was studying in the United States when Ting was born, he was raised in mainland China and Taiwan and at the age of 20 immigrated to the United States. He was educated at the University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, where he received his doctorate in 1962. Ting taught briefly at Columbia University and was group leader at a nuclear facility at Hamburg, W.Ger., before joining the faculty of the Massachusetts Institute of Techn...
</Question>
<Choice>Ting, Samuel C. C.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Prussian astronomer, physicist, and biologist whose law (1766) expressing the distances between the planets and the Sun was popularized by German astronomer Johann Elert Bode in 1772.Having received a degree from the University of Leipzig (1752), Titius joined the faculty of the University of Wittenberg in 1756. Titius proposed his law of planetary distances in an unsigned interpolation in his German translation of Swiss philosopher Charles Bonnet'sContemplation de la nature (“Contemplation of Nature”). Titius fixed the scale by assigning 100 to the distance of Saturn from the Sun. On this sca...
</Question>
<Choice>Titius, Johann Daniel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese physicist, joint winner, with Richard P. Feynman and Julian S. Schwinger of the United States, of the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1965 for developing basic principles of quantum electrodynamics.Tomonaga became professor of physics at Bunrika University (later Tokyo University of Education) in 1941, the year he began his investigations of the problems of quantum electrodynamics. World War II isolated him from Western scientists, but in 1943 he completed and published his research. Tomonaga's theoretical work made quantum electrodynamics (the theory of the interactions of charged subatom...
</Question>
<Choice>Tomonaga Shin'ichiro</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian physicist and mathematician who invented the barometer and whose work in geometry aided in the eventual development of integral calculus. Inspired by Galileo's writings, he wrote a treatise on mechanics, De Motu (“Concerning Movement”), which impressed Galileo. In 1641 Torricelli was invited to Florence, where he served the elderly astronomer as secretary and assistant during the last three months of Galileo's life. Torricelli was then appointed to succeed him as professor of mathematics at the Florentine Academy.Two years later, pursuing a suggestion by Galileo, he filled a glass tube...
</Question>
<Choice>Torricelli, Evangelista</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist, joint winner with the Soviet physicists Aleksandr M. Prokhorov and Nikolay G. Basov of the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1964 for his role in the invention of the maser and the laser.Townes studied at Furman University (B.A., B.S., 1935), Duke University (M.A., 1937), and the California Institute of Technology (Ph.D., 1939). In 1939 he joined the technical staff of Bell Telephone Laboratories, Inc., where he worked until 1948, when he joined the faculty of Columbia University. Three years later he conceived the idea of using ammonia molecules to amplify microwave radiation. To...
</Question>
<Choice>Townes, Charles Hard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physicist who pioneered in the study of electrical conduction in gases and made the first direct measurement of the unit electrical charge (e).In 1895 he entered Trinity College, Cambridge, becoming a research student at the Cavendish Laboratory under J.J. Thomson. In 1899 he became a fellow of Trinity College and the following year was appointed the first Wykeham Professor of Experimental Physics at Oxford University.In 1897 Townsend developed the falling-drop method for measuring e. His procedure, which used saturated clouds of water, was later improved and ultimately led to the high...
</Question>
<Choice>Townsend, Sir John Sealy Edward</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese-born American physicist who, with Horst L. Störmer and Robert B. Laughlin, received the 1998 Nobel Prize for Physics for the discovery that the electrons in a powerful magnetic field at very low temperatures can form a quantum fluid whose particles have fractional electric charges. This effect is known as the fractional quantum Hall effect.Tsui graduated from Augustana College, Rock Island, Illinois, in 1961, and he obtained a Ph.D in physics from the University of Chicago in 1967. He then joined the research staff at Bell Laboratories (Murray Hill, New Jersey), where he and Störmer ma...
</Question>
<Choice>Tsui, Daniel C.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American research physicist and geophysicist who developed the radio-wave exploration method for the ionosphere. The observations he made provided the theoretical foundation for the development of radar.With the American physicist Gregory Breit, Tuve in 1925 succeeded in measuring the height of the Earth's ionosphere by bouncing short-pulse radio waves off its ionized layer of air and determining the amount of time taken by the echoes to return. In 1926 Tuve investigated long-range seismic refraction (change in the path through the Earth of a disturbance as it passes through material of varyin...
</Question>
<Choice>Tuve, Merle Antony</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British experimental physicist who was an avid promoter of science in the Victorian era.Tyndall was born into a poor Protestant Irish family. After a thorough basic education he worked as a surveyor in Ireland and England (1839–47). When his ambitions turned from engineering to science, Tyndall spent his savings on gaining a Ph.D. from the University of Marburg, Germany (1848–50), but then struggled to find employment.In 1853 Tyndall was appointed professor of natural philosophy at the Royal Institution, London. There he became a friend of the much-admired physicist and chemist Michael Faraday...
</Question>
<Choice>Tyndall, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch-American physicist who, with Samuel A. Goudsmit, proposed the concept of electron spin.In 1925, while working on his Ph.D. at the University of Leiden, Neth. (1927), he and Goudsmit put forth their idea of electron spin after ascertaining that electrons rotate about an axis. Uhlenbeck joined the physics department at the University of Michigan, U.S., in 1927, returned to The Netherlands, as professor at the State University at Utrecht, and then became full professor at the University of Michigan in 1939. From 1943 to 1945 he worked at the Radiation Laboratory of the Massachusetts Institu...
</Question>
<Choice>Uhlenbeck, George Eugene</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American mathematician and physicist who, as assistant to Thomas Edison, contributed to the development of the American electric industry.Upton studied at Bowdoin College, Brunswick, Maine; Princeton University; and—with Hermann von Helmholtz—Berlin University. In 1878 he joined Edison at his laboratory in Menlo Park, N.J. There he worked out mathematical problems arising during the development of such devices as the incandescent lamp, the watt-hour meter, and large dynamos. He was a partner and general manager of the Edison Lamp Works, established in 1880.Upton also helped Edison publicize hi...
</Question>
<Choice>Upton, Francis Robbins</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist, whose discovery of the Van Allen radiation belts, two zones of radiation encircling Earth, brought about new understanding of cosmic radiation and its effects on Earth.Van Allen attended Iowa Wesleyan College (B.S., 1935) and the University of Iowa (M.S., 1936; Ph.D., 1939). During World War II he served as a naval officer and helped develop the radio proximity fuse for naval artillery shells. In 1946 he was placed in charge of high altitude research at the Applied Physics Laboratory of Johns Hopkins University, Silver Spring, Md. He supervised the testing and use of captur...
</Question>
<Choice>Van Allen, James A.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist and mathematician who shared the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1977 with Philip W. Anderson and Sir Nevill F. Mott. The prize honoured Van Vleck's contributions to the understanding of the behaviour of electrons in magnetic, noncrystalline solid materials.Educated at the University of Wisconsin, Madison, and at Harvard University, where he received his Ph.D. in 1922, Van Vleck joined the faculty of the University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, in 1924. He taught at Wisconsin from 1928 to 1934, and he then went to Harvard, where he eventually served as chairman of the physics depart...
</Question>
<Choice>Van Vleck, John H.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch physicist, corecipient with Gerardus 't Hooft of the 1999 Nobel Prize for Physics for their development of a method of mathematically predicting the properties of both the subatomic particles that make up the universe and the fundamental forces through which they interact. Their work led to the discovery of a new subatomic particle, the topquark.In 1963 Veltman received a doctorate in physics at the University of Utrecht and three years later joined the school's faculty. In 1981 he moved to the United States to teach at the University of Michigan, Ann Arbor, where he became professor eme...
</Question>
<Choice>Veltman, Martinus J. G.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physicist who at Mont Blanc in the French-Swiss Alps made the first high-altitude determination of the solar constant (1875). A graduate of the École Normale Supérieure at Paris, he taught at the University of Lyon (1883), then at the École and, from 1891, at the Conservatoire des Arts et Métiers, Paris.Violle also determined the fusion points of palladium, platinum, and gold. His interest in high-temperature radiation led to his proposing the photometric unit, violle, or Violle's standard. He was also interested in the theory of geysers, the origin of hail, and atmospheric exploration...
</Question>
<Choice>Violle, Jules-Louis-Gabriel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian physicist whose invention of the electric battery provided the first source of continuous current.In 1775 Volta's interest in electricity led him to invent the electrophorus, a device used to generate static electricity. He became professor of physics at the Royal School of Como in 1774 and discovered and isolated methane gas in 1778. One year later he was appointed to the chair of physics at the University of Pavia.In 1780 Volta's friend Luigi Galvani discovered that contact of two different metals with the muscle of a frog resulted in the generation of an electric current. Volta bega...
</Question>
<Choice>Volta, Conte Alessandro</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch physicist, winner of the 1910 Nobel Prize for Physics for his research on the gaseous and liquid states of matter. His work made the study of temperatures near absolute zero possible.A self-educated man who took advantage of the opportunities offered by the University of Leiden, van der Waals first attracted notice in 1873 with his doctoral treatise “On the Continuity of the Liquid and Gaseous State,” for which he was awarded a doctorate. In pursuing his research, he knew that the ideal-gas law could be derived from the kinetic theory of gases if it could be assumed that gas molecules ha...
</Question>
<Choice>Waals, Johannes Diederik van der</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Irish physicist, corecipient, with Sir John Douglas Cockcroft of England, of the 1951 Nobel Prize for Physics for the development of the first nuclear particle accelerator, known as the Cockcroft-Walton generator.After studying at the Methodist College, Belfast, and graduating in mathematics and experimental science from Trinity College, Dublin (1926), Walton went in 1927 to Trinity College, Cambridge, where he was to work with Cockcroft in the Cavendish Laboratory under Lord Rutherford until 1934. In 1928 he attempted two methods of high-energy particle acceleration. Both failed, mainly becau...
</Question>
<Choice>Walton, Ernest Thomas Sinton</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish physicist credited with the development of radar in England.Watson-Watt attended the University of St. Andrews and later taught at University College, Dundee. From 1915 to 1952 he held a number of government positions, beginning as a meteorologist working on devices for locating thunderstorms. In early February 1935, while heading the radio department of the National Physical Laboratory, he wrote a memorandum to the British government in which he explained how radio waves could be used to detect aircraft. He quickly followed with an experimental demonstration. By July 1935 Watson-Watt...
</Question>
<Choice>Watson-Watt, Sir Robert Alexander</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist who, with his friend Carl Friedrich Gauss, investigated terrestrial magnetism and in 1833 devised an electromagnetic telegraph. The magnetic unit, termed a weber, formerly the coulomb, is named after him.Weber was educated at Halle and later at Göttingen, where he was appointed professor of physics in 1831. He was professor at the University of Leipzig from 1843 to 1849, and he then returned to Göttingen and became director of the astronomical observatory there. He played an important role in the development of electrical science, particularly by his work to establish a system...
</Question>
<Choice>Weber, Wilhelm Eduard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American nuclear physicist who in 1979 shared the Nobel Prize for Physics with Sheldon Lee Glashow and Abdus Salam (qq.v.) for work in formulating the electroweak theory, which explains the unity of electromagnetism with the weak nuclear force.Weinberg and Glashow were members of the same classes at the Bronx High School of Science, New York City (1950), and Cornell University (1954). Weinberg went from Cornell to the Nordic Institute for Theoretical Atomic Physics in Copenhagen for a year and then obtained his doctorate at Princeton University in 1957.Weinberg proposed his version of the elec...
</Question>
<Choice>Weinberg, Steven</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physicist who investigated magnetism and determined the Weiss magneton unit of magnetic moment.Weiss graduated (1887) at the head of his class from the Zürich Polytechnikum with a degree in mechanical engineering and was admitted to the École Normale Supérieure in Paris in 1888. He was named maître de conférences at the University of Rennes in 1895 and at the University of Lyons in 1899. In 1902 he became professor at the Zürich Polytechnikum, where Albert Einstein was a colleague. There he developed a great laboratory for magnetic research that attracted a number of well-known physicis...
</Question>
<Choice>Weiss, Pierre-Ernest</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German American mathematician who, through his widely varied contributions in mathematics, served as a link between pure mathematics and theoretical physics, in particular adding enormously to quantum mechanics and the theory of relativity.As a student at the University of Göttingen (graduated 1908), Weyl came under the influence of David Hilbert. In 1913 he became professor of mathematics at the Technische Hochschule, Zürich, where he was a colleague of Albert Einstein. The outstanding characteristic of Weyl's work was his ability to unite previously unrelated subjects. In Die Idee der Rieman...
</Question>
<Choice>Weyl, Hermann</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physicist who popularized the Wheatstone bridge, a device that accurately measured electrical resistance and became widely used in laboratories.Wheatstone was appointed professor of experimental philosophy at King's College, London, in 1834, the same year that he used a revolving mirror in an experiment to measure the speed of electricity in a conductor. The same revolving mirror, by his suggestion, was later used in measurements of the speed of light. Three years later, with Sir William Fothergill Cooke of England, he patented an early telegraph. In 1843, he brought to notice the Whea...
</Question>
<Choice>Wheatstone, Sir Charles</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
physicist, the first American involved in the theoretical development of the atomic bomb. He also originated a novel approach to the unified field theory and came up with the term black hole.Wheeler, who was the son of librarians, first became interested in science as a boy reading scientific articles. He was educated at Baltimore City College and Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, Md., where he received his doctorate in 1933. He also studied with Niels Bohr at the University of Copenhagen. He and Bohr wrote “The Mechanism of Nuclear Fission” (1939), a seminal treatise that singled out urani...
</Question>
<Choice>Wheeler, John Archibald</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist who, with Eric A. Cornell and Wolfgang Ketterle, won the Nobel Prize for Physics in 2001 for creating a new ultracold state of matter, the so-called Bose-Einstein condensate (BEC).After studying at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (B.S., 1973), Wieman earned a Ph.D. from Stanford University in 1977. He then taught and conducted research at the University of Michigan in Ann Arbor until 1984, when he joined the faculty at the University of Colorado.Wieman's work on the Bose-Einstein condensate began in the late 1980s. This new state of matter, which had been predicted...
</Question>
<Choice>Wieman, Carl E.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physicist who received the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1911 for his displacement law concerning the radiation emitted by the perfectly efficient blackbody (a surface that absorbs all radiant energy falling on it).Wien obtained his doctorate at the University of Berlin in 1886 and soon began to work on the problem of radiation. Although the radiation emitted from a blackbody is distributed over a wide range of wavelengths, there is an intermediate wavelength at which the radiation reaches a maximum. In 1893 Wien stated in his law that this maximum wavelength is inversely proportional to t...
</Question>
<Choice>Wien, Wilhelm</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hungarian-born American physicist, joint winner, with J. Hans D. Jensen of West Germany and Maria Goeppert Mayer of the United States, of the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1963. He received the prize for his many contributions to nuclear physics, which include his formulation of the law of conservation of parity.Wigner studied chemical engineering and received his Ph.D. from the Institute of Technology in Berlin in 1925. After serving as a lecturer there and at the University of Göttingen, he went to the United States. Apart from two years (1936–38) as professor of physics at the University of Wi...
</Question>
<Choice>Wigner, Eugene Paul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist who, with David J. Gross and H. David Politzer, was awarded the Nobel Prize for Physics in 2004 for discoveries regarding the strong force—the nuclear force that binds together quarks (the smallest building blocks of matter) and holds together the nucleus of the atom.After graduating from the University of Chicago (B.S., 1970), Wilczek studied under Gross at Princeton University, earning an M.S. in mathematics (1972) and a Ph.D. in physics (1974). He later served on the faculty at Princeton (1974–81) and taught at the University of California, Santa Barbara (1980–88). In 198...
</Question>
<Choice>Wilczek, Frank</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish physicist who, with Arthur H. Compton, received the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1927 for his invention of the Wilson cloud chamber, which became widely used in the study of radioactivity, X rays, cosmic rays, and other nuclear phenomena.Wilson began studying clouds as a meteorologist in 1895. In an effort to duplicate the effects of certain clouds on mountaintops, he devised a way of expanding moist air in a closed container. The expansion cooled the air so that it became supersaturated and moisture condensed on dust particles.Wilson noted that when he used dust-free air the air remain...
</Question>
<Choice>Wilson, C. T. R.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist who was awarded the 1982 Nobel Prize for Physics for his development of a general procedure for constructing improved theories concerning the transformations of matter called continuous, or second-order, phase transitions.Wilson graduated from Harvard University in 1956. In 1961 he received a Ph.D. from the California Institute of Technology, where he completed a dissertation under Murray Gell-Mann (winner of the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1969) and Francis Low. After a year at the European Council for Nuclear Research, Wilson was appointed assistant professor at Cornell Uni...
</Question>
<Choice>Wilson, Kenneth Geddes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American radio astronomer who shared, with Arno Penzias, the 1978 Nobel Prize for Physics for a discovery that supported the big-bang model of creation. (Soviet physicist Pyotr Leonidovich Kapitsa also shared the award, for unrelated research.)Educated at Rice University in Houston and the California Institute of Technology in Pasadena, where he received his doctorate in 1962, Wilson then worked (1963–76) at the Bell Telephone Laboratories at Holmdel, New Jersey, where, in collaboration with Penzias, he began monitoring radio emissions from a ring of gas encircling the Milky Way Galaxy. The tw...
</Question>
<Choice>Wilson, Robert Woodrow</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. physicist who extended the technique of Raman spectroscopy, a useful method of studying matter by analyzing the light scattered by it.In 1897 Wood was the first to observe field emission, charged particles emitted from a conductor in an electric field. This electrical phenomenon is used in the field-emission microscope for studying atomic structure. From 1901 he was at Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, Md., as professor and, later, research professor of experimental physics. In addition to his fundamental discoveries in physical optics, he introduced improvements in the ruling of close...
</Question>
<Choice>Wood, Robert Williams</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese-born American physicist who provided the first experimental proof that the principle of parity conservation does not hold in weak subatomic interactions.Wu graduated from the National Central University in Nanking, China, in 1936 and then traveled to the United States to pursue graduate studies in physics at the University of California at Berkeley, studying under Ernest O. Lawrence. After receiving a Ph.D. in 1940, she taught at Smith College and at Princeton University. In 1944 she undertook work on radiation detection in the Division of War Research at Columbia University. Remaining...
</Question>
<Choice>Wu, Chien-Shiung</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American research scientist, a pioneer in the application of X-ray methods to determine crystal structures and one of the first to use these methods for studying biological substances.Wyckoff was educated at Cornell University and was an instructor in analytical chemistry from 1917 to 1919. He subsequently worked in the Geophysical Laboratory of the Carnegie Institute of Washington (1919–27). From 1927 to 1937 he was associated with the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research, after which he joined Lederle Laboratories and then Reichel Laboratories. He subsequently worked for the U.S. Publi...
</Question>
<Choice>Wyckoff, Ralph Walter Graystone</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American medical physicist and joint recipient (with Andrew V. Schally and Roger Guillemin) of the 1977 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine, awarded for her development of the radioimmunoassay (RIA), an extremely sensitive technique for measuring minute quantities of biologically active substances.Yalow graduated with honours from Hunter College of the City University of New York in 1941 and four years later received her Ph.D. in physics from the University of Illinois. From 1946 to 1950 she lectured on physics at Hunter, and in 1947 she became a consultant in nuclear physics to the Bronx V...
</Question>
<Choice>Yalow, Rosalyn S.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese-born American theoretical physicist whose research with Tsung-Dao Lee showed that parity—the symmetry between physical phenomena occurring in right-handed and left-handed coordinate systems—is violated when certain elementary particles decay. Until this discovery it had been assumed by physicists that parity symmetry is as universal a law as the conservation of energy or electric charge. This and other studies in particle physics earned Yang and Lee the Nobel Prize for Physics for 1957.
</Question>
<Choice>Yang, Chen Ning</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physician and physicist who established the principle of interference of light and thus resurrected the century-old wave theory of light. He was also an Egyptologist who helped decipher the Rosetta Stone (see).In 1799 Young set up a medical practice in London. His primary interest was in sense perception, and, while still a medical student, he had discovered the way in which the lens of the eye changes shape to focus on objects at differing distances. He discovered the cause of astigmatism in 1801, the same year he turned to the study of light.By allowing light to pass through two clos...
</Question>
<Choice>Young, Thomas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese physicist and recipient of the 1949 Nobel Prize for Physics for research on the theory of elementary particles.Yukawa graduated from Kyoto Imperial University (now Kyoto University) in 1929 and became a lecturer there; in 1933 he moved to Osaka Imperial University (now Osaka University), where he earned his doctorate in 1938. He rejoined Kyoto Imperial University as a professor of theoretical physics (1939–50), held faculty appointments at the Institute for Advanced Study in Princeton, New Jersey (U.S.), and at Columbia University in New York City, and became director of the Research...
</Question>
<Choice>Yukawa Hideki</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch physicist who shared with Hendrik A. Lorentz the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1902 for his discovery of the Zeeman effect (q.v.).Zeeman, who had been a student of Lorentz at the University of Leiden, began lecturing at Leiden in 1890. Six years later, at the suggestion of Lorentz, he investigated the effect of magnetic fields on a source of light and found that each of the lines in the spectrum of emitted light split into several lines; this became known as the Zeeman effect. Zeeman was appointed professor of physics at the University of Amsterdam in 1900 and director of its Physical Insti...
</Question>
<Choice>Zeeman, Pieter</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch physicist, winner of the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1953 for his invention of the phase-contrastmicroscope, an instrument that permits the study of internal cell structure without the need to stain and thus kill the cells.Zernike obtained a doctorate from the University of Amsterdam in 1915. He became an assistant at the State University of Groningen in 1913 and served as a full professor there from 1920 to 1958. His earliest work in optics was concerned with astronomical telescopes. While studying the flaws that occur in some diffraction gratings because of the imperfect spacing of engr...
</Question>
<Choice>Zernike, Frits</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss astronomer and physicist who made valuable contributions to the theory and understanding of supernovas (stars that for a short time are far brighter than normal).Zwicky received a doctorate in physics (1922) from the Swiss Federal Institute of Technology, Zürich, and served on the faculty of the California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, from 1925 to 1972.During the early 1930s Zwicky contributed substantially to the physics of the solid state, gaseous ionization, and thermodynamics but soon turned to the study of supernovas, novas, and cosmic rays. In 1933 he discovered the existence...
</Question>
<Choice>Zwicky, Fritz</Choice>
</item>
</topics>