<topics>
<item>
<Question>
American pharmacologist and physiological chemist who made important contributions to a modern understanding of the ductless, or endocrine, glands. He isolated adrenaline in the form of a chemical derivative (1897) and crystallized insulin (1926). He also invented a primitive artificial kidney.Abel taught at the University of Michigan, Ann Arbor (1891–93), and at Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore (1893), and directed the Laboratory for Endocrine Research (1932). He also helped found and edit several important scientific periodicals, including the Journal of Pharmacology and Experimental Ther...
</Question>
<Choice>Abel, John Jacob</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
clinician noted for his contributions to the knowledge of heart disease and gout. In 1827 he described a condition characterized by a very slow pulse and by transient giddiness or convulsive seizures, now known as the Stokes-Adams disease or syndrome.Educated at Trinity College, Dublin, Adams studied medicine in Europe and then returned to Dublin, where he established his practice and served as surgeon to the Jervis Street and Richmond hospitals. In 1861 he was appointed surgeon to the queen in Ireland and regius professor of surgery at the University of Dublin.
</Question>
<Choice>Adams, Robert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physician after whom Addison's disease, a metabolic dysfunction caused by atrophy of the adrenal cortex, and Addison's (pernicious) anemia were named. He was the first to correlate a set of disease symptoms with pathological changes in one of the endocrine glands.In 1837 Addison became a full physician at Guy's Hospital, London, and a joint lecturer on medicine with Richard Bright, with whom he wrote Elements of the Practice of Medicine (1839). He gave a preliminary account in 1849 of the two diseases named after him and in 1855 wrote On the Constitutional and Local Effects of Disease...
</Question>
<Choice>Addison, Thomas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
physician, pathologist, and bacteriologist, a member of the Reed Yellow Fever Board of the U.S. Army that discovered (1901) the role of the mosquito in the transmission of yellow fever.Agramonte was the son of a prominent physician who had been killed while serving in the Cuban Army of Liberation. Brought up in New York City, Agramonte received his M.D. in 1892 from the College of Physicians and Surgeons of Columbia University. After he had served his internship, he conducted research in pathology and bacteriology at Bellevue Hospital and with the New York City Department of Health. He was app...
</Question>
<Choice>Agramonte y Simoni, Aristides</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German scholar and scientist known as “the father of mineralogy.” While a highly educated classicist and humanist, well regarded by scholars of his own and later times, he was yet singularly independent of the theories of ancient authorities. He was indeed among the first to found a natural science upon observation, as opposed to speculation. His De re metallica dealt chiefly with the arts of mining and smelting; his De natura fossilium, considered the first mineralogy textbook, presented the first scientific classification of minerals (based on their physical properties) and described many ne...
</Question>
<Choice>Agricola, Georgius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek philosopher and physiologist of the academy at Croton (now Crotone, southern Italy), the first person recorded to have practiced dissection of human bodies for research purposes. He may also have been the first to attempt vivisection. Alcmaeon inferred that the brain was the centre of intelligence and that the soul was the source of life. Applying the Pythagorean principle of cosmic harmony between pairs of contraries, he posited that health consists in the isonomy (equilibrium) of the body's component contraries (e.g., dry-humid, warm-cold, sweet-bitter), thus anticipating Hippocrates'...
</Question>
<Choice>Alcmaeon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Renaissance naturalist and physician noted for his systematic and accurate observations of animals, plants, and minerals.After studying mathematics, Latin, law, and philosophy, Aldrovandi went to Padua in about 1545 to continue his studies. There he began to study medicine, the field in which he eventually earned a degree in 1553. On his return to Bologna in 1549 he was arrested, charged with heresy, and sent to Rome, where he was able to exonerate himself, probably in part because of his noble parentage. Returning to the University of Bologna, he was made a full professor in 1561 as a result...
</Question>
<Choice>Aldrovandi, Ulisse</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physician, the inventor of the short clinical thermometer. His investigations also led to the improved treatment of arterial diseases.During a 28-year practice in Leeds, Allbutt made valuable clinical studies, primarily of arterial and nervous disorders. In 1866 he introduced the modern clinical thermometer, a welcome alternative to the foot-long instrument that required 20 minutes to register a patient's temperature. In 1871 he published a monograph outlining use of the ophthalmoscope (used to inspect the interior of the eye) as a diagnostic instrument. In 1892 Allbutt became regius p...
</Question>
<Choice>Allbutt, Sir Thomas Clifford</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
physician and botanist who is credited with the introduction to Europe of coffee and bananas. While a medical adviser to Giorgio Emo, the Venetian consul in Cairo (1580–83), Alpini made an extensive study of Egyptian and Mediterranean flora. He is reputed to have been the first to fertilize date palms artificially.Alpini was appointed professor of botany at the University of Padua (1593), where he cultivated several species of Oriental plants described in his De plantis Aegypti liber (1592; “Book of Egyptian Plants”). Included in this work were the first European botanical accounts of coffee,...
</Question>
<Choice>Alpini, Prospero</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physician who advocated the admission of women to professional education, especially in medicine.Refused admission to medical schools, Anderson began in 1860 to study privately with accredited physicians and in London hospitals and was licensed to practice in 1865 by the Society of Apothecaries. She was appointed (1866) general medical attendant to the Marylebone Dispensary, later the New Hospital for Women, where she worked to create a medical school for women. In 1918 the hospital was renamed Elizabeth Garrett Anderson Hospital in her honour.Anderson received the M.D. degree from the...
</Question>
<Choice>Anderson, Elizabeth Garrett</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician, anesthesiologist, and medical researcher who developed the Apgar Score System, a method of evaluating an infant shortly after birth to assess its well-being and to determine if any immediate medical intervention is required.Apgar graduated from Mount Holyoke College in 1929 and from the Columbia University College of Physicians and Surgeons in 1933. After an internship at Presbyterian Hospital, New York City, she held residencies in the relatively new specialty of anesthesiology at the University of Wisconsin and then at Bellevue Hospital, New York City, in 1935–37. In 1937...
</Question>
<Choice>Apgar, Virginia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss microbiologist, corecipient with Daniel Nathans and Hamilton Othanel Smith (qq.v.) of the United States of the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for 1978. All three were cited for their work in molecular genetics, specifically the discovery and application of enzymes that break the giant molecules of deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) into manageable pieces, small enough to be separated for individual study but large enough to retain bits of the genetic information inherent in the sequence of units that make up the original substance.Arber studied at the Swiss Federal Institute of Technolo...
</Question>
<Choice>Arber, Werner</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek physician from Cappadocia who practiced in Rome and Alexandria, led a revival of Hippocrates' teachings, and is thought to have ranked second only to the father of medicine himself in the application of keen observation and ethics to the art. In principle he adhered to the pneumatic school of medicine, which believed that health was maintained by “vital air,” or pneuma. Pneumatists felt that an imbalance of the four humours—blood, phlegm, choler (yellow bile), and melancholy (black bile)—disturbed the pneuma, a condition indicated by an abnormal pulse. In practice, however, Aretaeus was...
</Question>
<Choice>Aretaeus of Cappadocia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek physician who established Greek medicine in Rome. His influence continued until Galen began to practice medicine in Rome in AD 164.He opposed the humoral doctrine of Hippocrates and instead taught that disease results from constricted or relaxed conditions of the solid particles, a doctrine derived from the atomic theory of the 5th-century philosopher Democritus. Asclepiades believed that harmony would be restored through fresh air, light, appropriate diet, hydrotherapy, massage, and exercise. A pioneer in the humane treatment of mental disorders, he had insane persons freed from confine...
</Question>
<Choice>Asclepiades of Bithynia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian physician who contributed to the knowledge of the circulation of body fluids by discovering the lacteal vessels.Aselli became professor of anatomy and surgery at the University of Pavia and practiced at Milan. His discovery of the lacteals (lymph vessels that take up the end products of fat digestion from the intestine) occurred in 1622 during the vivisection of a dog that had been richly fed just prior to the operation. On opening the abdomen, he noticed whitish cords that exuded a creamlike liquid. Upon careful repetition of the experiment, he described these new vessels as venae alb...
</Question>
<Choice>Aselli, Gaspare</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
physician who devised the diagnostic technique of percussion (the art of striking a surface part of the body with short, sharp taps to diagnose the condition of the parts beneath the sound). In 1761, after seven years of investigation, he published a description of the method in his book Inventum Novum. Although a few doctors began to use Auenbrugger's techniques, it was not until a French translation by Jean-Nicolas Corvisart des Marest, personal physician to Napoleon, appeared in 1808 that the diagnostic method gained worldwide acceptance. It remains an important procedure in bedside diagnos...
</Question>
<Choice>Auenbrugger von Auenbrugg, Leopold</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
influential Islamic religious philosopher who integrated Islamic traditions with ancient Greek thought. At the request of the Almohad caliph Abu Ya?qub Yusuf, he produced a series of summaries and commentaries on most of Aristotle's works (1169–95) and on Plato'sRepublic, which exerted considerable influence in both the Islamic world and Europe for centuries. He wrote the Decisive Treatise on the Agreement Between Religious Law and Philosophy (Fa?l al-Ma?al), Examination of the Methods of Proof Concerning the Doctrines of Religion (Kashf al-Manahij), and The Incoherence of the Incoherence (Tah...
</Question>
<Choice>Averroes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Iranian physician, the most famous and influential of the philosopher-scientists of Islam. He was particularly noted for his contributions in the fields of Aristotelian philosophy and medicine. He composed the Kitab al-shifa? (“Book of Healing”), a vast philosophical and scientific encyclopaedia, and The Canon of Medicine, which is among the most famous books in the history of medicine.
</Question>
<Choice>Avicenna</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American scientist who, with Linda B. Buck, won the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 2004 for pioneering research on the olfactory system.Axel received an A.B. (1967) from Columbia University and an M.D. (1970) from Johns Hopkins University School of Medicine. In 1978 he became a member of the pathology and biochemistry faculty at Columbia, where in the early 1980s Buck worked under him as a postdoctoral student. Axel joined the Howard Hughes Medical Institute (HHMI) as an investigator in 1984.In 1991 Buck and Axel jointly published their seminal paper, based on research they had cond...
</Question>
<Choice>Axel, Richard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biochemist and pharmacologist who, along with the British biophysicist Sir Bernard Katz and the Swedish physiologist Ulf von Euler, was awarded the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1970. Axelrod's contribution was his identification of an enzyme that degrades chemical neurotransmitters within the nervous system after they are no longer needed to transmit nerve impulses.A graduate of the College of the City of New York (B.S., 1933), New York University (M.S., 1941), and George Washington University (Ph.D., 1955), Axelrod worked as a chemist in the Laboratory of Industrial Hygi...
</Question>
<Choice>Axelrod, Julius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
physician, founder of modern epidemiology, who revived Hippocratic medical practice in Renaissance Europe. Dean of the University of Paris medical faculty (1580), he compiled a clear account of epidemics between 1570 and 1579, the first comprehensive work of its kind since Hippocrates. He was probably the first to describe whooping cough (1578) and to define the term rheumatism in its modern sense. His descriptions of plague, diphtheria, and measles and works on epidemiology, especially Epidemiorum, 2 vol. (1640; “Of Epidemics”), may have influenced the great 17th-century Hippocratic physician...
</Question>
<Choice>Baillou, Guillaume de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
astronomer noted for his observations of comets.Bainbridge practiced medicine at Ashby-de-la-Zouch from 1614 to 1618. Soon after he moved to London, he was appointed (1619) Savilian professor of astronomy at the University of Oxford, largely on the basis of his Astronomical Description of the Comet of 1618 (1619). Although this work accepted to a point the superstitious belief that comets appear as signs of impending disaster, in Antiprognosticon (1642) he recanted and vigorously denounced astrological superstition that based predictions on conjunctions of the planets and appearances of comets...
</Question>
<Choice>Bainbridge, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician who contributed significantly to public health and child welfare in the United States.Baker prepared at private schools for Vassar College, but the death of her father put that school out of reach. She decided to study medicine and after a year of private preparation entered the Women's Medical College of the New York Infirmary in New York City. After graduating in 1898 she interned at the New England Hospital for Women and Children and then entered private practice in New York City.In 1901 Baker was appointed a medical inspector for the city health department, and in 1907 s...
</Question>
<Choice>Baker, Sara Josephine</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American virologist who shared the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1975 with Howard M. Temin and Renato Dulbecco. Working independently, Baltimore and Temin discovered reverse transcriptase, an enzyme that synthesizes DNA from RNA. Baltimore also conducted research that led to an understanding of the interaction between viruses and the genetic material of the cell. The research of all three men contributed to an understanding of the role of viruses in the development of cancer.Baltimore and Temin both studied the process by which certain tumour-causing RNA viruses (those whose geneti...
</Question>
<Choice>Baltimore, David</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Canadian physician who, with Charles H. Best, was the first to extract (1921) the hormone insulin from the pancreas. Injections of insulin proved to be the first effective treatment for diabetes, a disease in which glucose accumulates in abnormally high quantities in the blood. Banting was awarded a share of the 1923 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for his achievement.Banting was educated at the University of Toronto, served in World War I, and then practiced medicine in London, Ont. In 1889 Joseph von Mering and Oskar Minkowski had found that complete removal of the pancreas in dogs im...
</Question>
<Choice>Banting, Sir Frederick Grant</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian otologist who won the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1914 for his work on the physiology and pathology of the vestibular (balancing) apparatus of the inner ear.Bárány graduated in medicine from the University of Vienna in 1900. After study at German clinics he became assistant at the ear clinic of the University of Vienna and, in 1909, a lecturer on otological medicine. He devised new tests for detecting vestibular disease and for examining activities of the cerebellum and their relation to disturbances of equilibrium. Bárány served in the Austrian army in World War I and w...
</Question>
<Choice>Barany, Robert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Danish physician and theologian who wrote one of the most widely read Renaissance manuals of anatomy.At the University of Padua (1608–10) Bartholin conducted anatomical studies under the famed Italian anatomist Hieronymus Fabricius ab Aquapendente. These formed the basis for his manual Anatomicae Institutiones Corporis Humani (1611; “Textbook of Human Anatomy”). A professor at the University of Copenhagen (1613–29), he was first to describe the olfactory nerve (associated with the sense of smell) as the first cranial nerve.
</Question>
<Choice>Bartholin, Caspar Berthelsen</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physiologist, co-discoverer (with the British physiologist Ernest Starling) of hormones; he conducted pioneer research in major areas of physiology, biochemistry, and physical chemistry.Bayliss studied at University College, London, and Wadham College, Oxford. He began a long and profitable collaboration with Starling soon after he obtained a teaching post at University College, London (1888), where he became professor of general physiology (1912–24). Their study in the 1890s of nerve-controlled contraction and dilation of blood vessels resulted in the development of an improved hemopi...
</Question>
<Choice>Bayliss, Sir William Maddock</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German bacteriologist who was one of the founders of immunology. In 1901 he received the first Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for his work on serum therapy, particularly for its use in the treatment of diphtheria.Behring received his medical degree in 1878 from the Friedrich-Wilhelms-Institut, the Prussian army's medical college, in Berlin. After serving 10 years with the Army Medical Corps, he became an assistant (1889) at the Institute for Hygiene, Berlin, where Robert Koch was director. There, with the Japanese bacteriologist Kitasato Shibasaburo, he showed that it was possible to p...
</Question>
<Choice>Behring, Emil von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicist and physiologist who received the 1961 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for his discovery of the physical means by which sound is analyzed and communicated in the cochlea, a portion of the inner ear.As director of the Hungarian Telephone System Research Laboratory (1923–46), Békésy worked on problems of long-distance communication and became interested in the mechanics of human hearing. At the telephone laboratory, the University of Budapest (1939–46), the Karolinska Institute, Stockholm (1946–47), and Harvard University (1947–66) he conducted intensive research that l...
</Question>
<Choice>Bekesy, Georg von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
physician and anatomist who described the collecting, or excretory, tubules of the kidney, known as Bellini's ducts (tubules).In Exercitatio anatomica de structura et usu renum (1662; “Anatomical Exercise on the Structure and Function of the Kidney”), published when he was a 19-year-old student at the University of Pisa, Bellini showed for the first time that the kidney consists of an immense number of tiny canals. A professor at Pisa for 30 years, Bellini described the taste organs (1665) and stressed the value of urinalysis as an aid to diagnosis (1683). He was a pioneer in the attempt to ex...
</Question>
<Choice>Bellini, Lorenzo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Venezuelan-born American pathologist and immunologist who shared (with George Snell and Jean Dausset) the 1980 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for his discovery of genes that regulate immune responses and of the role that some of these genes play in autoimmune diseases.From the age of five until the outbreak of World War II, Benacerraf lived in Paris. In 1940 he entered Columbia University in New York City, from which he graduated in 1942. He became a naturalized U.S. citizen in 1943, while a student at the Medical College of Virginia in Richmond. After receiving his M.D. in 1945 and in...
</Question>
<Choice>Benacerraf, Baruj</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian physician and anatomist who was the first to describe the heart valves. He also was one of the first to illustrate medical works with drawings from nature.Berengario was a professor at the University of Bologna from 1502 to 1527. While there he became known for his use of mercurial ointment in the treatment of syphilis.
</Question>
<Choice>Berengario da Carpi, Jacopo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish biochemist, corecipient with fellow Swede Bengt Ingemar Samuelsson and Englishman John Robert Vane of the 1982 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine. All three were honoured for their isolation, identification, and analysis of prostaglandins, which are biochemical compounds that influence blood pressure, body temperature, allergic reactions, and other physiological phenomena in mammals. Bergström was the first to demonstrate the existence of more than one such compound and to determine the elemental compositions of two of them.Bergström was educated at the Karolïnska Institute in Stoc...
</Question>
<Choice>Bergstrom, Sune K.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physiologist known chiefly for his discoveries concerning the role of the pancreas in digestion, the glycogenic function of the liver, and the regulation of the blood supply by the vasomotor nerves. On a broader stage, Bernard played a role in establishing the principles of experimentation in the life sciences, advancing beyond the vitalism and indeterminism of earlier physiologists to become one of the founders of experimental medicine. His most seminal contribution was his concept of the internal environment of the organism, which led to the present understanding of homeostasis—i.e.,...
</Question>
<Choice>Bernard, Claude</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physiologist, politician, and diplomat, founder of modern aerospace medicine, whose research into the effects of air pressure on the body helped make possible the exploration of space and the ocean depths. While professor of physiology at the Sorbonne (1869–86), he found that the illness suffered by animals at high altitudes is caused mainly by the low oxygen content of the sparse atmosphere.Bert also made a study of decompression sickness, suffered by deep-sea divers (who know its agonizing pain as “the bends”) when they are brought too quickly to the surface from the great pressures o...
</Question>
<Choice>Bert, Paul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
physiologist who, with Sir Frederick Banting, was the first to obtain (1921) a pancreatic extract of insulin in a form that controlled diabetes in dogs. The successful use of insulin in treating human patients followed. But because Best did not receive his medical degree until 1925, he did not share the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine awarded to Banting and J.J.R. Macleod in 1923 for their role in the work. Best also discovered the vitamin choline and the enzyme histaminase. He was one of the first to introduce anticoagulants in treatment of thrombosis (blood clots).In May 1921, while s...
</Question>
<Choice>Best, Charles H.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-born American theoretical physicist who helped shape quantum physics and increased the understanding of the atomic processes responsible for the properties of matter and of the forces governing the structures of atomic nuclei. He received the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1967 for his work on the production of energy in stars. Moreover, he was a leader in emphasizing the social responsibility of science.
</Question>
<Choice>Bethe, Hans</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French anatomist and physiologist whose systematic study of human tissues helped found the science of histology.Bichat studied anatomy and surgery under Marc-Antoine Petit, chief surgeon at the Hôtel Dieu in Lyon. In 1793 he became a pupil, then assistant, of Pierre-Joseph Desault, surgeon and anatomist in Paris. After his teacher's death in 1795, Bichat completed the fourth volume of Desault's Journal de chirurgie, adding a biographical memoir of its author.In addition to his observations at the bedsides of patients at the Hôtel Dieu, Bichat studied the postmortem changes induced in various o...
</Question>
<Choice>Bichat, Marie-Francois-Xavier</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American surgeon and librarian whose organization of U.S. medical institutions played a central role in the modernization of hospital care and the maintenance of public health.Billings graduated from Miami University (Oxford, Ohio) in 1857 and from the Medical College of Ohio (Cincinnati) in 1860. During the American Civil War he served as a surgeon in the field and in hospitals until 1864.While on the staff of the U.S. surgeon general, Washington, D.C. (1864–95), Billings developed the library later known as the Army Medical Library. Under successive directors it grew into the Surgeon General...
</Question>
<Choice>Billings, John Shaw</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Persian scholar and scientist, one of the most learned men of his age and an outstanding intellectual figure.Possessing a profound and original mind of encyclopaedic scope, al-Biruni had varying degrees of proficiency in a number of languages, including Khwarezmian (an eastern Middle Iranian language), Persian, Sanskrit, Hebrew, and Syriac, in addition to the Arabic in which he wrote. He applied his talents in many fields of knowledge, excelling particularly in astronomy, mathematics, chronology, physics, medicine, and history. He corresponded with the great philosopher Ibn Sina (Avicenna). So...
</Question>
<Choice>Biruni, al-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American virologist and co-winner (with Harold Varmus) of the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1989 for achievements in clarifying the origins of cancer.Bishop graduated from Gettysburg College (Pa.) in 1957 and from Harvard Medical School in 1962. After spending two years in internship and residency at Massachusetts General Hospital, Boston, he became a researcher in virology at the National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, Md. In 1968 he joined the faculty of the University of California Medical Center in San Francisco, becoming a full professor in 1972. From 1981 he also served as d...
</Question>
<Choice>Bishop, J. Michael</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British pharmacologist who (along with George H. Hitchings and Gertrude B. Elion) received the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1988 for his development of two important drugs, propranolol and cimetidine.Black earned a medical degree from the University of St. Andrews in Scotland in 1946. He taught at various universities for the next 10 years and then joined Imperial Chemical Industries as a senior pharmacologist in 1958. He became head of biological research at Smith Kline &amp; French Laboratories in 1964, and he joined the Wellcome Research Laboratories as director of therapeutic...
</Question>
<Choice>Black, Sir James</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Anglo-American physician who is considered the first woman doctor of medicine in modern times.Elizabeth Blackwell was of a large, prosperous, and cultured family and was well educated by private tutors. Financial reverses and the family's liberal social and religious views prompted them to immigrate to the United States in the summer of 1832. Soon after taking up residence in New York, her father, Samuel Blackwell, became active in abolitionist activities. The Blackwells moved to Jersey City, New Jersey, in 1835 and to Cincinnati, Ohio, in 1838. Soon afterward Samuel Blackwell's death left the...
</Question>
<Choice>Blackwell, Elizabeth</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English-born American physician and educator who, with her elder sister, Elizabeth Blackwell, contributed greatly to the education and acceptance of women medical professionals in the United States.Like her sister, Emily was well educated by the private tutors afforded her by her affluent and cultivated family. She grew up in New York City, in Jersey City, New Jersey, and in Cincinnati, Ohio, and in 1848, following her sister's example, she began studying medicine. She was rejected by several medical schools, including the Geneva (New York) Medical College, which had accepted Elizabeth. In 185...
</Question>
<Choice>Blackwell, Emily</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
physician who became the leading organizer and supporter of Unitarianism in Transylvania.After serving as physician to Queen Bona Sforza of Poland from 1540 to 1552, Blandrata returned to Italy to practice medicine at Pavia, where he aroused the hostility of the authorities of the Inquisition by his interest in theological speculation. In 1556 he fled to Geneva and became an elder in the Calvinist congregation of Italians there. He soon antagonized John Calvin by declaring that debates over the nature of the Trinity threatened the concept of the unity of God. Two years later Blandrata was back...
</Question>
<Choice>Blandrata, George</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
physician known for his reforms in naval hygiene and medicine, which included the use of citrus fruits to prevent scurvy.Blane studied medicine at the University of Edinburgh and took his M.D. degree at Glasgow in 1778. He then became private physician to Admiral (later Lord) Rodney, whom he accompanied to the West Indies in 1779. On the expedition, Blane enforced the use of lemon juice and other fresh foods in the diet.After his return to London, Blane became physician to St. Thomas' Hospital (1783–95) and physician-in-ordinary to George IV and to William IV. He received a baronetcy in 1812....
</Question>
<Choice>Blane, Sir Gilbert, 1st Baronet</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-born American cellular and molecular biologist who was awarded the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1999 for his discovery that proteins have signals that govern their movement and position in the cell.Blobel received a medical degree at Eberhard-Karl University of Tübingen, Ger., in 1960 and in 1967 earned a Ph.D. in oncology at the University of Wisconsin. That year he joined the Rockefeller University protein laboratory in New York City, then led by George Palade. In 1976 Blobel became a professor at the university, and in 1992 he was named John D. Rockefeller, Jr., Professo...
</Question>
<Choice>Blobel, Gunther</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-born American biochemist who shared the 1964 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine with Feodor Lynen for their discoveries concerning the natural synthesis of cholesterol and fatty acids.After receiving a chemical engineering degree in 1934 at the Technische Hochschule in Munich, Bloch went to Switzerland and then to the United States. At Columbia University (where he obtained his Ph.D. in 1938) he became a research associate of Rudolf Schoenheimer in the isotopic analysis of cell metabolism. After teaching at the University of Chicago (1946–54), Bloch became professor of biochemistry...
</Question>
<Choice>Bloch, Konrad E.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American research physician whose discovery of an antigen that provokes antibody response against hepatitis B led to the development by other researchers of a successful vaccine against the disease. He shared the Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine in 1976 with D. Carleton Gajdusek for their work on the origins and spread of infectious viral diseases.Blumberg received his M.D. degree from Columbia University's College of Physicians and Surgeons and his Ph.D. degree in biochemistry from Oxford University in 1957. In 1960 he became chief of the Geographic Medicine and Genetics Section of the U...
</Question>
<Choice>Blumberg, Baruch S.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German anthropologist, physiologist, and comparative anatomist, frequently called the father of physical anthropology, who proposed one of the earliest classifications of the races of mankind.He joined the faculty of the University of Göttingen in 1776, publishing Institutiones Physiologicae (1787; Institutes of Physiology) and a handbook of comparative anatomy and physiology (1824). Blumenbach was the first to show the value of comparative anatomy in the study of man's history. His research in the measurement of craniums led him to divide mankind into five great families—Caucasian, Mongolian,...
</Question>
<Choice>Blumenbach, Johann Friedrich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch physician and professor of medicine who was the first great clinical, or “bedside,” teacher.Boerhaave graduated in philosophy from the University of Leiden in 1684 and in medicine from the academy at Harderwijk in 1693. He spent the whole of his professional life at the University of Leiden, serving as professor of botany and of medicine, rector of the university, professor of practical medicine, and professor of chemistry. By his brilliant teaching he restored the prestige of the Faculty of Medicine at the University of Leiden, and students came from all parts of Europe to hear his lect...
</Question>
<Choice>Boerhaave, Hermann</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physician and author of the first English guidebook to Europe.Boorde was educated at the University of Oxford and was admitted as a member of the Carthusian order while still a minor. In 1521 he was “dispensed from religion” to act as suffragan bishop of Chichester, though he never filled the office, and in 1529 he was freed from his monastic vows, not being able to endure the hardships of religiosity. He visited the universities of Orléans, Poitiers, Toulouse, Montpellier, and Wittenberg, saw “much abominable vices” at Rome, and went on pilgrimage to Santiago de Compostela in Spain. I...
</Question>
<Choice>Boorde, Andrew</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Belgian physician, bacteriologist, and immunologist who received the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1919 for his discovery of factors in blood serum that destroy bacteria; this work was vital to the diagnosis and treatment of many dangerous contagious diseases.Bordet's research on the destruction of bacteria and red corpuscles in blood serum, conducted at the Pasteur Institute, Paris (1894–1901), contributed significantly to the foundation of serology, the study of immune reactions in body fluids. In 1895 he found that two components of blood serum are responsible for the rupture of...
</Question>
<Choice>Bordet, Jules</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian physiologist and physicist who was the first to explain muscular movement and other body functions according to the laws of statics and dynamics.He was appointed professor of mathematics at Messina in 1649 and at Pisa in 1656. In 1667 he returned to Messina and in 1674 went to Rome, where he lived under the protection of Christina, former queen of Sweden. His best-known work is De Motu Animalium (1680–81; “On the Movement of Animals”), in which he sought to explain the movements of the animal body on mechanical principles; he thus ranks as the founder of the iatrophysical school.Borell...
</Question>
<Choice>Borelli, Giovanni Alfonso</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian plant physiologist and physicist whose invention of highly sensitive instruments for the detection of minute responses by living organisms to external stimuli enabled him to anticipate the parallelism between animal and plant tissues noted by later biophysicists. Bose's experiments on the quasi-optical properties of very short radio waves (1895) led him to make improvements on the coherer, an early form of radio detector, which have contributed to the development of solid-state physics.With a degree from the University of Cambridge (1884), Bose became professor of physical science at Pr...
</Question>
<Choice>Bose, Sir Jagadis Chandra</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physician and medical researcher who was the first to establish clinically that the centre of speech is located in the anterior lobes of the brain. He was also the first to differentiate between loss of speech resulting from the inability to create word forms and remember them and that resulting from the inability to control the movements involved in speech. Bouillaud further made important contributions in cardiology, establishing the connection between the occurrence of heart disease and acute articular rheumatism. He helped explain the mechanism and significance of the normal heart s...
</Question>
<Choice>Bouillaud, Jean-Baptiste</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss-born Italian pharmacologist who received the 1957 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for his discoveries of certain chemotherapeutic agents—namely, sulfa drugs, antihistamines, and muscle relaxants.Bovet studied at the University of Geneva, graduating with a doctorate in science in 1929. That same year, he went on to the Pasteur Institute in Paris and became head of the therapeutic chemistry laboratory there in 1939. In 1937 Bovet discovered the first antihistamine substance, which (in counteracting the effect of histamine) is effective in treating allergic reactions. This discovery...
</Question>
<Choice>Bovet, Daniel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
physician who introduced smallpox inoculation into the American colonies. Inoculation consisted of collecting a small quantity of pustular material from a smallpox victim and introducing it into the arm of one who had not had the disease. The result was usually a mild case that conferred lifelong protection.During the Boston smallpox epidemic of 1721, Boylston was urged to begin inoculations of the virus by the minister Cotton Mather, who had heard reports from Europe of their use in Turkey. Boylston responded enthusiastically, beginning with his own family and eventually inoculating about 250...
</Question>
<Choice>Boylston, Zabdiel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
South-African born biologist who, with John E. Sulston and H. Robert Horvitz, won the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 2002 for their discoveries about how genes regulate tissue and organ development via a key mechanism called programmed cell death, or apoptosis.After receiving a Ph.D. (1954) from the University of Oxford, Brenner began work with the Medical Research Council (MRC) in England. He later directed the MRC's Laboratory of Molecular Biology (1979–86) and Molecular Genetics Unit (1986–91). In 1996 he founded the California-based Molecular Sciences Institute, and in 2000 Bren...
</Question>
<Choice>Brenner, Sydney</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French epidemiologist who in 1825 performed the first successful tracheotomy (incision of and entrance into the trachea through the skin and muscles of the neck).He received his M.D. degree in Paris in 1815 and became chief physician of the hospital at Tours the following year. Bretonneau made the clinical distinction of diphtheria, to which he gave its name. He also distinguished between typhoid and typhus. In his doctrine of specific causes of infectious diseases, he foreshadowed the germ theory of Pasteur.
</Question>
<Choice>Bretonneau, Pierre-Fidele</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian physician and physiologist who was acknowledged by Sigmund Freud and others as the principal forerunner of psychoanalysis. Breuer found, in 1880, that he had relieved symptoms of hysteria in a patient, Bertha Pappenheim, called Anna O. in his case study, after he had induced her to recall unpleasant past experiences under hypnosis. He concluded that neurotic symptoms result from unconscious processes and will disappear when these processes become conscious. The case of Anna O. was important because it introduced Freud to the cathartic method (the “talking cure”) that was pivotal in hi...
</Question>
<Choice>Breuer, Josef</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physician who was the first to describe the clinical manifestations of the kidney disorder known as Bright's disease, or nephritis.Bright graduated in medicine from the University of Edinburgh in 1813. After working in hospitals on the Continent and in London, he became an assistant physician at Guy's Hospital, London, in 1820. He became a full physician there in 1824, eventually retiring from his post in 1843 to devote himself to private practice.Bright excelled at making meticulous clinical observations and correlating them with careful postmortem examinations. The results of his wid...
</Question>
<Choice>Bright, Richard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
surgeon who was closely associated with the development of modern physical anthropology in France and whose study of brain lesions contributed significantly to understanding the origins of aphasia, the loss or impairment of the ability to form or articulate words. He founded the anthropology laboratory at the École des Hautes Études, Paris (1858), and the Société d'Anthropologie de Paris (1859).Much of Broca's research concerned the comparative study of the craniums of the so-called races of mankind. Following precedents set by Samuel Morton in the United States, Broca developed numerous techn...
</Question>
<Choice>Broca, Paul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physiologist and surgeon whose name is applied to certain diseases of the bones and joints.Brodie was assistant surgeon at St. George's Hospital for 14 years. In 1810 he was elected a fellow of the Royal Society. Probably his most important work was Pathological and Surgical Observations on the Diseases of the Joints (1818), in which he attempted to trace the beginnings of disease in the different tissues that form a joint and to give an exact value to the symptom of pain as evidence of organic disease. This volume led to conservative measures in the treatment of diseases of the joints...
</Question>
<Choice>Brodie, Sir Benjamin Collins, 1st Baronet</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physician whose advocacy of bleeding, leech treatments, and fasting dominated Parisian medical practice early in the 19th century.Following publication of L'Examen des doctrines médicales (1816; “The Examination of Medical Doctrines”), Broussais' system of “physiological medicine” rapidly became the most popular medical philosophy around Paris. His doctrine insisted that all disease originates as an irritation of the gastrointestinal tract that passes to other organs “sympathetically.” Broussais is one of history's most notorious “bleeders.” His methods fell into disfavour, however, whe...
</Question>
<Choice>Broussais, Francois-Joseph-Victor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British propounder of the “excitability” theory of medicine, which classified diseases according to whether they had an over- or an understimulating effect on the body.Brown studied under the distinguished professor of medicine William Cullen at the University of Edinburgh, but was forced to receive his M.D. from St. Andrews (1779) because of his unpopularity with his colleagues. It was while studying with Cullen that Brown began to develop his theory, which held that all living tissues are “excitable” and postulated that the state of life is dependent on certain internal and external “excitin...
</Question>
<Choice>Brown, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American molecular geneticist who, along with Joseph L. Goldstein, was awarded the 1985 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for their elucidation of a key link in the metabolism of cholesterol in the human body.Brown graduated from the University of Pennsylvania, Philadelphia, in 1962 and received his M.D. from that university's medical school in 1966. He became friends with Goldstein when they were both working as interns at Massachusetts General Hospital in Boston during 1966–68. After conducting research at the National Institutes of Health from 1968 to 1971, he became an assistant profe...
</Question>
<Choice>Brown, Michael S.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British metaphysician whose work marks a turning point in the history of the common-sense school of philosophy.Between 1792 and 1803 Brown studied philosophy, law, and medicine at the University of Edinburgh, where he met the philosopher Dugald Stewart and the founders of the Edinburgh Review. After practicing medicine briefly, Brown was deputy lecturer for Stewart (1808–09) and became joint professor of moral philosophy with him in 1810.From Stewart, who was the chief expositor of the views of Thomas Reid (1710–96), a Scottish philosopher of common sense, Brown accepted many of Reid's argumen...
</Question>
<Choice>Brown, Thomas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physiologist and neurologist, a pioneer endocrinologist and neurophysiologist who was among the first to work out the physiology of the spinal cord.After graduating in medicine from the University of Paris in 1846, Brown-Séquard taught at Harvard University (1864–68) and practiced medicine briefly in New York and London. He succeeded Claude Bernard in 1878 as professor of experimental medicine in the Collège de France.In 1849 Brown-Séquard discovered that the sensory—but not the motor—fibres in the spinal cord are crossed, so that a cut halfway through the cord from one side produces pa...
</Question>
<Choice>Brown-Sequard, Charles-Edouard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physiologist who helped to introduce physical and chemical methods into medical research.Brücke studied medicine in Berlin and was trained as a physiologist by Johannes Müller. From 1849 to 1891 he was a professor of physiology at the University of Vienna.Brücke was a member of a school of physiologists (including Emil Du Bois-Reymond, Carl Ludwig, and Hermann von Helmholtz) who, about 1847, undertook to develop a new biology rigorously based on physics and chemistry and who became known as the “Berlin medical materialists.” Although Brücke and his colleagues did not achieve their goal,...
</Question>
<Choice>Brucke, Ernst Wilhelm von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physician who played a major role in establishing pharmacology as a rigorous science. He is best known for his discovery that amyl nitrite relieves the pain of angina pectoris.Brunton studied medicine at the University of Edinburgh and for three years abroad. He returned to London and was associated in turn with the Middlesex (1870) and St. Bartholomew's (1871–1904) hospitals. His most important work is A Textbook of Pharmacology, Therapeutics, and Materia Medica (1885), which was the first comprehensive treatise on pharmacology, emphasizing the physiological actions of pure drugs.
</Question>
<Choice>Brunton, Sir Thomas Lauder, 1st Baronet</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American scientist and corecipient, with Richard Axel, of the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 2004 for discoveries concerning the olfactory system.Buck received a B.S. (1975) in both microbiology and psychology from the University of Washington and a Ph.D. (1980) in immunology from the University of Texas Southwestern Medical Center. She first worked with Axel in the early 1980s at Columbia University in New York City, where Axel was a professor and Buck was his postdoctoral student. Buck held various positions with the Howard Hughes Medical Institute (HHMI) and at Harvard Medical Sc...
</Question>
<Choice>Buck, Linda B.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Australian physician, immunologist, and virologist who, with Sir Peter Medawar, was awarded the 1960 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for the discovery of acquired immunological tolerance, the concept on which tissue transplantation is founded.Burnet received his medical degree in 1924 from the University of Melbourne and performed research (1925–27) at the Lister Institute of Preventive Medicine, London. After receiving his Ph.D. from the University of London (1928), he became assistant director of the Walter and Eliza Hall Institute of Medical Research at Royal Melbourne Hospital in 19...
</Question>
<Choice>Burnet, Sir Macfarlane</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French philosopher and physiologist noted for Rapports du physique et du moral de l'homme (1802; “Relations of the Physical and the Moral in Man”), which explained all of reality, including the psychic, mental, and moral aspects of man, in terms of a mechanistic Materialism.Cabanis' early interest in poetry and medicine and a budding political career were eventually abandoned in favour of philosophical science. Nevertheless, he attended the Comte de Mirabeau in his final illness as friend and private physician. He also moved in the company of Diderot, d'Alembert, Condorcet, Condillac, and d'Ho...
</Question>
<Choice>Cabanis, Pierre-Jean-Georges</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the last of the medical writers of the Western Roman Empire, usually considered the greatest Greco-Roman physician after Galen. Caelius probably practiced and taught in Rome and is now thought to rank second only to the physician Celsus as a Latin medical writer. His most famous work, De morbis acutis et chronicis (“Concerning Acute and Chronic Diseases”), is a thorough exposition of classical medical knowledge.Although his works are largely adapted from those of Soranus of Ephesus, the 2nd-century leader of the methodist school of medicine, known for its deprecation of theory in favour of the...
</Question>
<Choice>Caelius Aurelianus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prominent Humanist and physician whose classic account of the English sweating sickness is considered one of the earliest histories of an epidemic.After his student days at Cambridge, Caius visited Italy (1539), studying under Montanus and Andreas Vesalius at Padua. Upon returning to London he practiced medicine and served as president of the Royal College of Physicians for several years. In 1557 he expanded his old college (Gonville Hall), named it Gonville and Caius College, endowed it generously, and in 1559 accepted its mastership.Caius' medical writings are of particular interest, especia...
</Question>
<Choice>Caius, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician and writer who, as cofounder and head of the Sexuality Information and Education Council of the United States (SIECUS), crusaded for the inclusion of responsible sex education in the public-school curriculum.Mary Steichen, daughter of the photographer Edward Steichen, graduated from Vassar College, Poughkeepsie, New York, in 1925. After a failed marriage she attended the medical school of the University of Rochester, New York (M.D., 1939). She interned for a year at Bellevue Hospital in New York City and then studied at the Columbia University School of Public Health (M.P.H....
</Question>
<Choice>Calderone, Mary Steichen</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Australian-born American physician and activist whose advocacy focused on the medical and environmental hazards of nuclear weapons.Helen Broinowski graduated in 1961 from the University of Adelaide Medical School with Bachelor of Medicine and Bachelor of Surgery degrees (the equivalent of an American M.D.) and married William Caldicott, a physician, in 1962. She worked as a general practitioner and pediatric intern, then founded and directed a cystic fibrosis clinic at Queen Elizabeth Hospital in Adelaide.Caldicott began her antinuclear activism in 1971 with a warning to the Australian public...
</Question>
<Choice>Caldicott, Helen Broinowski</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American neurologist and physiologist who was the first to use X rays in physiological studies. These led to his publication of The Mechanical Factors of Digestion (1911). His investigations on hemorrhagic and traumatic shock during World War I were summarized in Traumatic Shock (1923). He worked on methods of blood storage and in 1931 discovered sympathin, an adrenaline-like substance that is liberated at the tips of certain nerve cells.Cannon's work on the emergency functions of the sympathetic nervous system and on homeostasis are reported in Bodily Changes in Pain, Hunger, Fear and Rage (1...
</Question>
<Choice>Cannon, Walter Bradford</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian physician, mathematician, and astrologer who gave the first clinical description of typhus fever and whose book Ars magna (The Great Art; or, The Rules of Algebra) is one of the cornerstones in the history of algebra.Educated at the universities of Pavia and Padua, Cardano received his medical degree in 1526. In 1534 he moved to Milan, where he lived in great poverty until he became a lecturer in mathematics. Admitted to the college of physicians in 1539, he soon became rector. His fame as a physician grew rapidly, and many of Europe's crowned heads solicited his services; however, he...
</Question>
<Choice>Cardano, Girolamo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish pharmacologist who, along with Paul Greengard and Eric Kandel, was awarded the 2000 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for his research establishing dopamine as an important neurotransmitter in the brain.Carlsson received a medical degree from the University of Lund in 1951 and subsequently held teaching positions there until 1959, when he became professor of pharmacology at the University of Gothenburg. When Carlsson began his pioneering studies in the 1950s, scientists thought that dopamine worked only indirectly, by causing brain cells to make another neurotransmitter, noradrena...
</Question>
<Choice>Carlsson, Arvid</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French surgeon who received the 1912 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for developing a method of suturing blood vessels.Carrel received an M.D. (1900) from the University of Lyon. Soon after graduating, he became interested in the repair of blood vessels, and he developed a method to suture them together end-to-end with a minimum of stitches. This technique became essential for many surgical operations, including the transplantation of blood vessels and organs. In 1904 Carrel left France for the United States, working first at the University of Chicago and then at the Rockefeller Institu...
</Question>
<Choice>Carrel, Alexis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
one of the greatest Roman medical writers, author of an encyclopaedia dealing with agriculture, military art, rhetoric, philosophy, law, and medicine, of which only the medical portion has survived. De medicina, now considered one of the finest medical classics, was largely ignored by contemporaries. It was discovered by Pope Nicholas V (1397–1455) and was among the first medical works to be published (1478) after the introduction of the printing press.Most remarkable in Celsus' work is the apparently advanced state of medical practice at the time. He recommended cleanliness and urged that wou...
</Question>
<Choice>Celsus, Aulus Cornelius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian physician, philosopher, and botanist who sought a philosophical and theoretical approach to plant classification based on unified and coherent principles rather than on alphabetical sequence or medicinal properties. He helped establish botany as an independent science.Cesalpino succeeded his teacher, Luca Ghini, as professor of medicine and director of the botanical gardens at the University of Pisa. From 1592 he served as physician to Pope Clement VIII and taught at Sapienza University in Rome. His work on the anatomy and physiology of the cardiovascular system anticipated the work of...
</Question>
<Choice>Cesalpino, Andrea</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
lawyer and social reformer who devoted his life to sanitary reform in Britain.As secretary of the royal commission on reform of the poor laws (1834–46), Chadwick was largely responsible for devising the system under which the country was divided into groups of parishes administered by elected boards of guardians, each board with its own medical officer. Later, as commissioner of the Board of Health (1848–54), he conducted a campaign that culminated in passage of the Public Health Act of 1848. This legislation embodied his belief that public health should be administered locally so as to encour...
</Question>
<Choice>Chadwick, Sir Edwin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-born British biochemist who, with pathologist Howard Walter Florey (later Baron Florey), isolated and purified penicillin (which had been discovered in 1928 by Sir Alexander Fleming) and performed the first clinical trials of the antibiotic. For their pioneering work on penicillin Chain, Florey, and Fleming shared the 1945 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine.Chain graduated in chemistry and physiology from the Friedrich Wilhelm University of Berlin and then engaged in research at the Institute of Pathology, Charité Hospital, Berlin (1930–33). Forced to flee Germany because of the ant...
</Question>
<Choice>Chain, Sir Ernst Boris</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. physician and one of the founders of the Boston Lying-In Hospital (1832), brother of the clergyman William Ellery Channing; he was the first (1847) to use ether as an anesthetic in obstetrics and the first professor of obstetrics at Harvard University (1815).A graduate in medicine (1809) of the University of Pennsylvania, Channing studied in Europe, returning in 1812 to an obstetrical practice. He was a coeditor of the New England Journal of Medicine and Surgery and wrote the classic Treatise on Etherization in Childbirth (1848).
</Question>
<Choice>Channing, Walter</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
founder (with Guillaume Duchenne) of modern neurology and one of France's greatest medical teachers and clinicians.Charcot took his M.D. at the University of Paris in 1853 and three years later was appointed physician of the Central Hospital bureau. He then became a professor at the University of Paris (1860–93), where he began a lifelong association with the Salpêtrière Hospital, Paris (1862); there, in 1882, he opened what was to become the greatest neurological clinic of the time in Europe. A teacher of extraordinary competence, he attracted students from all parts of the world. In 1885 one...
</Question>
<Choice>Charcot, Jean-Martin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Belgian-American cytologist who developed the principal methods of separating and analyzing components of the living cell. For this work, on which modern cell biology is partly based, Claude, his student George Palade, and Christian de Duve shared the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1974.Upon obtaining his M.D. at Liège University, Belgium, in 1928, Claude began research at the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (now Rockefeller University) in New York City. In attempting to isolate the Rous sarcoma virus from chicken tumours, he spun cell extracts containing the virus in cen...
</Question>
<Choice>Claude, Albert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician and college professor, widely respected among her male colleagues and a strong force for professional opportunity and education for women in medicine.Emeline Horton grew up in Madison county, New York. She worked as a teacher until she could afford to enroll at Oberlin (Ohio) College, from which she graduated in 1853. She then entered the Female (later Woman's) Medical College of Pennsylvania in Philadelphia and took her M.D. degree in 1855. While working toward her medical degree she married the Reverend Giles B. Cleveland. Her husband's ill health ended their plan to under...
</Question>
<Choice>Cleveland, Emeline Horton</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biochemist who, with Rita Levi-Montalcini, shared the 1986 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for his researches on substances produced in the body that influence the development of nerve and skin tissues.Cohen was educated at Brooklyn College (B.A., 1943), Oberlin College (M.A., 1945), and at the University of Michigan, where he received a Ph.D. in biochemistry in 1948. He joined Levi-Montalcini at Washington University, St. Louis, Mo., as a researcher in 1952. His training as a biochemist enabled him to help isolate nerve growth factor, a natural substance that Levi-Montalcini h...
</Question>
<Choice>Cohen, Stanley</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
physician who established the study of comparative osteology and first described cerebrospinal meningitis. Through a grant from Groningen he studied in Italy and France and was a pupil of Fallopius, Eustachius, Arantius, and Rondelet. He became city physician of Nürnberg (1569) and later entered military service as field surgeon to Johann Casimir, the palatine prince.Coiter's researches included postmortem studies. He described human embryology as well as the comparative osteology of animals and illustrated his own work. He also investigated the sense organs and the nervous system.
</Question>
<Choice>Coiter, Volcher</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English medical researcher who introduced the use of Prontosil, the first sulfonamide drug, as a cure for puerperal, or childbed, fever, a condition resulting from infection after childbirth or abortion.Colebrook joined researcher Almroth Wright in 1907 at St. Mary's Hospital. In 1926 Colebrook became interested in the incidence of puerperal fever in women who had just undergone childbirth. Nine years later, he obtained the newly discovered antibacterial drug Prontosil and used it to treat a woman who was dying of puerperal fever. The patient recovered, and the drug was next used successfully...
</Question>
<Choice>Colebrook, Leonard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
medieval medical scholar who initiated the translation of Arabic medical works into Latin, a development that profoundly influenced Western thought.Constantine possessed an excellent knowledge of Greek, Latin, Arabic, and several Oriental languages acquired during his extensive travels in Syria, India, Ethiopia, Egypt, and Persia. He studied at the University of Salerno, Europe's first organized medical school, and entered Monte Cassino, the monastery founded by St. Benedict in 529. At the monastery he translated 37 books from Arabic into Latin, including two treatises by Isaac Israeli, or Isa...
</Question>
<Choice>Constantine the African</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biochemists, husband-and-wife team whose discovery of a phosphate-containing form of the simple sugar glucose, and its universal importance to carbohydrate metabolism, led to an understanding of hormonal influence on the interconversion of sugars and starches in the animal organism. Their discoveries earned them (with Bernardo Houssay) the Nobel Prize for Medicine or Physiology in 1947.They met while students at the German University of Prague and were married in 1920, receiving their medical degrees the same year. Immigrating to the United States in 1922, they joined the staff of the...
</Question>
<Choice>Cori, Carl & Gerty</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
South African-born American physicist who, with Godfrey Hounsfield, was awarded the 1979 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for his work in developing the powerful new diagnostic technique of computerized axial tomography (CAT). Cormack was unusual in the field of Nobel laureates because he never earned a doctorate degree in medicine or any other field of science.After graduating from the University of Cape Town in 1944 Cormack pursued advanced studies there and at the University of Cambridge. He was a lecturer at Cape Town from 1950 to 1956 and then, after a year's research fellowship at...
</Question>
<Choice>Cormack, Allan MacLeod</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Irish physician and author of several reports on diseases of the heart. His paper on aortic insufficiency (1832) is generally regarded as the classic description of the condition. Many eponyms (Corrigan's respiration, Corrigan's cirrhosis, Corrigan's pulse) came into general use as a result of his diverse studies.Corrigan was educated at the school of Maynooth College, near Dublin, and received his first instruction in medicine from a local physician. In 1825 he received his M.D. from the University of Edinburgh. He became a physician at Jervis Street Hospital in Dublin, where he began his cli...
</Question>
<Choice>Corrigan, Sir Dominic John, Baronet</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French-American physician and physiologist who in 1956 shared the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine with Dickinson W. Richards and Werner Forssmann for discoveries concerning heart catheterization and circulatory changes.His medical studies interrupted by World War I, Cournand graduated from the University of Paris in 1930. He studied at Bellevue Hospital, New York City, where he met Richards. Together they collaborated in clinical lung and heart research and perfected Forssmann's procedure, now termed cardiac catheterization, whereby a tube is passed into the heart from a vein at the elb...
</Question>
<Choice>Cournand, Andre F.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
classical pharmacologist, artist, and physician to Mithradates VI, king of Pontus (120–63 BC). Crateuas' drawings are the earliest known botanical illustrations. His work on pharmacology was the first to illustrate the plants described; it also classified the plants and explained their medicinal use. The drawings that exist today and bear his name are copies, made about AD 500. Of the text of his book, only quotations by Pedanius Dioscorides, a Greek physician (flourished c.AD 50), are extant. All later pharmacology and medicine were influenced by Crateuas' work.
</Question>
<Choice>Crateuas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British biophysicist, who, with James Watson and Maurice Wilkins, received the 1962 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for their determination of the molecular structure of deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA), the chemical substance ultimately responsible for hereditary control of life functions. This accomplishment became a cornerstone of genetics and was widely regarded as one of the most important discoveries of 20th-century biology.During World War II, Crick interrupted his education to work as a physicist in the development of magnetic mines for use in naval warfare, but afterward he turned t...
</Question>
<Choice>Crick, Francis Harry Compton</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish novelist and physician whose works combining realism with social criticism won a large Anglo-American readership.Cronin was educated at the University of Glasgow and served as a surgeon in the Royal Navy during World War I. He practiced in South Wales (1921–24) and then, as medical inspector of mines, investigated occupational diseases in the coal industry. He opened medical practice in London in 1926 but quit because of ill health, using his leisure to write his first novel, Hatter's Castle (1931; filmed 1941), the story of a Scottish hatmaker obsessed with the idea of the possibilit...
</Question>
<Choice>Cronin, A. J.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French pathologist, anatomist, and physician who wrote several important works on pathological anatomy.Cruveilhier trained in medicine at the University of Montpellier and in 1825 became professor of anatomy at the University of Paris. He became the first occupant of the chair of pathology at Paris when that teaching post was established in 1836. Cruveilhier possessed a broad knowledge of morbid anatomy and published a series of multivolume works on the subject. The greatest of these, an atlas of pathology titled Anatomie pathologique du corps humain, 2 vol. (1829–42; “Pathological Anatomy of...
</Question>
<Choice>Cruveilhier, Jean</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish physician and professor of medicine, best known for his innovative teaching methods.After attending the University of Glasgow and the new medical school at Edinburgh, Cullen returned to Hamilton. He spent eight years in private clinical practice, attending without fee those too poor to afford his services. In 1740 he received his M.D. from Glasgow and several years later obtained permission to deliver a series of independent lectures on chemistry and medicine, the first to be offered in Great Britain. He was elected to the chair of medicine at Glasgow in 1751. In 1755 Cullen returned...
</Question>
<Choice>Cullen, William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physiologist who in 1936 shared the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine with the German pharmacologist Otto Loewi for their discoveries in the chemical transmission of nerve impulses.After receiving his bachelor's degree (1903) from the University of Cambridge, Dale began his research career in 1904 at the Wellcome Physiological Research Laboratories. In 1909 he completed his medical degree (M.D.) at Cambridge and in 1914 joined the staff of what later became the Medical Research Council. From 1928 to 1942 he was director of its subsidiary organization, the National Institute for Me...
</Question>
<Choice>Dale, Sir Henry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Danish biochemist who, with Edward A. Doisy, was awarded the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1943 for research into antihemorrhagic substances and the discovery of vitamin K (1939).Dam, a graduate of the Polytechnic Institute of Copenhagen (1920), taught in the School of Agriculture and Veterinary Medicine there and later at the Physiological Laboratory of the University of Copenhagen. He went to the United States in 1940, lecturing and continuing his research, mainly at the University of Rochester, N.Y. In 1946 he returned to the Polytechnic Institute.Dam and his associates demonstr...
</Question>
<Choice>Dam, Henrik</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physician, poet, and botanist noted for his republican politics and materialistic theory of evolution. Although today he is best known as the grandfather of naturalist Charles Darwin and of biologist Sir Francis Galton, Erasmus Darwin was an important figure of the Enlightenment in his own right.
</Question>
<Choice>Darwin, Erasmus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French hematologist and immunologist whose studies of the genetic basis of the immunological reaction earned him a share (with George Snell and Baruj Benacerraf) of the 1980 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine.After serving with the Free French forces in World War II, Dausset resumed his interrupted medical studies and took his degree from the University of Paris in 1945. He pursued advanced studies in the United States at Harvard University and later returned to France and became laboratory director of the National Blood Transfusion Centre. From 1958 to 1977 he conducted research and taugh...
</Question>
<Choice>Dausset, Jean</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American cardiovascular surgeon, educator, international medical statesman, and pioneer in surgical procedures for treatment of defects and diseases of the cardiovascular system.In 1932 DeBakey devised the “roller pump,” an essential component of the heart-lung machine that permitted open-heart surgery. He also developed an efficient method of correcting aortic aneurysms by grafting frozen blood vessels to replace diseased vessels. By 1953 DeBakey had developed a technique of using plastic tubing (Dacron) instead of arterial homographs to replace diseased vessels. In 1953 he performed the firs...
</Question>
<Choice>DeBakey, Michael</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-born U.S. biologist, a pioneer in the study of molecular genetics. With Alfred Day Hershey and Salvador Luria, he was awarded the 1969 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for work on bacteriophages—viruses that infect bacteria.Delbrück received a Ph.D. in physics (1930) from the University of Göttingen. His interest in bacteriophages was aroused while he was a research assistant at the Kaiser Wilhelm Institute for Chemistry in Berlin (1932–37). A refugee from Nazi Germany, Delbrück went to the United States in 1937, serving as a faculty member of the California Institute of Technolog...
</Question>
<Choice>Delbruck, Max</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician and pathologist who, with his wife, Gladys Henry Dick, discovered the cause of, and devised means of preventing, scarlet fever.Dick studied scarlet fever while serving in the Army Medical Corps in World War I. After the war he was professor of clinical medicine at Rush Medical College, Chicago (1918–33), and head of the department of medicine at the University of Chicago (1933–45).In 1923 he and his wife isolated the hemolytic streptococcus bacterium that causes scarlet fever, prepared the toxin (Dick toxin) used for immunization, and devised the Dick method for prevention o...
</Question>
<Choice>Dick, George Frederick</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
philosopher and pioneer in medicine, among Greek physicians second only to Hippocrates in reputation and ability, according to tradition.A resident of Athens, Diocles was the first to write medical treatises in Attic Greek rather than in the Ionic Greek customarily used for such writings; only fragments of his writings survive. Usually regarded as the chief representative of the dogmatic school, he wrote on animal anatomy, dietetics, physiology, embryology, and medical botany, among other subjects. His work on animal anatomy, prepared with the aid of his work in dissection, was the first syste...
</Question>
<Choice>Diocles</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek philosopher remembered for his cosmology and for his efforts to synthesize ancient views and new discoveries.It is uncertain whether Diogenes' birthplace, from which his name is derived, was the Apollonia of Crete or that of Phrygia (in modern Turkey). He lived most of his life in Athens, where his opinions were a source of danger to his life and were derided by the playwright Aristophanes in his Nephelai (“The Clouds”). Among numerous fragments of his works, written in Ionic Greek, is the important book Peri physeos (“On Nature”). The treatises Against the Sophists and the Nature of Man...
</Question>
<Choice>Diogenes of Apollonia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek physician and pharmacologist whose work De materia medica was the foremost classical source of modern botanical terminology and the leading pharmacological text for 16 centuries.Dioscorides' travels as a surgeon with the armies of the Roman emperor Nero provided him an opportunity to study the features, distribution, and medicinal properties of many plants and minerals. Excellent descriptions of nearly 600 plants, including cannabis, colchicum, water hemlock, and peppermint, are contained in De materia medica. Written in five books around the year 77, this work deals with approximately 1...
</Question>
<Choice>Dioscorides, Pedanius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Flemish physician and botanist whose Stirpium historiae pemptades sex sive libri XXX (1583) is considered one of the foremost botanical works of the late 16th century.Dodoens received a medical degree from the Catholic University of Leuven (Louvain) in 1535 and composed works on cosmography and physiology before turning to botany with the brief treatise De frugum historia (1552). His Cruydeboek (1554), an extensive herbal, owes a great deal to the “German fathers of botany,” especially Leonhard Fuchs; instead of arranging plants in alphabetical order, Dodoens grouped plants according to their...
</Question>
<Choice>Dodoens, Rembert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Australian immunologist and pathologist who, with Rolf Zinkernagel of Switzerland, received the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1996 for their discovery of how the body's immune system distinguishes virus-infected cells from normal cells.Doherty earned bachelor's (1962) and master's (1966) degrees in veterinary medicine from the University of Queensland but switched to pathology while earning his doctorate (1970) from the University of Edinburgh, Scot. While conducting research (1972–75) at the John Curtin School of Medical Research in Canberra, Doherty began collaborating with Zinke...
</Question>
<Choice>Doherty, Peter C.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biochemist who shared the 1943 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine with Henrik Dam for his isolation and synthesis of the antihemorrhagic vitamin K (1939), used in medicine and surgery.Doisy earned his bachelor's and master's degrees at the University of Illinois and his Ph.D. at Harvard University (1920). He taught at Washington University School of Medicine, St. Louis, Mo. (1919–23), and St. Louis University (1923–65; emeritus 1965–86). From 1922 to 1934 he worked with the embryologist Edgar Allen in developing assay techniques that facilitated research on sex hormones. Doisy and...
</Question>
<Choice>Doisy, Edward Adelbert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German bacteriologist and pathologist who was awarded the 1939 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for his discovery (announced in 1932) of the antibacterial effects of Prontosil, the first of the sulfonamide drugs.Domagk earned a medical degree from the University of Kiel in 1921. After teaching at the universities of Greifswald (1924) and Munich (1925), he became director of the I.G. Farbenindustrie (Bayer) Laboratory for Experimental Pathology and Bacteriology, Wuppertal-Elberfeld. There, inspired by the ideas of Paul Ehrlich, he began testing newly developed dyes for their possible effe...
</Question>
<Choice>Domagk, Gerhard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
ophthalmologist, the most eminent of 19th-century Dutch physicians, whose investigations of the physiology and pathology of the eye made possible a scientific approach to the correction of refractive disabilities such as nearsightedness, farsightedness, and astigmatism.Donders' interest in ophthalmology began in 1847 with a study of muscae volitantes, the problem of specks seen floating before the eye. This study resulted in his formulation of what is now known as Donders' law: the rotation of the eye around the line of sight is involuntary.As professor of physiology at the University of Utrec...
</Question>
<Choice>Donders, Frans Cornelis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
“jungle doctor” whose lectures and books recounted his efforts to supply medical aid to peoples of less developed countries, mainly in Southeast Asia.A graduate of St. Louis University medical school (M.D. 1953), he was serving with the U.S. Navy as a medical officer when the end of French rule in Indochina in 1954 resulted in of an independent but divided Vietnam. Volunteering for duty in the American effort to evacuate refugees from North to South Vietnam, Dooley instituted rigorous public-health measures and organized the processing of more than 600,000 Vietnamese for evacuation between Sep...
</Question>
<Choice>Dooley, Thomas Anthony</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
African American physician and surgeon who was an authority on the preservation of human blood for transfusion.Drew was educated at Amherst College (graduated 1926), McGill University, Montreal (1933), and Columbia University (1940). While earning his doctorate at Columbia in the late 1930s, he conducted research into the properties and preservation of blood plasma. He soon developed efficient ways to process and store large quantities of blood plasma in “blood banks.” As the leading authority in the field, he organized and directed the blood-plasma programs of the United States and Great Brit...
</Question>
<Choice>Drew, Charles Richard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian virologist who shared the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1975 with Howard M. Temin and David Baltimore, both of whom had studied under him.Dulbecco obtained an M.D. from the University of Turin in 1936 and remained there several years as a member of its faculty. He came to the United States in 1947 and studied viruses, first with Salvador Luria at Indiana University, then at the California Institute of Technology (1949–63). He was a fellow at the Salk Institute for Biological Studies in La Jolla, Calif. (1963–72), and returned there in 1977 as a distinguished research profes...
</Question>
<Choice>Dulbecco, Renato</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physiologist who discovered and named the phenomenon of osmosis (the passage of solvent through a semipermeable membrane) and was the first to recognize the importance of green pigment in the use of carbon dioxide by plant cells.Dutrochet studied medicine in Paris (M.D., 1806) and then served as a military medical officer in Spain for several years before giving up the practice of medicine to devote his career to scientific research. When Dutrochet noticed the similarity of physical and chemical processes in plants and animals, he directed his studies toward plant and animal physiology....
</Question>
<Choice>Dutrochet, Henri</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Belgian cytologist and biochemist who discovered lysosomes (the digestive organelles of the cell) and peroxisomes (organelles that are the site of metabolic processes involving hydrogen peroxide). For this work he shared the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1974 with Albert Claude and George Palade.De Duve's discovery of lysosomes arose out of his research on the enzymes involved in the metabolism of carbohydrates by the liver. While using Claude's technique of separating the components of cells by spinning them in a centrifuge, he noticed that the cells' release of an enzyme called a...
</Question>
<Choice>Duve, Christian Rene de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Australian research physiologist who received (with Alan Hodgkin and Andrew Huxley) the 1963 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for his discovery of the chemical means by which impulses are communicated or repressed by nerve cells (neurons).After graduating from the University of Melbourne in 1925, Eccles studied at the University of Oxford under a Rhodes scholarship. He received a Ph.D. there in 1929 after having worked under the neurophysiologist Charles Scott Sherrington. He held a research post at Oxford before returning to Australia in 1937, teaching there and in New Zealand over the...
</Question>
<Choice>Eccles, Sir John Carew</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician and physical chemist who elucidated the structure of antibodies—proteins that are produced by the body in response to infection. For this work he shared the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1972 with British biochemist Rodney Porter. Edelman also made significant contributions to developmental biology and neurobiology.Edelman received his M.D. degree from the University of Pennsylvania (1954) and then served two years in the Army Medical Corps in Paris. During that time he became intrigued by questions concerning the immune system, and upon his return to the United...
</Question>
<Choice>Edelman, Gerald Maurice</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British gynecologist who, together with British medical researcher Robert Edwards, perfected in vitro fertilization (IVF) of the human egg. Their technique made possible the birth of Louise Brown, the world's first “test-tube baby,” on July 25, 1978.In 1939 Steptoe graduated from the University of London's St. George Hospital Medical School and joined the Royal Navy Volunteer Reserve, serving as a surgeon until his ship was sunk and he was taken prisoner by the Italians (1941–43). After his release he continued his medical training in London, Dublin, and Manchester before becoming senior obste...
</Question>
<Choice>Edwards, Robert Geoffrey</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Portuguese neurologist and statesman who was the founder of modern psychosurgery. With Walter Hess he was awarded the 1949 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for the development of prefrontal leucotomy (lobotomy) as a radical therapy for certain psychoses, or mental disorders.As the University of Lisbon's first professor of neurology (1911–44), Egas Moniz introduced and developed (1927–37) cerebral angiography (arteriography), a method of making visible the blood vessels of the brain by injecting into the carotid artery substances that are opaque to X rays. This technique has proved to be...
</Question>
<Choice>Egas Moniz, Antonio</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German medical scientist known for his pioneering work in hematology, immunology, and chemotherapy and for his discovery of the first effective treatment for syphilis. He received jointly with Élie Metchnikoff the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1908.
</Question>
<Choice>Ehrlich, Paul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch physician and pathologist whose demonstration that beriberi is caused by poor diet led to the discovery of vitamins. Together with Sir Frederick Hopkins, he was awarded the 1929 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine.Eijkman received a medical degree from the University of Amsterdam (1883) and served as a medical officer in the Dutch East Indies (1883–85). He then worked with Robert Koch in Berlin on bacteriological research and in 1886 returned to Java to investigate the cause of beriberi. In 1888 Eijkman was appointed director of the research laboratory for pathological anatomy and bac...
</Question>
<Choice>Eijkman, Christiaan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch physiologist who was awarded the 1924 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for his discovery of the electrical properties of the heart through the electrocardiograph, which he developed as a practical clinical instrument and an important tool in the diagnosis of heart disease.Einthoven was graduated in medicine from the University of Utrecht and served as professor of physiology at the University of Leiden from 1886 until his death. In 1903 he devised the first string galvanometer, known as the Einthoven galvanometer; with this instrument he was able to measure the changes of electrica...
</Question>
<Choice>Einthoven, Willem</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian surgeon, teacher, and researcher who carried out important studies in the physiology of the thyroid gland and surgery of the central nervous system.Eiselsberg studied medicine at Vienna, Würzburg, Zürich, and Paris. In 1884 he received his M.D. from Vienna, where he was a pupil of and assistant to the brilliant Viennese surgeon Theodor Billroth. He was professor of surgery at Utrecht (1893), Königsberg (1896), and Vienna (1901). In 1890 he made note of the frequent occurrence of tetany cramps after goiter operations and two years later produced tetany experimentally by removal of the...
</Question>
<Choice>Eiselsberg, Anton, Freiherr von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician and public health official who served (1993–94) as U.S. surgeon general, the first black and the second woman to hold that post.Elders was the first of eight children in a family of sharecroppers. At age 15 she entered Philander Smith College, a historically black liberal arts college in Little Rock, Arkansas, on a scholarship from the United Methodist Church. That year she saw a doctor for the first time in her life and subsequently determined to become a physician herself. In 1952 she graduated from college after only three years. The following year she joined the army; sh...
</Question>
<Choice>Elders, Joycelyn</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physician who advocated the use of hypnosis in therapy and who in 1849 founded a mesmeric hospital. He was one of the first teachers in London to emphasize clinical lecturing and was one of the earliest of British physicians to urge use of the stethoscope.After studying medicine at the University of Edinburgh, at the University of Cambridge, and in London hospitals, Elliotson taught at London University (now University College). In 1834 he became physician to University College Hospital, where his interest in hypnosis led to conflicts with the hospital's medical committee and his resig...
</Question>
<Choice>Elliotson, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American virologist and microbiologist who, with Frederick C. Robbins and Thomas H. Weller, was awarded the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for 1954 for his part in cultivating the poliomyelitis virus in nonnervous-tissue cultures, a preliminary step to the development of the polio vaccine.Enders was a student of English literature at Harvard University (M.A., 1922) before he turned to bacterial studies there (Ph.D., 1930). His early researches contributed new and basic knowledge to problems of tuberculosis, pneumococcal infections, and resistance to bacterial diseases. In 1929 he joine...
</Question>
<Choice>Enders, John Franklin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. botanist, physician, and meteorologist who is known primarily for his botanical monographs, especially one on the cactus and also A Monography of North American Cuscutinae (1842).Engelmann studied at the universities of Heidelberg and Berlin and received his M.D. degree from the University of Würzburg in 1831. His illustrated thesis, De Antholysi Prodromus, was an important study of the morphology of monstrosities. He went to the United States in 1833, and in 1835 he settled in St. Louis, where he became a leading physician. Continuing his studies in biology, he pointed out the adaptation...
</Question>
<Choice>Engelmann, George</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek anatomist and physician in Alexandria, regarded by some as the founder of physiology.Known especially for his studies of the circulatory and nervous systems, Erasistratus noted the difference between sensory and motor nerves, but thought that the nerves were hollow tubes containing fluid. He believed that air entered the lungs and heart and was carried through the body in the arteries, and that the veins carried blood from the heart to the various parts of the body. He correctly described the function of the epiglottis and the valves of the heart, including the tricuspid, which he named....
</Question>
<Choice>Erasistratus of Ceos</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physiologist, who received (with Herbert Gasser) the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1944 for discovering that fibres within the same nerve cord possess different functions.Erlanger's research into nerve function was the product of a profitable collaboration with Gasser, one of his students at the University of Wisconsin, Madison (1906–10). Soon after Erlanger's appointment as professor of physiology at Washington University, St. Louis (1910–46), Gasser joined him there, and they began studying ways in which the recently developed field of electronics could be applied to phy...
</Question>
<Choice>Erlanger, Joseph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish physiologist who, with British biophysicist Sir Bernard Katz and American biochemist Julius Axelrod, received the 1970 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine. All three were honoured for their independent study of the mechanics of nerve impulses.Euler was the son of 1929 Nobel laureate Hans von Euler-Chelpin. After his graduation from the Karolinska Institute in Stockholm, Euler served on the faculty of the institute from 1930 to 1971. He joined the Nobel Committee for Physiology and Medicine in 1953 and was president of the Nobel Foundation for 10 years (1966–75).Euler's outstanding a...
</Question>
<Choice>Euler, Ulf von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Danish pathologist who received the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1926 for achieving the first controlled induction of cancer in laboratory animals, a development of profound importance to cancer research.A student of the bacteriologists Robert Koch and Emil von Behring in Berlin, Fibiger became professor of pathological anatomy at the University of Copenhagen (1900). In 1907, while dissecting rats infected with tuberculosis, he found tumours in the stomachs of three animals. After intensive research, he concluded that the tumours, apparently malignant, followed an inflammation of...
</Question>
<Choice>Fibiger, Johannes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Cuban epidemiologist who discovered that yellow fever is transmitted from infected to healthy humans by a mosquito. Although he published experimental evidence of this discovery in 1886, his ideas were ignored for 20 years.A graduate of Jefferson Medical College, Philadelphia (1855), he returned to Cuba, where he practiced medicine in Matanzas and Havana. In 1879 Finlay was appointed by the Cuban government to work with the North American commission studying the causes of yellow fever, and two years later he was chosen to attend the fifth International Sanitary Conference in Washington, D.C.,...
</Question>
<Choice>Finlay, Carlos J.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Danish physician, founder of modern phototherapy (the treatment of disease by the influence of light), who received the 1903 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for the application of light in the treatment of skin diseases.Finsen was born into a prominent Icelandic family that was involved in the administration of the Faroe Islands. He attended schools in Denmark and Iceland before entering the University of Copenhagen (M.D., 1890), where he became interested in the effects of light on living organisms. In 1893 Finsen found that lengthy exposure of smallpox sufferers to the red light forme...
</Question>
<Choice>Finsen, Niels Ryberg</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biochemist who was the corecipient with Edwin G. Krebs of the 1992 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for their discoveries concerning reversible phosphorylation, a biochemical mechanism that governs the activities of cell proteins.The son of Swiss parents, Fischer earned a Ph.D. in chemistry from the University of Geneva in 1947 and conducted research there until 1953. That year he went to the United States, where he joined Krebs on the faculty of the University of Washington, Seattle. He became a full professor there in 1961.Fischer and Krebs made their discoveries in the mid-19...
</Question>
<Choice>Fischer, Edmond H.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish bacteriologist best known for his discovery of penicillin. Fleming had a genius for technical ingenuity and original observation. His work on wound infection and lysozyme, an antibacterial enzyme found in tears and saliva, guaranteed him a place in the history of bacteriology. But it was his discovery of penicillin in 1928, which started the antibiotic revolution, that sealed his lasting reputation. Fleming was recognized for this achievement in 1945, when he received the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine, along with Australian pathologist Howard Walter Florey and British biochem...
</Question>
<Choice>Fleming, Sir Alexander</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
educator who played a major role in the introduction of modern medical and science education to American colleges and universities.Founder and director of a progressive college-preparatory school in Louisville (1890–1904), Flexner issued an appraisal of American educational institutions (The American College: A Criticism; 1908) that earned him a Carnegie Foundation commission to survey the quality of the 155 medical colleges in the United States and Canada. His report (1910) had an immediate and sensational impact on American medical education. Many of the colleges that were severely criticize...
</Question>
<Choice>Flexner, Abraham</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
one of the most eminent of 19th-century physicians, and a pioneer of heart research in the United States. He discovered (1862) a disorder—now known as the Austin Flint murmur—characterized by regurgitation of blood from the aorta into the heart before contraction of the ventricles.As professor of medicine at medical schools in Chicago, Buffalo, N.Y., Louisville, Ky., and the Bellevue Hospital Medical College in New York City (1861–86) and as president of the American Medical Association (1883–84), Flint had a great influence on the early course of medicine in the United States. A proponent of...
</Question>
<Choice>Flint, Austin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Australian pathologist who, with Ernst Boris Chain, isolated and purified penicillin (discovered in 1928 by Sir Alexander Fleming) for general clinical use. For this research Florey, Chain, and Fleming shared the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1945.Florey studied medicine at Adelaide and Oxford universities until 1924. After holding teaching and research posts at Cambridge and Sheffield universities, he was professor of pathology at Oxford (1935–62). He was appointed provost of Queen's College, Oxford (1962), and chancellor of the Australian National University, Canberra (1965), pos...
</Question>
<Choice>Florey, Howard Walter Florey, Baron</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physiologist who was the first to demonstrate experimentally the general functions of the major portions of the vertebrate brain.After receiving his medical degree from the University of Montpellier, Flourens went to Paris, where the renowned French naturalist Georges Cuvier became his patron. Under his sponsorship, Flourens conducted a series of experiments (1814–22) to determine physiological changes in pigeons after removal of certain portions of their brains. He found that removal of the cerebral hemispheres, at the front of the brain, destroys will, judgment, and all the senses of...
</Question>
<Choice>Flourens, Marie-Jean-Pierre</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physician, author, and mystical philosopher remembered for his occultist opposition to science.The son of Sir Thomas Fludd, he studied at St. John's College, Oxford, before traveling in Europe for six years. On his return to Oxford he earned medical degrees (1605) and joined the College of Physicians (1609). He eventually became a prosperous London doctor.Most of Fludd's writings represent the culmination of the occult, as distinct from the scientific, tendencies of the 17th century. Deriving his ideas from such diverse sources as the Old Testament, the Jewish Kabbala, alchemy, astrolo...
</Question>
<Choice>Fludd, Robert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German surgeon who shared with André F. Cournand and Dickinson W. Richards the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1956. A pioneer in heart research, Forssmann contributed to the development of cardiac catheterization, a procedure in which a tube is inserted into a vein at the elbow and passed through the vein into the heart. While a surgical resident in Berlin (1929), Forssmann used himself as the first human subject, watching the progress of the catheter in a mirror held in front of a fluoroscope screen. Forssmann's daring experiment was condemned at the time as foolhardy and dangerous...
</Question>
<Choice>Forssmann, Werner</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physiologist and educator who introduced modern methods of teaching biology and physiology that emphasize laboratory training.Foster earned a medical degree from University College, London, in 1859 and was a protégé of the biologist T.H. Huxley. Foster became an instructor at University College in 1867 and went on to become a teacher (1870–83) and then the first professor of physiology (1883–1903) at the University of Cambridge. He greatly enlarged and modernized the teaching of biology at Cambridge, and under his leadership that school became a world centre for research into physiolog...
</Question>
<Choice>Foster, Sir Michael</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
physician who was the first to record coronary arteriosclerosis (hardening of the walls of the arteries supplying blood to the heart muscle) in association with a case of angina pectoris.Fothergill, a Quaker, studied medicine at the University of Edinburgh and later became a highly successful London practitioner. His “Account of the Sore Throat Attended with Ulcers” (1748) was the first authoritative paper on diphtheria. He also described facial neuralgia and migraine. Fothergill popularized the use of coffee in England and promoted its cultivation in the West Indies. A friend of Benjamin Fran...
</Question>
<Choice>Fothergill, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
physician, writer, and reformer, one of the first American women to hold a medical degree and to become a professor of medicine in an American college.Lydia Folger attended the Wheaton Seminary in Norton, Massachusetts, from 1838 to 1839 and taught there from 1842 to 1844. In 1844 she married Lorenzo Niles Fowler, a well-known phrenologist and one of a family of promoters in that field. Lydia Fowler soon took to the lecture circuit as a phrenologist herself, and she wrote Familiar Lessons on Physiology (1847), Familiar Lessons on Phrenology (1847), and Familiar Lessons on Astronomy (1848) for...
</Question>
<Choice>Fowler, Lydia Folger</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian physician, poet, astronomer, and geologist, who proposed a scientific germ theory of disease more than 300 years before its empirical formulation by Louis Pasteur and Robert Koch.At the University of Padua Fracastoro was a colleague of the astronomer Copernicus. As a physician, he maintained a private practice in Verona. He is best-known for “Syphilis sive morbus Gallicus” (1530; “Syphilis or the French Disease”), a work in rhyme giving an account of the disease, which he named. He made an intense study of epidemic diseases, and, while in the service of Pope Paul III at the Council of...
</Question>
<Choice>Fracastoro, Girolamo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physician who was a pioneer in public health.Frank studied at Heidelberg and Strasbourg. He became court and garrison physician in Rastadt (1769), professor in Göttingen (1784) and in Pavia (1785), director of sanitation in Lombardy (1786), and sanitary officer to the Vienna hospitals (1795). In 1811, after a short time in St. Petersburg as ordinary physician and counselor of state, he returned to practice in Vienna.Frank's fame rests on his massive System einer vollständigen medizinischen Polizey (9 vol., 1779–1827; “System of a Complete Medical Policy”), which covers the hygiene of al...
</Question>
<Choice>Frank, Johann Peter</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German founder of experimental pathology whose emphasis on the teaching of physiology and medical biochemistry helped give clinical medicine a scientific foundation.Frerichs worked at the University of Breslau (1851–59) and then directed the Charité Hospital at the University of Berlin (1859–85). A leading exponent of clinical medicine supported by exacting laboratory analyses and experiments, he decisively influenced the development of his students, one of whom was Paul Ehrlich, a corecipient of the 1908 Nobel Prize for Medicine for work in immunity. Frerichs' investigations into the general...
</Question>
<Choice>Frerichs, Friedrich Theodor von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
zoologist whose studies of communication among bees added significantly to the knowledge of the chemical and visual sensors of insects. He shared the 1973 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine with animal behaviourists Konrad Lorenz and Nikolaas Tinbergen.Frisch received a Ph.D. from the University of Munich in 1910. He was appointed director of the Zoological Institution of the University of Rostock in 1921, and in 1923 he accepted a similar position at the University of Breslau. In 1925 Frisch returned to the University of Munich, where he established the Zoological Institution. When this i...
</Question>
<Choice>Frisch, Karl von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German botanist and physician whose botanical work Historia Stirpium (1542) is a landmark in the development of natural history because of its organized presentation, the accuracy of its drawings and descriptions of plants, and its glossary.Fuchs obtained a humanistic education under Catholic guidance but later adhered to Protestantism. He studied medicine and became a professor at Tübingen. He was most interested in the medicinal properties of plants, and his book was intended primarily as a guide for plant collection. Well acquainted with the Greek and Latin classics, and an excellent observ...
</Question>
<Choice>Fuchs, Leonhard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician and missionary to China who ministered to many thousands not only through her own practice but by greatly expanding the availability of medical education in that country.Fulton was educated at Lawrence University in Appleton, Wisconsin, and at Hillsdale (Michigan) College. She graduated from the latter in 1874, took a master's degree in 1877, and for three years taught in public schools in Indianapolis, Indiana. In 1880 she entered the Woman's Medical College of Pennsylvania, and on graduating in 1884 she set out for southern China, where her elder brother, a minister, had p...
</Question>
<Choice>Fulton, Mary Hannah</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American pharmacologist who, along with Louis J. Ignarro and Ferid Murad, was co-awarded the 1998 Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine for the discovery that nitric oxide (NO) acts as a signaling molecule in the cardiovascular system. Their combined work uncovered an entirely new mechanism by which blood vessels in the body relax and widen.Furchgott received his B.S. in chemistry from the University of North Carolina in 1937 and his Ph.D. in biochemistry from Northwestern University in 1940. He joined SUNY-Brooklyn's department of pharmacology in 1956, a position he held until 1989, when he r...
</Question>
<Choice>Furchgott, Robert F.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician and medical researcher, corecipient (with Baruch S. Blumberg) of the 1976 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for his research on the causal agents of various degenerative neurological disorders.Gajdusek graduated from the University of Rochester (N.Y.) in 1943. He received his M.D. from Harvard University in 1946 and was a fellow in pediatrics and infectious diseases at Harvard from 1949 to 1952. In the next three years he held positions at the Institute of Research of the Walter Reed Army Medical Center in Washington, D.C., and the Institut Pasteur, Tehran. It was in 19...
</Question>
<Choice>Gajdusek, D. Carleton</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek physician, writer, and philosopher who exercised a dominant influence on medical theory and practice in Europe from the Middle Ages until the mid-17th century. His authority in the Byzantine world and the Muslim Middle East was similarly long-lived.
</Question>
<Choice>Galen of Pergamum</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German anatomist and physiologist, a pioneer in ascribing cerebral functions to various areas of the brain (localization). He originated phrenology, the attempt to divine individual intellect and personality from an examination of skull shape.Convinced that mental functions are localized in specific regions of the brain and that human behaviour is dependent upon these functions, Gall assumed that the surface of the skull faithfully reflects the relative development of the various regions of the brain. His popular lectures in Vienna on “cranioscopy” (called phrenology by his followers) offended...
</Question>
<Choice>Gall, Franz Joseph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian physician and physicist who investigated the nature and effects of what he conceived to be electricity in animal tissue. His discoveries led to the invention of the voltaic pile, a kind of battery that makes possible a constant source of current electricity.
</Question>
<Choice>Galvani, Luigi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physiologist, corecipient (with Joseph Erlanger) of the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1944 for fundamental discoveries concerning the functions of different kinds of nerve fibres.At Washington University, St. Louis, Mo. (1916–31), where he was professor of pharmacology, Gasser collaborated with Erlanger in studying the barely detectable electrical impulses carried by isolated mammalian nerve fibres. By 1924 they had succeeded in adapting the oscillograph to physiological research, enabling them to visualize amplified nerve impulses on a fluorescent screen. Using this devic...
</Question>
<Choice>Gasser, Herbert Spencer</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss physician and naturalist, best known for his systematic compilations of information on animals and plants.
</Question>
<Choice>Gesner, Conrad</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
pioneer researcher into magnetism who became the most distinguished man of science in England during the reign of Queen Elizabeth I.Educated as a physician, Gilbert settled in London and began to practice in 1573. His principal work, De Magnete, Magneticisque Corporibus, et de Magno Magnete Tellure (1600; On the Magnet, Magnetic Bodies, and the Great Magnet of the Earth), gives a full account of his research on magnetic bodies and electrical attractions. After years of experiments he concluded that a compass needle points north–south and dips downward because the Earth acts as a bar magnet. Th...
</Question>
<Choice>Gilbert, William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American pharmacologist who shared the 1994 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine with American biochemist Martin Rodbell for their separate research in discovering molecules called G proteins, which are intermediaries in the multistep pathway cells use to react to an incoming signal, such as a hormone or neurotransmitter.Gilman attended Yale University (B.S., 1962) and Case Western Reserve University (M.D. and Ph.D., 1969), where he studied under Nobel Prize recipient Earl W. Sutherland, Jr. Following three years of postdoctoral research at the National Institutes of Health, Gilman took a po...
</Question>
<Choice>Gilman, Alfred G.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American molecular geneticist who, along with Michael S. Brown, was awarded the 1985 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for their elucidation of the process of cholesterol metabolism in the human body.Goldstein received his B.S. degree from Washington and Lee University, Lexington, Va., in 1962 and obtained his medical degree from the Southwestern Medical School of the University of Texas at Dallas in 1966. Goldstein became friends with Brown when they were both working as interns at Massachusetts General Hospital from 1966 to 1968. Goldstein then conducted research under the auspices of t...
</Question>
<Choice>Goldstein, Joseph L.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian physician and cytologist whose investigations into the fine structure of the nervous system earned him (with the Spanish histologist Santiago Ramón y Cajal) the 1906 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine.As a physician at a home for incurables in Abbiategrasso, Italy (1872–75), and with only rudimentary facilities at his disposal, Golgi devised (1873) the silver nitrate method of staining nerve tissue, an invaluable tool in subsequent nerve studies. This stain enabled him to demonstrate the existence of a kind of nerve cell (which came to be known as the Golgi cell) possessing many sh...
</Question>
<Choice>Golgi, Camillo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish anatomist and investigator in cellular physiology and pathology who insisted on the importance of the cell as the centre of nutrition and declared that the cell is divided into a number of departments. He was described as “one of the earliest and most acute observers of cell life” by the noted physiologist Rudolf Virchow, who dedicated his Cellularpathologie (Eng. trans., 1858) to him.In 1841 Goodsir was appointed conservator of the museum of the Royal College of Surgeons in Edinburgh; in 1843 he moved to the University of Edinburgh, becoming curator of the university museum in 1845.
</Question>
<Choice>Goodsir, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. Army surgeon who contributed greatly to the building of the Panama Canal by introducing mosquito control to prevent yellow fever and malaria.After receiving his medical degree (1879) from the Bellevue Hospital Medical College, New York City, Gorgas joined the U.S. Army medical corps in 1880. From 1898 to 1902 he was in charge of sanitation measures in Havana and conducted many experiments on the transmission of yellow fever by the mosquito. Having effectively eliminated yellow fever from the area, he was sent in 1904 as chief sanitary officer to Panama. In two years he eradicated yellow f...
</Question>
<Choice>Gorgas, William Crawford</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch physician who discovered the follicles of the ovary (known as Graafian follicles), in which the individual egg cells are formed. He was also important for his studies on the pancreas and on the reproductive organs of mammals.Graaf obtained his M.D. at the University of Angers, France, in 1665, and settled in Delft in 1667, where he established a medical practice and privately pursued his research. He used the word “ovary” to refer to the female mammalian gonad, and he was the first to note the morphological changes that the ovary undergoes in the course of ovulation.
</Question>
<Choice>Graaf, Reinier de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Finnish-born Swedish physiologist who was a corecipient (with George Wald and Haldan Hartline) of the 1967 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for his analysis of the internal electrical changes that take place when the eye is exposed to light.Granit received an M.D. degree from the University of Helsinki in 1927, after which he conducted research at the University of Pennsylvania and at the laboratory of Sir Charles Scott Sherrington at Oxford, England. He was appointed professor of physiology at the University of Helsinki in 1937. A naturalized Swede, Granit joined the medical school of t...
</Question>
<Choice>Granit, Ragnar Arthur</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Irish physician and a leader of the Irish, or Dublin, school of diagnosis, which emphasized the clinical observation of patients and which significantly advanced the fields of physical diagnosis and internal medicine.Graves received his degree from the University of Dublin in 1818. After studying in London and on the European continent, he returned to Dublin in 1821 and set up the Park Street School of Medicine. He also served as a physician at Meath Hospital, introducing reforms in medical training that he had witnessed on his travels. In addition to teaching traditional textbook medicine, Gr...
</Question>
<Choice>Graves, Robert James</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American neurobiologist who, along with Arvid Carlsson and Eric Kandel, was awarded the 2000 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for his discovery of how dopamine and other neurotransmitters work in the nervous system.After receiving a Ph.D. from Johns Hopkins University in 1953, Greengard became director of the biochemistry department at Geigy Research Laboratories (1959–67) in Ardsley, New York, and held professorships at Albert Einstein College of Medicine (1961–70) and Yale University (1968–83). In 1983 he became professor and head of the Laboratory of Molecular and Cellular Neuroscienc...
</Question>
<Choice>Greengard, Paul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English medical missionary who was the tireless benefactor of the people of Labrador.While still a medical student at London University in 1887, Grenfell was impressed by the sermons of the American evangelist Dwight L. Moody and, in the same year, joined the Royal National Mission to Deep Sea Fishermen. During the next five years he served as surgeon on the first hospital ship dispatched to the North Sea fisheries, and in 1892 he initiated missionary service to the fishermen of Labrador. He soon became absorbed in improving the living conditions of the inhabitants of the Labrador coast, and h...
</Question>
<Choice>Grenfell, Sir Wilfred Thomason</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American surgeon, teacher of medicine, and author of an influential textbook on surgery and a widely read treatise on pathological anatomy.Born and raised on a farm in Pennsylvania, Gross at first was apprenticed to a local country doctor. He continued his education at Wilkes-Barre Academy in Pennsylvania and graduated from Jefferson Medical College in Philadelphia in 1828. After setting up a practice in Philadelphia, Gross began translating medical treatises by foreign authors into English.In 1830 Gross published a treatise on diseases of the bones and joints. Nine years later, he wrote his m...
</Question>
<Choice>Gross, Samuel David</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French-born American physiologist whose researches into the hormones produced by the hypothalamus gland resulted in his being awarded a share (along with Andrew Schally and Rosalyn Yalow) of the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1977.Guillemin was educated at the universities of Dijon, Lyon, and Montreal. He taught at the Baylor College of Medicine in Houston, Texas, from 1953 to 1970, except for the years 1960–63, when he was on the faculty of the Collège de France in Paris. From 1970 he was a resident fellow and research professor at the Salk Institute for Biological Studies in La Jo...
</Question>
<Choice>Guillemin, Roger Charles Louis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
leading English physician of his time, lecturer and physician at Guy's Hospital, London, and an outstanding clinical teacher.Gull received his M.D. from the University of London in 1846 and became lecturer on physiology and anatomy and then physician, at Guy's, where he taught or served as consulting physician for the rest of his life. He was a famous and popular teacher, and some of his epigrams are still current. Gull had a successful and fashionable private practice as well—including among his patients Queen Victoria and the Prince of Wales—which made him wealthier than any English physicia...
</Question>
<Choice>Gull, Sir William Withey, 1st Baronet</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish ophthalmologist, recipient of the 1911 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for his research on the eye as a light-refracting apparatus.Gullstrand studied in Uppsala, Vienna, and Stockholm, earning a doctorate in 1890. He became professor of diseases of the eye at Uppsala in 1894 and in 1913 was appointed professor of physiological and physical optics there.Gullstrand contributed to knowledge of the structure and function of the cornea and to research on astigmatism. He improved corrective lenses for use after surgery for cataracts and devised the Gullstrand slit lamp, a valuable dia...
</Question>
<Choice>Gullstrand, Allvar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian botanist, pioneer in the development of physiological plant anatomy, and the first person to study plant tissue culture (1921).Haberlandt's first botanical paper appeared in 1874, one year after he entered the University of Vienna, where he obtained his Ph.D. (1876). He went to the University of Tübingen (1877) to study under Simon Schwendener, who subsequently influenced Haberlandt's belief that structure and function should be studied together. He returned to Austria in 1880 to teach botany at the Technical Academy in Graz. In 1910 Haberlandt succeeded Schwendener in the chair of pl...
</Question>
<Choice>Haberlandt, Gottlieb</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physician, founder of the system of therapeutics known as homeopathy (q.v.).Hahnemann studied medicine at Leipzig and Vienna, taking the degree of M.D. at Erlangen in 1779. After practicing in various places, he settled in Dresden in 1784 and then moved to Leipzig in 1789. In the following year, while translating William Cullen's Lectures on the Materia medica into German, he was struck by the fact that the symptoms produced by quinine on the healthy body were similar to those of the disordered states that quinine was used to cure. This observation led him to assert the theory that “lik...
</Question>
<Choice>Hahnemann, Samuel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British geneticist, biometrician, physiologist, and popularizer of science who opened new paths of research in population genetics and evolution.Son of the noted physiologist John Scott Haldane, he began studying science as assistant to his father at the age of eight and later received formal education in the classics at Eton College and at New College, Oxford (M.A., 1914). After World War I he served as a fellow of New College and then taught at the University of Cambridge (1922–32), the University of California, Berkeley (1932), and the University of London (1933–57).In the 1930s Haldane bec...
</Question>
<Choice>Haldane, J. B. S.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physiologist and philosopher chiefly noted for his work on the physiology of respiration.Haldane developed several procedures for studying the physiology of breathing and the physiology of the blood and for the analysis of gases consumed or produced by the body. Among his most widely used devices were the hemoglobinometer, an apparatus for the analysis of blood gas, and an apparatus for the analysis of mixtures of gases.In 1905 Haldane reported his fundamental discovery that the regulation of breathing is usually determined by the effect of the tension of carbon dioxide in the blood on...
</Question>
<Choice>Haldane, John Scott</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English botanist, physiologist, and clergyman who pioneered quantitative experimentation in plant and animal physiology.While a divinity student at Corpus Christi College, Cambridge, he studied science, particularly botany and chemistry. Ordained in 1703, he was appointed in 1709 to the parish of Teddington, where he remained until his death.Hales introduced new techniques of measurement to the study of plant physiology. One of the best-known of these concerned the measurement of water vapour emitted by plants. He measured this emission, known as transpiration, finding that it was the leaves t...
</Question>
<Choice>Hales, Stephen</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physiologist who was the first to advance a scientific explanation of reflex action.While maintaining a highly successful private medical practice in London (1826–53), Hall conducted physiological research that gained him renown on the European continent and derision from established medical organizations in England. He denounced the practice of bloodletting in Observations on Blood-Letting (1830). In his Experimental Essay on the Circulation of the Blood (1831), he was the first to show that the capillaries bring the blood into contact with the tissues.Hall's discovery that a headless...
</Question>
<Choice>Hall, Marshall</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss biologist, the father of experimental physiology, who made prolific contributions to physiology, anatomy, botany, embryology, poetry, and scientific bibliography.At the University of Göttingen (1736–53), where he served as professor of medicine, anatomy, surgery, and botany, Haller undertook the exhaustive biological experimentation that was to make his encyclopaedic Elementa Physiologiae Corporis Humani (8 vol., 1757–66; “Physiological Elements of the Human Body”) a landmark in medical history. Because of his impressive accomplishments at the newly formed university, the scientific worl...
</Question>
<Choice>Haller, Albrecht von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English biochemist and corecipient, with Hans von Euler-Chelpin, of the 1929 Nobel Prize for Chemistry for work on the fermentation of sugar and the enzyme action involved.After studies at Manchester and at Erlangen, Germany, Harden became a lecturer-demonstrator at the University of Manchester (1888–97). He took charge of the chemical and water laboratory at the Jenner Institute of Preventive Medicine and from 1907 to 1930 headed the biochemistry department. He became a professor of biochemistry at the University of London in 1912.His more than 20 years of study of the fermentation of sugar a...
</Question>
<Choice>Harden, Sir Arthur</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physiologist who was a cowinner (with George Wald and Ragnar Granit) of the 1967 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for his work in analyzing the neurophysiological mechanisms of vision.Hartline began his study of retinal electrophysiology as a National Research Council Fellow at Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, receiving his M.D. in 1927. After attending the universities of Leipzig and Munich as an Eldridge Johnson traveling research scholar, he became professor of biophysics and chairman of the department at Johns Hopkins in 1949. He joined the staff of Rockefeller Universit...
</Question>
<Choice>Hartline, Haldan Keffer</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American scientist who, with Sir Paul M. Nurse and R. Timothy Hunt, shared the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 2001 for discovering key regulators of the cell cycle.Hartwell studied at the California Institute of Technology (B.S., 1961) and the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (Ph.D., 1964). He served on the faculty of the University of California at Irvine from 1965 to 1968, when he moved to the University of Washington. In 1996 he joined the Fred Hutchinson Cancer Research Center in Seattle, Washington, becoming president and director in 1997.In the late 1960s Hartwell began u...
</Question>
<Choice>Hartwell, Leland H.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physician who was the first to recognize the full circulation of the blood in the human body and to provide experiments and arguments to support this idea.
</Question>
<Choice>Harvey, William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German scientist and philosopher who made fundamental contributions to physiology, optics, electrodynamics, mathematics, and meteorology. He is best known for his statement of the law of the conservation of energy. He brought to his laboratory research the ability to analyze the philosophical assumptions on which much of 19th-century science was based, and he did so with clarity and precision.
</Question>
<Choice>Helmholtz, Hermann von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Flemish physician, philosopher, mystic, and chemist who recognized the existence of discrete gases and identified carbon dioxide.
</Question>
<Choice>Helmont, Jan Baptista van</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician who with Edward C. Kendall in 1948 successfully applied an adrenal hormone (later known as cortisone) in the treatment of rheumatoid arthritis. With Kendall and Tadeus Reichstein of Switzerland, Hench received the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1950 for discoveries concerning hormones of the adrenal cortex, their structure and biological effects.Hench received his medical degree from the University of Pittsburgh in 1920 and spent almost his entire career at the Mayo Clinic in Rochester, Minn. For many years he sought a method of treating the painful and crippling...
</Question>
<Choice>Hench, Philip Showalter</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
physiologist who first used the name plankton to describe the organisms that live suspended in the sea (and in bodies of freshwater) and are important because practically all animal life in the sea is dependent on them, directly or indirectly.Hensen was a professor at the University of Kiel from 1871 to 1911 and led a detailed survey of Atlantic plankton in 1899. He was also known for his work in embryology and in the anatomy and physiology of the sense organs, especially the ear; the cells of Hensen and the canal of Hensen, both within the mammalian inner ear, were named for him.
</Question>
<Choice>Hensen, Victor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physiologist and psychologist whose chief work concerned the physiology of colour perception. He taught at the University of Leipzig (1895), following professorships at the Josephs-Akademie, Vienna (1865–70), and at the University of Prague (1870–95). Hering challenged the colour-vision theory of Hermann von Helmholtz, postulating three types of receptors, each capable of a dual response to pairs of colours (yellow–blue, red–green, or black–white). He also investigated respiration and, with Josef Breuer in 1868, demonstrated the role of the vagus nerve in the regulation of breathing. Th...
</Question>
<Choice>Hering, Ewald</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Alexandrian physician who was an early performer of public dissections on human cadavers; and often called the father of anatomy.As a member of the well-known scholastic community in the newly founded city of Alexandria during the single, brief period in Greek medical history when the ban on human dissection was lifted, Herophilus studied the ventricles (cavities) of the brain, the organ he regarded as the centre of the nervous system; traced the sinuses of the dura mater (the tough membrane covering the brain) to their junction, known as the torcular Herophili; and classified the nerve trunks...
</Question>
<Choice>Herophilus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician and clinical cardiologist who was the first to observe and describe sickle-cell anemia.Herrick received his M.D. from Rush Medical College in 1888. He worked as an intern at Cook County Hospital and then taught at Rush, where he was professor of medicine from 1900 to 1927. He was also on the staff of Presbyterian Hospital in Chicago from 1895 to 1945. His practice, originally in general medicine, soon developed into a specialization in internal medicine, with a particular emphasis on cardiovascular diseases.Among his published material on what came to be known as sickle-cell...
</Question>
<Choice>Herrick, James Bryan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss physiologist, who received (with António Egas Moniz) the 1949 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for discovering the role played by certain parts of the brain in determining and coordinating the functions of internal organs.Originally an ophthalmologist (1906–12), Hess turned to the study of physiology, becoming a research assistant first at the Physiological Institute at the University of Zürich in 1912 and then at the University of Bonn in 1915. In 1917 he was appointed professor of physiology and later director of the Physiological Institute (1917–51) at Zürich. He became interest...
</Question>
<Choice>Hess, Walter Rudolf</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British anatomist and physiologist who described blood coagulation and isolated a key protein in the coagulation process, fibrinogen, which he called coagulable lymph. He also investigated the structure of the lymphatic system and described red blood cells.Hewson was trained in medicine at William Hunter's anatomy school in London (1759–61) and at Edinburgh (1761–62). He then returned to Hunter's school as a partner, but after a dispute with Hunter over the priority of his discoveries, he left in 1772 to establish his own school. In 1770 he was elected to the Royal Society and was awarded the...
</Question>
<Choice>Hewson, William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Belgian physiologist who received the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1938 for his discovery of the regulatory effect on respiration of sensory organs associated with the carotid artery in the neck and with the aortic arch leading from the heart.After taking his M.D. degree at the University of Ghent in 1920, Heymans studied physiology in Paris, Lausanne, Vienna, London, and the United States. In 1930 he succeeded his father, Jean-François Heymans, as professor of pharmacology at Ghent. His research, which was begun in collaboration with his father, sought to determine the way in whi...
</Question>
<Choice>Heymans, Corneille</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physiologist and biophysicist who received (with Otto Meyerhof) the 1922 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for discoveries concerning the production of heat in muscles. His research helped establish the origin of muscular force in the breakdown of carbohydrates with formation of lactic acid in the absence of oxygen.At the University of Cambridge (1911–14) Hill began his investigations of the physiological thermodynamics of muscle and nerve tissue. Working with a straplike thigh muscle in the frog, he was able to demonstrate that oxygen is needed only for the recovery, not the cont...
</Question>
<Choice>Hill, A. V.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
ancient Greek physician who lived during Greece's Classical period and is traditionally regarded as the father of medicine. It is difficult to isolate the facts of Hippocrates' life from the later tales told about him or to assess his medicine accurately in the face of centuries of reverence for him as the ideal physician. About 60 medical writings have survived that bear his name, most of which were not written by him. He has been revered for his ethical standards in medical practice, mainly for the Hippocratic Oath, which, it is suspected, he did not write.
</Question>
<Choice>Hippocrates</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American pharmacologist who, along with Gertrude B. Elion and Sir James W. Black, received the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1988 for their development of drugs that became essential in the treatment of several major diseases.Hitchings received his bachelor's and master's degrees from the University of Washington and earned a Ph.D. in biochemistry at Harvard University in 1933. He taught at Harvard until 1939, and in 1942 he joined the Burroughs Wellcome Laboratories, at which he conducted research until his retirement in 1975.Over a span of nearly 40 years, Hitchings worked with E...
</Question>
<Choice>Hitchings, George Herbert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American plant physiologist and authority on plant and soil interactions.Hoagland graduated from Stanford University (1907) with a major in chemistry. In 1908 he became an instructor and assistant in the Laboratory of Animal Nutrition at the University of California at Berkeley, an institution with which he would be associated for the remainder of his life. He worked in the field of animal nutrition and biochemistry until 1912, when he entered the graduate school in the department of agricultural chemistry at the University of Wisconsin, receiving his master's degree in 1913. The following yea...
</Question>
<Choice>Hoagland, Dennis Robert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physiologist and biophysicist, who received (with Andrew Fielding Huxley and Sir John Eccles) the 1963 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for the discovery of the chemical processes responsible for the passage of impulses along individual nerve fibres.Hodgkin was educated at Trinity College, Cambridge. After conducting radar research (1939–45) for the British Air Ministry, he joined the faculty at Cambridge, where he worked (1945–52) with Huxley on measuring the electrical and chemical behaviour of individual nerve fibres. By inserting microelectrodes into the giant nerve fibres of...
</Question>
<Choice>Hodgkin, Sir Alan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physician who early described (1832) the malignant disease of lymph tissue that bears his name.Educated at the University of Edinburgh, Hodgkin was an associate of the eminent physicians Richard Bright and Thomas Addison at Guy's Hospital, London. His achievements in the field of pathology also include one of the earliest descriptions of aortic insufficiency (1827).
</Question>
<Choice>Hodgkin, Thomas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biochemist who shared the Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine in 1968 with Marshall Warren Nirenberg and Har Gobind Khorana. Their research helped explain how the genetic code controls the synthesis of proteins.Holley obtained his Ph.D. in organic chemistry from Cornell University, Ithaca, N.Y., in 1947. He investigated a variety of biochemical questions at the state and federal agricultural experiment stations at Cornell (1948–64). He began his research on RNA after spending a year studying with James F. Bonner at the California Institute of Technology (1955–56).By 1960 Holley and...
</Question>
<Choice>Holley, Robert William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician, poet, and humorist notable for his medical research and teaching, and as the author of the “Breakfast-Table” series of essays.Holmes read law at Harvard University before deciding on a medical career; and, following studies at Harvard and in Paris, he received his degree from Harvard in 1836. He practiced medicine for 10 years, taught anatomy for two years at Dartmouth College (Hanover, N.H.), and in 1847 became professor of anatomy and physiology at Harvard. He was later made dean of the Harvard Medical School, a post he held until 1882. His most important medical contribu...
</Question>
<Choice>Holmes, Oliver Wendell</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Czech poet noted for his detached, lyrical reflections on humanist and scientific subjects.A clinical pathologist and immunologist by profession, Holub received his M.D. from the Charles University School of Medicine (1953) and his Ph.D. from the Czechoslovak (now Czech) Academy of Sciences Institute of Microbiology (1958), both in Prague. His first poetry was published in 1947; by the mid-1950s he was associated with the young writers of the literary magazine Kveten, who opposed the bombastic Socialist Realism promoted by Czechoslovakia's communist rulers. His first verse collection was Denní...
</Question>
<Choice>Holub, Miroslav</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British biochemist, who received (with Christiaan Eijkman) the 1929 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for discovery of essential nutrient factors—now known as vitamins—needed in animal diets to maintain health.In 1901 Hopkins discovered the amino acidtryptophan, isolated it from protein, and eventually (1906–07) showed that it and certain other amino acids (known as essential amino acids) cannot be manufactured by certain animals from other nutrients and must be supplied in the diet. Noticing that rats failed to grow on a diet of artificial milk but grew rapidly when a small quantity of c...
</Question>
<Choice>Hopkins, Sir Frederick Gowland</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physician, known for his work toward establishing physiological chemistry (biochemistry) as an academic discipline. He was the first to obtain lecithin in a pure form and introduced the word proteid (now protein). Additional contributions included metabolic studies and researches on chlorophyll and on blood, especially hemoglobin, which he obtained in crystalline form.Hoppe-Seyler founded (1877) and edited the first biochemical journal, Zeitschrift für Physiologische Chemie, and, apart from numerous scientific papers, published Physiologische Chemie, 4 vol. (1877–81), and Handbuch der P...
</Question>
<Choice>Hoppe-Seyler, Ernst Felix Immanuel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian musicologist and ethnologist.Brought up in a highly musical home, Hornbostel studied piano, harmony, and counterpoint. Although by his late teens he was a skilled performer and composer, his university studies (at Heidelberg, 1895–99) were in the natural sciences and philosophy, and his Ph.D. was in chemistry (Heidelberg, 1900). He then moved to Berlin, where, influenced by Carl Stumpf, he combined his musicological studies with experimental psychology, especially the phenomena of tone psychology. He became assistant to Stumpf at the Psychological Institute, and, when its archives bec...
</Question>
<Choice>Hornbostel, Erich Moritz von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physiologist and neurosurgeon who was first to remove a spinal tumour (1887). He also made valuable studies of thyroid activity, rabies prevention, and the functions of localized areas of the brain.By removing the thyroid glands of monkeys, he was able to establish (1883) the gland's role in determining the body's rate of growth, development, and metabolism and to implicate thyroid malfunction as the cause of myxedema (a condition characterized by dry, waxy swelling) and cretinism. As secretary to a government commission (1886) appointed to study the effectiveness of Louis Pasteur's ra...
</Question>
<Choice>Horsley, Sir Victor Alexander Haden</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biologist who, with Sydney Brenner and John E. Sulston, won the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 2002 for their discoveries about how genes regulate tissue and organ development via a key mechanism called programmed cell death, or apoptosis.Horvitz received a B.A. (1972) and a Ph.D. (1974) from Harvard University. In 1978, after a stint with Brenner at the Medical Research Council in England, he moved to the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, where he became a full professor in 1986.In the 1970s Horvitz began his prizewinning work on programmed cell death, a process that...
</Question>
<Choice>Horvitz, H. Robert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English electrical engineer who shared the 1979 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine with Allan Cormack for his part in developing the diagnostic technique of computerized axial tomography (CAT), or computerized tomography (CT). In this technique, information obtained from X rays taken by scanners rotating around the patient are combined by a computer to yield a high-resolution image of a slice of the body.After studying electronics and radar as a member of the Royal Air Force during World War II and at Faraday House Electrical Engineering College in London, Hounsfield joined the research st...
</Question>
<Choice>Hounsfield, Sir Godfrey Newbold</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Canadian-born American surgeon and urologist whose investigations demonstrated the relationship between hormones and certain types of cancer. For his discoveries Huggins received (with Peyton Rous) the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1966.Huggins was educated at Acadia University (Wolfville, N.S.) and at Harvard University, where he received his M.D. in 1924. He went to the University of Michigan for further training in surgery (1924–27) and then joined the faculty of the University of Chicago, where he served as director of the Ben May Laboratory for Cancer Research from 1951 to 196...
</Question>
<Choice>Huggins, Charles B.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician and reformer whose medical practice, though not sanctioned by a degree for some 20 years, achieved considerable success by applying principles of good nutrition, exercise, and physical and mental hygiene.Hunt was reared in a family of liberal social and religious views and educated privately. She opened a school of her own in her parents' house in 1827. The lengthy illness of her sister in the early 1830s, during which a series of physicians demonstrated the futility of a variety of therapies, induced Hunt and her sister to begin studying in 1833 under an English couple name...
</Question>
<Choice>Hunt, Harriot Kezia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British scientist who, with Leland H. Hartwell and Sir Paul M. Nurse, won the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 2001 for discovering key regulators of the cell cycle.After receiving a Ph.D. from the University of Cambridge in 1968, Hunt conducted research at the Albert Einstein College of Medicine in New York. He later taught at Cambridge (1981–90) and in 1991 became principal scientist at the Imperial Cancer Research Fund (now Cancer Research UK).Hunt's research centred on the chain of events that a cell undergoes from one division to another. Known as the cell cycle, the process incl...
</Question>
<Choice>Hunt, R. Timothy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
surgeon, founder of pathological anatomy in England, and early advocate of investigation and experimentation. He also carried out many important studies and experiments in comparative aspects of biology, anatomy, physiology, and pathology.Hunter never completed a course of studies in any university, and, as was common for surgeons during the 18th century, he never attempted to become a doctor of medicine. He went to London in 1748 to assist in the preparation of dissections for the course of anatomy taught by his brother William, a famed obstetrician. For 11 winters he studied anatomy in his b...
</Question>
<Choice>Hunter, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British obstetrician, educator, and medical writer who did much, by his high standards of teaching and medical practice, to remove obstetrics from the hands of the midwives and establish it as an accepted branch of medicine.Hunter received his medical degree from the University of Glasgow in 1750 and became a licensed physician in London in 1756. He did his first teaching in 1746 and continued to lecture, usually on topics of surgery or anatomy, throughout his life. While in France (1743–44 and 1748) he observed that individual medical students in that country were provided with cadavers for d...
</Question>
<Choice>Hunter, William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physiologist, cowinner (with Sir Alan Hodgkin and Sir John Carew Eccles) of the 1963 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine. His researches centred on nerve and muscle fibres and dealt particularly with the chemical phenomena involved in the transmission of nerve impulses. He was knighted in 1974 and was president of the Royal Society from 1980 to 1985.Andrew Fielding, a grandson of the biologist T.H. Huxley and son of the biographer and man of letters Leonard Huxley, received his M.A. from Trinity College, Cambridge, where later, from 1941 to 1960, he was a fellow and then director of...
</Question>
<Choice>Huxley, Sir Andrew Fielding</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Arab physician who first described the pulmonary circulation of the blood. In finding that the wall between the right and left ventricles of the heart is solid and without pores, he disputed Galen's view that the blood passes directly from the right to the left side of the heart. Ibn an-Nafis correctly stated that the blood must pass from the right ventricle to the left ventricle by way of the lungs. But the significance of his statement remained unheeded, and, in fact, was probably unknown by physicians in western countries. It was only in the 20th century that his work was brought to light....
</Question>
<Choice>Ibn an-Nafis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French Jewish physician, translator, and astronomer whose work was utilized by Copernicus and Dante. He was highly regarded as a physician and served as regent of the faculty of medicine at the University of Montpellier. He was the grandson of the renowned translator Samuel ben Judah ibn Tibbon.Jacob translated into Hebrew a large number of works, including Arabic versions of Euclid's Elements and Ptolemy's encyclopaedic work on astronomy, the Almagest. He also translated Arabic works by al-Ghazali (1058–1111) and Averroës.As a student of astronomy, Jacob described a quadrant of his own invent...
</Question>
<Choice>ibn Tibbon, Jacob ben Machir</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
one of medieval Islam's foremost thinkers and the greatest medical clinician of the western caliphate.An intensely practical man, Ibn Zuhr disliked medical speculation; for that reason, he opposed the teachings of the Persian master physician Avicenna. In his Taysir fi al-mudawat wa al-tadbir (“Practical Manual of Treatments and Diet”), later translated into Hebrew and Latin, he described serious pericarditis (inflammation of the membranous sac surrounding the heart) and mediastinal abscesses (affecting the organs and tissues in the thoracic cavity above the diaphragm, excluding the lungs) and...
</Question>
<Choice>Ibn Zuhr</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American pharmacologist who, along with Robert F. Furchgott and Ferid Murad, was co-awarded the 1998 Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine for the discovery that nitric oxide (NO) acts as a signaling molecule in the cardiovascular system. This work uncovered an entirely new mechanism by which blood vessels in the body relax and widen.Ignarro studied at Columbia University, earning a bachelor's degree in pharmacy in 1962. He received his Ph.D. in pharmacology from the University of Minnesota in 1966. In 1979 he became a professor of pharmacology at Tulane University's School of Medicine in New...
</Question>
<Choice>Ignarro, Louis J.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
vizier, sage, architect, astrologer, and chief minister to Djoser (reigned 2630–2611 BCE), the second king of Egypt's third dynasty, who was later worshipped as the god of medicine in Egypt and in Greece, where he was identified with the Greek god of medicine, Asclepius. He is considered to have been the architect of the step pyramid built at the necropolis of ?aqqarah in the city of Memphis. The oldest extant monument of hewn stone known to the world, the pyramid consists of six steps and attains a height of 200 feet (61 metres).Although no contemporary account has been found that refers to I...
</Question>
<Choice>Imhotep</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch-born British physician and scientist who is best known for his discovery of the process of photosynthesis, by which green plants in sunlight absorb carbon dioxide and release oxygen.As a physician in London (1765–68), Ingenhousz was an early proponent of variolation, or the inoculation against smallpox through the use of live, unmodified virus taken from patients with mild cases of the disease. In 1768 he traveled to Vienna to inoculate the family of the Austrian empress Maria Theresa and subsequently served as court physician. Returning to London in 1779, he published the results of an...
</Question>
<Choice>Ingenhousz, Jan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jewish physician and philosopher, widely reputed in the European Middle Ages for his scientific writings and regarded as the father of medieval Jewish Neoplatonism. Although there is considerable disagreement about his birth and death dates, he is known to have lived more than 100 years and never to have married or to have had children.Israeli first gained note as an oculist, maintaining a practice near Cairo until about 904, when he became court physician in Al-Qayrawan to the last Aghlabid prince, Ziyadat Allah. He also studied medicine there under Is?aq ibn ?Amran al-Baghdadi, with whom he...
</Question>
<Choice>Israeli, Isaac ben Solomon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician, chemist, and pioneer geologist and mineralogist.Jackson received his M.D. from Harvard Medical School in 1829. He continued his medical studies at the University of Paris, also attending lectures on geology at the Royal School of Mines. He returned to Boston in 1832 and started a private medical practice but abandoned medicine in 1836 to establish a laboratory for the teaching of analytic chemistry. One of his students was a young dental surgeon, William Thomas Green Morton, with whom Jackson worked on chemical methods for painless dentistry.In 1845 Morton learned from Hora...
</Question>
<Choice>Jackson, Charles Thomas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician and educator, a pioneer in the struggle for the admission of women to the practice of medicine.Mercy Ruggles received what was for the time a good education. In June 1823 she married the Reverend John Bisbe, with whom she moved to Hartford, Connecticut, and later to Portland, Maine. After his death in 1829, she supported herself and her children by operating a girls' school until 1832, when she opened a dry-goods store. In 1835 she married Captain Daniel Jackson of Plymouth, Massachusetts. Her long-standing interest in medicine, particularly the treatment of children (of whi...
</Question>
<Choice>Jackson, Mercy Ruggles Bisbe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French biologist who, together with André Lwoff and Jacques Monod, was awarded the 1965 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for discoveries concerning regulatory activities in bacteria.Jacob received his M.D. degree (1947) and a doctorate in science (1954) from the Faculty of Medicine and the Faculty of Science, respectively, in Paris. Most of the work of Jacob, Lwoff, and Monod was carried out at the Pasteur Institute (Paris), which Jacob had joined as a research assistant in 1950. In 1960 he became head of the department of cellular genetics at the institute, and from 1965 he was also pro...
</Question>
<Choice>Jacob, Francois</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-born physician who established the first clinic for diseases of children in the United States (1860) and is considered the founder of American pediatrics.Because he took part in the German revolutionary movement (1848), Jacobi was imprisoned in Berlin and Cologne during the year of his graduation in medicine (1851). In 1853 he began his medical practice in New York City and became professor of children's diseases at the New York Medical College in 1860, holding the first chair in the subject founded in the United States. He later held professorships at New York University (1865–70) and...
</Question>
<Choice>Jacobi, Abraham</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician, writer, and suffragist who is considered to have been the foremost woman doctor of her era.Mary Putnam was the daughter of George Palmer Putnam, founder of the publishing firm of G.P. Putnam's Sons, and was an elder sister of Herbert Putnam, later librarian of Congress. The family returned from England in 1848, and Mary grew up in Staten Island, Yonkers, and Morrisania, New York. Her scientific bent determined her on a medical career, but in 1860, before she was 18, she had a story published in The Atlantic Monthly. She graduated from the New York College of Pharmacy in 186...
</Question>
<Choice>Jacobi, Mary Putnam</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physiologist who was a pioneer in the scientific study of alcoholism.Jellinek studied at several European universities and received his master's degree in 1914 from the University of Leipzig. He became a biometrician (i.e., one concerned with the statistics of biological studies) and worked for various institutions and organizations in Budapest (1914–20), Sierra Leone (1920–25), Honduras (1925–30), and at the Worcester State Hospital, Mass. (1931–39). In 1939 he began directing that hospital's studies on the effects of alcohol, and in 1941 he became an associate professor of applied p...
</Question>
<Choice>Jellinek, Elvin M.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Danish immunologist who shared the 1984 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine with César Milstein and Georges Köhler for his theoretical contributions to the understanding of the immune system.Jerne was born of Danish parents and grew up in The Netherlands. After studying physics for two years at the University of Leiden, Netherlands, he worked at the Danish State Serum Institute from 1943 to 1956. He received his medical degree from the University of Copenhagen in 1951, and in 1956 he was appointed chief medical officer of the World Health Organization, a position he held until 1962. During...
</Question>
<Choice>Jerne, Niels K.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physician who successfully sought legislation (1876) permitting women in Britain to receive the M.D. degree and a license to practice medicine and surgery. Through her efforts a medical school for women was opened in London in 1874, and in 1886 she established one in Edinburgh.Jex-Blake attended Queen's College, London, and then studied for three years in Boston and New York, returning to England in 1868. She was admitted to classes in medicine at the University of Edinburgh but was not allowed to take a degree. In 1877 she obtained the M.D. of the University of Bern and, through the K...
</Question>
<Choice>Jex-Blake, Sophia Louisa</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
pope from 1276 to 1277, one of the most scholarly pontiffs in papal history.Educated at the University of Paris (c.. 1228–35), where he received his master's degree c. 1240, John taught medicine at the new University of Siena, Italy. In 1272 Pope Gregory X, who made John his personal physician, appointed him archbishop of Braga and cardinal bishop of Tusculum in 1273 (consecrated 1274). After the five-week pontificate of Adrian V, John was elected on Sept. 8, 1276. He chose as his principal adviser Cardinal John Gaetan Orsini, who soon was to succeed him as Nicholas III. John's short pontifica...
</Question>
<Choice>John XXI</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian-born American neurobiologist who, with Arvid Carlsson and Paul Greengard, was awarded the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 2000 for discovering the central role synapses play in memory and learning.Kandel received a medical degree from New York University's School of Medicine in 1956. Following residency in psychiatry and employment at Harvard University, he served as associate professor at New York University (1965–74). Beginning in 1974, Kandel held a series of professorships at Columbia University, where he also directed its Center for Neurobiology and Behavior until 1983....
</Question>
<Choice>Kandel, Eric</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-born British physiologist who investigated the functioning of nerves and muscles. His studies on the release of the neurotransmitter acetylcholine—which carries impulses from nerve fibre to muscle fibre or from one nerve ending to another—won him a share (with Julius Axelrod and Ulf von Euler) of the 1970 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine.After receiving a medical degree from the University of Leipzig in 1934, Katz immigrated to England, where he pursued advanced studies at University College in London, taking a Ph.D. in 1938. Upon receiving a Carnegie fellowship, he studied in Aus...
</Question>
<Choice>Katz, Sir Bernard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
doctor who was the United States' first brain surgeon.After graduating (M.D., 1862) from Jefferson Medical College, Philadelphia, Keen was a surgeon for the U.S. Army in 1862–64 during the American Civil War. The next two years he did postgraduate work in Paris and Berlin. On his return to the United States, he became a lecturer in surgical pathology (1866–75) at his alma mater, concurrently teaching at the Philadelphia School of Anatomy. He also taught at the Women's Medical College of Philadelphia (1884–89) and was a professor of surgery (1889–1907) at Jefferson Medical College.Keen was one...
</Question>
<Choice>Keen, William Williams</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician and health-food pioneer whose development of dry breakfast cereals was largely responsible for the creation of the flaked-cereal industry.Kellogg received his M.D. from Bellevue Hospital Medical College, New York City, in 1875. A Seventh-day Adventist and vegetarian, Kellogg became superintendent in 1876 of the Seventh-day Adventist Western Health Reform Institute, which then became the Battle Creek Sanitarium. (In 1959 it was renamed the Battle Creek Health Center.) Kellogg developed numerous nut and vegetable products to vary the diet of the patients, including a flaked-wh...
</Question>
<Choice>Kellogg, John Harvey</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American chemist who, with Philip S. Hench and Tadeus Reichstein, won the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1950 for research on the structure and biological effects of adrenal cortex hormones.A graduate of Columbia University (Ph.D. 1910), Kendall joined the staff of the Mayo Foundation, Rochester, Minn., in 1914. His early research concerned the isolation of the active constituent (thyroxine) of the thyroid hormone. He also crystallized and established the chemical nature of glutathione, a compound important to biological oxidation-reduction reactions.Kendall's most important researc...
</Question>
<Choice>Kendall, Edward Calvin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physiologist who was the first to trace the movements of sodium and potassium during the transmission of a nerve impulse by using radioactive sodium and potassium.Keynes graduated from the University of Cambridge with a degree in natural science (1946). After receiving a Ph.D. in 1949 from Cambridge, he joined its faculty. Keynes was head of the physiology department of the Agricultural Research Council's Institute of Animal Physiology at Babraham in 1960–64 and assumed the directorship of the institute from 1965 to 1973. He then taught physiology at Cambridge (1973–87).Keynes contribu...
</Question>
<Choice>Keynes, Richard Darwin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian-born American biochemist who shared the Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine in 1968 with Marshall W. Nirenberg and Robert W. Holley for research that helped to show how the nucleotides in nucleic acids, which carry the genetic code of the cell, control the cell's synthesis of proteins.Khorana was born into a poor family and attended Punjab University at Lahore and the University of Liverpool, England, on government scholarships. He obtained his Ph.D. at Liverpool in 1948. He began research on nucleic acids during a fellowship at the University of Cambridge (1951) under Sir Alexander T...
</Question>
<Choice>Khorana, Har Gobind</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jesuit priest and scholar, sometimes called the last Renaissance man, important for his prodigious activity in disseminating knowledge.Kircher learned Greek and Hebrew at the Jesuit school in Fulda, pursued scientific and humanistic studies at Paderborn, Cologne, and Koblenz, and in 1628 was ordained at Mainz. He fled the increasing factional and dynastic fighting in Germany (part of the Thirty Years' War) and, after occupying various academic positions at Avignon, settled in 1634 in Rome. There he remained for most of his life, functioning as a kind of one-man intellectual clearinghouse for c...
</Question>
<Choice>Kircher, Athanasius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese physician and bacteriologist who helped discover a method to prevent tetanus and diphtheria and, in the same year as Alexandre Yersin, discovered the infectious agent responsible for the bubonic plague.Kitasato began his study of medicine at Igakusho Hospital (now Kumamoto Medical School). When his mentor, Dutch physician C.G. van Mansvelt, left the school, Kitasato entered Tokyo Medical School (now the Faculty of Medicine, University of Tokyo). After graduation (M.D., 1883) he carried out bacteriological research at the Central Sanitary Bureau of the Ministry of Home Affairs.In 1885...
</Question>
<Choice>Kitasato Shibasaburo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician whose popular treatise on birth control, the object of celebrated court actions in the United States and England, initiated the widespread use of contraceptives.A graduate (M.D., 1824) of Dartmouth College, Hanover, N.H., Knowlton published anonymously a book advising couples of birth-control methods, The Fruits of Philosophy: or The Private Companion of Young Married People (1832), the first work of its kind in the United States. A second edition, bearing the author's name, appeared in 1833.Although the treatise presented a temperate discussion of the medical, social, and e...
</Question>
<Choice>Knowlton, Charles</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physician and one of the founders of bacteriology. He discovered the anthrax disease cycle (1876) and the bacteria responsible for tuberculosis (1882) and cholera (1883). For his discoveries in regard to tuberculosis, he received the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1905.
</Question>
<Choice>Koch, Robert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss surgeon who won the 1909 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for his work on the thyroid gland.After qualifying in medicine at the University of Bern in 1865, Kocher studied in Berlin, London, Paris, and Vienna, where he was a pupil of Theodor Billroth. In 1872 he became professor of clinical surgery at Bern, remaining at the head of the surgical clinic for 45 years. There Kocher became the first surgeon to excise the thyroid gland in the treatment of goitre (1876). In 1883 he announced his discovery of a characteristic cretinoid pattern in patients after total excision of the thyroid...
</Question>
<Choice>Kocher, Emil Theodor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German immunologist who in 1984, with César Milstein and Niels K. Jerne, received the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for his work in developing a technique for producing monoclonal antibodies—pure, uniform, and highly sensitive protein molecules used in diagnosing and combating a number of diseases (see ).Köhler obtained his doctoral degree in biology (1974) from the University of Freiburg in West Germany. From 1974 to 1976 he worked with Milstein at the Medical Research Council Laboratory of Molecular Biology in Cambridge, England. Together, in 1975, they discovered the technique for...
</Question>
<Choice>Kohler, Georges J. F.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biochemist and physician who received (with Severo Ochoa) the 1959 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for discovering the means by which deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) molecules are duplicated in the bacterial cell, as well as the means for reconstructing this duplication process in the test tube.At the U.S. National Institutes of Health, Bethesda, Md. (1942–53), Kornberg directed research on enzymes and intermediary metabolism. He also helped discover the chemical reactions in the cell that result in the construction of flavine adenine dinucleotide (FAD) and diphosphopyridine nucleo...
</Question>
<Choice>Kornberg, Arthur</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German biochemist who was awarded the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1910 for his contributions to understanding the chemistry of nucleic acids and proteins. He discovered the nucleic acids that are the bases in the DNA molecule, the genetic substance of the cell.After graduating in medicine (1878) from the German University (now the University of Strasbourg), Kossel did research there and at the Physiological Institute in Berlin. In 1895 he became professor of physiology and director of the Physiological Institute at Marburg, going in 1901 to a similar post at Heidelberg, where he...
</Question>
<Choice>Kossel, Albrecht</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-born British biochemist who received (with Fritz Lipmann) the 1953 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for the discovery in living organisms of the series of chemical reactions known as the tricarboxylic acid cycle (also called the citric acid cycle, or Krebs cycle). These reactions involve the conversion—in the presence of oxygen—of substances that are formed by the breakdown of sugars, fats, and protein components to carbon dioxide, water, and energy-rich compounds.At the University of Freiburg (1932), Krebs discovered (with the German biochemist Kurt Henseleit) a series of chemica...
</Question>
<Choice>Krebs, Sir Hans Adolf</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Danish physiologist who received the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1920 for his discovery of the motor-regulating mechanism of capillaries (small blood vessels).Krogh studied zoology at the University of Copenhagen, becoming professor of animal physiology there in 1916. In 1906 he was awarded a prize by the Vienna Academy of Science for investigations described in his treatise Mechanism of Gas Exchange in Lungs. Krogh found that the capillaries contract or dilate in proportion to the tissue's requirement for blood—that active muscles, for example, have a greater number of open capi...
</Question>
<Choice>Krogh, August</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physician and philosopher whose Materialistic interpretation of psychic phenomena laid the groundwork for future developments of behaviourism and played an important part in the history of modern Materialism.La Mettrie obtained a medical degree at Reims, studied medicine in Leiden under Hermann Boerhaave (some of whose works he translated into French), and served as surgeon to the French military. A personal illness convinced him that psychic phenomena were directly related to organic changes in the brain and nervous system. The outcry following publication of these views in Histoire na...
</Question>
<Choice>La Mettrie, Julien Offroy de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physician who invented the stethoscope and perfected the art of auditory examination of the chest cavity.When Laënnec was five years old, his mother, Michelle Félicité Guesdon, died from tuberculosis, leaving Laënnec and his brother, Michaud, in the incompetent care of their father, Théophile-Marie Laënnec, who worked as a civil servant and had a reputation for reckless spending. In 1793, during the French Revolution, Laënnec went to live with his uncle, Guillaume-François Laënnec, in the port city of Nantes, located in the Pays de la Loire region of western France. Laënnec's uncle was...
</Question>
<Choice>Laennec, Rene-Theophile-Hyacinthe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British medical journal established in 1823. The journal's founder and first editor was Thomas Wakley, considered at the time to be a radical reformer. Wakley stated the intent of the new journal was to report on the metropolitan hospital lectures and to describe the important cases of the day. The Lancet has since played an important role in medical and hospital reform movements in England and has become a highly prestigious medical journal around the world.
</Question>
<Choice>Lancet, The</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian clinician and anatomist who is considered the first modern hygienist.Lancisi graduated in medicine from the University of Rome at age 18. He was appointed physician to Pope Innocent XI in 1688 and subsequently was physician to Popes Innocent XII and Clement XI. Lancisi's monographs on influenza, cattle plague (rinderpest), and malaria revealed his gifts as an epidemiologist. In his book De noxiis paludum effluviis (1717; “On the Noxious Effluvia of Marshes”) he related the prevalence of malaria in swampy districts to the presence of mosquitoes and recommended drainage of the swamps to...
</Question>
<Choice>Lancisi, Giovanni Maria</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian American immunologist and pathologist who received the 1930 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for his discovery of the major blood groups and the development of the ABO system of blood typing that has made blood transfusion a routine medical practice.After receiving his M.D. in 1891 from the University of Vienna, Landsteiner studied organic chemistry with many notable scientists in Europe, including the German chemist Emil Fischer. In 1897 he returned to the University of Vienna, where he pursued his interest in the emerging field of immunology and in 1901 published his discovery...
</Question>
<Choice>Landsteiner, Karl</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French military surgeon in the service of Napoleon; he introduced field hospitals, ambulance service, and first-aid practices to the battlefield.Larrey began his medical studies with his uncle in Toulouse and, in 1787, traveled to North America. Returning to Paris, he continued his studies and during the Revolution, in 1792, was attached to the Army of the North. He eventually became principal surgeon of the French Army and thereafter followed Napoleon Bonaparte in almost all his campaigns—in Egypt, in Italy, in Germany and Austria, in Russia, and, finally, at Waterloo. Napoleon made him baron...
</Question>
<Choice>Larrey, Dominique-Jean, Baron</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American chemist who, with English physicist Sir Peter Mansfield, won the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 2003 for the development of magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), a computerized scanning technology that produces images of internal body structures, especially those comprising soft tissues.Lauterbur received a Ph.D. in chemistry from the University of Pittsburgh in 1962. He served as a professor at the University of New York at Stony Brook from 1969 to 1985, when he accepted the position of professor at the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign and director of its Biomedical...
</Question>
<Choice>Lauterbur, Paul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physician, pathologist, and parasitologist who discovered the parasite that causes human malaria. For this and later work on protozoal diseases he received the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1907.Educated at the Strasbourg faculty of medicine, he served as an army surgeon in the Franco-German War (1870–71) and practiced and taught military medicine until 1897, when he joined the Pasteur Institute, Paris. While serving as a military surgeon in Algeria in 1880, Laveran discovered the cause of malaria in the course of the autopsies he conducted on malaria victims. He found the c...
</Question>
<Choice>Laveran, Alphonse</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician and member of the commission that proved that the infectious agent of yellow fever is transmitted by a mosquito, later known as Aëdes aegypti.Lazear received his medical degree (1892) from the College of Physicians and Surgeons of Columbia University. After a period of study in Europe, he joined the staff of Johns Hopkins Hospital, Baltimore, where he was among the first to investigate the structure of the malarial parasite. In 1900 he went to Cuba as a surgeon with the U.S. Army. There he was asked to join the yellow-fever commission, which included Walter Reed, James Carro...
</Question>
<Choice>Lazear, Jesse William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American geneticist, pioneer in the field of bacterial genetics, who shared the 1958 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine (with George W. Beadle and Edward L. Tatum) for discovering the mechanisms of genetic recombination in bacteria.Lederberg studied under Tatum at Yale (Ph.D., 1948) and taught at the University of Wisconsin (1947–59), where he established a department of medical genetics. In 1959 he joined the faculty of the Stanford Medical School, serving as director of the Kennedy Laboratories of Molecular Medicine there from 1962 to 1978, when he moved to New York City to become presid...
</Question>
<Choice>Lederberg, Joshua</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
neurologist who, with biochemist Stanley Cohen, shared the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1986 for her discovery of a bodily substance that stimulates and influences the growth of nerve cells. She held dual citizenship in Italy and the United States.Levi-Montalcini studied medicine at the University of Turin and did research there on the effects that peripheral tissues have on nerve cell growth. Forced into hiding in Florence during the German occupation of Italy (1943–45) because of her Jewish ancestry, she was able to resume her research at Turin after the war. In 1947 she accepte...
</Question>
<Choice>Levi-Montalcini, Rita</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American developmental geneticist who, along with geneticists Christiane Nüsslein-Volhard and Eric F. Wieschaus, was awarded the 1995 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for discovering the functions that control early embryonic development.Lewis's interest in genetics was kindled in high school. He studied biostatistics at the University of Minnesota (B.A., 1939) and genetics at the California Institute of Technology (Ph.D., 1942), where he taught from 1946 to 1988. Working independently of Nüsslein-Volhard and Wieschaus, Lewis based his research on studies of the fruit fly, or vinegar fly...
</Question>
<Choice>Lewis, Edward B.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physician, classical scholar, founder and first president of the Royal College of Physicians of London.Educated at the University of Oxford (1480–84), Linacre traveled extensively through Italy (1485–97), studying Greek and Latin classics under several noted scholars, and medicine at the University of Padua (M.D., 1496). Returning to England, he was appointed (1500) tutor to Prince Arthur, son of Henry VII, and served as physician (1509–20) to Henry VIII. He conducted a highly successful practice in London, numbering among his patients the humanist Desiderius Erasmus; Sir Thomas More,...
</Question>
<Choice>Linacre, Thomas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
physician, “founder of naval hygiene in England,” whose recommendation that fresh citrus fruit and lemon juice be included in the diet of seamen eventually resulted in the eradication of scurvy from the British Navy.A British naval surgeon (1739–48) and a physician at the Haslar Hospital for men of the Royal Navy, Gosport (1758–94), Lind observed thousands of cases of scurvy, typhus, and dysentery and the conditions on board ship that caused them. In 1754, when he published A Treatise on Scurvy, more British sailors were dying from scurvy during wartime than were killed in combat. In an early...
</Question>
<Choice>Lind, James</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-born American biochemist, who received (with Sir Hans Krebs) the 1953 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for the discovery of coenzyme A, an important catalytic substance involved in the cellular conversion of food into energy.Lipmann earned an M.D. degree (1924) and a Ph.D. degree (1927) from the University of Berlin. He conducted research in the laboratory of the biochemist Otto Meyerhof at the University of Heidelberg (1927–30) and then did research at the Biological Institute of the Carlsberg Foundation (Carlsbergfondets Biologiske Institut), Copenhagen (1932–39), and at the Cor...
</Question>
<Choice>Lipmann, Fritz Albert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-born American physician and pharmacologist who, with Sir Henry Dale, received the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1936 for their discoveries relating to the chemical transmission of nerve impulses.After Loewi graduated in medicine (1896) from the German University (now the University of Strasbourg), he studied and taught in European universities, becoming professor of pharmacology at Graz, Austria, in 1909. In 1940 he went to the United States; he was made research professor at the School of Medicine of New York University, New York City, where he remained until his death.His...
</Question>
<Choice>Loewi, Otto</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician traditionally considered the first to have used ether as an anesthetic in surgery.After serving in hospitals in New York City, Long returned to Georgia, where he set up practice in Jefferson. There he observed that persons injured in “ether frolics” (social gatherings of people who were in a playful state of ether-induced intoxication) seemed to suffer no pain, and in 1842 he painlessly removed a tumour from the neck of a patient to whom he had administered ether. He continued to use ether in other cases but did not publish any report of its use until 1849. Three years earli...
</Question>
<Choice>Long, Crawford Williamson</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian zoologist, founder of modern ethology, the study of animal behaviour by means of comparative zoological methods. His ideas contributed to an understanding of how behavioral patterns may be traced to an evolutionary past, and he was also known for his work on the roots of aggression. He shared the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1973 with the animal behaviourists Karl von Frisch and Nikolaas Tinbergen.Lorenz was the son of an orthopedic surgeon. He showed an interest in animals at an early age, and he kept animals of various species—fish, birds, monkeys, dogs, cats, and rabbi...
</Question>
<Choice>Lorenz, Konrad</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
a founder of the physicochemical school of physiology in Germany.A professor of physiology at the universities of Marburg (1846–49), Zürich (1849–55), Vienna (1855–65), and Leipzig (1865–95), Ludwig is best known for his study of the cardiovascular system. He invented (1847) a device known as a kymograph to record changes in arterial blood pressure; a simple stromuhr (1867), or flowmeter, to measure the rate of blood flow through arteries and veins; and a mercurial blood-gas pump for the separation of gases from the blood, which led to an understanding of the role played by oxygen and other ga...
</Question>
<Choice>Ludwig, Carl F. W.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian-born American biologist who (with Max Delbrück and Alfred Day Hershey) won the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1969 for research on bacteriophages, viruses that infect bacteria.Luria graduated from the University of Turin in 1935 and became a radiology specialist. He fled Italy for France in 1938 and went to the United States in 1940 after learning the techniques of phage research at the Pasteur Institute in Paris. Soon after his arrival, he met Delbrück, through whom he became involved with the American Phage Group, an informal scientific organization devoted to solving the...
</Question>
<Choice>Luria, Salvador</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French biologist who contributed to the understanding of lysogeny, in which a bacterial virus, or bacteriophage, infects bacteria and is transmitted to subsequent bacterial generations solely through the cell division of its host. Lwoff's discoveries brought him (with François Jacob and Jacques Monod) the Nobel Prize for Medicine or Physiology in 1965.Lwoff, born of Russian-Polish parents, was educated at the University of Paris. He spent most of his research career at the Pasteur Institute in Paris, serving on the board of directors from 1966 to 1972. From 1959 to 1968 he was also a professor...
</Question>
<Choice>Lwoff, Andre</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German biochemist who, for his research on the metabolism of cholesterol and fatty acids, was a corecipient (with Konrad Bloch) of the 1964 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine.Lynen was trained at the University of Munich. After several years as a lecturer in the chemistry department there (1942–47), he became a professor. While at Munich he worked on the intermediary metabolism of the living cell. This research led to his demonstration in the early 1950s that the acetylation of coenzyme A is the key first step in a chain of reactions that result in the formation of cholesterol and fatty ac...
</Question>
<Choice>Lynen, Feodor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish cardiologist, pioneer in the study of cardiac arrhythmias. He was first to make simultaneous records of the arterial and venous pulses to evaluate the condition of the heart, a procedure that laid the foundation for much future research. Mackenzie also drew attention to the question of the heart's capacity for work, paving the way for the study of the energetics of the heart muscle.After receiving his M.D. degree at the University of Edinburgh in 1882, Mackenzie practiced medicine for more than a quarter of a century in Burnley, Lancashire, where he was also physician to Victoria Hosp...
</Question>
<Choice>Mackenzie, Sir James</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physician who was at the centre of a bitter international controversy over the death of Emperor Frederick III of Germany.Mackenzie, the leading throat specialist of the time, was called into the difficult case of the German crown prince Frederick in May 1887. Frederick's illness had been diagnosed by German physicians as throat cancer. Basing his opinion on a biopsy made by the eminent German pathologist Rudolf Virchow, Mackenzie insisted that the throat lesion was not demonstrably cancerous and that an operation was unnecessary.Mackenzie was knighted in September 1887 and decorated wi...
</Question>
<Choice>Mackenzie, Sir Morell</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish physiologist noted as a teacher and for his work on carbohydrate metabolism. Together with Sir Frederick Banting, with whom he shared the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1923, and Charles H. Best, he achieved renown as one of the discoverers of insulin.Macleod held posts in physiology and biochemistry at the London Hospital (1899–1902) and as professor of physiology at Western Reserve University, Cleveland, Ohio, U.S. (1903–18). In 1918 he joined the University of Toronto, Ont., Can., as associate dean of medicine and subsequently became director of its physiological laborat...
</Question>
<Choice>Macleod, J. J. R.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French experimental physiologist who was the first to prove the functional difference of the spinal nerves. His pioneer studies of the effects of drugs on various parts of the body led to the scientific introduction into medical practice of such compounds as strychnine and morphine. In 1822 he confirmed and elaborated the observation by the Scottish anatomist Sir Charles Bell (1811) that the anterior roots of the spinal nerves are motor in function, while the posterior roots serve to communicate sensory impulses.Appointed professor of medicine at the Collège de France, Paris (1831), Magendie w...
</Question>
<Choice>Magendie, Francois</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jewish philosopher, jurist, and physician, the foremost intellectual figure of medieval Judaism. His first major work, begun at age 23 and completed 10 years later, was a commentary on the Mishna, the collected Jewish oral laws. A monumental code of Jewish law followed in Hebrew, The Guide for the Perplexed in Arabic, and numerous other works, many of major importance. His contributions in religion, philosophy, and medicine have influenced Jewish and non-Jewish scholars alike.
</Question>
<Choice>Maimonides, Moses</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian physician and biologist who, in developing experimental methods to study living things, founded the science of microscopicanatomy. After Malpighi's researches, microscopic anatomy became a prerequisite for advances in the fields of physiology, embryology, and practical medicine.
</Question>
<Choice>Malpighi, Marcello</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physicist who, with American chemist Paul Lauterbur, won the 2003 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for the development of magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), a computerized scanning technology that produces images of internal body structures, especially those comprising soft tissues.Mansfield received a Ph.D. in physics from the University of London in 1962. Following two years as a research associate in the United States, he joined the faculty of the University of Nottingham, where he became professor in 1979. Mansfield was knighted in 1993.Mansfield's prize-winning work expanded...
</Question>
<Choice>Mansfield, Sir Peter</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physiologist who invented the sphygmograph, an instrument for recording graphically the features of the pulse and variations in blood pressure. His basic instrument, with modifications, is still used today.Marey wrote extensively on the circulation of the blood, cholera, terrestrial and aerial locomotion, experimental physiology, and graphic methods in physiology. He also contributed to the development of the motion picture. To study the flight of birds, he invented a camera in 1882 with magazine plates that recorded a series of photographs; the pictures could be combined to represent m...
</Question>
<Choice>Marey, Etienne-Jules</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Australian physician who won, with J. Robin Warren, the 2005 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for their discovery that stomach ulcers are an infectious disease caused by bacteria.Marshall obtained a bachelor's degree from the University of Western Australia in 1974. From 1977 to 1984 he worked at Royal Perth Hospital, and he later taught medicine at the University of Western Australia, where he also was a research fellow.In the early 1980s Marshall became interested in the research of Warren, who in 1979 had first observed the presence of spiral-shaped bacteria in a biopsy of a patient's...
</Question>
<Choice>Marshall, Barry J.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician and educator, whose leadership engendered a notable increase in quality and course offerings at the Women's Medical College.Marshall was of a prominent Quaker family. At the age of 24, after having taught school for a time, she enrolled in the Woman's Medical College of Pennsylvania. On graduating in 1875 she was appointed a demonstrator in materia medica (drugs or medical remedies) and practical pharmacy in the college, and that same year she became the first woman admitted to the Philadelphia College of Pharmacy. After a year of study there, during which her academic stand...
</Question>
<Choice>Marshall, Clara</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American research team noted for their studies of human sexuality. William H. Masters (in full William Howell Masters; ), a physician, and Virginia E. Johnson (née Virginia Eshelman; ), a psychologist, were codirectors of the Masters &amp; Johnson Institute (1973–94).Masters was educated at Hamilton College in Clinton, N.Y. (B.S.), and the School of Medicine and Dentistry of the University of Rochester (M.D., 1943). In 1947 he joined the faculty of the School of Medicine of Washington University in St. Louis. Johnson studied at Drury College (Springfield, Mo.), the University of Missouri, Col...
</Question>
<Choice>Masters, William Howell</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the most famous group of physicians in the United States. Three generations of the Mayo family established at Rochester, Minn., the world-renowned nonprofit Mayo Clinic and the Mayo Foundation for Medical Education and Research, which are dedicated to diagnosing and treating nearly every known illness.William Worrall Mayo (b. May 31, 1819, near Manchester, Eng.—d. March 6, 1911, Rochester, Minn., U.S.) was the father of the doctors Mayo who developed a large-scale practice of medicine.Mayo studied chemistry at Owens College in Manchester and, after immigrating to the United States in 1845, lea...
</Question>
<Choice>Mayo family</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English chemist and physiologist who, about a hundred years before Joseph Priestley and Antoine-Laurent Lavoisier, identified spiritus nitroaereus (oxygen) as a distinct atmospheric entity.Though a doctor of law from the University of Oxford (1670), Mayow made medicine his profession. His writings include a remarkably correct anatomical description of respiration and a recognition of the role of oxygen in the combustion of metals.
</Question>
<Choice>Mayow, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American cell biologist who was notable for his work in nuclear and cellular physiology, especially the mechanisms involved in mitosis (the process by which the chromosomes within the nucleus of a cell double and divide prior to cell division).Mazia was educated at the University of Pennsylvania (Ph.D., 1937). He was a National Research Council fellow at Princeton University and at the Marine Biological Laboratories, Woods Hole, Mass. (1937–38). He then taught at the University of Missouri (1938–50) and joined the faculty of the University of California at Berkeley (1951–79).Throughout his car...
</Question>
<Choice>Mazia, Daniel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American scientist whose discovery in the 1940s and '50s of mobile genetic elements, or “jumping genes,” won her the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1983.McClintock, whose father was a physician, took great pleasure in science as a child and evidenced early the independence of mind and action that she would exhibit throughout her life. After attending high school, she enrolled as a biology major at Cornell University in 1919. She received a B.S. in 1923, a master's degree two years later, and, having specialized in cytology, genetics, and zoology, a Ph.D. in 1927. During graduate sch...
</Question>
<Choice>McClintock, Barbara</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
leading 18th-century British physician who contributed to the study of preventive medicine.A graduate of the University of Padua (M.D., 1695) and of Oxford (M.D., 1707) and a staff member of St. Thomas' Hospital and Medical School, London (1703–15), Mead attended some of the foremost personalities of the day, including King George I, Queen Anne, King George II, the British prime minister Sir Robert Walpole, Sir Isaac Newton, and the poet Alexander Pope.He wrote on the prevention and treatment of plague, smallpox, measles, and scurvy; his Mechanical Account of Poisons (1702) includes original o...
</Question>
<Choice>Mead, Richard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Brazilian-born British zoologist who received with Sir Frank Macfarlane Burnet the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1960 for developing and proving the theory of acquired immunological tolerance, a model that paved the way for successful organ and tissue transplantation.Medawar was born in Brazil and moved to England as a young boy. In 1935 he took a degree in zoology from Magdalen College, Oxford, and in 1938 he became a fellow of the college. During World War II at the Burns Unit of the Glasgow Royal Infirmary in Scotland, he carried out research on tissue transplants, particularly...
</Question>
<Choice>Medawar, Sir Peter B.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physicians who pioneered methods of psychiatric treatment in the 20th century.Charles Frederick Menninger began practicing general medicine in Topeka in 1889 and became convinced of the benefit of group medical practice after visiting the Mayo Clinic in Rochester, Minnesota, in 1908. Menninger was joined in practice by his son Karl Augustus Menninger (—, who received his medical degree from Harvard Medical School in 1917 and who spent two years working under Ernest Southard at the Boston Psychopathic Hospital. In 1919 the two Menningers established the Menninger Diagnostic Clinic in T...
</Question>
<Choice>Menninger family</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
philosopher of the Skeptical school of empirical medicine, credited with elaborating the first scientific method of observation. Like many other physicians of the period, he considered medicine an art; this left him free to perfect his art while remaining a Skeptic. He also wrote against Asclepiades, who espoused Atomism and a theory of imbalance of corpuscles as the cause of illness. Some scholars think the voluminous writings of Menodotus, frequently mentioned by Galen, suggest two contemporary physicians of the same name.
</Question>
<Choice>Menodotus of Nicomedia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physician whose system of therapeutics, known as mesmerism, was the forerunner of the modern practice of hypnotism.Mesmer's dissertation at the University of Vienna (M.D., 1766), which borrowed heavily from the work of the British physician Richard Mead, suggested that the gravitational attraction of the planets affected human health by affecting an invisible fluid found in the human body and throughout nature. In 1775 Mesmer revised his theory of “animal gravitation” to one of “animal magnetism,” wherein the invisible fluid in the body acted according to the laws of magnetism. Accordin...
</Question>
<Choice>Mesmer, Franz Anton</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian zoologist and microbiologist who received (with Paul Ehrlich) the 1908 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for his discovery in animals of amoeba-like cells that engulf foreign bodies such as bacteria—a phenomenon known as phagocytosis and a fundamental part of the immune response.Metchnikoff received his bachelor's degree from the University of Kharkov (1864) and completed his doctoral degree at the University of St. Petersburg (1868). He served as professor of zoology and comparative anatomy at the University of Odessa (1870–82). In Messina, Italy (1882–86), while studying the ori...
</Question>
<Choice>Metchnikoff, Elie</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German biochemist and corecipient, with Archibald V. Hill, of the 1922 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for research on the chemical reactions of metabolism in muscle. His work on the glycogen-lactic acid cycle remains a basic contribution to the understanding of muscular action, despite revisions resulting from the later research of others.After receiving his M.D. from the University of Heidelberg in 1909, Meyerhof held posts in physiology and physical chemistry at Kiel and other German universities. From 1929 to 1938 he headed the department of physiology at the Kaiser Wilhelm (now Max...
</Question>
<Choice>Meyerhof, Otto</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
actor, director, producer, medical doctor, and man of letters noted for his wide-ranging abilities.Miller was the son of a psychiatrist and a novelist. He graduated from St. John's College, Cambridge, in 1956 and studied medicine at the University College School of Medicine of London University, from which he took a degree in medicine in 1959. Miller made his professional stage debut at the Edinburgh Festival in 1961 as actor and coauthor in the satirical review Beyond the Fringe. He left the show in 1963 to write television scripts and to direct live theatre. His sometimes controversial inter...
</Question>
<Choice>Miller, Jonathan Wolfe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Argentine-British immunologist who in 1984, with Georges Köhler and Niels K. Jerne, received the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for his work in the development of monoclonal antibodies.Milstein attended the universities of Buenos Aires and Cambridge (Ph.D., 1960) and was on the staff of the National Institute of Microbiology in Buenos Aires (1957–63). Thereafter he was a member of the Medical Research Council Laboratory of Molecular Biology, Cambridge, England, and held dual Argentine and British citizenship.Milstein studied antibodies—the proteins produced by mature B lymphocytes (pla...
</Question>
<Choice>Milstein, Cesar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician who received (with George Whipple and William Murphy) the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1934 for the introduction of a raw-liver diet in the treatment of pernicious anemia, which was previously an invariably fatal disease.Minot received his medical degree at Harvard University in 1912. He did research at the Massachusetts General Hospital, Boston (1915–23), the Collis P. Huntington Memorial Hospital, Harvard University (1922–28), and the Peter Bent Brigham Hospital, Boston (1923–28). He served as director of the Thorndike Memorial Laboratory, Boston City Hospital...
</Question>
<Choice>Minot, George Richards</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French botanist whose book Traité d'anatomie et de physiologie végétale, 2 vol. (1802; “Treatise on Plant Anatomy and Physiology”), earned him recognition as a founder of plant cytology and plant physiology. His most notable contribution to plant cytology was his observation (1809) that each plant cell is contained in a continuous membrane.In 1798 Mirbel joined the staff of the National Museum of Natural History in Paris. Four years later the first volume of his Histoire naturelle des végétaux classés par familles (“Natural History of Plants Classified by Families”) appeared. In 1803 he became...
</Question>
<Choice>Mirbel, Charles-Francois Brisseau de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician and author who excelled in novels of psychology and historical romance.After study at the University of Pennsylvania and Jefferson Medical College (M.D., 1850), Mitchell spent a year in Paris specializing in neurology. As an army surgeon during the American Civil War, he became well known for his “rest cure.” His war experiences were the basis for “The Case of George Dedlow” (1866), a story about a quadruple amputee notable for its psychological insights and realistic war scenes. He wrote some 170 medical monographs on topics ranging from snake venom to neurasthenia and publ...
</Question>
<Choice>Mitchell, S. Weir</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German botanist noted for his research on the anatomy and physiology of plant cells.Von Mohl received his degree in medicine from the University of Tübingen in 1828. After studying for several years at Munich, he became professor of botany at Tübingen in 1835 and remained there until his death.As a result of his studies on the plant cell, von Mohl developed the idea that the nucleus of the cell was within the granular, colloidal material that made up the main substance of the cell. In 1846 he named this substance protoplasm, a word that had been invented by the Czech physiologist Jan Evangelis...
</Question>
<Choice>Mohl, Hugo von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
physiologist and philosopher noted for his belief in the material basis of emotion and thought. His most important work, Kreislauf des Lebens (1852; “The Circuit of Life”), added considerable impetus to 19th-century materialism by demanding “scientific answers to scientific questions.”Moleschott studied medicine (1842–45) at the University of Heidelberg in Germany. He worked for a time in Utrecht as a general practitioner and continued his studies. From 1847 to 1854 he was a Privatdozent at the University of Heidelberg; he resigned when he came up against the “official philosophy” of German un...
</Question>
<Choice>Moleschott, Jacob</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian physician and anatomist whose AnathomiaMundini (MS. 1316; first printed in 1478) was the first European book written since classical antiquity that was entirely devoted to anatomy and was based on the dissection of human cadavers. It remained a standard text until the time of the Flemish anatomist Andreas Vesalius (1514–64).Mondino received his medical training at the University of Bologna, and after graduation he studied and taught anatomy and surgery at that university while actively practicing medicine and surgery. Mondino was the first to reintroduce the systematic teaching of anat...
</Question>
<Choice>Mondino de' Luzzi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French biochemist who, with François Jacob, did much to elucidate how genes regulate cell metabolism by directing the biosynthesis of enzymes. The pair shared, along with André Lwoff, the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1965.In 1961 Jacob and Monod proposed the existence of a messenger ribonucleic acid (mRNA), a substance whose base sequence is complementary to that of deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) in the cell. They postulated that the messenger carries the “information” encoded in the base sequence to ribosomes, the sites of protein synthesis; here the base sequence of the messenger R...
</Question>
<Choice>Monod, Jacques</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
pioneer of American medical education, surgeon general of the Continental armies during the American Revolution, and founder of the first medical school in the United States.Morgan studied at the University of Edinburgh (M.D., 1763), at Paris, and in Italy. Returning to the colonies in 1765, he founded their first medical school at the College of Philadelphia (now the University of Pennsylvania) and there was appointed North America's first professor of medicine. His policies of requiring a liberal education for medical students and the separation of medicine, surgery, and pharmacology into di...
</Question>
<Choice>Morgan, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American zoologist and geneticist, famous for his experimental research with the fruit fly (Drosophila) by which he established the chromosome theory of heredity. He showed that genes are linked in a series on chromosomes and are responsible for identifiable, hereditary traits. Morgan's work played a key role in establishing the field of genetics. He received the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1933.
</Question>
<Choice>Morgan, Thomas Hunt</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician and educator whose wide-ranging medical career included an educational focus on physical fitness and health maintenance.In 1869, over the objections of friends and family, Mosher entered the New England Hospital for Women and Children as an intern apprentice. After a year she was forced to suspend her education to nurse her mother, and during that time she also assisted a woman doctor in Boston. In 1871 she entered the University of Michigan, where she completed the medical course and received her M.D. in 1875. From 1875 to 1877 she was in private practice with a classmate i...
</Question>
<Choice>Mosher, Eliza Maria</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American geneticist best remembered for his demonstration that mutations and hereditary changes can be caused by X rays striking the genes and chromosomes of living cells. His discovery of artificially induced mutations in genes had far-reaching consequences, and he was awarded the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1946.Muller attended Columbia University from 1907 to 1909. At Columbia his interest in genetics was fired first by E.B. Wilson, the founder of the cellular approach to heredity, and later by T.H. Morgan, who had just introduced the fruit fly Drosophilaas a tool in experimen...
</Question>
<Choice>Muller, Hermann Joseph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physiologist and comparative anatomist, one of the great natural philosophers of the 19th century. His major work was Handbuch der Physiologie des Menschen für Vorlesungen, 2 vol. (1834–40; Elements of Physiology).Müller was the son of a shoemaker. In 1819 he entered the University of Bonn, where the faculty of medicine was permeated with Naturphilosophie, which the young Müller eagerly espoused. He continued his studies at the University of Berlin, where he came under the influence of the sober, precise anatomist Karl Rudolphi and thereby freed himself from naturalistic speculation.In...
</Question>
<Choice>Muller, Johannes Peter</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss chemist who received the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1948 for discovering the potent toxic effects on insects of DDT. With its chemical derivatives, DDT became the most widely used insecticide for more than 20 years and was a major factor in increased world food production and the suppression of insect-borne diseases.A research chemist at the J.R. Geigy Company, Basel (1925–65), Müller began his career with investigations of dyes and tanning agents. In 1935 he began his search for an “ideal” insecticide, one that would show rapid, potent toxicity for the greatest number of...
</Question>
<Choice>Muller, Paul Hermann</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American pharmacologist, who, along with Robert F. Furchgott and Louis J. Ignarro, was co-awarded the 1998 Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine for the discovery that nitric oxide (NO) acts as a signaling molecule in the cardiovascular system. Their combined work uncovered an entirely new mechanism for how blood vessels in the body relax and widen.Murad received his M.D. and Ph.D. from Western Reserve University (later Case Western Reserve University) in Cleveland, Ohio, in 1965. In addition to his clinical practice, Murad taught pharmacology at the University of Virginia School of Medicine,...
</Question>
<Choice>Murad, Ferid</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician who with George R. Minot in 1926 reported success in the treatment of pernicious anemia with a liver diet. The two men shared the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1934 with George H. Whipple, whose research they had built upon.Murphy received his M.D. from Harvard University (1920). He joined the staff of Peter Bent Brigham Hospital (later Brigham and Women's Hospital) in Boston in 1923, where he began his collaboration with Minot. Whipple in the early 1920s had demonstrated that liver in the diet sharply raised red blood cell counts in anemic patients. Acting on th...
</Question>
<Choice>Murphy, William P.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physician who pioneered in the treatment of endocrine disorders. He was one of the first to use extractions of animal thyroid to relieve myxedema (severe hypothyroidism) in humans.Murray, the son of a prominent physician, William Murray, received clinical training at University College Hospital, London. He was awarded both his M.B. (1889) and M.D. (1896) by the University of Cambridge. Determined to pursue a career in experimental medicine, Murray in 1891 became pathologist to the Hospital for Sick Children in Newcastle. He also lectured in bacteriology and comparative anatomy at Durha...
</Question>
<Choice>Murray, George Redmayne</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American surgeon who in 1990 was cowinner (with E. Donnall Thomas) of the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for his work in lifesaving organ- and tissue-transplant techniques.Murray received a bachelor of arts degree (1940) from Holy Cross College, Worcester, Mass., and a medical degree (1943) from Harvard Medical School, Cambridge, Mass. He completed his surgical residency at Peter Bent Brigham Hospital (later Brigham and Women's Hospital), Boston, where he began his prizewinning research. From 1964 to 1986 he served as chief plastic surgeon at Brigham, and from 1972 to 1985 he was chief...
</Question>
<Choice>Murray, Joseph E.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
cardinal, mathematician, scholar, experimental scientist, and influential philosopher who stressed the incomplete nature of man's knowledge of God and of the universe. At the Council of Basel in 1432, he gained recognition for his opposition to the candidate put forward by Pope Eugenius IV for the archbishopric of Trier. To his colleagues at the council he dedicated De concordantia catholica (1433; “On Catholic Concordance”), in which he expressed support for the supremacy of the general councils of the church over the authority of the papacy. In the same work he discussed the harmony of the c...
</Question>
<Choice>Nicholas of Cusa</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sierra Leonean diplomat, physician, medical researcher, and writer whose short stories and poems are among the best to have come out of West Africa.Nicol was educated in medicine and natural sciences in Sierra Leone, Nigeria, and England, and he subsequently served in various medical posts in those countries. He became known for his research into the structure of insulin, and he lectured and wrote widely on medical topics. He was principal of Fourah Bay College, Freetown (1960–68), vice chancellor of the University of Sierra Leone (1966–68), and his country's ambassador to the United Nations (...
</Question>
<Choice>Nicol, Davidson</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French bacteriologist who received the 1928 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for his discovery (1909) that typhus is transmitted by the body louse.After obtaining his medical degree in Paris in 1893, Nicolle returned to Rouen, where he became a member of the medical faculty and engaged in bacteriological research. In 1902 he was appointed director of the Pasteur Institute in Tunis, and during his 31 years' tenure in that post, the institute became a distinguished centre for bacteriological research and for the production of serums and vaccines to combat infectious diseases.In Tunis Nicol...
</Question>
<Choice>Nicolle, Charles-Jules-Henri</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biochemist and corecipient, with Robert William Holley and Har Gobind Khorana, of the 1968 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine. He was cited for his role in deciphering the genetic code. He demonstrated that, with the exception of “nonsense codons,” each possible triplet (called a codon) of four different kinds of nitrogen-containing bases found in deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) and, in some viruses, in ribonucleic acid (RNA) ultimately causes the incorporation of a specific amino acid into a cell protein. Nirenberg's work and that of Holley and Khorana helped to show how genetic inst...
</Question>
<Choice>Nirenberg, Marshall Warren</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French astrologer and physician, the most widely read seer of the Renaissance.Nostradamus began his medical practice in Agen in 1529 and moved to Salon in 1544, where he gained renown for his innovative medicine and treatment during outbreaks of the plague at Aix and Lyon in 1546–47. He began making prophecies about 1547, which he published in 1555 in a book entitled Centuries. The work consisted of rhymed quatrains grouped in hundreds, each set of 100 called a century. Astrology was then at a peak, and an enlarged second edition, dedicated to the French king, appeared in 1558.Some of his prop...
</Question>
<Choice>Nostradamus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British industrialist and philanthropist whose automobile manufacturing firm introduced the Morris cars.The son of a farm labourer, Morris was obliged by his father's illness to abandon plans to study medicine and go to work at age 15. Behind his home he set up a bicycle repair shop, built bicycles to order, and raced them with success. Later he sold and maintained motorcycles, an interest he easily extended to automobiles. In 1903 he took in a partner, but their garage went bankrupt. In 1904, with only his tools left and a £50 debt, he started again. He set up works in Cowley, and the first M...
</Question>
<Choice>
Nuffield, William Richard Morris, Viscount, Baron Nuffield of Nuffield
</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British scientist who, with Leland H. Hartwell and R. Timothy Hunt, won the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 2001 for discovering key regulators of the cell cycle.Nurse earned a Ph.D. from the University of East Anglia in 1973 and was a professor at the University of Oxford from 1987 to 1993. He headed the Cell Cycle Laboratory (1984–87, 1993– ) at the Imperial Cancer Research Fund (ICRF; now Cancer Research UK) and in 1996 became director-general of the ICRF.In the mid-1970s Nurse, using yeast as his model organism, discovered the genecdc2. His research demonstrated that the gene ser...
</Question>
<Choice>Nurse, Sir Paul M.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American-born British biologist and physician who contributed substantially to many branches of biology and founded the Molteno Institute of Biology and Parasitology (1921) at the University of Cambridge.Nuttall graduated from the University of California Medical School (M.D., 1884) and received his Ph.D. from the University of Göttingen, Germany (1890). He became a lecturer in bacteriology and preventive medicine at Cambridge, England, in 1900, when he acquired British citizenship. In 1906 he was elected the first Quick Professor of Biology at Cambridge (emeritus 1931). He made significant, i...
</Question>
<Choice>Nuttall, George Henry Falkiner</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
biochemist and molecular biologist who received (with the American biochemist Arthur Kornberg) the 1959 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for discovery of an enzyme in bacteria that enabled him to synthesize ribonucleic acid (RNA), a substance of central importance to the synthesis of proteins by the cell.Ochoa was educated at the University of Madrid, where he received his M.D. in 1929. He then spent two years studying the biochemistry and physiology of muscle under the German biochemist Otto Meyerhof at the University of Heidelberg. He also served as head of the physiology division, Ins...
</Question>
<Choice>Ochoa, Severo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Canadian physician and professor of medicine who practiced and taught in Canada, the United States, and Great Britain and whose book The Principles and Practice of Medicine (1892) was a leading textbook. Osler played a key role in transforming the organization and curriculum of medical education, emphasizing the importance of clinical experience. He was created a baronet in 1911.William Osler was the youngest of the nine children of the Reverend Featherstone Osler, who had gone to Canada as an Anglican missionary, and his wife, Ellen. William, like his father, was intended for the church. But...
</Question>
<Choice>Osler, Sir William, Baronet</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British surgeon and surgical pathologist.Working at St. Bartholomew's Hospital, London (1834–71), Paget discovered (1834) in human muscle the parasitic worm that causes trichinosis. Paget was a professor of anatomy and surgery (1847–52) and was later vice president (1873–74) and president (1875) of the Royal College of Surgeons. He rendered excellent descriptions of breast cancer, an early indication of breast cancer known as Paget's disease (1874; an inflammatory cancerous condition around the nipple in elderly women), and Paget's disease of bone (1877; a bone inflammation also known as ostei...
</Question>
<Choice>Paget, Sir James, 1st Baronet</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Romanian-born American cell biologist who developed tissue-preparation methods, advanced centrifuging techniques, and conducted electron microscopy studies that resulted in the discovery of several cellular structures. With Albert Claude and Christian de Duve he was awarded the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1974.Palade received a degree in medicine from the University of Bucharest in 1940 and remained there as a professor until after World War II. He immigrated to the United States in 1946 and began work at the Rockefeller Institute in New York. Palade performed many studies on the...
</Question>
<Choice>Palade, George E.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-Swiss physician and alchemist who established the role of chemistry in medicine. He published Der grossen Wundartzney (Great Surgery Book) in 1536 and a clinical description of syphilis in 1530.
</Question>
<Choice>Paracelsus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physician, one of the most notable surgeons of the European Renaissance, regarded by some medical historians as the father of modern surgery.About 1533 Paré went to Paris, where he soon became a barber-surgeon apprentice at the Hôtel-Dieu. He was taught anatomy and surgery and in 1537 was employed as an army surgeon. By 1552 he had gained such popularity that he became surgeon to the king; he served four French monarchs: Henry II, Francis II, Charles IX, and Henry III.At the time Paré entered the army, surgeons treated gunshot wounds with boiling oil since such wounds were believed to b...
</Question>
<Choice>Pare, Ambroise</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Alexandrian physician and surgeon, the last major ancient Greek medical encyclopaedist, who wrote the Epitomes iatrikes biblio hepta, better known by its Latin title, Epitomae medicae libri septem (“Medical Compendium in Seven Books”), containing nearly everything known about the medical arts in the West in his time.Based largely on the works of such earlier Greek physicians as Galen, Oribasius, and Aëtius, the Epitome greatly influenced the medical practice of the Arabs, who considered Paul among the most authoritative of Greek medical writers. The Persian master physician ar-Razi (Rhazes) dr...
</Question>
<Choice>Paul of Aegina</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian physiologist known chiefly for his development of the concept of the conditioned reflex. In a now-classic experiment, he trained a hungry dog to salivate at the sound of a bell, which was previously associated with the sight of food. He developed a similar conceptual approach, emphasizing the importance of conditioning, in his pioneering studies relating human behaviour to the nervous system. He was awarded the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1904 for his work on digestive secretions.
</Question>
<Choice>Pavlov, Ivan Petrovich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
physician, novelist, and one of western Africa's most important poets.Peters was educated at Bathurst, Freetown (Sierra Leone), and at Trinity College, Cambridge, where he earned a medical degree in 1959, with further studies in surgery. He broadcast on several British Broadcasting Corporation programs (and chaired its Africa Forum) before returning to Gambia.His novel The Second Round (1965) is semiautobiographical in its story of the disillusionment and alienation of a young doctor returning from England to Freetown after completing his medical studies and finding his home unsettled and unse...
</Question>
<Choice>Peters, Lenrie</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German botanist whose work on osmotic pressure made him a pioneer in the study of plant physiology.After earning his Ph.D. from the University of Göttingen in 1865 Pfeffer continued his studies at the universities of Marburg and Bonn. He then held teaching positions at Bonn (1873), Basel (1877), Tübingen (1878), and Leipzig (1877), where he remained until his death. Pfeffer's work on cell metabolism led to his work in 1877 in devising a semi-permeable membrane that he used to study osmosis. He developed a method for measuring osmotic pressure and showed that pressure depended on the size of th...
</Question>
<Choice>Pfeffer, Wilhelm Friedrich Philipp</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physician who pioneered in the humane treatment of the mentally ill.Arriving in Paris (1778), he supported himself for a number of years by translating scientific and medical works and by teaching mathematics. During that period he also began visiting privately confined mental patients and writing articles on his observations. In 1792 he became the chief physician at the Paris asylum for men, Bicêtre, and made his first bold reform by unchaining patients, many of whom had been restrained for 30 to 40 years. He did the same for the female inmates of Salpêtrière when he became the directo...
</Question>
<Choice>Pinel, Philippe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
successful American patent-medicine proprietor who claimed that her Vegetable Compound could cure any “female complaint” from nervous prostration to a prolapsed uterus.Lydia Estes grew up in a Quaker family and attended Lynn Academy. For several years she taught school, and she was an ardent member of many reform groups for abolition, Swedenborgianism, phrenology, temperance, women's rights, and other causes. In 1843 she married a young widower, Isaac Pinkham. She devoted herself to domestic life for the next 30 years. The Panic of 1873 left the family in financial straits, and it was at the s...
</Question>
<Choice>Pinkham, Lydia E.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian physician who originated a tuberculin skin test that bears his name.Pirquet attended the universities of Vienna, Königsberg, and Graz and graduated with a medical degree from Graz in 1900. He became a professor of pediatrics at Johns Hopkins University in Baltimore, Maryland, U.S., in 1909, a position he held for one year before returning to the University of Vienna.In 1905 Pirquet noticed that patients who had received injections of horse serum or smallpox vaccine usually had quicker, more severe reactions to second injections. To the collection of symptoms resulting from serum injec...
</Question>
<Choice>Pirquet, Clemens, Freiherr von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physician and physiologist who formulated a mathematical expression for the flow rate for the laminar (nonturbulent) flow of fluids in circular tubes. Discovered independently by Gotthilf Hagen, a German hydraulic engineer, this relation is also known as the Hagen-Poiseuille equation.Poiseuille received his medical degree in 1828 and established his practice in Paris. His interest in the circulation of the blood led him to conduct a series of experiments on the flow of liquids in narrow tubes, from which he determined the law that bears his name. This equation states that the flow rate...
</Question>
<Choice>Poiseuille, Jean-Louis-Marie</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British biochemist who, with Gerald M. Edelman, received the 1972 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for his contribution to the determination of the chemical structure of an antibody.Porter was educated at the University of Liverpool (B.S., 1939) and the University of Cambridge (Ph.D., 1948) and worked at the National Institute for Medical Research at Mill Hill from 1949 to 1960. He served as professor of immunology at St. Mary's Hospital Medical School, London, until 1967, when he joined the faculty at the University of Oxford.Porter approached the problem of antibody structure by using...
</Question>
<Choice>Porter, Rodney Robert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician and educator who struggled for the rights of women to learn, practice, and teach medicine in the mid-1800s.Preston was educated in Quaker schools and later became active in the abolition and temperance movements. Her temperance work had aroused in her an interest in physiology and hygiene, and she studied those subjects as well as Latin on her own for a time. She began to teach classes in physiology and hygiene to other interested women and in 1847 became a medical apprentice in the office of a physician friend in Philadelphia. Two years later, having completed her apprentic...
</Question>
<Choice>Preston, Ann</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physician, an early exponent of the importance of ordinary putrefactive processes in the production of disease. His application of this principle to the administration of hospitals and army camps has earned him distinction as a founder of modern military medicine.A pupil of the Dutch physician Hermann Boerhaave and the German anatomist Bernard Albinus at the University of Leiden (M.D., 1730), Pringle served as professor of moral philosophy at the University of Edinburgh (1734–44). In 1742 he became physician to the Earl of Stair, who was commander of the British army on the European co...
</Question>
<Choice>Pringle, Sir John, 1st Baronet</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English chemist and biochemist noted for his discoveries concerning digestion, metabolic chemistry, and atomic weights.The son of a tenant farmer, Prout graduated from the University of Edinburgh in 1811 with a medical degree. Thereafter he practiced as a successful physician, specializing in the treatment of urinary and digestive ailments. Prout's other career, as an experimentalist and theorist, was many-sided. Between 1815 and 1827 he published a number of papers that helped establish the barely explored areas of metabolic and physiological chemistry. He discovered that the gastric juices o...
</Question>
<Choice>Prout, William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biochemist and neurologist whose discovery in 1982 of disease-causing proteins called prions won him the 1997 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine.Prusiner grew up in Cincinnati, Ohio, and was educated at the University of Pennsylvania (A.B., 1964; M.D., 1968). After spending four years in biochemical research, he became (1972) a resident in neurology at the University of California, San Francisco, School of Medicine. He joined the faculty there in 1974 and became a professor of neurology and biochemistry. While a neurology resident, he was in charge of a patient who died of a rare...
</Question>
<Choice>Prusiner, Stanley B.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
pioneer Czech experimental physiologist whose investigations in the fields of histology, embryology, and pharmacology helped create a modern understanding of the eye and vision, brain and heart function, mammalian reproduction, and the composition of cells.Purkinje's research at the University of Prague (M.D., 1819), where he later served as professor of physiology (1850–69), led to his discovery of a phenomenon known as the Purkinje effect (as light intensity decreases, red objects are perceived to fade faster than blue objects of the same brightness). His studies of human vision attracted th...
</Question>
<Choice>Purkinje, Jan Evangelista</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian physician, considered a founder of occupational medicine.A professor of medicine at the University of Modena (1682–1700), and an early student of epidemiology, he described outbreaks of lathyrism (1690; chick-pea poisoning) and malaria (1690–95) in Italy. A strong proponent of the use of cinchona bark in the treatment of malaria, Ramazzini recognized the introduction of this medicament (from which the alkaloid quinine is derived) as a revolutionary event in the history of medicine, completing the downfall of the classic Greek physician Galen's medical theories advocating administration...
</Question>
<Choice>Ramazzini, Bernardino</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish histologist who (with Camillo Golgi) received the 1906 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for establishing the neuron, or nerve cell, as the basic unit of nervous structure. This finding was instrumental in the recognition of the neuron's fundamental role in nervous function and in gaining a modern understanding of the nerve impulse.Ramón y Cajal obtained a medical degree at the University of Zaragoza in 1873 and became an assistant in the medical faculty there two years later. He served as professor of descriptive anatomy at the University of Valencia (1884–87) and professor of hi...
</Question>
<Choice>Ramon y Cajal, Santiago</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
celebrated alchemist and Muslim philosopher who is also considered to have been the greatest physician of the Islamic world.One tradition holds that al-Razi was already an alchemist before he gained his medical knowledge. After serving as chief physician in a Rayy hospital, he held a similar position in Baghdad for some time. Like many intellectuals in his day, he lived at various small courts under the patronage of minor rulers. With references to his Greek predecessors, al-Razi viewed himself as the Islamic version of Socrates in philosophy and of Hippocrates in medicine.Al-Razi's two most s...
</Question>
<Choice>Razi, ar-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian physician and poet who demonstrated that the presence of maggots in putrefying meat does not result from spontaneous generation but from eggs laid on the meat by flies.He read in the book on generation by William Harvey a speculation that vermin such as insects, worms, and frogs do not arise spontaneously, as was then commonly believed, but from seeds or eggs too small to be seen. In 1668, in one of the first examples of a biological experiment with proper controls, Redi set up a series of flasks containing different meats, half of the flasks sealed, half open. He then repeated the exp...
</Question>
<Choice>Redi, Francesco</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. Army pathologist and bacteriologist who led the experiments that proved that yellow fever is transmitted by the bite of a mosquito. The Walter Reed Hospital, Washington, D.C., was named in his honour.Reed was the youngest of five children of Lemuel Sutton Reed, a Methodist minister, and his first wife, Pharaba White. In 1866 the family moved to Charlottesville, where Walter intended to study classics at the University of Virginia. After a period at the university he transferred to the medical faculty, completed his medical course in nine months, and in the summer of 1869, at the age of 18...
</Question>
<Choice>Reed, Walter</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss chemist who, with Philip S. Hench and Edward C. Kendall, received the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1950 for his discoveries concerning hormones of the adrenal cortex.Reichstein was educated in Zürich and held posts in the department of organic chemistry at the Federal Institute of Technology, Zürich, from 1930. From 1946 to 1967 he was professor of organic chemistry at the University of Basel. He received the Nobel Prize for research carried out independently on the steroid hormones produced by the adrenal cortex, the outer layer of the adrenal gland. Reichstein and his coll...
</Question>
<Choice>Reichstein, Tadeus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
physician and social-service administrator who, as the founder of France's first newspaper, is considered the father of French journalism.In 1612 Renaudot traveled to Paris, where he became a protégé of Armand (later Cardinal) de Richelieu, who obtained his appointment as physician to King Louis XIII and commissary general of the poor, with the task of organizing a program of public assistance. Not until 1630, however, was he able to open in Paris a bureau d'adresse, combining the services of a labour bureau, intelligence department, and charity organization that directed sick persons to physi...
</Question>
<Choice>Renaudot, Theophraste</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physiologist who shared the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1956 with Werner Forssmann and André F. Cournand. Cournand and Richards adapted Forssmann's technique of using a flexible tube (catheter), conducted from an elbow vein to the heart, as a probe to investigate the heart.Richards received an A.B. degree from Yale University in 1917 and later studied at Columbia University's College of Physicians and Surgeons (M.A., 1922; M.D., 1923). After a hospital internship and a brief study in England, he returned to Columbia University in 1928 and taught there from 1947 to 1961....
</Question>
<Choice>Richards, Dickinson Woodruff</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physiologist who won the 1913 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for his discovery of and coining of the term anaphylaxis, the life-threatening allergic reaction he observed in a sensitized animal upon second exposure to an antigen. This research provided the first evidence that an immune response could cause damage as well as provide protection against disease. During his career Richet helped to elucidate problems of hay fever, asthma, and other allergic reactions to foreign substances and explained some cases of toxicity and sudden death not previously understood.Richet earned a m...
</Question>
<Choice>Richet, Charles</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American pediatrician and virologist who received (with John Enders and Thomas Weller) the 1954 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for successfully cultivating poliomyelitis virus in tissue cultures. This accomplishment made possible the production of polio vaccines, the development of sophisticated diagnostic methods, and the isolation of new viruses.A graduate of Harvard University Medical School (1940), Robbins served in the United States, Italy, and North Africa during World War II (1942–46) as chief of the U.S. Army's 15th medical general laboratory virus and rickettsia section, where...
</Question>
<Choice>Robbins, Frederick Chapman</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
molecular biologist, the winner, with Phillip A. Sharp, of the 1993 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for his independent discovery of “split genes.”Roberts received a Ph.D. in organic chemistry from the University of Sheffield, Eng., in 1968. After postdoctoral research at Harvard University, he took a post at Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory in New York in 1972. In 1992 he joined New England Biolabs, a biotechnology firm.In 1977 Roberts and a team including Thomas Broker, Louise Chow, and Richard Gelinas established that the genes of the adenovirus—one of the viruses that cause the common...
</Question>
<Choice>Roberts, Richard J.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British doctor who received the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1902 for his work on malaria. His discovery of the malarial parasite in the gastrointestinal tract of the Anopheles mosquito led to the realization that malaria was transmitted by Anopheles, and laid the foundation for combating the disease.After graduating in medicine (1879), Ross entered the Indian Medical Service and served in the third Anglo-Burmese War (1885). On leave he studied bacteriology in London (1888–89) and then returned to India, where, prompted by Patrick Manson's guidance and assistance, he began (1895)...
</Question>
<Choice>Ross, Sir Ronald</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American pathologist whose discovery of cancer-inducing viruses earned him a share of the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1966.Rous was educated at Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, and at the University of Michigan. He joined the Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research (now Rockefeller University) in New York City in 1909 and remained there throughout his career. In 1911 Rous found that sarcomas in hens could be transmitted to fowl of the same inbred stock not only by grafting tumour cells but also by injecting a submicroscopic agent extractable from them; this discovery gave...
</Question>
<Choice>Rous, Peyton</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician and political leader, a member of the Continental Congress and a signer of the Declaration of Independence. His encouragement of clinical research and instruction was frequently offset by his insistence upon bloodletting, purging, and other debilitating therapeutic measures.Rush was born into a pious Presbyterian family. He was sent to a private academy and on to the College of New Jersey at Princeton, from which he was graduated in 1760. After a medical apprenticeship of six years, he sailed for Europe. He took a medical degree at the University of Edinburgh in 1768 and the...
</Question>
<Choice>Rush, Benjamin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polish American physician and microbiologist best known for developing the oralpoliovaccine. He was also known for his research in the fields of human viral diseases, toxoplasmosis, and cancer.Sabin immigrated with his parents to the United States in 1921 and became an American citizen nine years later. He received an M.D. degree from New York University in 1931, where he began research on human poliomyelitis. After serving for two years as a house physician at Bellevue Hospital in New York City, he attended the Lister Institute of Preventive Medicine in London. In 1935 he joined the staff of...
</Question>
<Choice>Sabin, Albert Bruce</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American anatomist and investigator of the lymphatic system who was considered to be one of the leading women scientists of the United States.Sabin was educated in Denver, Colorado, and in Vermont and graduated from Smith College in Massachusetts, in 1893. After teaching in Denver and at Smith to earn tuition money, she entered the Johns Hopkins University Medical School in Baltimore, Maryland, in 1896. While a student she demonstrated a particular gift for laboratory work; her model of the brain stem of a newborn infant was widely reproduced for use as a teaching model in medical schools. Aft...
</Question>
<Choice>Sabin, Florence Rena</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German botanist whose experimental study of nutrition, tropism, and transpiration of water greatly advanced the knowledge of plant physiology, and the cause of experimental biology in general, during the second half of the 19th century.Sachs became an assistant to the physiologist Jan Evangelista Purkinje at the University of Prague, where he received the Ph.D. in 1856. In 1859 he was appointed assistant in physiology at the Agricultural Academy of Tharandt in Saxony. Two years later he was made director of the Agricultural Academy at Poppelsdorf near Bonn. In 1867 he accepted the chair of bot...
</Question>
<Choice>Sachs, Ferdinand Gustav Julius von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician, medical publisher, and art collector who made large donations of money and art to universities and museums.Sackler studied at New York University (B.S., 1933; M.D., 1937) and worked as a psychiatrist at Creedmore State Hospital in Queens, New York (1944–46), where in 1949 he founded the Creedmore Institute of Psychobiological Studies, a field in which he did pioneering research. After 1942 he was also president of William Douglas MacAdams, Inc., a medical advertising agency, and became chairman of its board in 1955. While editor in chief of the Journal of Clinical and Exper...
</Question>
<Choice>Sackler, Arthur Mitchell</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician whose extensive nursing experience during the Civil War determined her on a medical career.Safford grew up from the age of three in Crete, Illinois. During the 1850s she taught school while living with an older brother successively in Joliet, Shawneetown, and Cairo, Illinois. At the outbreak of the Civil War in the spring of 1861, Cairo became a town of some strategic importance because of its situation at the confluence of the Ohio and Mississippi rivers. The town was quickly occupied by volunteer troops from Chicago, and almost as quickly a variety of epidemic diseases bro...
</Question>
<Choice>Safford, Mary Jane</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician and medical researcher who developed the first safe and effective vaccine for polio.Salk received his M.D. in 1939 from New York University College of Medicine, where he worked with Thomas Francis, Jr., who was conducting killed-virus immunology studies. Salk joined Francis in 1942 at the University of Michigan School of Public Health and became part of a group that was working to develop an immunization against influenza.In 1947 Salk became associate professor of bacteriology and head of the Virus Research Laboratory at the University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine. At Pi...
</Question>
<Choice>Salk, Jonas Edward</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish biochemist, corecipient with fellow Swede Sune K. Bergström and Englishman John Robert Vane of the 1982 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine. The three scientists were honoured for their isolation, identification, and analysis of numerous prostaglandins, a family of natural compounds that influence blood pressure, body temperature, allergic reactions, and other physiological phenomena in mammals.Samuelsson graduated from the University of Lund, where Bergström was one of his professors. He continued his studies at the Karolinska Institute in Stockholm, earning doctorates in biochemis...
</Question>
<Choice>Samuelsson, Bengt Ingemar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian physician who was the first to employ instruments of precision in the practice of medicine, and whose studies of basal metabolism introduced quantitative experimental procedure into medical research.Santorio was a graduate of the University of Padua (M.D., 1582), where he later became professor of medical theory (1611–24). About 1587 he was apparently summoned to attend as physician on a Croatian nobleman. From 1587 to 1599 Santorio seems to have spent much time among the southern Slavs, though he maintained a frequent correspondence with his Paduan colleagues, the astronomer Galileo G...
</Question>
<Choice>Santorio Santorio</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American medical doctor and public health administrator who was (1998–2002) the 16th surgeon general of the United States.The son of a small farmer, Satcher nearly died of whooping cough at age two because his family had little access to health care. He was attended by the only black physician in the area and resolved from an early age to become a doctor. At his racially segregated high school, he was class valedictorian and was one of only three graduates to go on to college, earning a B.S. in 1963 from Morehouse College, a historically black institution in Atlanta, Georgia. In 1970 he became...
</Question>
<Choice>Satcher, David</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polish-born American endocrinologist and corecipient, with Roger Guillemin and Rosalyn Yalow, of the 1977 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine. He was noted for isolating and synthesizing three hormones that are produced by the region of the brain known as the hypothalamus; these hormones control the activities of other hormone-producing glands.Schally fled Poland with his family in 1939. He attended the University of London and worked for three years at the National Institute for Medical Research in London before traveling to Montreal to enter McGill University. He graduated in 1955 and two...
</Question>
<Choice>Schally, Andrew V.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physiologist who investigated the effects produced by removal of the thyroid gland.A graduate of the University of Göttingen (M.D., 1844) and a student of the French physiologist François Magendie in Paris, Schiff became director of the ornithology section of the Frankfurt Zoological Museum in 1846. Because of his medical assistance to revolutionaries during the 1848 insurrection, he lost a prospective post at Göttingen, but six years later he was appointed the University of Bern's first professor of comparative anatomy.At Bern, Schiff demonstrated (1856) that excision of the thyroid gl...
</Question>
<Choice>Schiff, Moritz</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physician whose attempts to establish medicine as a natural science helped create modern methods for the teaching and practice of clinical medicine.A professor of medicine at the universities of Würzburg (1824–33), Zürich (1833–40), and Berlin (1840–59), Schönlein was the first to use the microscope in conjunction with chemical analyses of urine and blood in the diagnosis of disease. He found and described (1839) the fungus (Achorion schonleinii) responsible for the skin disease favus and coined the term hemophilia (1828).Schönlein was the first to describe the minute hemorrhages of the...
</Question>
<Choice>Schonlein, Johann Lukas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physiologist who founded modern histology by defining the cell as the basic unit of animal structure.After studying medicine in Berlin, Schwann assisted the physiologist Johannes Peter Müller (1834–38). In 1836, while investigating digestive processes, he isolated a substance responsible for digestion in the stomach and named it pepsin, the first enzyme prepared from animal tissue. While professor of physiology at the Catholic University of Leuven (Louvain), Belg. (1839–48), he observed the formation of yeast spores and concluded that the fermentation of sugar and starch was the result...
</Question>
<Choice>Schwann, Theodor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
GermanGerman-Hungarian physician who discovered the cause of puerperal (“childbed”) fever and introduced antisepsis into medical practice.Educated at the universities of Pest and Vienna, Semmelweis received his doctor's degree from Vienna in 1844 and was appointed assistant at the obstetric clinic in Vienna. He soon became involved in the problem of puerperal infection, the scourge of maternity hospitals throughout Europe. Although most women delivered at home, those who had to seek hospitalization because of poverty, illegitimacy, or obstetrical complications faced mortality rates ranging as...
</Question>
<Choice>Semmelweis, Ignaz Philipp</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish physician and theologian whose unorthodox teachings led to his condemnation as a heretic by both Protestants and Roman Catholics and to his execution by Calvinists from Geneva.While living in Toulouse, France, Servetus studied law and delved into the problem of the Trinity. In February 1530 he accompanied his patron, the Franciscan Juan de Quintana, to the coronation of Emperor Charles V at Bologna. Distressed by papal ostentation and by the emperor's deference to the worldly pope, he left his patron and visited Lyon, Geneva, and Basel. At Basel and Strasbourg he met with Reformation l...
</Question>
<Choice>Servetus, Michael</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American molecular biologist, awarded the 1993 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine, along with Richard J. Roberts, for his independent discovery that individual genes are often interrupted by long sections of DNA that do not encode protein structure.Sharp received a doctorate in chemistry from the University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign in 1969. In that year he began working at the California Institute of Technology, moving to the Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory in New York in 1971. In 1974 he went to the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT), where he joined the Center for Cancer Re...
</Question>
<Choice>Sharp, Phillip A.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physiologist and inventor of the prone-pressure method (Schafer method) of artificial respiration adopted by the Royal Life Saving Society.The first holder of the Sharpey Scholarship (1871) at University College, London, he studied with William Sharpey there, qualifying in medicine. (In 1918, to perpetuate the name of his teacher, he prefixed it to his own.) Upon graduation he remained with the college in teaching and research, going to the University of Edinburgh (1899–1933) as professor of physiology. His demonstration with George Oliver in 1894 of the existence of epinephrine stimul...
</Question>
<Choice>Sharpey-Schafer, Sir Edward Albert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American psychologist and physician who was best known for his theory associating physique, personality, and delinquency.Sheldon attended the University of Chicago, where he received a Ph.D. in psychology in 1926 and an M.D. in 1933. In 1951, after having worked at various universities, Sheldon joined the University of Oregon Medical School, where he became distinguished professor of medicine and director of the constitution clinic, which examined the relationships between physical characteristics and disease; he remained there until his retirement in 1970. Also in 1951 he became director of r...
</Question>
<Choice>Sheldon, William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physiologist whose 50 years of experimentation laid the foundations for an understanding of integrated nervous function in higher animals and brought him (with Edgar Adrian) the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1932.Sherrington was educated at Gonville and Caius College, Cambridge (B.A., 1883); at St. Thomas' Hospital Medical School, where he qualified in medicine in 1885; and at the University of Berlin, where he worked with Rudolf Virchow and Robert Koch. After serving as a lecturer at St. Thomas' Hospital, he was successively a professor at the universities of London (1891–...
</Question>
<Choice>Sherrington, Sir Charles Scott</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first systematic teacher of anatomy, surgery, and obstetrics in the United States. He was also one of the first to use dissected human bodies in the teaching of anatomy in America.Shippen graduated from the College of New Jersey (Princeton) in 1754, studied in London, and went on to Edinburgh for his M.D. (1761). As one of the few physicians in Philadelphia educated abroad, Shippen was uniquely qualified to open his own school of anatomy. Using pictures and casts of the human body as well as dissected cadavers, he lectured on both anatomy and midwifery. His use of human bodies proved unpopular...
</Question>
<Choice>Shippen, William, Jr.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English surgeon and public health reformer whose efforts to improve the hygienic quality of urban life led to the establishment of modern standards of public health service.A surgeon at King's College Hospital, London (1840–47), Simon was appointed first medical officer of health to the City of London (1848–55) and to the central government (1855–76). In this capacity he gradually created a state medical department to administer public health, establish state scientific research, perfect the vaccination system, and supervise the medical profession. His advocacy of public health legislation res...
</Question>
<Choice>Simon, Sir John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish obstetrician who was the first to use chloroform in obstetrics and the first in Britain to use ether.Simpson was professor of obstetrics at the University of Edinburgh, where he obtained his M.D. in 1832. After news of the use of ether in surgery reached Scotland in 1846, Simpson tried it in obstetrics the following January. Later that year he substituted chloroform for ether and published his classic Account of a New Anaesthetic Agent.Simpson persisted in the use of chloroform for relief of labour pains, against opposition of obstetricians and the clergy. He was appointed one of the...
</Question>
<Choice>Simpson, Sir James Young, 1st Baronet</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American microbiologist who shared, with Werner Arber and Daniel Nathans, the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1978 for his discovery of a new class of restriction enzymes that recognize specific sequences of nucleotides in a molecule of DNA (deoxyribonucleic acid) and cleave the molecule at that particular point.Smith graduated from the University of California at Berkeley in 1952 and received a medical degree from Johns Hopkins University in 1956. After internship and residency he joined the faculty of the University of Michigan in 1962. In 1967 he returned to Johns Hopkins, becomin...
</Question>
<Choice>Smith, Hamilton Othanel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American immunogeneticist who, with Jean Dausset and Baruj Benacerraf, was awarded the 1980 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for his studies of histocompatibility (a compatibility between the genetic makeup of donor and host that allows a tissue graft from the former to be accepted by the latter).Snell graduated from Dartmouth College in 1926 and received a Ph.D. in genetics from Harvard University in 1930. During 1931–33 he studied under the geneticist Hermann J. Muller at the University of Texas. In 1935 he joined the staff of the Jackson Laboratory in Bar Harbor, Maine, where he remai...
</Question>
<Choice>Snell, George Davis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(near modern Selçuk, Turkey; fl. 2nd century AD, Alexandria and Rome), Greek gynecologist, obstetrician, and pediatrician, chief representative of the methodist school of medicine (emphasizing simple rules of practice, based on a theory that attributed all disease to an adverse state of “internal pores”). His writings set medical opinion concerning women's diseases, pregnancy, and infant care for nearly 1,500 years.Soranus' remarkable work, On Midwifery and the Diseases of Women, includes numerous descriptions of contraceptive measures; he also describes the obstetric chair and podalic version...
</Question>
<Choice>Soranus of Ephesus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian physiologist who made important contributions to the experimental study of bodily functions and animal reproduction. His investigations into the development of microscopic life in nutrient culture solutions paved the way for the research of Louis Pasteur.Spallanzani was the son of a distinguished lawyer. He attended the Jesuit college at Reggio, where he received a sound education in the classics and philosophy. He was invited to join the order, but, although he was eventually ordained (in 1757), he declined this offer and went to Bologna to study law. Under the influence of his kinswo...
</Question>
<Choice>Spallanzani, Lazzaro</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German embryologist who was awarded the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1935 for his discovery of the effect now known as embryonic induction, the influence exercised by various parts of the embryo that directs the development of groups of cells into particular tissues and organs.Spemann, initially a medical student, attended the universities of Heidelberg, Munich, and Würzburg and graduated in zoology, botany, and physics. He worked at the Zoological Institute of Würzburg (1894–1908), held a professorship at Rostock (1908–14), was director of the Kaiser Wilhelm Institute for Biology...
</Question>
<Choice>Spemann, Hans</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American pediatrician whose books on child rearing, especially his Common Sense Book of Baby and Child Care (1946; 6th ed., 1992), influenced generations of parents and made his name a household word.Spock received his medical degree in 1929 from Columbia University's College of Physicians and Surgeons and trained for six years at the New York Psychoanalytic Institute. He practiced pediatrics in New York City while teaching the subject at the Cornell University Medical College from 1933 to 1947. Spock wrote Baby and Child Care partly to counteract the rigid pediatric doctrines of his day, whic...
</Question>
<Choice>Spock, Benjamin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German educator, chemist, and esteemed medical theorist and practitioner. His chemical theory of phlogiston dominated European chemistry until the “Chemical Revolution” at the end of the 18th century.
</Question>
<Choice>Stahl, Georg Ernst</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physiologist whose prolific contributions to a modern understanding of body functions, especially the maintenance of a fluid balance throughout the tissues, the regulatory role of endocrine secretions, and mechanical controls on heart function, made him one of the foremost scientists of his time.While serving as an instructor (1889–99) at Guy's Hospital, London (M.D., 1890), Starling undertook investigations of lymph secretion that resulted in his clarification of the nature of fluid exchanges between vessels and tissues. Formulating what is known as Starling's hypothesis (1896), he st...
</Question>
<Choice>Starling, Ernest Henry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
physician and the leading representative of the Irish, or Dublin, school of anatomical diagnosis, which emphasized clinical examination of patients in forming a diagnosis. He was also the author of two important works in the emerging field of cardiac and pulmonary diseases.Son of Whitley Stokes, regius professor of medicine at Dublin University, William Stokes received his medical degree from the University of Edinburgh in 1825. Upon his return to Dublin he became a clinical instructor, then physician to the Meath Hospital, succeeding his father in this position. Stokes encouraged students to...
</Question>
<Choice>Stokes, William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British biologist who, with Sydney Brenner and H. Robert Horvitz, won the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 2002 for their discoveries about how genes regulate tissue and organ development via a key mechanism called programmed cell death, or apoptosis.Sulston earned a B.A. (1963) and a Ph.D. (1966) from the University of Cambridge. Following three years of postdoctoral work in the United States, he joined Brenner's group at the Medical Research Council in England (1969). From 1992 to 2000 Sulston was director of the Sanger Institute in Cambridge.Sulston's award-winning research examine...
</Question>
<Choice>Sulston, John E.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American pharmacologist and physiologist who was awarded the 1971 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for isolating cyclic adenosine monophosphate (cyclic AMP) and demonstrating its involvement in numerous metabolic processes that occur in animals.Sutherland graduated from Washburn College (Topeka, Kansas) in 1937 and received his M.D. degree from Washington University Medical School (St. Louis, Missouri) in 1942. After serving in the U.S. Army during World War II, he joined the faculty of Washington University. In 1953 he became chairman of the department of pharmacology at Western Reserve...
</Question>
<Choice>Sutherland, Earl W., Jr.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
physician recognized as a founder of clinical medicine and epidemiology. Because he emphasized detailed observations of patients and maintained accurate records, he has been called “the English Hippocrates.”Although his medical studies at the University of Oxford were interrupted by his participation on the parliamentary side during the first of the English Civil Wars, Sydenham received his M.B. in 1648 and began to practice about 1656 in London, where he made an exacting study of epidemics. This work formed the basis of his book on fevers (1666), later expanded into Observationes Medicae (167...
</Question>
<Choice>Sydenham, Thomas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
physician, physiologist, anatomist, and chemist who is considered the founder of the 17th-century iatrochemical school of medicine, which held that all phenomena of life and disease are based on chemical action. His studies helped shift medical emphasis from mystical speculation to a rational application of universal laws of physics and chemistry.Basing his medical system on the recent discovery of the circulation of the blood by the English anatomist William Harvey, while keeping it within the general framework of the classic Greek physician Galen's humoral theories, Sylvius felt that the mos...
</Question>
<Choice>Sylvius, Franciscus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hungarian biochemist whose discoveries concerning the roles played by certain organic compounds, especially vitamin C, in the oxidation of nutrients by the cell brought him the 1937 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine.Szent-Györgyi earned a medical degree from the University of Budapest in 1917. He became interested in biochemistry and pursued studies in Germany and The Netherlands in that field. While working at the University of Cambridge (1927, 1929) and at the Mayo Foundation, Rochester, Minn., U.S. (1928), Szent-Györgyi found and isolated an organic reducing agent, which he called hexu...
</Question>
<Choice>Szent-Gyorgyi, Albert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biochemist who helped demonstrate that genes determine the structure of particular enzymes or otherwise act by regulating specific chemical processes in living things. His research helped create the field of molecular genetics and earned him (with George Beadle and Joshua Lederberg) the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1958.Tatum earned his doctorate from the University of Wisconsin in 1934. As a research associate at Stanford University (1937–41), Tatum collaborated with Beadle in an attempt to confirm the following concepts: all biochemical processes in all organisms are ul...
</Question>
<Choice>Tatum, Edward L.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician recognized as the founder of pediatric cardiology, best known for her contributions to the development of the first successful treatment of “blue baby” syndrome.Helen Taussig was born into a distinguished family as the daughter of Frank and Edith Guild Taussig. Her father was a prominent economics professor at Harvard University, and her mother was one of the first women to attend Radcliffe College (today known as the Radcliffe Institute for Advanced Study), an extension of Harvard that provided instruction for women. Although Taussig enjoyed a privileged upbringing, adversi...
</Question>
<Choice>Taussig, Helen Brooke</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American virologist who in 1975 shared the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine with his former professor Renato Dulbecco and another of Dulbecco's students, David Baltimore, for his codiscovery of the enzyme reverse transcriptase.While working toward his Ph.D. under Dulbecco at the California Institute of Technology, Temin began investigating how the Rous sarcoma virus causes animal cancers. One puzzling observation was that the virus, the essential component of which is ribonucleic acid (RNA), could not infect the cell if the synthesis of deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) was stopped. Temin prop...
</Question>
<Choice>Temin, Howard Martin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
South African-born American microbiologist who won the 1951 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for his development of a vaccine against yellow fever.Theiler received his medical training at St. Thomas's Hospital, London, and the London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine, graduating in 1922. In that year he joined the department of tropical medicine at Harvard Medical School, Boston. There he carried out important studies of amebic dysentery and rat-bite fever and began work on yellow fever.In 1930 Theiler joined the Rockefeller Institute (now Rockefeller University) in New York City,...
</Question>
<Choice>Theiler, Max</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish biochemist whose study of enzymes that facilitate oxidation reactions in living cells contributed to the understanding of enzyme action and led to the discovery of the ways in which nutrients are used by organisms in the presence of oxygen to produce usable energy. Theorell won the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1955.While serving as an assistant professor of biochemistry at Uppsala University (1932–33; 1935–36), Theorell was the first to isolate crystalline myoglobin, an oxygen-carrying protein found in red muscle (1932). At the Kaiser Wilhelm Institute (now Max Planck Inst...
</Question>
<Choice>Theorell, Axel Hugo Teodor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English-born American plant physiologist who isolated auxin, an important plant growth hormone.Thimann studied chemistry at Imperial College in London, where he received a Ph.D. in biochemistry in 1928. After teaching for two years at King's College for Women in London, Thimann went to the United States, where he served on the faculties at the California Institute of Technology in Pasadena (1930–35), Harvard University (1935–65), and the University of California at Santa Cruz from 1965. He became a U.S. citizen in 1941.Thimann began his search for the growth hormone with Hermann Dolk in the ea...
</Question>
<Choice>Thimann, Kenneth V.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician who in 1990 was corecipient (with Joseph E. Murray) of the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for his work in transplanting bone marrow from one person to another—an achievement related to the treatment of patients with leukemia and other blood cancers or blood diseases.Thomas studied at the University of Texas (B.A., 1941; M.A., 1943) and the Harvard Medical School (M.D., 1946). He served at a few hospitals and a research centre before becoming a professor of medicine at Columbia University's College of Physicians and Surgeons (1955–63) and the University of Washington...
</Question>
<Choice>Thomas, E. Donnall</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch-born British zoologist and ethologist (specialist in animal behaviour) who, with Konrad Lorenz and Karl von Frisch, received the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1973.Tinbergen was the brother of the economist Jan Tinbergen. After receiving a Ph.D. degree (1932) from the University of Leiden, he taught there until 1949. He then served on the faculty of the University of Oxford (1949–74), where he organized a research department of animal behaviour. He became a British citizen in 1955.With Lorenz and Frisch, Tinbergen is credited with revitalizing the science of ethology. Their e...
</Question>
<Choice>Tinbergen, Nikolaas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese molecular biologist who was awarded the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1987 for his discovery of the genetic mechanisms underlying the great diversity of antibodies produced by the vertebrate immune system.Tonegawa earned a B.S. degree from Kyoto University in 1963 and a Ph.D. in molecular biology from the University of California at San Diego, U.S., in 1969. He was a member of the Basel Institute for Immunology in Switzerland from 1971 to 1981. During that time Tonegawa applied the newly devised recombinant DNA techniques of molecular biology to immunology and began to tac...
</Question>
<Choice>Tonegawa Susumu</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physician and pioneer of comparative anatomy whose delineation of the similarities and differences between men and chimpanzees (he called them “orang-outangs”) provided an empirical basis for the study of man. His work suggested a continuity of traits between humans and other primates nearly a century before evolution was first theorized.Tyson's comparisons, set forth in his landmark treatise (1699) of anthropology and comparative anatomy, remarkable for its empirical approach, served as an aid to naturalists 150 years later. He worked within the context of the “chain of being,” whereb...
</Question>
<Choice>Tyson, Edward</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English biochemist who, with Sune K. Bergström and Bengt Ingemar Samuelsson, won the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1982 for the isolation, identification, and analysis of prostaglandins, which are biochemical compounds that influence blood pressure, body temperature, allergic reactions, and other physiological phenomena in mammals.Vane graduated from the University of Birmingham in 1946 and earned a doctorate at the University of Oxford in 1953. He spent several years on the faculty of Yale University (1953–55) in the United States before returning to England to join the Institute...
</Question>
<Choice>Vane, Sir John Robert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American virologist and cowinner (with J. Michael Bishop) of the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1989 for their work on the origins of cancer.Varmus graduated from Amherst (Mass.) College (B.A.) in 1961, from Harvard University (M.A.) in 1962, and from Columbia University, New York City (M.D.), in 1966. He then joined the National Cancer Institute, Bethesda, Md., where he studied bacteria. In 1970 he went to the University of California, San Francisco, as a postdoctoral fellow. There he and Bishop began the research that was to win them the Nobel Prize.Varmus and Bishop found that, u...
</Question>
<Choice>Varmus, Harold</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Renaissance physician who revolutionized the study of biology and the practice of medicine by his careful description of the anatomy of the human body. Basing his observations on dissections he made himself, he wrote and illustrated the first comprehensive textbook of anatomy.
</Question>
<Choice>Vesalius, Andreas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physician who proved tuberculosis to be an infectious disease, transmitted by contact from humans to animals and from one animal to another.Villemin studied at Bruyères and at the military medical school at Strasbourg, qualifying as an army doctor in 1853. He was sent for further study to the Val-de-Grâce, the military medical school in Paris. As an army doctor he observed that healthy young men from the country often developed tuberculosis while living in the close quarters of the barracks. Aware that glanders in horses, a similar disease, is transmitted by inoculation, Villemin began...
</Question>
<Choice>Villemin, Jean Antoine</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German pathologist and statesman, one of the most prominent physicians of the 19th century. He pioneered the modern concept of pathological processes by his application of the cell theory to explain the effects of disease in the organs and tissues of the body. He emphasized that diseases arose, not in organs or tissues in general, but primarily in their individual cells. Moreover, he campaigned vigorously for social reforms and contributed to the development of anthropology as a modern science.
</Question>
<Choice>Virchow, Rudolf Carl</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physiologist whose definitive measurements of gross metabolism in mammals, including humans, helped establish the study of the physiology of metabolism and laid much of the foundation for modern nutritional science.A pupil of the German chemists Justus von Liebig and Friedrich Wöhler at the University of Munich, where he later served as professor of physiology (1863–1908), Voit became involved in experiments designed to determine the utilization and disposition of proteins, fats, and carbohydrates in animals under varying conditions.In 1862 he began a collaboration with the German chemi...
</Question>
<Choice>Voit, Carl von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian psychiatrist and neurologist whose treatment of syphilitic meningoencephalitis, or general paresis, by the artificial induction of malaria brought a previously incurable fatal disease under partial medical control. His discovery earned him the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1927.While a member of the psychiatric staff (1883–89) at the University of Vienna, Wagner-Jauregg noted that persons suffering from certain nervous disorders showed a marked improvement after contracting febrile (characterized by fever) infections. In 1887 he suggested that such infections be deliberate...
</Question>
<Choice>Wagner-Jauregg, Julius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ukrainian-born American biochemist who was one of the world's foremost authorities on soil microbiology. After the discovery of penicillin, he played a major role in initiating a calculated, systematic search for antibiotics among microbes. His consequent codiscovery of the antibiotic streptomycin, the first specific agent effective in the treatment of tuberculosis, brought him the 1952 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine.A naturalized U.S. citizen (1916), Waksman spent most of his career at Rutgers University, New Brunswick, New Jersey, where he served as professor of soil microbiology (19...
</Question>
<Choice>Waksman, Selman Abraham</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biochemist who received (with Haldan K. Hartline of the United States and Ragnar Granit of Sweden) the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1967 for his work on the chemistry of vision.While studying in Berlin as a National Research Council fellow (1932–33), Wald discovered that vitamin A is a vital ingredient of the pigments in the retina and, hence, important in maintaining vision. After further research in Heidelberg and at the universities of Zürich and Chicago, he joined the faculty of Harvard University in 1934.By the early 1950s Wald had succeeded in elucidating the chemic...
</Question>
<Choice>Wald, George</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician and reformer who is thought to have been the only woman surgeon formally engaged for field duty during the Civil War.Walker overcame many obstacles in graduating from the Syracuse (New York) Medical College in 1855. After a few months in Columbus, Ohio, she established a practice in Rome, N.Y., and married Albert Miller, also a physician, with whom she practiced but whose name she did not take; the couple separated in 1859 and finally divorced 10 years later.Walker had from an early age been interested in dress reform and became an ardent follower of Amelia Bloomer in the ca...
</Question>
<Choice>Walker, Mary Edwards</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German biochemist awarded the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1931 for his research on cellular respiration.After earning doctorates in chemistry at the University of Berlin (1906) and in medicine at Heidelberg (1911), Warburg became a prominent figure in the institutes of Berlin-Dahlem. He first became known for his work on the metabolism of various types of ova at the Marine Biological Station in Naples. His Nobel Prize in 1931 was in recognition of his research into respiratory enzymes. In 1944 he was offered a second Nobel Prize but was prevented from receiving the award by Adolf...
</Question>
<Choice>Warburg, Otto</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Australian pathologist who was corecipient, with Barry J. Marshall, of the 2005 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for their discovery that stomach ulcers are an infectious disease caused by bacteria.Warren received a bachelor's degree from the University of Adelaide in 1961. He worked at several hospitals before becoming in 1968 a pathologist at Royal Perth Hospital, where he remained until his retirement in 1999.When Warren began his prizewinning research, physicians believed that peptic ulcers (sores in the stomach lining) were caused by an excess of gastric acid, which was commonly bla...
</Question>
<Choice>Warren, J. Robin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician and scientist, a pioneer in smallpox vaccination.Upon reading in 1799 of the work of Edward Jenner, the British surgeon and doctor who discovered vaccination, Waterhouse began a lifelong crusade for vaccination in the United States, beginning with his five-year-old son. Waterhouse was in his day perhaps the best-educated physician in North America, having studied for seven years in London, Edinburgh, and Leiden. In 1783 he formed, with John Warren and Aaron Dexter, the first faculty of the Harvard Medical School.
</Question>
<Choice>Waterhouse, Benjamin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American geneticist and biophysicist who played a crucial role in the discovery of the molecular structure of deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA), the substance that is the basis of heredity. For this accomplishment he was awarded the 1962 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine with Francis Crick and Maurice Wilkins.Watson enrolled at the University of Chicago when only 15 and graduated in 1947. From his virus research at Indiana University (Ph.D., 1950), and from the experiments of Canadian-born American bacteriologist Oswald Avery, which proved that DNA affects hereditary traits, Watson became convi...
</Question>
<Choice>Watson, James Dewey</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German anatomist and physiologist whose fundamental studies of the sense of touch introduced a concept—that of the just-noticeable difference, the smallest difference perceivable between two similar stimuli—that is important to psychology and sensory physiology.The eldest of three brothers, all of whom achieved scientific distinction, Weber was a professor at the University of Leipzig from 1818 until 1871. Though he conducted many anatomical investigations, he is known chiefly for his work on sensory response to weight, temperature, and pressure; he described a number of his experiments in thi...
</Question>
<Choice>Weber, Ernst Heinrich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American pathologist who played a major role in the introduction of modern medical practice and education to the United States while directing the rise of Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, to a leading position among the nation's medical centres.Undertaking graduate medical study in Germany (1876–78), Welch was working in the laboratory of the pathologist Julius Cohnheim at the University of Breslau when he witnessed Robert Koch's historic demonstration of the infectivity of Bacillus anthracis. Returning to the United States, Welch became professor of pathology and anatomy at Bellevue Hospi...
</Question>
<Choice>Welch, William Henry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician and virologist who was the corecipient (with John Enders and Frederick Robbins) of the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1954 for the successful cultivation of poliomyelitis virus in tissue cultures. This made it possible to study the virus “in the test tube”—a procedure that led to the development of polio vaccines.After his education at the University of Michigan at Ann Arbor (A.B., 1936; M.S., 1937) and Harvard University (M.D., 1940), Weller became a teaching fellow at the Harvard Medical School (1940–42) and served in the U.S. Army Medical Corps during World War...
</Question>
<Choice>Weller, Thomas H.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American pathologist whose discovery that raw liver fed to chronically bled dogs will reverse the effects of anemia led directly to successful liver treatment of pernicious anemia by the American physicians George R. Minot and William P. Murphy. This major advance in the treatment of noninfectious diseases brought the three men the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1934.After obtaining a medical degree from Johns Hopkins University (Baltimore) in 1905, Whipple began in 1908 a study of bile pigments. This led to his interest in the body's manufacture of the oxygen-carrying hemoglobin, w...
</Question>
<Choice>Whipple, George H.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French physician and bacteriologist who made important contributions to the diagnosis, treatment, and prevention of many diseases.In 1896 Widal developed a procedure for diagnosing typhoid fever based on the fact that antibodies in the blood of an infected individual cause the bacteria to bind together into clumps (the Widal reaction). A professor of pathology and internal medicine at the University of Paris (1911–29), he also recognized (1906) the body's retention of sodium chloride as a feature of nephritis (inflammation of the kidney) and cardiac edema (accumulation of excessive fluid in ti...
</Question>
<Choice>Widal, Georges-Fernand-Isidore</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English entomologist, noted for his contribution to the study of insect physiology. His investigations of the living insect body and its tissues and organs revealed much about the dynamic complexity of individual insects and their interactions with the environment. His Insect Physiology (1934) is often considered the foundation for this branch of entomology.After military service in France during World War I, Wigglesworth completed his education at the University of Cambridge and St. Thomas' Hospital in London. He lectured in medical entomology at the London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medi...
</Question>
<Choice>Wigglesworth, Sir Vincent Brian</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
New Zealand-born British biophysicist whose X-ray diffraction studies of deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) proved crucial to the determination of DNA's molecular structure by James D. Watson and Francis Crick. For this work the three scientists were jointly awarded the 1962 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine.Wilkins, the son of a physician (who was originally from Dublin), was educated at King Edward's School in Birmingham, England, and St. John's College in Cambridge. His doctoral thesis, completed for the University of Birmingham in 1940, contained his original formulation of the electron-trap...
</Question>
<Choice>Wilkins, Maurice</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician and founder of Provident Hospital in Chicago, credited with the first successful heart surgery.Williams graduated from Chicago Medical College in 1883. He served as surgeon for the South Side Dispensary (1884–92) and physician for the Protestant Orphan Asylum (1884–93). In response to the lack of opportunity for blacks in the medical professions, he founded (1891) the nation's first interracial hospital, Provident, to provide training for black interns and the first school for black nurses in the United States. He was a surgeon at Provident (1892–93, 1898–1912) and surgeon i...
</Question>
<Choice>Williams, Daniel Hale</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British physicians, leader of the English iatrochemists, who attempted to explain the workings of the body from current knowledge of chemical interactions; he is known for his careful studies of the nervous system and of various diseases. An Oxford professor of natural philosophy (1660–75), he opened a London practice in 1666 that became the most fashionable and profitable of the period.In his Cerebri Anatome, cui accessit Nervorum descriptio et usus (1664; “Anatomy of the Brain, with a Description of the Nerves and Their Function”), the most complete and accurate account of the nervous system...
</Question>
<Choice>Willis, Thomas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American relief worker and reformer who helped supply medical aid and dietary assistance to army hospitals during the Civil War and was subsequently an influential organizer in the temperance movement.Wittenmyer and her husband settled in Keokuk, Iowa, in 1850. At the outbreak of the Civil War, having shortly before been left a widow with a considerable estate, Wittenmyer devoted herself to relief work. As secretary of the Keokuk Soldiers' Aid Society, she visited troop encampments and organized a statewide system of local aid societies to promote the collection of hospital supplies, and soon...
</Question>
<Choice>Wittenmyer, Annie Turner</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician and investigator in pediatric pathology.Wollstein graduated from the Woman's Medical College of the New York Infirmary in 1889. In 1890 she joined the staff of the Babies Hospital in New York City, where she was appointed pathologist in 1892. Her first experimental work involved infant diarrhea and confirmed earlier studies relating the dysentery bacillus to the disease. Her study brought her to the attention of the Rockefeller Institute of Medical Research in New York City, where she collaborated on the first experimental work on polio in the United States. There she also w...
</Question>
<Choice>Wollstein, Martha</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German physiologist and psychologist who is generally acknowledged as the founder of experimental psychology.Wundt earned a medical degree at the University of Heidelberg in 1856. After studying briefly with Johannes Müller, he was appointed lecturer in physiology at the University of Heidelberg, where in 1858 he became an assistant to the physicist and physiologist Wilhelm von Helmholtz. There he wrote Beiträge zur Theorie der Sinneswahrnehmung (1858–62; “Contributions to the Theory of Sense Perception”).It was during this period, in 1862, that Wundt offered the first course ever taught in sc...
</Question>
<Choice>Wundt, Wilhelm</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American medical physicist and joint recipient (with Andrew V. Schally and Roger Guillemin) of the 1977 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine, awarded for her development of the radioimmunoassay (RIA), an extremely sensitive technique for measuring minute quantities of biologically active substances.Yalow graduated with honours from Hunter College of the City University of New York in 1941 and four years later received her Ph.D. in physics from the University of Illinois. From 1946 to 1950 she lectured on physics at Hunter, and in 1947 she became a consultant in nuclear physics to the Bronx V...
</Question>
<Choice>Yalow, Rosalyn S.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Soviet physician who, with cosmonauts Vladimir M. Komarov and Konstantin P. Feoktistov, was a participant in the first multimanned spaceflight, that of Voskhod (“Sunrise”) 1, on Oct. 12–13, 1964, and was also the first practicing physician in space.Upon graduating in 1961 from the First Medical Institute, Moscow, Yegorov joined the team of physicians who studied medical telemetry data from Soviet spaceflights. An expert on the sense-of-balance mechanism in the inner ear, he began training for the Voskhod 1 flight during the summer of 1964. During the flight (which, with an apogee of 254 miles...
</Question>
<Choice>Yegorov, Boris Borisovich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American psychologist and a principal developer of comparative (animal) psychology in the United States.After graduating from Ursinus College, Yerkes took his Ph.D. degree at Harvard University in 1902 and then served first as instructor and then as professor of psychology at Harvard until 1917. His early studies of the behaviour of invertebrates soon gave way to work with the lower mammals, and his first book, The Dancing Mouse (1907), helped establish the use of mice and rats as standard laboratory subjects in psychological testing. He became interested in the psychological testing of humans...
</Question>
<Choice>Yerkes, Robert M.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physician and physicist who established the principle of interference of light and thus resurrected the century-old wave theory of light. He was also an Egyptologist who helped decipher the Rosetta Stone (see).In 1799 Young set up a medical practice in London. His primary interest was in sense perception, and, while still a medical student, he had discovered the way in which the lens of the eye changes shape to focus on objects at differing distances. He discovered the cause of astigmatism in 1801, the same year he turned to the study of light.By allowing light to pass through two clos...
</Question>
<Choice>Young, Thomas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-born American physician who founded the New England Hospital for Women and Children and contributed greatly to women's opportunities and acceptance as medical professionals.Zakrzewska early developed a strong interest in medicine, and at age 20 she was admitted to the school for midwives at the Charité Hospital in Berlin. She became a teaching assistant in her second year, graduating in 1851. The following year she was appointed chief midwife and professor in the school, but staff opposition to her forced her resignation after six months.In 1853 Zakrzewska immigrated to the United State...
</Question>
<Choice>Zakrzewska, Marie Elizabeth</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss immunologist and pathologist who, along with Peter C. Doherty of Australia, received the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine in 1996 for their discovery of how the immune system distinguishes virus-infected cells from normal cells.Zinkernagel received his M.D. from the University of Basel in 1970 and his Ph.D. from the Australian National University, Canberra, in 1975. He joined the John Curtin School of Medical Research in Canberra in 1973 as a research fellow and soon began collaborating with Doherty on a study of the role the immune system plays in protecting mice against infection...
</Question>
<Choice>Zinkernagel, Rolf M.</Choice>
</item>
</topics>