<topics>
<item>
<Question>
More than 2,300 years ago, in the Age of Pericles, the Greeks created the most beautiful temples and statues in the ancient world from white marble. The best of these stood upon the Acropolis, a small plateau in the heart of Athens.
</Question>
<Choice>Acropolis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
served as capital of ancient Kingdom of Aksum, which flourished from 3rd to 9th century; extended influence over much of Arabian Peninsula; Christianized during 4th century; kingdom ended 1270 with abdication of ruling prince; city today a tourist attraction known for its 126 tall granite obelisks and other antiquities; pop. 17,753.
</Question>
<Choice>Aksum</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(356–323 BC). More than any other world conqueror, Alexander III of Macedon, or ancient Macedonia, deserves to be called the Great. Although he died before the age of 33, he conquered almost all the then known world and gave a new direction to history.
</Question>
<Choice>Alexander the Great</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
More than 2,000 years ago Alexandria was the capital and the greatest city of Egypt. Today, though it has been surpassed by Cairo in both size and importance, Alexandria is Egypt's foremost seaport and its second largest city. Roads, trains, and airlines connect it with Cairo, 110 miles (175 kilometers) up the Nile Delta to the southeast.
</Question>
<Choice>Alexandria</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(63 BC–AD 14). The first emperor of Rome was Augustus. During his long reign, which began in 27 BC during the Golden Age of Latin literature, the Roman world also entered a splendid era of civil peace and prosperity.
</Question>
<Choice>Augustus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The story of Western civilization began on a small plain in southwest Asia. Here 50 centuries ago cities rose, government developed, and great inventions—including writing—were made. The civilization that was born here spread westward to Palestine, Greece, and Rome. From these Mediterranean lands it entered the mainstream of Western civilization.
</Question>
<Choice>Babylonia and Assyria</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The most brilliant of medieval civilizations was the Eastern Roman Empire. The Roman Empire was divided in AD 395 into two parts. The Western half, ruled from Rome, fell to the tribal Germanic peoples known as barbarians in the 5th century. The Eastern half, known as the Byzantine Empire, lasted for more than 1,000 years. Until the mid-11th...
</Question>
<Choice>Byzantine Empire</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(100?–44 BC). Assassins ended the career of Julius Caesar before he had finished his lifework. But what he accomplished made him one of the few individuals who changed the course of history. Some historians consider him Rome's greatest genius. He was a soldier of remarkable ability, an accomplished scholar and writer, and a statesman gifted with...
</Question>
<Choice>Caesar, Julius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In about 800 BC settlers from the region of Phoenicia established Carthage in a part of North Africa that is now Tunisia. The city became the commercial center of the western Mediterranean and retained that position until overthrown by Rome.
</Question>
<Choice>Carthage</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Qin (or Ch'in) Dynasty, from which the name China is derived, ruled for only a brief period—from 221 to 207 BC. But during that time it established the approximate boundaries and basic administrative system that lasted in China for the next 2,000 years.
</Question>
<Choice>Ch'in dynasty</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(69–30 BC). One of the most fascinating women of all time was Cleopatra VII, queen of Egypt. She had great intelligence and beauty, and she used both to further Egypt's political aims.
</Question>
<Choice>Cleopatra</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(AD 280?–337). Two important events marked the reign of Constantine the Great, the first Christian emperor of Rome. He made Christianity a lawful religion in Roman society, and he founded the city of Constantinople, the brilliant capital of the Eastern Roman Empire.
</Question>
<Choice>Constantine the Great</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the greatest archaeological finds of modern times, the Dead Sea Scrolls are the remains of about 800–900 ancient manuscripts found in some 15,000 fragments. They take their name from where they were found: in 11 caves along the northwest shore of the Dead Sea, near the ruins of Qumran. Among the scrolls are fragments from nearly all the...
</Question>
<Choice>Dead Sea Scrolls</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Long before the days of Rome's greatness, Italy was the home of a people far advanced in civilization—the Etruscans, or Tyrrhenians. These people rose to prosperity and power, then almost vanished from recorded history, leaving unsolved many questions about their origin and culture.
</Question>
<Choice>Etruscans</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the ancient Roman world, fighters known as gladiators engaged in combat with one another or with wild beasts for the entertainment of the people. The shows were held outdoors before large crowds, eventually in amphitheaters. For the most part the gladiators were prisoners taken in war, slaves, or criminals. When a gladiator was disabled or...
</Question>
<Choice>gladiator</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
About 100 years after the birth of Christ an ancient Teutonic people began moving out of northern Europe. In time they overran the Roman Empire. The first of these barbarians to conquer Rome were the Visigoths, or West Goths.
</Question>
<Choice>Goths</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
“The glory that was Greece,” in the words of Edgar Allan Poe, was short-lived and confined to a very small geographic area. Yet it has influenced the growth of Western civilization far out of proportion to its size and duration. The Greece that Poe praised was primarily Athens during its golden age in the 5th century BC. Strictly speaking, the...
</Question>
<Choice>Greece, Ancient</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(76–138). Publius Aelius Hadrianus, called Hadrian, was Roman emperor from AD 117 until 138. He regarded his 20-year reign as a golden age of peace and prosperity, comparable to that of his great predecessor Augustus more than 100 years earlier (see Augustus). Monuments to Hadrian's reign are the Tivoli villa near Rome; Castel Sant'Angelo...
</Question>
<Choice>Hadrian</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(247?–183? BC).“I swear that so soon as age will permit?.?.?.?I will use fire and steel to arrest the destiny of Rome.” The boy Hannibal said this as he stood at the altar beside his father, the great Carthaginian general Hamilcar Barca. The father and son were leaving for Spain, where Hamilcar hoped to make up for the losses that Carthage had...
</Question>
<Choice>Hannibal</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(6th century BC?). Traditionally, it was thought that a sage named Laozi (or Lao-Tzu) wrote the most translated work in all the literature of China, the Daodejing, which was also previously known as the Laozi. The book is the earliest document in the history of Daoism (“the Way”), one of the major philosophical-religious traditions that, along...
</Question>
<Choice>Lao-tzu</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the 1st millennium BC the region called Phoenicia was a great colonial and commercial power in the Mediterranean. Its people, the Phoenicians, were the great mariners and merchants of ancient times. The Phoenicians (the Canaanites, or Sidonians, of the Bible) were Semitic people. Their country was a narrow strip of the Syrian coast, about...
</Question>
<Choice>Phoenicians</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Italian countryside around the Bay of Naples, called Campania, has always been noted for its beauty. In the days of the Roman Empire, its blue skies and magnificent scenery led many wealthy Romans to build villas there. The old and prosperous cities of Pompeii and Herculaneum and the quiet little town of Stabiae were among the many local...
</Question>
<Choice>Pompeii and Herculaneum</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
When the ancient Greeks were reaching the height of their glory, the power of Rome, to the west, was slowly rising. The genius of the Greeks lay in art, literature, science, and philosophy. The Romans were best in warfare, engineering, and government.
</Question>
<Choice>Roman Empire</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The legendary founders of the city of Rome were Romulus and Remus. They were said to be the twin sons of Mars, the god of war, and Rhea Silvia, the daughter of Numitor, king of Alba Longa. Rhea had been forced to become a vestal virgin by her uncle, Amulius, who had deposed Numitor. When Rhea gave birth, Amulius imprisoned Rhea Silvia and...
</Question>
<Choice>Romulus and Remus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In ancient Greece, the great rival of Athens was Sparta. The city-state and its surrounding territory were located on the Peloponnesus, a peninsula southwest of Athens. Sparta (also called Lacedaemon) was the capital of the district of Laconia.
</Question>
<Choice>Sparta</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The romantic images conjured up by legends sometimes obscure the real-life truths that inspired them. Because the Homeric epic ‘The Iliad' involved ancient Greek gods and goddesses in fantasies of heroism and revenge, the poem's background—the end of the Trojan War after a 10-year siege of Troy—seems to be part of the mythology.
</Question>
<Choice>Trojan War</Choice>
</item>
</topics>