<topics>
<item>
<Question>
Beginning on July 21, 1588, a great fleet of ships from Spain engaged English forces in combat in English waters. This was the Invincible Armada, sent by Philip II, king of Spain. The Armada was made up of 130 ships, not more than 50 of them real men-of-war. They carried 30,493 men, of whom 18,973 were soldiers.
</Question>
<Choice>Armada, Spanish</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1475–1519). The first European to look upon the Pacific Ocean from the shores of the New World was Vasco Núñez de Balboa. The Spanish adventurer and explorer sailed for America in 1500 and settled in Santo Domingo. There his unsuccessful attempts at farming led him into debt. In 1510, hoping to escape his creditors, he stowed away on a ship...
</Question>
<Choice>Balboa, Vasco Núñez de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The terms colonialism and imperialism belong together. Imperialism refers to the practice of extending political power, especially through the acquisition of conquered territory. The territories that are acquired are called colonies. The Roman Empire, for example, began as a small city-state. Gradually, by force, it extended its control...
</Question>
<Choice>colonialism and imperialism</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1485–1547). The Spanish soldier Cortez is known as the conqueror of Mexico. He was born in the small town of Medellin in southwestern Spain.
</Question>
<Choice>Cortez, Hernando</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the Middle Ages the Roman Catholic church considered all the Christians of Europe to be within its fold. That unity and inclusiveness were shattered by the Protestant Reformation of the 16th century. In response to the Reformation, the church launched a major effort to reform itself, to combat the Protestant movement and reclaim lost...
</Question>
<Choice>Counter-Reformation</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1450?–1500). The first European to see the stormy Cape of Good Hope at the southern tip of Africa was Bartholomew Diaz (or Dias), a courageous Portuguese sea captain and explorer. Diaz was one of the great Portuguese seamen who helped find the southeastern water route between western Europe and Asia.
</Question>
<Choice>Dias, Bartolomeu</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1543?–96). The first Englishman to sail around the world was Sir Francis Drake. He also took a leading part in defeating the Great Armada sent by Spain to invade England.
</Question>
<Choice>Drake, Francis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1533–1603). Popularly known as the Virgin Queen and Good Queen Bess, Elizabeth Tudor was 25 years old when she became queen of England. The golden period of her reign is called the Elizabethan Age.
</Question>
<Choice>Elizabeth I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
To understand the natural world and humankind's place in it solely on the basis of reason and without turning to religious belief was the goal of the wide-ranging intellectual movement called the Enlightenment. The movement claimed the allegiance of a majority of thinkers during the 17th and 18th centuries, a period that Thomas Paine called the...
</Question>
<Choice>Enlightenment</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
When most of the world was still unexplored, many people made long journeys over uncharted seas and unmapped territories. Some of them were looking for new trade routes. Some were seeking wealth and fame. Others wanted to claim new lands for their rulers. Finally there were explorers who struck out into the unknown simply for the personal thrill...
</Question>
<Choice>exploration</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
By their marriage in October 1469, Ferdinand II of Aragon and Isabella of Castile initiated a confederation of the two kingdoms that became the basis for the unification of Spain. By their support of the explorations of Christopher Columbus, they also laid the foundations for Spain's colonies in the New World.
</Question>
<Choice>Ferdinand and Isabella</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1460?–1524). During the 15th century Portuguese navigators pressed farther and farther down the uncharted west coast of Africa. They were searching for a sea route to India, whose highly valued spices promised wealth to European traders. By 1488 a Portuguese expedition under Bartholomew Diaz had reached the Cape of Good Hope (see Diaz...
</Question>
<Choice>Gama, Vasco da</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A persecuted minority in France during most of the period from the early 1500s until 1789, the French Protestants were given the name Huguenots in the time of the Reformation. The word may come from the German word Eidgenossen, or “confederates,” a term once applied to Swiss Protestants.
</Question>
<Choice>Huguenots</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1483–1546). The Protestant Reformation in Germany was inaugurated by Martin Luther in 1517. It was his intent to reform the medieval Roman Catholic church, but the firm resistance of the church to Luther's challenge led instead to permanent divisions in the structure of Western Christianity (see Reformation).
</Question>
<Choice>Luther, Martin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1480?–1521). The first European to sail across the Pacific Ocean and the first to discover a route by which ships could sail a complete circle around the world, Ferdinand Magellan was the Portuguese navigator for whom the Strait of Magellan is named. The strait, located at the southern tip of South America, proved to be the long-sought...
</Question>
<Choice>Magellan, Ferdinand</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Its rulers governed India for more than 200 years. They reformed government, encouraged artistry, and tried to unite their subjects. The last Mughal emperors allowed the empire to break apart, however. As a result, the Mughal Empire came to an end, and India came under British control.
</Question>
<Choice>Mughal Empire</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1672–1725). The founder of the Russian Empire was Peter I, called Peter the Great. Under him, Russia ceased to be a poor and backward Asian country and became a modern power in the Western European world.
</Question>
<Choice>Peter the Great</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sea robbers, or men who attack and rob ships at sea, are called pirates. Many of the romantic stories that have been written about them are imaginative pieces of fiction. Nevertheless, their actual adventures often changed the course of history.
</Question>
<Choice>pirates and piracy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1460–1521). A Spanish soldier and explorer, Juan Ponce de León is probably best remembered for his search for the fabled Fountain of Youth. He was born in the province of León in northwestern Spain in 1460. In 1493 he accompanied Christopher Columbus on his second voyage to America. Ponce de León established a colony on Puerto Rico in 1508 and...
</Question>
<Choice>Ponce de León, Juan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the greatest of all revolutions was the 16th-century religious revolt known as the Reformation. This stormy, often brutal, conflict separated the Christians of Western Europe into Protestants and Catholics. So far-reaching were the results of the separation that the Reformation has been called a turning point in history. It ushered in the...
</Question>
<Choice>Reformation</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Historians call the period we live in today Modern Times. Modern Times began with the Renaissance, one of the rare periods of genius in the world's history. It began in Italy during the 14th century and reached its height in the 15th. In the 16th and 17th centuries it spread to the rest of Europe.
</Question>
<Choice>Renaissance</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1756–63). During the early part of the 18th century, both France and England sought undisputed supremacy of the seas. Each nation tried to outdo the other in forming military alliances. Diplomatic intrigues stemming from these alliances created bitter rivalries among European powers. The political atmosphere was so tense that even a small...
</Question>
<Choice>Seven Years' War</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
African trading empire, located in what is now Mali and parts of Niger and Nigeria; flourished 15th and 16th centuries; expansion begun in 1492 by Sonni ?Ali; chief cities were Gao and Timbuktu; mainly Muslim state, with native religions practiced in remote areas; aimed to control caravan routes and trading posts; disintegrated under Moroccan...
</Question>
<Choice>Songhai Empire</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Thirty Years' War was a series of conflicts that began early in the 17th century in the Holy Roman Empire and finally involved much of Europe. It started as a conflict between Protestants and Roman Catholics but soon became a struggle for political power.
</Question>
<Choice>Thirty Years War</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
For 265 years—from 1603 to 1868—Japan enjoyed an era of peace and prosperity, cut off from most contacts with the outside world. The rulers of the country were members of the Tokugawa family, who held the title of shogun. Shoguns were military dictators who governed in the name of, and instead of, the emperors (see shogunate).
</Question>
<Choice>Tokugawa Family</Choice>
</item>
</topics>