<topics>
<item>
<Question>
Three Romanov rulers of Russia were named Alexander.
</Question>
<Choice>Alexander, czars of Russia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
After centuries as one of the most powerful nations of Europe, proud Austria was forced to divide its empire with Hungary in 1867. The two nations formed a dual monarchy—Austria-Hungary.
</Question>
<Choice>Austria-Hungary</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Since 1880, Bastille Day has been celebrated annually on July 14 as the national independence festival of France. The date commemorates the capture of the Bastille, a state prison in Paris that fell to a mob on July 14, 1789, signaling the end of the reign of Louis XVI and the beginning of the French Revolution. The holiday is celebrated with...
</Question>
<Choice>Bastille Day</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
South Africa's Cape of Good Hope was colonized in the 17th century by Dutch Boers (farmers). The Boers used African slaves on their farms. Britain occupied the Cape during the Napoleonic wars and took complete control after the Congress of Vienna. Slavery was abolished throughout the British Empire in 1833. Many of the Boers then decided that...
</Question>
<Choice>Boer War</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1783–1830). Six nations—Venezuela, Colombia, Panama, Ecuador, Peru, and Bolivia—venerate Simón Bolívar as their liberator from the rule of Spain. This great statesman, writer, and revolutionary general is known as the George Washington of South America. He inspired men to follow him through trackless wilderness to fight and die for liberty. Bol...
</Question>
<Choice>Bolívar, Simón</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1729–96). An obscure German princess became one of the most powerful women in history as Catherine II the Great, empress of Russia. She expanded the territory of Russia and was known for her brilliant court, to which the greatest minds of Europe were drawn.
</Question>
<Choice>Catherine the Great</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1728–79). The English navigator Captain Cook became an explorer because of his love of adventure and curiosity about distant lands and their people. He surveyed a greater length of coastline than any other man and remade the map of the Pacific. His explorations gave Britain the lands now occupied by Australia and New Zealand.
</Question>
<Choice>Cook, James</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1712–86; ruled 1740–86). The boy who was to become a great military leader and king of Prussia began his career hating the life of a soldier. Frederick II was born on Jan. 24, 1712, in Berlin. His father was King Frederick William I. His mother was Princess Sophia Dorothea of Hanover, sister of George II of England.
</Question>
<Choice>Frederick the Great</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1807–82). When the Italian patriot and soldier Garibaldi was born, there was no Italy, only a group of small backward states. These states had long been under foreign domination. Garibaldi was one of the three great leaders who freed the Italians from foreign rule and unified the country. Giuseppe Mazzini inspired the people to demand liberation...
</Question>
<Choice>Garibaldi, Giuseppe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John Augustus Sutter emigrated from Switzerland to California in 1839. California was then a Mexican province, and from its governor he gained title to land in order to start a settlement named New Switzerland at the meeting point of the Sacramento and American rivers. He took possession of 50,000 acres (20,235 hectares), and 10 years later he...
</Question>
<Choice>gold rush</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Atop the 1,682-foot- (513-meter-) high Wülpelsberg, a mountain near Aarau in northern Switzerland, stands the ruins of the Habichtsburg, or Hawk's Castle. This castle, built in 1020, was the original seat of the famous Hapsburg (or Habsburg) family. Members of this family ruled Austria from 1278 to the end of World War I.
</Question>
<Choice>Hapsburg, House of</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Most products people in the industrialized nations use today are turned out swiftly by the process of mass production, by people (and sometimes, robots) working on assembly lines using power-driven machines. People of ancient and medieval times had no such products. They had to spend long, tedious hours of hand labor even on simple objects. The...
</Question>
<Choice>Industrial Revolution</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first of the many French kings to bear the name Louis was actually Clovis (see Clovis). He ruled from 481 to 511 and founded the kingdom of the Franks. Later the “C” was dropped and the “v” was written as “u,” thus making the name Louis. It is the same as the English Lewis and the German Ludwig.
</Question>
<Choice>Louis, kings of France</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1755–93). Frivolous and extravagant, Marie Antoinette, queen of France and wife of Louis XVI, became the symbol of the people's hatred for the old regime during the French Revolution. According to legend, when informed that the poor people had no bread to eat, she responded, “Let them eat cake.” Her extravagance contributed only slightly to...
</Question>
<Choice>Marie Antoinette</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1852–1912). For several centuries before the year 1868, Japan was governed by warlords called shoguns. When the emperor Meiji Tenno was crowned in 1868, the last shogunate—that of the Tokugawas—ended, and Japan began its radical transformation from a feudal society into one of the most powerful nations in the modern world.
</Question>
<Choice>Meiji</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
To the troops he commanded in battle Napoleon was known fondly as the “Little Corporal.” To the monarchs and kings whose thrones he overthrew he was “that Corsican ogre.” Some believed him a great reformer. Others thought him a monster. Friend and foe alike, however, could agree on one fact: Napoleon I, emperor of the French and for 16 years...
</Question>
<Choice>Napoleon I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Two of Russia's Romanov rulers were named Nicholas. Nicholas II was the last Russian czar, or emperor.
</Question>
<Choice>Nicholas, czars of Russia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the earliest period of European history, the name Prussia was applied to lands along the southeast coast of the Baltic Sea. Over the centuries Prussian territories increased, mostly through conquest, until they came to include great parts of present-day Poland and most of Germany. By the late 19th century Prussia was a great military power...
</Question>
<Choice>Prussia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The French people overthrew their ancient government in 1789. They took as their slogan the famous phrase “Liberté, Égalité, Fraternité”—Liberty, Equality, Fraternity. Equality, or doing away with privilege, was the most important part of the slogan to the French revolutionists. For equality they were willing to sacrifice their political liberty...
</Question>
<Choice>Revolution, French</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A revolutionary movement swept with unprecedented speed across the breadth of Europe in the early months of 1848. Declared the “Springtime of the Peoples” by contemporaries and known to history as the Revolution of 1848, the upheaval proved extremely short-lived. By the summer of 1849, the forces of revolution across the continent had been...
</Question>
<Choice>Revolution of 1848</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In terms of casualties, China's Taiping Rebellion was one of the worst civil wars in history. Some 20 million people died and 17 provinces were ravaged in this political and religious upheaval, which took place from 1850 to 1864. It was the most serious of several internal disturbances that took place in China in the second half of the 19th...
</Question>
<Choice>Taiping Rebellion</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1819–1901). On June 22, 1897, as cheering throngs massed in the streets, cannon roared, and the bells of London rang, a carriage pulled up to the steps of St. Paul's Cathedral. The greatest empire on Earth was paying tribute to Victoria, the queen-empress, on her Diamond Jubilee.
</Question>
<Choice>Victoria, Queen</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1878–1923). A Mexican bandit and guerrilla leader who became a folk hero, Pancho Villa led brutal attacks on American citizens in Mexico and the American Southwest. In 1916 a United States military expedition pursued Villa across the Mexican state of Chihuahua in retaliation for raids on Santa Isabel, where 16 Americans were executed, and on...
</Question>
<Choice>Villa, Pancho</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Throughout most of history women generally have had fewer legal rights and career opportunities than men. Wifehood and motherhood were regarded as women's most significant professions. In the 20th century, however, women in most nations won the right to vote and increased their educational and job opportunities. Perhaps most important, they...
</Question>
<Choice>women's rights</Choice>
</item>
</topics>