<topics>
<item>
<Question>
(1872–1928). One of the most important men in the history of polar exploration was Roald Amundsen. He was the first man to reach the South Pole, the first to sail around the world via the Northwest and Northeast passages, and the first to fly over the North Pole in a dirigible.
</Question>
<Choice>Amundsen, Roald</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An Afrikaans word for “apartness,” apartheid is the name that South Africa's white government applied to its policy of discrimination—racial, political, and economic—against the country's nonwhite majority in the second half of the 20th century. From the 1960s the government often referred to apartheid as “separate development.”
</Question>
<Choice>apartheid</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Israel and various Arab nations and political groups fought a series of wars in 1948–49, 1956, 1967, 1973, and 1982. Lower-level conflicts often continued during the years between the Arab-Israeli wars, however, and fighting persisted into the 21st century.
</Question>
<Choice>Arab-Israeli Wars</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(born 1926). The longtime leader of Cuba, Fidel Castro became a symbol of political revolution in the Western Hemisphere. Castro held the title of premier from 1959 until 1976, when he became president of the Council of State and the Council of Ministers.
</Question>
<Choice>Castro, Fidel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1887–1975). The lifelong dream of Gen. Chiang Kai-shek was for China to be united and free of foreign domination. As the military and civilian leader of the Republic of China, first on the Asian mainland and later on the island of Taiwan, General Chiang became one of the most controversial men of his time.
</Question>
<Choice>Chiang Kai-shek</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1871–1947). U.S. author Winston Churchill is known for his best-selling historical novels. He used the techniques of popular fiction to undertake a serious consideration of significant issues in the development of the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>Churchill, Winston</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A difficult period in Chinese history, the Cultural Revolution was a massive upheaval launched by Chinese leader Mao Zedong to renew the spirit of revolution in China. It lasted from 1966 until the mid-1970s. Its name in full is the Great Proletariat Cultural Revolution.
</Question>
<Choice>Cultural Revolution</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The republic of Czechoslovakia became an independent country in 1918 after the collapse of Austria-Hungary. It was put together from three provinces— Bohemia, Moravia, and Slovakia—of the former empire. The empire had been dissolved following World War I. As a geographic and political unit, Czechoslovakia lasted until Jan. 1, 1993. On that day...
</Question>
<Choice>Czechoslovakia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1890–1970). Twice in 20 years France looked to Charles de Gaulle for leadership in a time of trouble. General de Gaulle led the Free French government in the dark days of World War II. In 1958 he returned to power as president in an attempt to save France from civil war. Throughout his career as military leader and statesman De Gaulle was guided...
</Question>
<Choice>De Gaulle, Charles</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Like Elizabeth I of England's Golden Age, Elizabeth II came to the throne when she was 25 years old. “A fair and youthful figure,” said Winston Churchill, “princess, wife, and mother, is heir to all our traditions and glories.” The young queen had already won the affection of the British people by her charm and thoughtfulness, her modesty and...
</Question>
<Choice>Elizabeth II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The organization for the economic and political integration of Europe known as the European Union (EU) was officially created on Nov. 1, 1993. In practice, however, the union traces its origins back to 1950, and it has continued to grow in the 21st century. EU members are sovereign countries that have control over their own basic economic and...
</Question>
<Choice>European Union</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1929–45), Dutch diarist. One of the most famous Jewish victims of the Holocaust, Anne Frank penned one of the world's most powerful accounts of Jewish life during World War II. Although Anne's diary did not pertain directly to the Holocaust, its readers became personally acquainted with one of the millions of Jewish victims of Nazi persecution...
</Question>
<Choice>Frank, Anne</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1869–1948). Throughout history most national heroes have been warriors, but Gandhi ended British rule over his native India without striking a single blow. A frail man, he devoted his life to peace and brotherhood in order to achieve social and political progress. Yet less than six months after his nonviolent resistance to British rule won...
</Question>
<Choice>Gandhi, Mahatma</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(born 1931). At the age of 54 Mikhail Gorbachev became the youngest man to head the government of the Soviet Union since Joseph Stalin came to power in the 1920s. Gorbachev was also the first general secretary of the Communist party not to have served in the armed forces during World War II.
</Question>
<Choice>Gorbachev, Mikhail</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
United States President Franklin D. Roosevelt, in his first inaugural address, made some attempt to assess the enormous damage: “The withered leaves of industrial enterprise lie on every side; farmers find no markets for their produce; the savings of many years in thousands of families are gone. More important, a host of unemployed citizens face...
</Question>
<Choice>Great Depression</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1919–2008). At 11:30 AM on May 29, 1953, Edmund Hillary and the Nepalese mountaineer Tenzing Norgay reached the 29,035-foot (8,850-meter) summit of Mount Everest in the Himalayas. They were the first people to make it to the top of the world's highest mountain. For this achievement Hillary was knighted and Tenzing was awarded the George Medal...
</Question>
<Choice>Hillary, Edmund</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
port city at s.w. end of Honshu Island; founded in 16th century as a castle town, later became a military center; first city to be hit by an atomic bomb, on Aug. 6, 1945; device dropped by U.S. Army Air Force killed between 70,000 and 80,000 and left many to die of radiation poisoning; city underwent reconstruction beginning in 1950; site of...
</Question>
<Choice>Hiroshima</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1889–1945). The rise of Adolf Hitler to the position of dictator of Germany is the story of a frenzied ambition that plunged the world into the worst war in history. Only an army corporal in World War I, Hitler became Germany's chancellor 15 years later.
</Question>
<Choice>Hitler, Adolf</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1890–1969). As founder of the Indo-Chinese Communist party in 1930 and president of North Vietnam from 1945 to 1969, Ho Chi Minh led the longest and most costly 20th-century war against colonialism. His whole adult life was devoted to ending French and, later, American domination of Vietnam. His goals were achieved in 1975, six years after his...
</Question>
<Choice>Ho Chi Minh</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The killing of millions of people by Nazi Germany during World War II is referred to as the Holocaust, though the term is most commonly used to describe the fate of Europe's Jews. While Roma (Gypsies), Slavs, homosexuals, and others also were singled out for obliteration, the Nazis' various policies for exterminating the Jews were the most...
</Question>
<Choice>Holocaust</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1894–1971). Joseph Stalin, dictator of the Soviet Union for 29 years, died on March 5, 1953. The next day the government radio announced that to “prevent panic” a collective leadership had been formed to rule the Soviet Union. Nikita Khrushchev was not mentioned in the bulletin. Yet within a few years he triumphed over his rivals to become sole...
</Question>
<Choice>Khrushchev, Nikita</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first international organization set up to maintain world peace was the League of Nations. It was founded in 1920 as part of the settlement that ended World War I. Weakened from the start by the refusal of the United States to join, the organization proved ineffective in defusing the hostilities that led to World War II in 1939. After World...
</Question>
<Choice>League of Nations</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1870–1924). Few individuals in modern history had as profound an effect on their times or evoked as much heated debate as the Russian revolutionary Lenin. To his supporters, Lenin appeared as the individual who, through the sheer force of his will and dedication to the revolutionary struggle, played the decisive role in the 1917 revolution...
</Question>
<Choice>Lenin, Vladimir Ilich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(born 1918). In January 1990 Nelson Mandela was serving his 27th year as a political prisoner in South Africa. He was freed the next month, and in April 1994 he was elected president of the country. Mandela was a leader in the struggle against apartheid—South Africa's official system of segregation and discrimination against the country's...
</Question>
<Choice>Mandela, Nelson</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1893–1976). In China Mao Zedong is remembered and revered as the greatest of revolutionaries. His achievements as ruler, however, have been deservedly downgraded because he was among the worst of politicians. He knew well how to make a revolution, but once in power he could not put his love of revolution aside for the sake of governing.
</Question>
<Choice>Mao Zedong</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1898–1978). One of the founders of the state of Israel, Golda Meir served in many posts in the Israeli government. She also served as prime minister from 1969 to 1974.
</Question>
<Choice>Meir, Golda</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1883–1945). Driven by the spirit of conflict, Benito Mussolini was many things during his turbulent life—teacher, laborer, editor, soldier, politician, and revolutionary. Conflict, ambition, and the desire for power brought him to the day in late October 1922 when he founded Fascism and became dictator of Italy. The same forces ultimately led...
</Question>
<Choice>Mussolini, Benito</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1889–1964). For more than 20 years Jawaharlal Nehru worked with Mahatma Gandhi to free India from British rule. The two great leaders achieved their goal in 1947, when India became an independent country within the British Commonwealth. Nehru became the first prime minister of the new India.
</Question>
<Choice>Nehru, Jawaharlal</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Alfred Nobel, a Swedish chemist and the inventor of dynamite, left more than 9 million dollars of his fortune to found the Nobel prizes. Under his will, signed in 1895, the income from this fund was to be distributed yearly in five equal parts as prizes to those who had most helped humankind. A prize was to be awarded in each of five fields...
</Question>
<Choice>Nobel prizes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The North Atlantic Treaty Organization is a political and military alliance between the United States, Canada, and numerous European countries. Established in 1949 as a defense against the Soviet Union and its eastern European allies, NATO changed its membership and its goals following the breakup of the Soviet Union in 1991. NATO headquarters...
</Question>
<Choice>North Atlantic Treaty Organization</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Few citizens of the industrialized nations had ever heard of the Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries (OPEC) until 1973, when it imposed an oil embargo on the United States and raised the price of crude oil by 70 percent. The name of the oil cartel suddenly became a household word.
</Question>
<Choice>OPEC</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
When the state of Israel was established in 1948, nearby Arab states immediately waged war against the new nation. As a result, a severe refugee problem was created among the Palestinians—the Arabs who had been living in and near the territories that were taken over by Israel. Many of these millions of people were displaced to several Arab states...
</Question>
<Choice>Palestine Liberation Organization</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A great water tollway often called the “Big Ditch,” the Panama Canal links the Atlantic and Pacific oceans. It weaves across a strip of tropical land where the Isthmus of Panama narrows in the shape of a long flattened letter S. The fame of the Panama Canal is not in its size, for it is only about 51 miles (82 kilometers) long. Rather, the canal...
</Question>
<Choice>Panama Canal</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1895–1974). Although Juan Perón of Argentina was one of the more remarkable and charismatic Latin American politicians of the 20th century, he may eventually be remembered because of his marriage to the talented and shrewd Eva Duarte. It was she who became the center of a powerful personality cult that endured after her death. A television...
</Question>
<Choice>Perón, Juan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The roots of the Russian Revolution of 1917 were deep. Russia had suffered under an extremely oppressive form of government for centuries under the rule of the czars. During the 19th century the nation was filled with movements for political liberalization.
</Question>
<Choice>Revolution, Russian</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1918–81). The Egyptian soldier and statesman Anwar el-Sadat served as president of Egypt from 1970 until his death. Sadat participated in historic negotiations with Israel that resulted in the signing of a peace treaty and for which he was awarded the Nobel peace prize.
</Question>
<Choice>Sadat, Anwar el-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Apart from the two world wars, the Spanish Civil War was the bloodiest conflict in the first half of the 20th century. It lasted two years and 254 days—from July 17, 1936, until March 28, 1939. During that time about 1 million people perished. Of those million, approximately 600,000 were battle-related deaths—more than in the American Civil War...
</Question>
<Choice>Spanish Civil War</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1879–1953). One of the most ruthless dictators of modern times was Stalin, the despot who transformed the Soviet Union into a major world power. The victims of his campaigns of political terror included some of his followers. His real name was Iosif Vissarionovich Dzhugashvili. In 1912 he took the alias of “Stalin,” from the Russian word stal...
</Question>
<Choice>Stalin, Joseph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1866–1925). Known as the father of modern China, Sun Yat-sen worked to achieve his lofty goals to transform the country. These included the successful overthrow of the Qing, or Manchu, Dynasty and the establishment of a republic. He was the first provisional president of the Republic of China in 1911–12 and leader of the Chinese Nationalist party...
</Question>
<Choice>Sun Yat-sen</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Terrorists use violence in an attempt to achieve political goals. Their intent is to bring about political change by creating a climate of fear within the society they oppose. The targeting of innocent victims and symbolic locations for a high-profile attack has long been the preferred method of terrorist organizations.
</Question>
<Choice>terrorism</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Although it was considered “unsinkable” by its builders and the general public, the British ocean liner Titanic of the White Star Line sank on her maiden voyage in 1912, resulting in the death of more than 1,500 men, women, and children—more casualties than in any other marine disaster in peacetime history. The magnitude of this tragedy, combined...
</Question>
<Choice>Titanic</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Within one week's time, in the summer of 1991, the 74-year-old Union of Soviet Socialist Republics (U.S.S.R.)—or Soviet Union—became a finished part of history. The Soviet Union was the world's largest country. At its greatest extent, it covered an area of 8.6 million square miles (22.3 million square kilometers), almost seven times the area of...
</Question>
<Choice>Union of Soviet Socialist Republics</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The United Nations (UN) is an association of independent countries that have agreed to work together to prevent and end wars. The UN also attempts to improve social conditions by promoting international cooperation, economic development, public health, environmental conservation, and human rights. Members of the UN are supposed to cooperate...
</Question>
<Choice>United Nations</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A major international conflict fought from 1914 to 1918, World War I was the most deadly and destructive war the world had ever seen to that time. More than 25 countries eventually participated, aligned with either the Allied or the Central powers. The Allies—who won the war—included primarily France, Great Britain, Russia, Italy, Japan, and...
</Question>
<Choice>World War I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Some 20 years after the end of World War I, lingering disputes erupted in an even larger and bloodier conflict—World War II. The war began in Europe in 1939, but by its end in 1945 it had involved nearly every part of the world. The opposing sides were the Axis powers—consisting mainly of Germany, Italy, and Japan—and the Allies—primarily France...
</Question>
<Choice>World War II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1931–2007). After the repressive rule of czars and Communist dictators, the first freely elected leader in the 1,000-year history of Russia was Boris Yeltsin. A champion of the underdog, Yeltsin almost overnight made himself an international figure. In the anti-Communist sweep of the historic June 1991 election he became president of the Russian...
</Question>
<Choice>Yeltsin, Boris</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1879–1919). The 1952 movie ‘Viva Zapata', starring Marlon Brando, was the first introduction many Americans had to the Mexican revolutionary Emiliano Zapata. He was a champion of the poor, a land reformer, and a guerrilla fighter during the Mexican Revolution and its aftermath from 1911 to 1917.
</Question>
<Choice>Zapata, Emiliano</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The creation of the state of Israel in 1948 as a homeland for Jews the world over was the culmination of decades of effort by the Zionist movement. Modern Zionism originated in Eastern Europe during the late 19th century largely as a result of the persistent and severe persecutions of Jews in Russia and its neighbors to the west. In many ways...
</Question>
<Choice>Zionism</Choice>
</item>
</topics>