<topics>
<item>
<Question>
In the 14th century BC the Egyptian pharaoh Amenhotep IV undertook a religious reform by displacing all the traditional deities with the sun-god Aton (also Aten). In the god's honor, the pharaoh changed his name to Ikhnaton, which means “It is well with Aton.” Ikhnaton (also Akhenaton) ruled from 1379 to 1362 BC. His queen was Nofretete (also...
</Question>
<Choice>Ikhnaton</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the major figures in the history of religion is Abraham. He is considered the father of faith for the religions of Judaism, Christianity, and Islam. He is also called a patriarch, a term derived from the Greek words for “father” and “beginning.” Applied to Abraham, the term patriarch thus means that he is considered to be a founding father...
</Question>
<Choice>Abraham</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The earliest civilization in Europe appeared on the coasts and islands of the Aegean Sea. This body of water is a branch of the Mediterranean Sea. It is bounded by the Greek mainland on the west, Asia Minor (now Turkey) on the east, and the island of Crete on the south. Here, while the rest of Europe was still in the Stone Age, the Minoan...
</Question>
<Choice>Aegean civilizations</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
No other country—not even China or India—has such a long unbroken history as Egypt. Nearly 3,000 years before the birth of Jesus, the Egyptians had reached a high stage of civilization. They lived under an orderly government; they carried on commerce in ships; they built great stone structures; and, most important of all, they had acquired the...
</Question>
<Choice>Egypt, Ancient</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ancient Egyptians had three different writing systems. The oldest, best known, and most difficult to read is called hieroglyphics. The word, which means “sacred carving,” was used by Greeks who saw the script on temple walls and public monuments. The Greeks were somewhat mistaken in their terminology because hieroglyphs were used on gravestones...
</Question>
<Choice>hieroglyphics</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Four thousand years ago the warrior Hittites of Asia Minor rose to world power. For more than a thousand years they ruled most of the region now in modern Turkey and Syria. Their empire rivaled in size and strength the two other world powers of the time, Egypt and the Assyro-Babylonian empires of Mesopotamia.
</Question>
<Choice>Hittites</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The earliest known urban culture of the Indian subcontinent existed in the Indus Valley from about 2500 BC to about 1700 BC. Its main centers, most of which are now in Pakistan, were Mohenjo-daro, Harappa, Kalibangan, and Lothal.
</Question>
<Choice>Indus Valley civilization</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(or Cush), the ancient name for a region of what is now part of the Sudan, in Africa, and for two powerful kingdoms that extended their influence into Egypt; first kingdom of Kush raided Upper Egypt in about 1650 BC; destroyed by Egyptian Pharoah Amenhotep; new kingdom appeared about 750 BC; conquered all Egypt about 715 BC and founded 25th...
</Question>
<Choice>Kush</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the great museum of Egyptian antiquities in Cairo, throngs of sightseers daily look into the very faces of the pharaohs and nobles who ruled Egypt many centuries ago. They were preserved as mummies, thousands of which have been taken from the sands and tombs of Egypt. The word mummy refers to a dead body in which some of the soft tissue has...
</Question>
<Choice>mummy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In its most common form, a pyramid is a massive stone or brick structure with a square base and four sloping triangular sides that meet in a point at the top. Pyramids have been built by different peoples at various times in history. Probably the best-known pyramids are those of ancient Egypt, which were built to protect the tombs of rulers or...
</Question>
<Choice>pyramid</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A sphinx is a fabled monster. It has a human head and a lion's body. In ancient Egypt, where the idea originated, the head was usually a portrait of the reigning pharaoh. It also represented the sky-god Horus. The Egyptians always pictured their kings as calm and stately, with wide-open, staring eyes. The lion's body—symbolizing courage—is...
</Question>
<Choice>sphinx</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The prehistoric monument known as Stonehenge includes a circular arrangement of massive, upright stones surrounded by a large circular earthen embankment. It was built between about 3100 and 1500 BC and is located about 8 miles (13 kilometers) northwest of Salisbury, in southern England. There are hundreds of similar structures throughout Britain...
</Question>
<Choice>Stonehenge</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(ruled 1361–52 BC). He was only about 18 years old when he died, and as a pharaoh of Egypt he had no great claim to fame. Tutankhamen (originally Tutankhaten) owes his place in history mostly to the discovery of his tomb—completely intact and not violated by grave robbers—in 1922. The remarkable artifacts from the tomb, including the beautiful...
</Question>
<Choice>Tutankhamen</Choice>
</item>

</topics>