<topics>
<item>
<Question>
served as capital of ancient Kingdom of Aksum, which flourished from 3rd to 9th century; extended influence over much of Arabian Peninsula; Christianized during 4th century; kingdom ended 1270 with abdication of ruling prince; city today a tourist attraction known for its 126 tall granite obelisks and other antiquities; pop. 17,753.
</Question>
<Choice>Aksum</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(848?–899). The course of English history would have been very different had it not been for King Alfred. He won renown both as a statesman and as a warrior and is justly called “the Great.”
</Question>
<Choice>Alfred the Great</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Beginning in about 1050, an ancient civilization known as the Anasazi culture began building large apartment-like structures along the sides or under the overhangs of cliffs. These cliff dwellings, located in the four corners region where the borders of Arizona, New Mexico, Colorado, and Utah intersect, stood as high as five stories. By the end...
</Question>
<Choice>Anasazi culture</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Angkor means “capital,” and a wat is a monastery. The city of Angkor in northwestern Cambodia was for more than 500 years the capital of the Khmer Empire, a kingdom that once ruled most of the Indochinese peninsula. From the end of the 9th century until early in the 13th century, numerous large construction projects made Angkor one of the most...
</Question>
<Choice>Angkor Wat</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
As long as men have fought with one another they have doubtless used armor of some kind to protect themselves. Stone-Age men cushioned their bodies against the blows of clubs with layers of furry hides. One society used war clubs armed with shark's teeth. The suits of coconut fiber they wore as armor were designed to snag these clubs. Quilted or...
</Question>
<Choice>armor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
When Hernando Cortez and his Spanish soldiers reached the Valley of Mexico in 1519, they found a splendid city standing on an island in a lake. Three wide causeways led to huge white palaces and ornate temples on pyramids.
</Question>
<Choice>Aztec</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The most brilliant of medieval civilizations was the Eastern Roman Empire. The Roman Empire was divided in AD 395 into two parts. The Western half, ruled from Rome, fell to the tribal Germanic peoples known as barbarians in the 5th century. The Eastern half, known as the Byzantine Empire, lasted for more than 1,000 years. Until the mid-11th...
</Question>
<Choice>Byzantine Empire</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
From 632 until 1258 the nominal ruling power in the Islamic world was the caliphate, an institution formed to head off a leadership crisis brought on by the death in 632 of Muhammad, the founder of Islam. The successor chosen was Abu Bakr, Muhammad's father-in-law and longtime companion. His title was caliph, a term that means both “successor...
</Question>
<Choice>Caliphate</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In medieval Europe, the castle was the most common type of stronghold and often the residence of the king or territorial lord. It played an important role in the military history of the Middle Ages. It was often employed by kings and nobles as a means to impose their authority on their territory. The castle remained the dominant fortification in...
</Question>
<Choice>castle</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(742?–814). The man now known as Charlemagne became king of the Franks in 768. Within a few decades his conquests had united almost all the Christian lands of western Europe into one state, which became known as the Holy Roman Empire. His name means “Charles the Great.” His vast empire did not remain intact for long after his death, but during...
</Question>
<Choice>Charlemagne</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
From 1096 until the end of the Middle Ages, Christian warriors from Europe undertook a series of military campaigns, or Crusades, designed to take back from the Muslims control of the Holy Land (in the region of Palestine). After centuries of wars of expansion, Muslim powers had conquered some two thirds of the ancient Christian world, including...
</Question>
<Choice>Crusades</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
For more than 300 years one family, the Fujiwara clan, played so dominant a role in Japan's political life that the era of their influence is often called the Fujiwara period. The family's success was the more remarkable in that it rested not so much on military power as on political strategy and a special relationship with the imperial family...
</Question>
<Choice>Fujiwara family</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1162?–1227). From the high, windswept Gobi came one of history's most famous warriors. He was a Mongolian nomad known as Genghis Khan. With his fierce, hard-riding nomad horde, he conquered a huge empire that stretched through Asia from the Yellow Sea to the Black Sea.
</Question>
<Choice>Genghis Khan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first of the great medieval trading empires of western Africa; tradition dates its origins to the 4th century AD; flourished 7th–13th centuries; situated between the Sahara Desert and the headwaters of the Sénégal and Niger rivers; populated by Soninke clans of Mande-speaking people who acted as intermediaries between the Arab and Berber salt...
</Question>
<Choice>Ghana Empire</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
For more than two centuries, from about AD 320 to 540, the Gupta Dynasty governed the northern half of the Indian subcontinent. This territory included much of the northern part of present-day India, most of Pakistan, and some of Bangladesh. The first ruler, Candra Gupta I (not to be confused with Candragupta, who founded the Mauryan Dynasty in...
</Question>
<Choice>Gupta Dynasty</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1400?–68). Neither printing nor movable type was actually invented by Johannes Gutenberg, nor did he print the first book. Gutenberg's experiments made printing practical, and his method of using type endured almost unchanged for five centuries.
</Question>
<Choice>Gutenberg, Johannes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Eight of the kings of England have been named Henry. The first of these, Henry I, was the youngest son of the Norman conqueror, William I. The most recent one was the notorious Henry VIII, who ruled in the 1500s.
</Question>
<Choice>Henry, kings of England</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
From Christmas Day in AD 800 until Aug. 6, 1806, there existed in Europe a peculiar political institution called the Holy Roman Empire. The name of the empire as it is known today did not come into general use until 1254. It has truly been said that this political arrangement was not holy, or Roman, or an empire. Any holiness attached to it came...
</Question>
<Choice>Holy Roman Empire</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1337–1453). The struggle between France and England called the Hundred Years' War was the longest war in recorded history. It lasted, with some interruptions, through the reigns of five English kings (Edward III to Henry V) and five French kings (Philip VI to Charles VII).
</Question>
<Choice>Hundred Years' War</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
When the gold-seeking Spanish conquistadors reached Peru in 1532, they encountered the vast empire of a Quechua-speaking people called the Incas. The great civilization of the Incas extended along the Pacific coast of South America from modern Ecuador southward to central Chile and inland across the Andes. The Incas had conquered this vast...
</Question>
<Choice>Incas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Waves of opposition to the Roman Catholic church swept over Europe in the 13th century. The church established a tribunal called the Inquisition to try persons accused of being heretics, that is, of revolting against religious authority.
</Question>
<Choice>Inquisition</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
an African empire, located in the area around Lake Chad in west central Africa, where northeastern Nigeria, southern Chad, southern Libya, eastern Niger, and northern Cameroon now are; endured from 9th century to 19th under Sef dynasty; became an Islamic state in 11th century; chief point of trade between North Africa, Nile Valley, and sub-Sahara...
</Question>
<Choice>Kanem-Bornu Empire</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first European to land on the North American continent was a Viking seaman, Leif Ericson. A son of the explorer Eric the Red, he was born in Iceland in about AD 980. When Leif was about 2 years old, Eric took his family to Greenland. The boy grew up in Brattahild, now the Eskimo village of Kagsiarsuk, on Eric's Fjord, on the southwest coast.
</Question>
<Choice>Leif Eriksson</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A basic document that states the liberties guaranteed to the English people, the Magna Carta proclaims rights that have become a part of English law and are now the foundation of the constitution of every English-speaking nation. The Magna Carta, which means “great charter” in Latin, was drawn up by English barons and churchmen, who forced the...
</Question>
<Choice>Magna Carta</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Maya of Mesoamerica, along with the Aztecs of Mexico and the Incas of Peru, made up the high civilizations of the American Indians at the time of the Spanish conquest. Both the Aztecs and the Incas were late empires (about AD 1300–1533), capstones of a sequence of civilizations in Central Mexico and the Andes in South America, respectively...
</Question>
<Choice>Maya</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The medieval period, or the Middle Ages, was a time in European history before the modern era. In the 4th century AD Germanic peoples began crossing the frontiers of the Roman Empire, in part because of the advance of ferocious warriors from the east—the Huns. The movement of the Germanic peoples contributed to the so-called fall of the Roman...
</Question>
<Choice>Middle Ages</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The traditional homeland of the Central Asian people known as the Mongols is a vast highland region in what are now Mongolia and northern China. The Mongols share a common language and a tradition of following a nomadic way of life herding livestock. Their origin is unknown. By the 13th century a confederation of nomadic Mongol tribes had become...
</Question>
<Choice>Mongol Empire</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(570?–632). “There is no God but Allah, and Muhammad is the Prophet of Allah.” This is the fundamental statement of faith in Islam, and it declares that Muhammad is the founder of one of the world's major religions. He was also the founder of a state by his unification of Arabia. Within decades after his death his followers sent out armies that...
</Question>
<Choice>Muhammad</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Edward the Confessor, king of England, died childless on Jan. 5, 1066. It is possible that Edward had promised William, duke of Normandy, the throne. As William was Edward's cousin, it is likely that William had been given some encouragement about the succession. Nevertheless, when Edward died, Harold, the powerful earl of Wessex, had himself...
</Question>
<Choice>Norman Conquest</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Early in the 14th century the Turkish tribal chieftain Othman, or Osman, founded an empire in western Anatolia (Asia Minor) that was to endure for almost six centuries. As this empire grew by conquering lands of the Byzantine Empire and beyond, it came to include at the height of its power all of Asia Minor; the countries of the Balkan Peninsula...
</Question>
<Choice>Ottoman Empire</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1254?–1324). The Venetian merchant and adventurer Marco Polo wrote a fascinating book about his travels in China and other parts of Asia in the late 13th century. The book was an instant success and was translated into many languages. Fellow Europeans read his accounts of the riches of Asia and became eager to find sea routes to China, Japan...
</Question>
<Choice>Polo, Marco</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In April 1986 in Nikko, Japan, the Edo Mura Village was opened to the public. The village commemorates the period in Japan's history from 1603 to 1867, called the Tokugawa shogunate, when warlords called shoguns ruled the country. The warriors of the shoguns were called samurai. (See also Japan, “History”; Tokugawa Family.)
</Question>
<Choice>samurai</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
For most of the period between 1192 and 1868, the government of Japan was dominated by hereditary warlords called shoguns. The word shogun means “general.” The term used in Japan to describe their rule is bakufu, which literally means “tent government” and suggests the field headquarters of a general while on campaign.
</Question>
<Choice>shogunate</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1336–1405). Timur Lenk means “Timur, the lame.” But the handicap did not stop Timur from becoming one of the fiercest and most successful of the conquerors to come out of Central Asia. For almost four decades—from the 1360s until his death—he and his nomad warriors conquered every territory from Mongolia in the east to the Mediterranean lands...
</Question>
<Choice>Timur Lenk, or Tamerlane</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the 9th century AD, seafaring warriors known as Vikings began raiding the coasts of Europe, burning, plundering, and killing as they went. These marauders, or pirates, came from Scandinavia—what is now Denmark, Norway, and Sweden. The people who lived there were Norsemen, or Northmen. Their expression for these campaigns of swift, cruel raids...
</Question>
<Choice>Vikings</Choice>
</item>

</topics>