<topics>
<item>
<Question>
Alfred Stieglitz - Born this day in 1864, Alfred Stieglitz was an American art dealer, an advocate for Modernist art, and his era's preeminent photographer, among whose most famous photos were those of his wife, painter Georgia O'Keeffe.
</Question>
<Choice>1 January</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Isaac Asimov - American biochemist and author Isaac Asimov, born in Russia this day in 1920, was a popularizer of scientific ideas and a prolific writer of science fiction, in which he created an ethical system for humans and robots.
</Question>
<Choice>2 January</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Father Damien - Belgian priest Father Damien, born this day in 1840, went on a mission to the Hawaiian Islands in 1863 and subsequently devoted his life to ministering to the lepers who had been deported to Molokai island.
</Question>
<Choice>3 January</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Isaac Newton - Isaac Newton, born in England this day in 1643, was a leader of the scientific revolution whose Mathematical Principles of Natural Philosophy (1687) is among the most important single works in the history of modern science.
</Question>
<Choice>4 January</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Umberto Eco - A renowned critic and semiotician (student of signs and symbols), Umberto Eco, born this day in 1932, is perhaps better known as the author of the best-selling murder mystery and fantasy novel The Name of the Rose (1981).
</Question>
<Choice>5 January</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Richard II - Born this day in 1367, King Richard II of England, an ambitious ruler who reigned from 1377 to 1399, was deposed by his cousin Henry Bolingbroke (Henry IV) because of his arbitrary and factional rule.
</Question>
<Choice>6 January</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hirohito - Emperor Hirohito—the longest-reigning monarch in Japanese history, who was enthroned in 1926, ruled during World War II and in democratic postwar Japan, and died this day in 1989—was succeeded by his son Akihito.
</Question>
<Choice>7 January</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Elvis Presley - American popular singer and film star Elvis Presley, born this day in 1935, was widely known as the “King of Rock and Roll” and was one of that genre's dominant performers from the mid-1950s until his death in 1977.
</Question>
<Choice>8 January</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Richard M. Nixon - Born this day in 1913 was Richard M. Nixon, the 37th president of the United States (1969–74), who held office during the Vietnam War and became, in the wake of the Watergate Scandal, the only U.S. president to resign.
</Question>
<Choice>9 January</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dame Barbara Hepworth - Dame Barbara Hepworth, whose lyrical forms made her one of the most influential sculptors of the mid-20th century and whose abstract sculptures were among the earliest produced in England, was born this day in 1903.
</Question>
<Choice>10 January</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jean Chrétien - Born this day in 1934, lawyer and Liberal Party politician Jean Chrétien served as prime minister of Canada from 1993 to 2003—the first Canadian prime minister since 1945 to win three consecutive majorities.
</Question>
<Choice>11 January</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John Hancock - John Hancock, born this day in 1737, was a leader of the American Revolution, the first signer of the U.S. Declaration of Independence, and president of the Continental Congress from May 1775 to October 1777.
</Question>
<Choice>12 January</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Lilla Cabot Perry - American artist Lilla Cabot Perry, born this day in 1848 and influenced heavily by painter Claude Monet, emulated the innovations of French Impressionism in her art and was a major promoter of Impressionism in the U.S.
</Question>
<Choice>13 January</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Albert Schweitzer - Albert Schweitzer—the Alsatian German theologian, philosopher, organist, and mission doctor in Africa—was born this day in 1875 and received the 1952 Nobel Peace Prize for his works in behalf of “the Brotherhood of Nations.”
</Question>
<Choice>14 January</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Martin Luther King, Jr. - Martin Luther King, Jr., born this day in 1929, led the civil rights movement in the United States from the mid-1950s until his assassination in 1968 and was the recipient of the Nobel Peace Prize in 1964.
</Question>
<Choice>15 January</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dian Fossey - American zoologist Dian Fossey, born this day in 1932, became the world's leading authority on the mountain gorilla, and her autobiography, Gorillas in the Mist (1983), was subsequently adapted into a feature film.
</Question>
<Choice>16 January</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
David Lloyd George - Born this day in 1863, David Lloyd George, Liberal prime minister of Britain from 1916 to 1922, led his country to victory in World War I after laying the foundation of the modern welfare state as chancellor of the Exchequer.
</Question>
<Choice>17 January</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Paul Keating - Paul Keating, born this day in 1944, became Australia's youngest prime minister in December 1991, succeeding Robert Hawke as the leader of the Australian Labor Party and holding office until March 1996.
</Question>
<Choice>18 January</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Paul Cézanne - French painter Paul Cézanne, who was born this day in 1839 and whose works and ideas influenced the aesthetic development of many 20th-century artists and art movements, was one of the greatest of the Post-Impressionists.
</Question>
<Choice>19 January</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Federico Fellini - Italian director Federico Fellini, born this day in 1920, was one of the most celebrated filmmakers in the post-World War II period, his distinctive style imposing dreamlike or hallucinatory imagery on ordinary situations.
</Question>
<Choice>20 January</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Plácido Domingo - Plácido Domingo, an operatic tenor whose voice, physical stature, good looks, and dramatic ability made him one of the most popular tenors of the late 20th and early 21st centuries, was born in Madrid this day in 1941.
</Question>
<Choice>21 January</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Lord Byron - Born this day in 1788, British Romantic poet and satirist Lord Byron captured the imagination of Europe with his personality and work, notably Don Juan and the renowned autobiographical poem Childe Harold's Pilgrimage.
</Question>
<Choice>22 January</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Édouard Manet - French painter Édouard Manet, born this day in 1832, defied traditional techniques of representation and chose modern, urban subjects, antagonizing the critics but paving the way for Impressionism and Post-Impressionism.
</Question>
<Choice>23 January</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Winston Churchill - British statesman, orator, and author Winston Churchill, who as prime minister (1940–45, 1951–55) rallied the British people during World War II and led his country from the brink of defeat to victory, died this day in 1965.
</Question>
<Choice>24 January</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Corazon Aquino - Three years after her husband's assassination, Corazon Aquino, born this day in 1933, was elected president of the Philippines in February 1986, restoring democracy after the long dictatorship of Ferdinand Marcos.
</Question>
<Choice>25 January</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Wayne Gretzky - Canadian ice-hockey player Wayne Gretzky, who holds the NHL record for points (2,857), goals (894), and assists (1,963) and is considered by many the game's greatest player of all time, was born this day in 1961.
</Question>
<Choice>26 January</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart - Austrian composer Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart, who is widely recognized as one of the greatest composers in the history of Western music and who excelled at all the musical genres of his era, was born this day in 1756.
</Question>
<Choice>27 January</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mikhail Baryshnikov - Mikhail Baryshnikov, whose elegance, great physical prowess, and unsurpassed leaping ability made him the preeminent male ballet dancer of the 1970s and '80s, was born in Riga, Latvia, this day in 1948.
</Question>
<Choice>28 January</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Oprah Winfrey - Oprah Winfrey, born this day in 1954, became one of the wealthiest and most influential women in the United States largely as a result of the tremendous popularity of her Emmy Award-winning television talk show.
</Question>
<Choice>29 January</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Franklin D. Roosevelt - Born this day in 1882, Franklin D. Roosevelt, the only person to win four terms as U.S. president, introduced the New Deal to address the crisis brought on by the Great Depression and led his country during World War II.
</Question>
<Choice>30 January</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jackie Robinson - Jackie Robinson—the first African American baseball player in the U.S. major leagues in the 20th century and the league's Rookie of the Year in 1947 and Most Valuable Player in 1949—was born this day in 1919.
</Question>
<Choice>31 January</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Boris Yeltsin - Born this day in 1931, Boris Yeltsin, president of Russia from 1990 to 1999, became in 1991 the first popularly elected leader in Russian history and guided his country through a decade of political and economic transition.
</Question>
<Choice>1 February</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
James Joyce - Irish novelist James Joyce, born this day in 1882, was noted for his experimental use of language and his exploration of new literary methods in such large works of fiction as Ulysses (1922) and Finnegans Wake (1939).
</Question>
<Choice>2 February</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Felix Mendelssohn - One of the most celebrated figures of the early Romantic period, German composer Felix Mendelssohn, born this day in 1809, largely observed Classical models and practices while initiating key aspects of Romanticism.
</Question>
<Choice>3 February</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Betty Friedan - Born this day in 1921 was American feminist Betty Friedan, cofounder of the National Organization for Women and author of The Feminine Mystique (1963), which studied the frustrations of modern women in traditional roles.
</Question>
<Choice>4 February</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Andreas Papandreou - Andreas Papandreou, born this day in 1919, formed the Panhellenic Socialist Movement party shortly after the collapse of the Greek military dictatorship in 1974 and served as prime minister of Greece in 1981–89 and 1993–96.
</Question>
<Choice>5 February</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ronald Reagan - Born this day in 1911, Ronald Reagan, the 40th U.S. president (1981–89), was known for his fervent anticommunism, staunch conservatism, and appealing personal style that earned him the nickname the “Great Communicator.”
</Question>
<Choice>6 February</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Charles Dickens - Born in England this day in 1812, Charles Dickens, whose works include A Christmas Carol, David Copperfield, A Tale of Two Cities, and Great Expectations, is generally considered the greatest Victorian-era novelist.
</Question>
<Choice>7 February</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Il Guercino - Italian painter Il Guercino (“The Squinting One”), whose frescoes freshly exploited the illusionistic ceiling and made a profound impact on the evolution of 17th-century Roman High Baroque art, was born this day in 1591.
</Question>
<Choice>8 February</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Alice Walker - The works of American writer Alice Walker, born this day in 1944 and perhaps best known for the Pulitzer Prize-winning The Color Purple (1982), are noted for their insightful treatment of African American culture.
</Question>
<Choice>9 February</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mark Spitz - American swimmer Mark Spitz, born this day in 1950, became the first athlete to capture seven gold medals in a single Olympics, winning four individual and three team events at the 1972 Games in Munich, West Germany.
</Question>
<Choice>10 February</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
René Descartes - Often called the father of modern philosophy, French scientist, mathematician, and philosopher René Descartes, who erected new epistemic foundations with the dictum “I think, therefore I am,” died this day in 1650.
</Question>
<Choice>11 February</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Abraham Lincoln - Born this day in 1809, Abraham Lincoln, the 16th U.S. president (1861–65), preserved the Union during the American Civil War, brought about the emancipation of slaves, and was an eloquent spokesman for democracy.
</Question>
<Choice>12 February</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Grant Wood - Painter Grant Wood, born this day in 1892 in Iowa, was a major exponent of Midwestern Regionalism, and his American Gothic, a portrait of sober, hardworking rural Midwesterners, is one of the most iconic American artworks.
</Question>
<Choice>13 February</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Gregory Hines - American dancer, choreographer, and actor Gregory Hines, a major figure in the revitalization of tap dancing in the late 20th century who won a Tony Award for his portrayal of Jelly Roll Morton, was born this day in 1946.
</Question>
<Choice>14 February</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Galileo - Italian natural philosopher, astronomer, and mathematician Galileo, born this day in 1564, made fundamental contributions to the sciences of motion and astronomy, as well as to the development of the scientific method.
</Question>
<Choice>15 February</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Kim Jong Il - Kim Jong Il, son of North Korean communist dictator Kim Il-sung and his successor as head of the Korean Workers' Party and ruler of North Korea, was born in Siberia in the Soviet Union this day in 1941.
</Question>
<Choice>16 February</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Michael Jordan - Considered by many the greatest all-around player in the history of basketball, American Michael (“Air”) Jordan, who was born this day in 1963, led the Chicago Bulls to six NBA championships (1991–93, 1996–98).
</Question>
<Choice>17 February</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Toni Morrison - American writer Toni Morrison, noted for her examination of black (particularly black female) experience within the black community and recipient of the Nobel Prize for Literature in 1993, was born this day in 1931.
</Question>
<Choice>18 February</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nicolaus Copernicus - Polish astronomer Nicolaus Copernicus, born this day in 1473, reintroduced the heliocentric system, proposing that the Earth, like the other planets, revolves around the Sun and that it turns once daily on its axis.
</Question>
<Choice>19 February</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Honoré Daumier - French artist Honoré Daumier, born this day or February 26 in 1808, was renowned for his cartoons and drawings satirizing French society, and his paintings helped introduce Impressionist techniques into modern art.
</Question>
<Choice>20 February</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Robert Mugabe - Robert Mugabe, born this day in 1924, was the first prime minister (1980–87) of Zimbabwe (formerly Rhodesia), its president from 1987, and a black nationalist of Marxist persuasion who established one-party rule.
</Question>
<Choice>21 February</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
George Washington - Called the “Father of His Country,” George Washington, general and commander in chief of the colonial armies in the American Revolution (1775–83) and first president of the United States (1789–97), was born this day in 1732.
</Question>
<Choice>22 February</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
W.E.B. Du Bois - Born this day in 1868, W.E.B. Du Bois was the most important African American protest leader during the first half of the 20th century, helping to create the NAACP in 1909 and editing The Crisis, its magazine, for 24 years.
</Question>
<Choice>23 February</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Charles V - Born this day in 1500, Charles V, who reigned as Holy Roman emperor, king of Spain, and archduke of Austria, long struggled to preserve a Spanish and Habsburg empire that reached across Europe to Spanish America.
</Question>
<Choice>24 February</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pierre-Auguste Renoir - French painter Pierre-Auguste Renoir, born this day in 1841, was initially associated with Impressionism, but in the 1880s his early works of sparkling colour and light gave way to a more disciplined, formal technique.
</Question>
<Choice>25 February</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Johnny Cash - Born this day in 1932, singer-songwriter Johnny Cash, known to his fans as the “Man in Black” and a member of the Country Music and Rock and Roll halls of fame, broadened the scope of American country and western music.
</Question>
<Choice>26 February</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Constantine I - Thought to have been born this day after AD 280, Constantine I, the first Roman emperor to profess Christianity, sparked the empire's evolution into a Christian state and catalyzed a distinctively Christian culture.
</Question>
<Choice>27 February</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Frank O. Gehry - American architect and designer Frank O. Gehry—renowned worldwide for his original, sculptural, and often audacious work, including the curvaceous Guggenheim Museum in Bilbao, Spain—was born in Toronto this day in 1929.
</Question>
<Choice>28 February</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Balthus - In the midst of 20th-century avant-gardism, French painter Balthus, born this day in 1908, hewed to the figurative and, inspired by painters such as Nicolas Poussin, painted still lifes, landscapes, and portraits.
</Question>
<Choice>29 February</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Frédéric Chopin - Frédéric Chopin, born this day in 1810, was a Polish French composer and pianist of the Romantic period who ranks as one of music's greatest tone poets by reason of his imagination and fastidious craftsmanship.
</Question>
<Choice>1 March</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mikhail Gorbachev - Born this day in 1931, Mikhail Gorbachev, the general secretary of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union (1985–91) and president of the Soviet Union (1990–91), instituted reforms that led to the end of the Cold War.
</Question>
<Choice>2 March</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Alexander Graham Bell - Alexander Graham Bell, born in Edinburgh this day in 1847, was an audiologist who in his career was granted 18 individual patents and 12 with collaborators but was best known as the inventor of the telephone (1876).
</Question>
<Choice>3 March</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Miriam Makeba - South African singer Miriam Makeba, one of the world's most prominent black African performers of the 20th century, was born near Johannesburg this day in 1932 and introduced Xhosa and Zulu songs to Western audiences.
</Question>
<Choice>4 March</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Soong Mei-ling - Soong Mei-ling, born this day in 1897, was the wife of Chinese President Chiang Kai-shek, launched the anticommunist New Life Movement, and led the effort to secure Chiang's release after his abduction in the Sian Incident.
</Question>
<Choice>5 March</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Michelangelo - Born this day in 1475 was Italian Renaissance artist Michelangelo, who exerted an unparalleled influence on Western sculpture, painting, and architecture and whose works rank among the most famous in existence.
</Question>
<Choice>6 March</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Viv Richards - West Indian cricketer Viv Richards, born this day in 1952 and nicknamed “Master Blaster,” was arguably the finest batsman of his generation, scoring 8,540 runs and averaging more than 50 runs per innings in Test competition.
</Question>
<Choice>7 March</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Oliver Wendell Holmes, Jr. - Oliver Wendell Holmes, Jr., born this day in 1841, was a U.S. Supreme Court justice and legal historian who advocated judicial restraint, arguing that speech could be limited only if it was a “clear and present danger.”
</Question>
<Choice>8 March</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Francisco Bayeu - Francisco Bayeu, considered by his contemporaries to be the finest Spanish painter of their period and who was greatly influenced by Anton Raphael Mengs and Giovanni Battista Tiepolo, was born this day in 1734.
</Question>
<Choice>9 March</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Kim Campbell - Progressive Conservative Kim Campbell, who became Canada's first woman prime minister and its first leader from the West Coast when she succeeded Brian Mulroney in 1993, was born this day in 1947 in British Columbia.
</Question>
<Choice>10 March</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Harold Wilson - Harold Wilson, born this day in 1916 and a cabinet minister by age 31, led the Labour Party to victory in four of five general elections and was prime minister of the United Kingdom from 1964 to 1970 and from 1974 to 1976.
</Question>
<Choice>11 March</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
André Le Nôtre - André Le Nôtre, one of the greatest French landscape architects, whose masterpiece is the gardens of Versailles and whose genius was in demand throughout the capitals of Europe, was born in Paris this day in 1613.
</Question>
<Choice>12 March</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
William Glackens - American artist William Glackens, whose paintings of street scenes and urban life rejected the dictates of 19th-century academic art and introduced a matter-of-fact realism into U.S. art, was born this day in 1870.
</Question>
<Choice>13 March</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Albert Einstein - German American physicist Albert Einstein, born this day in 1879, had one of the most creative intellects in human history, developed groundbreaking theories of relativity, and won the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1921.
</Question>
<Choice>14 March</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Andrew Jackson - Military hero and seventh U.S. president Andrew Jackson, born this day in 1767, was the first president to come from west of the Appalachians and the first to gain office by a direct appeal to the mass of voters.
</Question>
<Choice>15 March</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
James Madison - Born this day in 1751, James Madison, the fourth U.S. president and an architect of the U.S. Constitution and its ratification, collaborated in the publication of the Federalist papers and sponsored the Bill of Rights.
</Question>
<Choice>16 March</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mia Hamm - Two-time FIFA Women's World Player of the Year Mia Hamm, born this day in 1972, was the first global star in women's football (soccer), retiring with 158 goals in international play—the most by any player, male or female.
</Question>
<Choice>17 March</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John Updike - American writer John Updike, whose novels, short stories, and poems are known for their realistic but subtle depiction of “American, Protestant, small-town, middle-class” life, was born this day in 1932.
</Question>
<Choice>18 March</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Willem de Kooning - Dutch American artist Willem de Kooning, a major exponent of Abstract Expressionism and Action painting whose series Woman I–VI caused a stir with its violent images and impulsive technique, died this day in 1997.
</Question>
<Choice>19 March</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sir Isaac Newton - Sir Isaac Newton, whose Principia (1687) was one of the most important single works in the history of modern science and who was the culminating figure of the scientific revolution of the 17th century, died this day in 1727.
</Question>
<Choice>20 March</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hans Hofmann - German painter Hans Hofmann, born this day in 1880, was an influential art teacher and a pioneer in the use of improvisatory techniques whose work paved the way for American painters to develop Abstract Expressionism.
</Question>
<Choice>21 March</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Andrew Lloyd Webber - English composer Andrew Lloyd Webber, whose works such as Evita, Jesus Christ Superstar, and The Phantom of the Opera helped revitalize British and American musical theatre in the late 20th century, was born this day in 1948.
</Question>
<Choice>22 March</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Kurosawa Akira - Born this day in 1910, Japanese director Kurosawa Akira won worldwide acclaim with subtle, brilliantly composed films, such as Rashomon (1950), that combined Japanese historic themes with a Western sense of action and drama.
</Question>
<Choice>23 March</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Harry Houdini - American magician Harry Houdini, born this day in 1874, earned an international reputation for his daring feats of extrication from shackles, ropes, and handcuffs and from locked containers such as coffins and prison cells.
</Question>
<Choice>24 March</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Aretha Franklin - American singer Aretha Franklin, born this day in 1942 and crowned the “Queen of Soul,” defined the golden age of 1960s soul music with hits such as I Never Loved a Man (the Way I Love You), Respect, and Think.
</Question>
<Choice>25 March</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Robert Frost - American poet Robert Frost, much admired for his depictions of New England rural life, his command of American colloquial speech, and his realistic verse portraying ordinary people, was born this day in 1874.
</Question>
<Choice>26 March</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mstislav Rostropovich - Born this day in 1927 in Azerbaijan was Mstislav Rostropovich, one of the best-known cellists of the 20th century and music director of the National Symphony Orchestra in Washington, D.C., from 1977 to 1994.
</Question>
<Choice>27 March</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Fra Bartolomeo - Painter Fra Bartolomeo, a prominent exponent of the High Renaissance style in early 16th-century Florence whose works include God the Father with SS. Catherine of Siena and Mary Magdalene (1509), was born this day in 1472.
</Question>
<Choice>28 March</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sam Walton - Retail magnate Sam Walton, born this day in 1918, became one of the wealthiest individuals in American history, founding Wal-Mart Stores, Inc., and developing it into the largest retail sales chain in the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>29 March</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Vincent van Gogh - Works of one of the greatest Post-Impressionists—Dutch painter Vincent van Gogh, born this day in 1853—convey not only keen observations of nature but the anguish of a mental illness that eventually led to his suicide.
</Question>
<Choice>30 March</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
René Descartes - René Descartes, born this day in 1596 and perhaps best known for the famous phrase “I think, therefore I am,” was a French mathematician, scientist, and philosopher who has often been called the father of modern philosophy.
</Question>
<Choice>31 March</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sergey Rachmaninoff - Sergey Rachmaninoff, who was born this day in 1873, was a great figure in Russian Romanticism and a leading piano virtuoso who is especially known for his piano concerti and his Rhapsody on a Theme of Paganini.
</Question>
<Choice>1 April</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Charlemagne - Born this day c. 742, Charlemagne, Holy Roman emperor and king of the Franks and the Lombards, united in one superstate practically all the Christian lands of western Europe and oversaw a cultural renaissance in his empire.
</Question>
<Choice>2 April</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Fazlur R. Khan - Born this day in 1929 in Dacca, India (now Dhaka, Bangladesh), Bangladeshi American civil engineer Fazlur R. Khan was known for his innovations in high-rise building construction, and among his works is Chicago's Sears Tower.
</Question>
<Choice>3 April</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Marguerite Duras - French writer and film director Marguerite Duras, internationally known for her screenplays for Hiroshima mon amour and India Song and winner of the prestigious Prix Goncourt for her novel L'Amant, was born this day in 1914.
</Question>
<Choice>4 April</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Colin Powell - U.S. general and statesman Colin Powell, born this day in 1937, served as chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff (1989–93) and secretary of state (2001–05), the first African American to hold either position.
</Question>
<Choice>5 April</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Raphael - Born this day in 1483 was Italian master painter and architect Raphael, whose work is admired for clarity of form and ease of composition and who is best known for his Madonnas and large figure compositions in the Vatican.
</Question>
<Choice>6 April</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ravi Shankar - Indian musician Ravi Shankar—a sitar virtuoso and composer who founded the National Orchestra of India and who was influential in stimulating Western appreciation of classical Hindustani music—was born this day in 1920.
</Question>
<Choice>7 April</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Kofi Annan - Ghanaian international civil servant Kofi Annan, the seventh secretary-general of the United Nations (from 1997) and corecipient with the United Nations of the Nobel Peace Prize in 2001, was born this day in 1938.
</Question>
<Choice>8 April</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jørn Utzon - Born this day in 1918, Danish architect Jørn Utzon is best known for his dynamic, imaginative, but problematic design for Australia's most famous building, the Sydney Opera House, a combination of lightness and monumentality.
</Question>
<Choice>9 April</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Max von Sydow - Swedish actor Max von Sydow, perhaps best known for his dour, brooding characterizations in films directed by Ingmar Bergman and whose film career spanned more than half a century, was born this day in 1929.
</Question>
<Choice>10 April</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Charles Evans Hughes - Jurist and statesman Charles Evans Hughes, born this day in 1862, served as an associate justice of the U.S. Supreme Court (1910–16), U.S. secretary of state (1921–25), and 11th chief justice of the United States (1930–41).
</Question>
<Choice>11 April</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Edward de Vere, 17th earl of Oxford - Born this day in 1550, English lyric poet Edward de Vere, 17th earl of Oxford, emerged in the 20th century as the strongest candidate proposed (other than William Shakespeare himself) as the author of Shakespeare's plays.
</Question>
<Choice>12 April</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Thomas Jefferson - Born this day in 1743, Thomas Jefferson was the third U.S. president, the principal author of the Declaration of Independence, an influential political philosopher, and the founder and architect of the University of Virginia.
</Question>
<Choice>13 April</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Julie Christie - British film actress Julie Christie, born in India this day in 1941, was renowned for a wide range of roles in English and American films, as well as for her striking looks and offbeat, free-spirited personality.
</Question>
<Choice>14 April</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Leonardo da Vinci - Italian artist Leonardo da Vinci, whose genius epitomized the Renaissance humanist ideal and whose Last Supper (1495–98) and Mona Lisa (1503–06) are widely influential paintings, was born this day in 1452.
</Question>
<Choice>15 April</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sir Peter Ustinov - English actor, director, playwright, and humanitarian Sir Peter Ustinov, who was born this day in 1921, made more than 70 films in Rome, Hollywood, and London during an acclaimed career that spanned some six decades.
</Question>
<Choice>16 April</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nikita Khrushchev - Soviet Premier Nikita Sergeyevich Khrushchev, born this day in 1894, guided the U.S.S.R. (and the communist movement) out from under the shadow of former premier Joseph Stalin and into closer orbit with the capitalist West.
</Question>
<Choice>17 April</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Albert Einstein - One of the most creative intellects in human history was Albert Einstein, who died in Princeton, New Jersey, this day in 1955 and whose advanced theories of relativity and gravitation revolutionized science and philosophy.
</Question>
<Choice>18 April</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Charles Darwin - English naturalist Charles Darwin, who died this day in 1882, had a revolutionary effect on modern society when he published his theory of evolution by natural selection in his book On the Origin of Species (1859).
</Question>
<Choice>19 April</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Adolf Hitler - Born this day in 1889 in Austria, Adolf Hitler became leader of the Nazi Party in 1920 and chancellor of Germany in 1933, created a formidable war machine, provoked World War II, and orchestrated the Holocaust.
</Question>
<Choice>20 April</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Elizabeth II - Born this day in 1926 was Queen Elizabeth II of the United Kingdom, who ascended the throne in 1952 at age 25 and is known to favour simplicity in court life and to take a serious, informed interest in government business.
</Question>
<Choice>21 April</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Miguel de Cervantes - Spanish author Miguel de Cervantes, who died this day in Madrid in 1616, has long been regarded as the most important figure in Spanish letters, largely for his novel Don Quixote, a classic of Western literature.
</Question>
<Choice>22 April</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
William Shakespeare - William Shakespeare, the poet, dramatist, and actor who is regarded as the national poet of England and is perhaps the most famous dramatist of all time, died this day in 1616 in his native town of Stratford-upon-Avon.
</Question>
<Choice>23 April</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Barbra Streisand - American entertainer Barbra Streisand—one of the most popular singers of her generation, a star of stage and screen (especially in musicals), and one of the most powerful women in show business—was born this day in 1942.
</Question>
<Choice>24 April</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Al Pacino - American actor Al Pacino, known for his intense, sometimes over-the-top acting style and for his gangster portrayals in The Godfather trilogy (1972–90) and Scarface (1983), was born in New York City this day in 1940.
</Question>
<Choice>25 April</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ma Rainey - The first great African American professional blues vocalist, Ma Rainey, was born this day in 1886 in Georgia and contributed greatly to the evolution and popularity of the blues form in the early 20th century.
</Question>
<Choice>26 April</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Coretta Scott King - Born this day in 1927 was Coretta Scott King—civil rights activist, wife of civil rights movement leader Martin Luther King, Jr., and, after her husband's assassination, the founder of a centre for nonviolent social change.
</Question>
<Choice>27 April</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
?addam ?ussein - ?addam ?ussein, who as president of Iraq (1979–2003) angered and outraged the international community with invasions of neighbouring Iran and Kuwait and who was unseated by the United States, was born this day in 1937.
</Question>
<Choice>28 April</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hirohito - Japanese Emperor Hirohito, who was born this day in 1901 in Tokyo, ruled his country from 1926 to 1989, a reign that included both Japan's military defeat in World War II and its postwar economic triumphs.
</Question>
<Choice>29 April</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Édouard Manet - French painter Édouard Manet, who died this day in 1883, broke with the historical tradition of illusionism and paved the way for Impressionism with such works as Déjeuner sur l'herbe (1863; “Luncheon on the Grass”).
</Question>
<Choice>30 April</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Arthur Wellesley, 1st duke of Wellington - Born in Dublin this day in 1769 was British army commander Arthur Wellesley, 1st duke of Wellington, who with his allies defeated Napoleon at the Battle of Waterloo (1815), conquering the world's conqueror.
</Question>
<Choice>1 May</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Catherine II - Catherine II (the Great) of Russia.Bridgeman Art LibraryCatherine the Great, who engineered the abdication of her husband, Peter III, to become empress of Russia (1762–96) and one of the most powerful women in history, was born in Prussia this day i
</Question>
<Choice>2 May</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pete Seeger - American singer, songwriter, and activist Pete Seeger, born this day in 1919, played a pivotal role in sustaining the folk music tradition and was an inspiration for younger performers in the folk revival of the 1960s.
</Question>
<Choice>3 May</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
El Cordobés - El CordobésMichael Kuh/Black StarEl Cordobés (“The Córdovan”), believed to have been born this day in 1936 in Spain, became the highest-paid bullfighter of his day, thrilling crowds with his reflexes and stunts, such as ki
</Question>
<Choice>4 May</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Karl Marx - Revolutionary, historian, and economist Karl Marx, born in Prussia this day in 1818, wrote (with Friedrich Engels) The Communist Manifesto (1848), the most celebrated pamphlet in the history of the socialist movement.
</Question>
<Choice>5 May</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Tony Blair - British Labour Party leader Tony Blair, born this day in 1953, became in 1997 the youngest British prime minister since 1812, and in 2005 he led his party to its third successive general election victory.
</Question>
<Choice>6 May</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pyotr Ilyich Tchaikovsky - Pyotr Ilyich Tchaikovsky—the most popular Russian composer in history, whose impressive harmonies, openhearted melodies, and colourful orchestration provoke profound emotional responses—was born this day in 1840.
</Question>
<Choice>7 May</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Paul Gauguin - French painter Paul Gauguin, who sought to achieve a “primitive” expression of spiritual and emotional states in his work and who was noted for his artistic experimentation, died in the Marquesas Islands this day in 1903.
</Question>
<Choice>8 May</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Howard Carter - British archaeologist Howard Carter, who made one of the richest and most celebrated contributions to Egyptology—the discovery (1922) of the largely intact tomb of King Tutankhamen—was born this day in 1873.
</Question>
<Choice>9 May</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Fred Astaire - Fred Astaire, born this day in 1899, is considered one of the greatest American popular-music dancers and is especially remembered for his partnership with Ginger Rogers in a series of highly successful musical comedy films.
</Question>
<Choice>10 May</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Salvador Dalí - Spanish artist Salvador Dalí, a leading Surrealist painter noted for his depiction of dreamworlds in which commonplace objects are juxtaposed or deformed in a bizarre and irrational fashion, was born this day in 1904.
</Question>
<Choice>11 May</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Katharine Hepburn - Born this day in 1907, American actress Katharine Hepburn brought a spirited individuality and depth of character to her roles that made her one of Hollywood's most dynamic leading ladies and earned her four Academy Awards.
</Question>
<Choice>12 May</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Georges Braque - Born this day in 1882, French painter Georges Braque revolutionized the art world by creating, with Pablo Picasso, Cubism and became in 1961 the first living painter to have his work exhibited in the Louvre Museum.
</Question>
<Choice>13 May</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Margaret of Valois - Born this day in 1553, Margaret of Valois, whose 1572 marriage to the king of Navarre failed to end fighting between Catholics and Protestants, earned fame for her licentiousness and her Mémoires, an exposé of life in France.
</Question>
<Choice>14 May</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Madeleine Albright - Madeleine Albright, born this day in Prague in 1937, earned a reputation as a savvy defender of American interests while a UN ambassador (1993–97) and was the first woman to serve as U.S. secretary of state (1997–2001).
</Question>
<Choice>15 May</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Olga Korbut - Soviet gymnast Olga Korbut, born this day in Belorussia (now Belarus) in 1955, earned three gold medals at the 1972 Olympics in Munich, West Germany, where she captivated audiences with her charm, youth, and diminutive size.
</Question>
<Choice>16 May</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ruhollah Khomeini - Shi?ite cleric Ruhollah Khomeini—born this day in 1900, it is believed—led the 1979 revolution that overthrew Mohammad Reza Shah Pahlavi and for the next 10 years served as Iran's ultimate political and religious authority.
</Question>
<Choice>17 May</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John Paul II - Born this day in Poland in 1920, Pope John Paul II traveled widely during his pontificate (1978–2005), campaigning for human rights and world peace, and played a key role in the dissolution of the Soviet Union (1991).
</Question>
<Choice>18 May</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Malcolm X - Black militant Malcolm X, born this day in 1925, promoted black pride and, later, racial unity, ideas articulated in his celebrated The Autobiography of Malcolm X, which was published shortly after his assassination in 1965.
</Question>
<Choice>19 May</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Honoré de Balzac - French author Honoré de Balzac—considered one of the greatest fiction writers and best known for a collection of novels and short stories collectively called La Comédie humaine (The Human Comedy)—was born this day in 1799.
</Question>
<Choice>20 May</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Malcolm Fraser - Malcolm Fraser of the Liberal Party, born this day in 1930, served as prime minister of Australia from 1975 to 1983, during which time he successfully reduced inflation and foreign debt but struggled to curb unemployment.
</Question>
<Choice>21 May</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sir Arthur Conan Doyle - Scottish writer Sir Arthur Conan Doyle, born this day in 1859, created Sherlock Holmes, one of the most vivid and enduring characters in English fiction and a prototype for the modern mastermind detective.
</Question>
<Choice>22 May</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Captain Kidd - Captain Kidd, a British privateer and semilegendary pirate celebrated in literature as one of the most colourful outlaws of all time, was hanged in London this day in 1701 after being found guilty of murder and piracy.
</Question>
<Choice>23 May</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Queen Victoria - Born this day in 1819, Victoria, queen of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland (1837–1901) and empress of India (1876–1901), gave her name to an era that was marked by British expansion and economic prosperity.
</Question>
<Choice>24 May</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sir Ian McKellen - Sir Ian McKellen, a British actor of great versatility who earned acclaim for his work with the Royal Shakespeare Company and for such films as The Lord of the Rings trilogy (2001, 2002, 2003), was born this day in 1939.
</Question>
<Choice>25 May</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sally Ride - In June 1983 astronaut Sally Ride, born this day in 1951, became the first American woman to travel into outer space, 20 years after Valentina Tereshkova of Russia had made history as the first woman to do so.
</Question>
<Choice>26 May</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hubert Humphrey - Born this day in 1911, Hubert Humphrey was the 38th U.S. vice president (1965–69), a presidential candidate (1968), and a liberal Senate leader (1949–65; 1971–78) whose political base was a Democrat-Farmer-Labor coalition.
</Question>
<Choice>27 May</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ian Fleming - British suspense-fiction novelist Ian Fleming, born this day in 1908, created one of the most successful and widely imitated heroes of popular fiction: James Bond, the stylish, high-living British secret service agent 007.
</Question>
<Choice>28 May</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John F. Kennedy - Born this day in 1917, John F. Kennedy, the 35th U.S. president, faced several foreign crises, most notably in Cuba and Berlin, and secured such achievements as the Nuclear Test-Ban Treaty before being assassinated in 1963.
</Question>
<Choice>29 May</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Countee Cullen - Born this day in 1903, Countee Cullen was one of the finest American poets of the Harlem Renaissance, noted for his fresh and sensitive treatment of racial themes and for the lyric, wistful beauty of his verse.
</Question>
<Choice>30 May</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Clint Eastwood - American film actor Clint Eastwood, born this day in 1930, emerged as one of the most popular Hollywood stars in the 1970s, playing such laconic and dangerous heroes as Dirty Harry, and later became an Oscar-winning director.
</Question>
<Choice>31 May</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Morgan Freeman - Morgan Freeman, whose emotional depth and versatility made him one of the most respected performers of his generation and the winner of an Academy Award for his role in Million Dollar Baby (2004), was born this day in 1937.
</Question>
<Choice>1 June</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Johnny Weissmuller - American swimmer Johnny Weissmuller, who won five Olympic gold medals and set 67 world records and who was even more famous as a motion-picture actor, most notably in the role of Tarzan, was born in Romania this day in 1904.
</Question>
<Choice>2 June</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Josephine Baker - Entertainer Josephine Baker, born in Missouri this day in 1906, became one of France's most popular performers, took French citizenship, worked with the Resistance in World War II, and received the Legion of Honour.
</Question>
<Choice>3 June</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
George III - Born this day in 1738 was George III, during whose 60-year reign Britain won an empire in the Seven Years' War, lost its American colonies, and then, after a struggle against France, emerged as a leading power in Europe.
</Question>
<Choice>4 June</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Federico García Lorca - Born this day in 1898 was Spanish writer Federico García Lorca, who in a brief career resurrected and revitalized the most basic strains of Spanish poetry and helped inaugurate a second Golden Age of the Spanish theatre.
</Question>
<Choice>5 June</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Diego Velázquez - Diego Velázquez, baptized this day in 1599 and trained in a naturalistic style, had remarkable power of observation in portraying both the living model and still life and was the leading Spanish painter of the 17th century.
</Question>
<Choice>6 June</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John Napier Turner - John Napier Turner, born this day in 1929, succeeded Pierre Trudeau in June 1984 as head of the Liberal Party and prime minister of Canada, though he was swept from office by the Progressive Conservatives in September 1984.
</Question>
<Choice>7 June</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Frank Lloyd Wright - Born this day in 1867 was architect Frank Lloyd Wright, whose Prairie style became the basis of 20th-century residential design in the U.S. and who was known as the most abundantly creative genius of American architecture.
</Question>
<Choice>8 June</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Peter I (the Great) - Born this day in 1672 was Russian Tsar Peter the Great—for whom the city of St. Petersburg is named—who reigned jointly or alone from 1682 to 1725 and was one of his country's greatest statesmen, organizers, and reformers.
</Question>
<Choice>9 June</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Judy Garland - Born this day in 1922 was American motion-picture singer and actress Judy Garland, who is best known for her role as Dorothy Gale in The Wizard of Oz (1939), for which she was honoured with a special Academy Award.
</Question>
<Choice>10 June</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jacques Cousteau - Born this day in 1910 was French naval officer and ocean explorer Jacques Cousteau, who conducted extensive undersea investigations, invented the Aqua-Lung, and wrote, produced, and appeared in films about the ocean.
</Question>
<Choice>11 June</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Anne Frank - Anne Frank—a young Jewish girl whose diary of her family's two years in hiding during the German occupation of The Netherlands became a classic of war literature—was born this day in 1929 in Frankfurt am Main, Germany.
</Question>
<Choice>12 June</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Christo - Environmental sculptor Christo, born this day in 1935 in Bulgaria, is noted for his controversial outdoor sculptures and displays, which have included the wrapping of Berlin's Reichstag in metallic silver fabric in 1995.
</Question>
<Choice>13 June</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Steffi Graf - Born this day in 1969 was German tennis star Steffi Graf, who dominated women's tennis in the late 1980s and '90s, winning singles titles at each grand slam event multiple times—including seven at Wimbledon.
</Question>
<Choice>14 June</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Edvard Grieg - Composer Edvard Grieg, a founder of the Norwegian nationalist school of music whose work is rooted in the country's national folk tradition and is noted for its refined lyrical sense, was born this day in 1843.
</Question>
<Choice>15 June</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Joyce Carol Oates - Joyce Carol Oates, noted for her vast literary output in a variety of styles and genres and for her particularly effective depictions of violence and evil in modern society, was born this day in 1938.
</Question>
<Choice>16 June</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Igor Stravinsky - Composer Igor Stravinsky, whose work had a revolutionary impact on the musical world just before and after World War I and whose compositions remain a touchstone of modernism, was born in Russia this day in 1882.
</Question>
<Choice>17 June</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sir Paul McCartney - British rock star Sir Paul McCartney, born this day in Liverpool, England, in 1942, was a principal member of the Beatles, the leading rock band of the 1960s, and was knighted by Queen Elizabeth II in 1997.
</Question>
<Choice>18 June</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Aung San Suu Kyi - Myanmar democratic and human rights activist Aung San Suu Kyi, the daughter of Aung San (a martyred national hero) and Khin Kyi (a prominent diplomat), was born this day in 1945 and was awarded the Nobel Peace Prize in 1991.
</Question>
<Choice>19 June</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Howlin' Wolf - American blues singer and composer Howlin' Wolf, one of the principal exponents of the urban blues style of Chicago and noted for his brooding lyrics and his earthy, aggressive stage presence, was born this day in 1910.
</Question>
<Choice>20 June</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Benazir Bhutto - Pakistani politician Benazir Bhutto, born this day in 1953, was the daughter of former president and prime minister Zulfikar Ali Bhutto and became in 1988 the first woman leader of a Muslim country in modern history.
</Question>
<Choice>21 June</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Meryl Streep - American film actress Meryl Streep, known for her masterly technique, expertise with dialects, subtly expressive face, and record-setting 13th Academy Award nomination in 2003, was born this day in 1949.
</Question>
<Choice>22 June</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Clarence Thomas - Born this day in 1948 was Clarence Thomas, associate justice of the U.S. Supreme Court from 1991, whose appointment to replace Thurgood Marshall (the court's first African American justice) gave the court a conservative cast.
</Question>
<Choice>23 June</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jack Dempsey - Born this day in 1895 was American heavyweight boxing champion Jack Dempsey, who held the world title from 1919, when he knocked out Jess Willard, until 1926, when he lost a 10-round decision to Gene Tunney.
</Question>
<Choice>24 June</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Antoni Gaudí - Born this day in 1852, Catalan architect Antoni Gaudí, whose distinctive style was typified by freedom of form and voluptuous colour and texture, spent much of his career building Barcelona's church of the Holy Family.
</Question>
<Choice>25 June</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Peter Lorre - American motion-picture actor Peter Lorre, who first achieved international fame as the psychotic child murderer in the German classic film M (1931; directed by Fritz Lang), was born in Rózsahegy, Hungary, this day in 1904.
</Question>
<Choice>26 June</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jack Lemmon - Adept at both comedy and drama in a career that spanned more than 50 years, American actor Jack Lemmon, who died this day in 2001, won two Academy Awards, including best actor for his performance in Save the Tiger (1973).
</Question>
<Choice>27 June</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Peter Paul Rubens - Flemish painter Peter Paul Rubens, the greatest exponent of Baroque painting's dynamism, vitality, and sensuous exuberance and perhaps best known for his religious and mythological compositions, was born this day in 1577.
</Question>
<Choice>28 June</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chandrika Bandaranaike Kumaratunga - Born this day in 1945 was Chandrika Bandaranaike Kumaratunga, a member of a prominent Sri Lankan political family who became prime minister and then president in 1994—the first woman to serve as the country's president.
</Question>
<Choice>29 June</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Lena Horne - Lena Horne, an American actress and civil rights activist who first came to fame in the 1940s and starred in such films as Cabin in the Sky (1942) and Stormy Weather (1943), was born in Brooklyn, New York, this day in 1917.
</Question>
<Choice>30 June</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Diana, princess of Wales - Born this day in 1961, Princess Diana—consort (1981–96) of Prince Charles and mother of Princes William and Harry—was widely admired for her charity work and style, and her 1997 death caused a massive outpouring of grief.
</Question>
<Choice>1 July</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Wislawa Szymborska - Polish poet Wislawa Szymborska, born this day in 1923, rejected Socialist Realism to pen intelligent and empathetic verse that explored philosophical and moral issues, for which she won the 1996 Nobel Prize for Literature.
</Question>
<Choice>2 July</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Leoš Janácek - Czech composer Leoš Janácek, born this day in 1854, was a leading exponent of musical nationalism during the 20th century, and he developed a style that was intimately connected with the inflections of the Czech language.
</Question>
<Choice>3 July</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Vivekananda - Hindu spiritual leader and reformer Vivekananda—who attempted to combine Indian spirituality with Western material progress, maintaining that they supplemented and complemented one another—died this day in Calcutta in 1902.
</Question>
<Choice>4 July</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Cecil Rhodes - Cecil Rhodes, born this day in 1853, was a financier and statesman of British South Africa who served as prime minister of Cape Colony, organized the diamond company De Beers, and created the Rhodes scholarships at Oxford.
</Question>
<Choice>5 July</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John Paul Jones - John Paul Jones, born this day in 1747 in Scotland, was a naval hero in the American Revolution, renowned for his victory over British battleships off the eastern coast of England on September 23, 1779.
</Question>
<Choice>6 July</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Marc Chagall - Born this day in 1887, French artist Marc Chagall created images based on emotional and poetic associations, and his early works, which predated Surrealism, were among the first expressions of psychic reality in modern art.
</Question>
<Choice>7 July</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Kim Il-sung - Kim Il-sung, the communist leader of North Korea (1948–94) whose invasion of South Korea in 1950 launched the Korean War, died on this day in 1994 in P'yongyang and was succeeded by his son Kim Jong Il.
</Question>
<Choice>8 July</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
O.J. Simpson - Born this day in 1947, O.J. Simpson was an outstanding running back—winning the 1968 Heisman Trophy and setting an NFL single-season record for rushing yards (2,003)—but became perhaps best known for his 1995 murder trial.
</Question>
<Choice>9 July</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John Calvin - French Protestant Reformer John Calvin, who advanced a theology—articulated in his Institutes of the Christian Religion (1536)—that became the foundation for the Reformed church and Presbyterianism, was born this day in 1509.
</Question>
<Choice>10 July</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Gough Whitlam - Born this day in 1916, Australian Labor leader Gough Whitlam was dismissed as prime minister in 1975 after refusing to call new elections to end a parliamentary deadlock brought on by falling support for his administration.
</Question>
<Choice>11 July</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Desiderius Erasmus - Dutch humanist Desiderius Erasmus, the leading scholar of the northern Renaissance who was known for his work involving the Greek New Testament and the Church Fathers, died this day in 1536 in Basel, Switzerland.
</Question>
<Choice>12 July</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Wole Soyinka - Nigerian playwright, poet, and novelist Wole Soyinka, born this day in 1934, wrote of modern West Africa in a satiric style and with a tragic sense of the obstacles of progress, winning the 1986 Nobel Prize for Literature.
</Question>
<Choice>13 July</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Woody Guthrie - American singer and composer Woody Guthrie, born this day in 1912, wrote politically charged songs of common people and their struggles, especially during the Depression, and his classics include This Land Is Your Land.
</Question>
<Choice>14 July</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Rembrandt van Rijn - Born this day in 1606 was Dutch painter and printmaker Rembrandt—one of the greatest storytellers in the history of art, known for his exceptional ability to render people in their various moods and dramatic guises.
</Question>
<Choice>15 July</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ginger Rogers - American dancer and actress Ginger Rogers, born this day in 1911, achieved fame as the partner of Fred Astaire in a series of popular musicals and later won an Oscar for her dramatic performance in Kitty Foyle (1940).
</Question>
<Choice>16 July</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Adam Smith - Scottish social philosopher and political economist Adam Smith—best known for his seminal work The Wealth of Nations (1776), the first comprehensive systematization of political economy—died this day in 1790 in Edinburgh.
</Question>
<Choice>17 July</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nelson Mandela - South African black nationalist and statesman Nelson Mandela, whose long imprisonment (1962–90) and ascension to the presidency (1994–99) symbolized the aspirations of his country's black majority, was born this day in 1918.
</Question>
<Choice>18 July</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Edgar Degas - Edgar Degas—a French painter and sculptor who was prominent in the Impressionist group and widely celebrated for his images of the female figure, especially ballet dancers and bathers—was born this day in 1834.
</Question>
<Choice>19 July</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sir Edmund Hillary - Explorer Sir Edmund Hillary—who in 1953, along with Tenzing Norgay, was the first to reach the summit of Mount Everest, the highest mountain in the world—was born this day in 1919 in Auckland, New Zealand.
</Question>
<Choice>20 July</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ernest Hemingway - American writer Ernest Hemingway—famous for his adventurous life and lucid, masculine prose, for which he earned the 1954 Nobel Prize for Literature—was born this day in 1899 in what is now Oak Park, Illinois.
</Question>
<Choice>21 July</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Friedrich Wilhelm Bessel - Born this day in 1784, German astronomer Friedrich Wilhelm Bessel made the first measurement of the distance of a star other than the Sun, and his work allowed the first accurate determination of interstellar distances.
</Question>
<Choice>22 July</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Haile Selassie - Haile Selassie, born this day in 1892 and regarded by many Rastas as the messiah, was the emperor of Ethiopia (1930–74) who sought to modernize the country and who steered it into the mainstream of African politics.
</Question>
<Choice>23 July</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Julie Krone - Born this day in 1963, American jockey Julie Krone was the first woman to win a U.S. Triple Crown race, capturing the Belmont Stakes in 1993, and in 2003 she became the first woman to win a Breeders' Cup race.
</Question>
<Choice>24 July</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Thomas Eakins - Thomas Eakins—who carried the tradition of 19th-century American realism to perhaps its highest achievement, exemplified by such works as The Gross Clinic (1875) and Between Rounds (1898–99)—was born this day in 1844.
</Question>
<Choice>25 July</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John Howard - Liberal leader John Howard, born this day in 1939, became prime minister of Australia in 1996, and his policies, including his strict immigration stance, proved popular with voters, who elected him to a fourth term in 2004.
</Question>
<Choice>26 July</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Charlotte Corday - Charlotte Corday—a young Girondin conservative who assassinated the French revolutionary Jean-Paul Marat in 1793 while he was bathing and who was subsequently tried, convicted, and guillotined—was born this day in 1768.
</Question>
<Choice>27 July</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis - Born this day in 1929 was Jacqueline Kennedy Onassis, who redefined the role of U.S. first lady with her elegance, charm, and especially her composure after the 1963 assassination of her husband, President John F. Kennedy.
</Question>
<Choice>28 July</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Benito Mussolini - Born this day in 1883, Benito Mussolini was the first of 20th-century Europe's fascist dictators, assuming absolute power of Italy in 1922, and his harsh rule and involvement in World War II led to his death in 1945.
</Question>
<Choice>29 July</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Henry Moore - Henry Moore, born this day in 1898, was an English sculptor whose organically shaped, abstract figures in bronze and stone constitute the major 20th-century manifestation of the humanist tradition in sculpture.
</Question>
<Choice>30 July</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Milton Friedman - American economist and educator Milton Friedman, who was one of the leading proponents of monetarism in the second half of the 20th century and who was awarded the 1976 Nobel Prize for Economics, was born this day in 1912.
</Question>
<Choice>31 July</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Maria Mitchell - Born this day in 1818, Maria Mitchell was the first professional woman astronomer in the United States, noted for her discovery that sunspots are whirling vertical cavities and not, as previously thought, clouds.
</Question>
<Choice>1 August</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Peter O'Toole - Irish actor Peter O'Toole, born this day in 1932, began his career on the stage but rose to fame with his successful motion-picture portrayal of T.E. Lawrence in David Lean's epic Lawrence of Arabia (1962).
</Question>
<Choice>2 August</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Stanley Baldwin, 1st Earl Baldwin of Bewdley - Born this day in 1867, Conservative politician Stanley Baldwin served as British prime minister (1923–24, 1924–29, 1935–37) during the General Strike of 1926, the Ethiopian crisis of 1935, and the abdication crisis of 1936.
</Question>
<Choice>3 August</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Barack Obama, Jr. - Born this day in 1961 was Illinois Democrat Barack Obama, Jr., a lawyer and politician who in 2004 defeated Republican Alan Keyes in the first U.S. Senate race in which the two main candidates were African Americans.
</Question>
<Choice>4 August</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Marilyn Monroe - American actress Marilyn Monroe—who achieved stardom as a sex symbol in such films as Gentlemen Prefer Blondes (1953) and later became a cultural icon—died on this day in 1962 after taking an overdose of sleeping pills.
</Question>
<Choice>5 August</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Diego Velázquez - Diego Velázquez—the most important Spanish painter of the 1600s, whose brilliant diversity of brushstrokes and subtle harmonies of colour made him a forerunner of 19th-century French Impressionism—died this day in 1660.
</Question>
<Choice>6 August</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Emil Nolde - Born this day in 1867, Emil Nolde was a leading German Expressionist painter, printmaker, and watercolourist whose art—notably violent religious works and foreboding landscapes—was later called “decadent” by the Nazis.
</Question>
<Choice>7 August</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Emiliano Zapata - Born this day in 1879, Emiliano Zapata was a Mexican revolutionary and champion of land reform who fought in guerrilla actions during the Mexican Revolution (1910–20) and was killed while occupying Mexico City.
</Question>
<Choice>8 August</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Amedeo Avogadro - Born this day in 1776, Amedeo Avogadro of Italy showed that, under controlled conditions of temperature and pressure, equal volumes of gases contain an equal number of molecules—what became known as Avogadro's law.
</Question>
<Choice>9 August</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Joaquín Sorolla y Bastida - Joaquín Sorolla y Bastida—a Spanish painter whose style was a variant of Impressionism and whose best works, painted in the open air, vividly portray the sunny seacoast of Valencia—died this day in 1923.
</Question>
<Choice>10 August</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pervez Musharraf - Born this day in 1943, General Pervez Musharraf assumed power in Pakistan following a 1999 coup, formed a military government, and later struggled to deal with rising Islamist extremism within the country.
</Question>
<Choice>11 August</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
William Blake - English poet and painter William Blake, who died this day in 1827, created a hand-illustrated series of lyric and epic poems that form one of the most strikingly original bodies of work in the Western cultural tradition.
</Question>
<Choice>12 August</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sir Alfred Hitchcock - Film director Sir Alfred Hitchcock—a master of suspense who used innovative techniques and a sound grasp of human psychology to create such immensely popular movies as Psycho (1960)—was born in London this day in 1899.
</Question>
<Choice>13 August</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Halle Berry - Born this day in 1966, Halle Berry in 2002 became the first African American to win the Academy Award for best actress, earning the honour for her nuanced portrayal of Leticia Musgrove in Monster's Ball (2001).
</Question>
<Choice>14 August</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
T.E. Lawrence - Born this day in 1888 was T.E. Lawrence, also called Lawrence of Arabia, best known for his legendary activities in the Middle East during World War I, which he recounted in The Seven Pillars of Wisdom (1926).
</Question>
<Choice>15 August</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Madonna - Born this day in 1958, American performer Madonna first rose to fame in the 1980s with catchy pop songs and provocative music videos and later achieved levels of power and control unprecedented for a woman in entertainment.
</Question>
<Choice>16 August</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sir V.S. Naipaul - Trinidadian writer Sir V.S. Naipaul, who was born this day in 1932, became known for his pessimistic novels set in Third World countries—such as A Bend in the River (1979)—and won the 2001 Nobel Prize for Literature.
</Question>
<Choice>17 August</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Virginia Dare - On this day in 1587, Virginia Dare was born on Roanoke Island, Virginia—the site of the first attempted English settlement in North America—becoming the first child born of English parents in the New World.
</Question>
<Choice>18 August</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Bill Clinton - Bill Clinton—who, as the 42nd president of the United States (1993–2001), oversaw the country's longest peacetime economic expansion but became, in 1998, only the second president to be impeached—was born this day in 1946.
</Question>
<Choice>19 August</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Eero Saarinen - Born this day in 1910 in Finland, Eero Saarinen, the son of noted architect Eliel Saarinen, was one of the leaders in a trend toward exploration and experiment in American architectural design in the 1950s.
</Question>
<Choice>20 August</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Count Basie - American jazz musician Count Basie, who was born this day in 1904, was noted for his spare, economical piano style and is regarded as one of the most important and influential bandleaders in the history of jazz.
</Question>
<Choice>21 August</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Henri Cartier-Bresson - Born this day in 1908 in France, Henri Cartier-Bresson helped establish photojournalism as an art form, snapping spontaneous though impeccably composed and timed images that captured what he called the “decisive moment.”
</Question>
<Choice>22 August</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Baron Georges Cuvier - French zoologist Baron Georges Cuvier—whose work, which included classifying animals based on their internal structure and not their outward appearance, laid the foundation of comparative anatomy—was born this day in 1769.
</Question>
<Choice>23 August</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Yasir ?Arafat - Palestinian leader Yasir ?Arafat, believed to have been born this day in Cairo in 1929, was president of the Palestinian Authority (1996–2004), chairman of the PLO (1969–2004), and cowinner of the 1994 Nobel Prize for Peace.
</Question>
<Choice>24 August</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sir Sean Connery - Born this day in 1930 in Scotland, actor Sir Sean Connery achieved international stardom portraying the suave secret agent James Bond and later earned an Oscar for his performance in The Untouchables (1987).
</Question>
<Choice>25 August</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Antoine-Laurent Lavoisier - Born this day in 1743, Antoine-Laurent Lavoisier was a prominent French chemist and leading figure in the 18th-century chemical revolution who developed an experimentally based theory of the chemical reactivity of oxygen.
</Question>
<Choice>26 August</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mother Teresa - Baptized in Macedonia this day in 1910, Mother Teresa founded the Order of the Missionaries of Charity, a Roman Catholic congregation of women dedicated to helping the poor, and later received the 1979 Nobel Prize for Peace.
</Question>
<Choice>27 August</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Paul Martin - Liberal politician Paul Martin—who, as prime minister of Canada (2003–06), fostered economic growth and introduced progressive social policies but lost power amid a financial scandal in his party—was born this day in 1938.
</Question>
<Choice>28 August</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Michael Jackson - Born this day in 1958, American entertainer Michael Jackson became a worldwide superstar with his music videos and best-selling albums, especially Thriller (1982), but later earned more attention for his eccentric lifestyle.
</Question>
<Choice>29 August</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mary Wollstonecraft Shelley - Mary Wollstonecraft Shelley, born this day in 1797, was the English Romantic novelist best known as the author of Frankenstein (1818), which recounts the consequences that arise after a scientist builds a human being.
</Question>
<Choice>30 August</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Diana, princess of Wales - On this day in 1997, Princess Diana died in Paris following an automobile accident—first thought to be caused by paparazzi but later blamed on the driver—that also claimed the lives of her companion Dodi Fayed and the driver.
</Question>
<Choice>31 August</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Joaquín Balaguer - Joaquín Balaguer (right), the outgoing president of the Dominican Republic, congratulating …John Riley—AP/Wide World PhotosLawyer, writer, and diplomat Joaquín Balaguer, born in the Dominican Republic this day in 1907, served a
</Question>
<Choice>1 September</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jimmy Connors - American tennis star Jimmy Connors, born this day in 1952, captured the U.S. Open title five times and in 1974 won three grand slam events (U.S., Australian, and Wimbledon) but was barred from competing in the French Open.
</Question>
<Choice>2 September</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Louis Sullivan - Born this day in 1856, architect Louis Sullivan—identified with early skyscraper design and considered the spiritual father of modern American architecture—remade the image of the architect as a creative personality.
</Question>
<Choice>3 September</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
François-Auguste-René, viscount de Chateaubriand - French author and diplomat François-Auguste-René, viscount de Chateaubriand, born this day in 1768, was one of the country's first Romantic writers and France's preeminent literary figure in the early 19th century.
</Question>
<Choice>4 September</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Crazy Horse - The Sioux Indian chief Crazy Horse, who died this day in 1877 during a scuffle with soldiers trying to imprison him, was a leader of the Sioux resistance to the invasion of America's northern Great Plains by whites.
</Question>
<Choice>5 September</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John Dalton - English scientist John Dalton, born this day (or September 5) in 1766, was a pioneer in the development of modern atomic theory and was considered by some contemporaries as the “father” of both meteorology and chemistry.
</Question>
<Choice>6 September</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Elizabeth I - Elizabeth I, born this day in 1533, was queen of England (1558–1603) during a period, often called the Elizabethan Age, when England asserted itself vigorously as a major European power in politics, commerce, and the arts.
</Question>
<Choice>7 September</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
King Richard I - Richard I (the Lion-Heart), born this day in 1157, was known for his knightly manner and prowess in the Third Crusade; though he was a popular king and was revered as a hero, scholars would later view him less kindly.
</Question>
<Choice>8 September</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Henri de Toulouse-Lautrec - French artist Henri de Toulouse-Lautrec, whose work reflected the aims of the Symbolist movement and greatly influenced French art through his innovations in style and subject matter, died on this day in 1901.
</Question>
<Choice>9 September</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Arthur Holly Compton - Born this day in 1892, American physicist Arthur Holly Compton confirmed the dual nature of electromagnetic radiation—both a wave and a particle—and was corecipient in 1927 of the Nobel Prize for Physics.
</Question>
<Choice>10 September</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
D.H. Lawrence - D.H. Lawrence, born this day in 1885, was one of the most influential English writers of the 20th century, known in particular for his novels Sons and Lovers (1913), The Rainbow (1915), and Women in Love (1920).
</Question>
<Choice>11 September</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jesse Owens - African American track-and-field athlete Jesse Owens, born this day in 1913, won four gold medals at the 1936 Olympic Games in Berlin, ruining Adolf Hitler's intent to use the Games as proof of Aryan superiority.
</Question>
<Choice>12 September</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Margaret Sanger - American social reformer Margaret Sanger, born this day in 1879, abandoned nursing in 1912 to devote herself to the birth-control movement, establishing what in 1942 became the Planned Parenthood Federation of America.
</Question>
<Choice>13 September</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dante - Italian poet and philosopher Dante, best known for the epic poem The Divine Comedy—considered one of the world's great works of literature and divided into Hell (Inferno), Purgatory, and Paradise—died September 13/14, 1321.
</Question>
<Choice>14 September</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Agatha Christie - English novelist and playwright Agatha Christie, born this day in 1890, was a master of the detective story whose books have sold more than 100 million copies and have been translated into some 100 languages.
</Question>
<Choice>15 September</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Tomás de Torquemada - Tomás de Torquemada, whose name is synonymous with the Spanish Inquisition's horror, bigotry, and cruel fanaticism and during whose tenure as grand inquisitor some 2,000 people were burned at the stake, died this day in 1498.
</Question>
<Choice>16 September</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Wenceslas II - Born on this day in 1271, Wenceslas II, son of Otakar II, succeeded to the Bohemian throne at age seven, and under his rule Bohemia extended its influence to Poland (of which Wenceslas became king in 1300) and to Hungary.
</Question>
<Choice>17 September</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Samuel Johnson - Samuel Johnson, born this day in 1709, was renowned for his A Dictionary of the English Language (1755) and his critical edition of Shakespeare's works and is regarded as one of England's greatest 18th-century figures.
</Question>
<Choice>18 September</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sir William Golding - English novelist Sir William Golding, born this day in 1911, won the Nobel Prize for Literature in 1983 for his parables of the human condition, most notably his acclaimed novel Lord of the Flies (1954).
</Question>
<Choice>19 September</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Upton Sinclair - American novelist Upton Sinclair, born this day in 1878, wrote The Jungle (1906), a landmark work that aroused indignation at impurities in processed meats and helped bring about federal food-inspection laws.
</Question>
<Choice>20 September</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Charles V - Holy Roman Emperor Charles V, who oversaw an empire extending across Europe but faced hostility from the pope and pressure from Turkey, France, and Protestants before abdicating his claims in 1556, died this day in 1558.
</Question>
<Choice>21 September</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Michael Faraday - Michael Faraday, born this day in 1791, was an English scientist whose pioneering work in electromagnetism included producing an electric current from a magnetic field and inventing the first electric motor and dynamo.
</Question>
<Choice>22 September</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John Coltrane - John Coltrane, born this day in 1926, was an American jazz saxophonist, bandleader, and composer who exerted as strong an influence on jazz in the 1960s and '70s as Charlie Parker did in the 1940s and '50s.
</Question>
<Choice>23 September</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jim Henson - American puppeteer Jim Henson, born this day in 1936, was the creator of the Muppets (a meld of “marionettes” and “puppets”), whose characters included Kermit the Frog, Miss Piggy, Big Bird, and the Cookie Monster.
</Question>
<Choice>24 September</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
William Faulkner - American novelist and short-story writer William Faulkner, considered one of the greatest writers of the 20th century, was born this day in Mississippi in 1897 and was awarded the Nobel Prize for Literature in 1949.
</Question>
<Choice>25 September</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
T.S. Eliot - Born on this day in 1888, T.S. Eliot, a leader of poetry's Modernist movement, revitalized English poetry with experiments in diction, style, and versification and exercised a strong influence on Anglo-American culture.
</Question>
<Choice>26 September</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Thomas Nast - German-born American cartoonist Thomas Nast, born this day in 1840, created one of the most popular images of Santa Claus but was perhaps best known for his attack on the Tammany Hall political machine of William M. Tweed.
</Question>
<Choice>27 September</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Élie, Duc Decazes - French politician Élie, Duc Decazes, born this day in 1780, was an intimate adviser to King Louis XVIII and head of the moderate constitutional monarchists, who favoured the liberalization of censorship and electoral laws.
</Question>
<Choice>28 September</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Enrico Fermi - Born in Italy this day in 1901, American physicist Enrico Fermi received the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1938, directed the first controlled chain reaction involving nuclear fission, and helped develop the first atomic bomb.
</Question>
<Choice>29 September</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Elie Wiesel - The works of Romanian-born Jewish writer Elie Wiesel, who was born this day in 1928 and received the 1986 Nobel Prize for Peace, provide a sober yet passionate testament of the destruction of Europe's Jews in the Holocaust.
</Question>
<Choice>30 September</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jimmy Carter - Born this day in 1924, Jimmy Carter served as the 39th U.S. president (1977–81) during a turbulent time at home and abroad, and he later received the Nobel Prize for Peace in 2002 for his humanitarian work.
</Question>
<Choice>1 October</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mohandas Karamchand Gandhi - Born this day in 1869, Mahatma Gandhi was the leader of the Indian nationalist movement against British rule and is esteemed internationally for his doctrine of nonviolence in pursuit of social and political change.
</Question>
<Choice>2 October</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Saint Francis of Assisi - St. Francis of Assisi, who died this day in 1226, founded the Franciscan order and stressed the need to imitate the life of Jesus, drawing followers with his evangelical zeal, consecration to poverty, charity, and charisma.
</Question>
<Choice>3 October</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Charlton Heston - American actor Charlton Heston, born this day in 1924 and best known for his performances in Ben-Hur (for which he won an Academy Award) and The Ten Commandments, also served as president of the National Rifle Association.
</Question>
<Choice>4 October</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Václav Havel - Czech writer and dissident Václav Havel, born this day in 1936, was known for his absurdist depiction of bureaucratic routines and later served as president of Czechoslovakia (1989–92) and the Czech Republic (1993–2003).
</Question>
<Choice>5 October</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Thor Heyerdahl - Norwegian ethnologist and adventurer Thor Heyerdahl, born this day in 1914, organized and led transoceanic expeditions in the hope of proving the possibility of ancient contacts between distant civilizations.
</Question>
<Choice>6 October</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Desmond Tutu - Anglican cleric Desmond Tutu, born this day in 1931, won the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1984 for his role in opposing apartheid in South Africa, and he later headed a committee investigating South African human rights abuses.
</Question>
<Choice>7 October</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jesse Jackson - Jesse Jackson, civil rights leader and the first African American man to make a serious bid for the U.S. presidency (in the Democratic Party's nomination races in 1983–84, 1987–88), was born this day in 1941.
</Question>
<Choice>8 October</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Charles X - Charles X, born this day in 1757, was the king of France (1824–30) whose reign dramatized the Bourbons' failure to reconcile monarchy by divine right with the spirit of democracy prevalent after the French Revolution.
</Question>
<Choice>9 October</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Giuseppe Verdi - Born October 9 or 10, 1813, Giuseppe Verdi was the leading Italian composer of the 19th century, noted for operas such as Rigoletto (1851), La traviata (1853), Aida (1871), and Falstaff (1893) and for his Requiem Mass (1874).
</Question>
<Choice>10 October</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Eleanor Roosevelt - Eleanor Roosevelt, born this day in 1884, was a United Nations diplomat, a humanitarian, the wife (and distant cousin) of President Franklin D. Roosevelt, and, in her time, one of the world's most widely admired women.
</Question>
<Choice>11 October</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Luciano Pavarotti - Born on this day in Modena, Italy, in 1935, Luciano Pavarotti, an operatic lyric tenor noted for his mastery of the highest notes of a tenor's range, is considered one of the finest bel canto singers of recent times.
</Question>
<Choice>12 October</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Margaret Thatcher - British Conservative politician Margaret Thatcher, born this day in 1925, was Europe's first woman prime minister and Britain's only prime minister in the 20th century to win three consecutive terms (1979–90).
</Question>
<Choice>13 October</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dwight D. Eisenhower - Dwight D. Eisenhower, born this day in 1890, served as Supreme Allied Commander in western Europe during World War II, overseeing the Normandy Invasion in June 1944, and was elected to two terms (1953–61) as U.S. president.
</Question>
<Choice>14 October</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John L. Sullivan - American prizefighter John L. Sullivan, born this day in 1858, was one of the most popular heavyweight champions and a symbol of the bareknuckle era of boxing that effectively ended with his knockout of Jake Kilrain in 1889.
</Question>
<Choice>15 October</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Günter Grass - The literary conscience of the generation that grew up in Nazi Germany, Günter Grass, poet, novelist, playwright, and 1999 winner of the Nobel Prize for Literature, was born this day in 1927 in Danzig (now Gdansk, Poland).
</Question>
<Choice>16 October</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mae Jemison - American physician Mae Jemison, born this day in 1956, was the first African American woman to become an astronaut and spent more than a week orbiting the Earth in the space shuttle Endeavour in 1992.
</Question>
<Choice>17 October</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pierre Elliott Trudeau - Pierre Elliott Trudeau, born this day in 1919, was the prime minister of Canada (1968–79; 1980–84) who defeated Quebec separatism, adopted bilingualism for Canada, and advocated on behalf of underdeveloped nations.
</Question>
<Choice>18 October</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jonathan Swift - Anglo-Irish author Jonathan Swift, considered the foremost prose satirist in English and known for his famed novel Gulliver's Travels and shorter works such as A Tale of a Tub and A Modest Proposal, died this day in 1745.
</Question>
<Choice>19 October</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Christiane Nüsslein-Volhard - Christiane Nüsslein-Volhard, a German developmental geneticist who in 1995 was a corecipient of the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for research into early embryonic development, was born this day in 1942.
</Question>
<Choice>20 October</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dizzy Gillespie - Born this day in 1917, Dizzy Gillespie, an American trumpeter, composer, and bandleader, helped to found the modern jazz style known as bebop, but his improvisations also influenced later jazz trumpeters such as Miles Davis.
</Question>
<Choice>21 October</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Franz Liszt - Hungarian composer Franz Liszt, born this day in 1811, was not only the greatest piano virtuoso of his time but also a composer of enormous originality and a principal figure in the Romantic Movement.
</Question>
<Choice>22 October</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pelé - Born this day in Brazil in 1940, Pelé became the most famous football (soccer) player in the sport's history, and, by the time of his retirement in 1977, he had arguably become the most famous athlete in the world.
</Question>
<Choice>23 October</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Luciano Berio - Italian musician Luciano Berio, born this day in 1925, combined lyric and expressive qualities with advanced techniques of electronic and aleatoric music and ranked among the leaders of the musical avant-garde.
</Question>
<Choice>24 October</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pablo Picasso - Pablo Picasso, who was born this day in 1881 in Málaga, Spain, but spent most of his life in Paris, was one of the creators of Cubism and is widely seen as one of the greatest and most influential artists in history.
</Question>
<Choice>25 October</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hillary Rodham Clinton - Hillary Rodham Clinton, born this day in 1947, served as American first lady during the presidency of Bill Clinton and became the first first lady to win elective office when she was elected to the U.S. Senate in 2000.
</Question>
<Choice>26 October</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Theodore Roosevelt - Theodore Roosevelt, born this day in 1858, was a writer and soldier, received the Nobel Prize for Peace, and, as the 26th U.S. president (1901–09), greatly expanded the powers of the presidency and federal government.
</Question>
<Choice>27 October</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John Locke - John Locke, an initiator of the Enlightenment and founder of British Empiricism whose ideas inspired liberalism and influenced the American and French revolutions and the U.S. Constitution, died this day in 1704.
</Question>
<Choice>28 October</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
George Luks - In 1908 George Luks, who died this day in 1933, and seven others formed The Eight, a group that sought to bring painting into closer touch with everyday life by depicting urban scenes and that evolved into the Ashcan school.
</Question>
<Choice>29 October</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John Adams - The first vice president and second president of the United States, John Adams, born this day in 1735 in what is now Quincy, Massachusetts, is regarded as one of the most significant statesmen of the Revolutionary era.
</Question>
<Choice>30 October</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indira Gandhi - Indira Gandhi, the four-term prime minister of India (1966–77; 1980–84) and daughter of independent India's first prime minister, Jawaharlal Nehru, was assassinated this day in 1984 by two of her own Sikh bodyguards.
</Question>
<Choice>31 October</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sholem Asch - Born this day in 1880, Polish American writer Sholem Asch, whose work entered the literary mainstream through translation, was among the most controversial and most widely known writers in modern Yiddish literature.
</Question>
<Choice>1 November</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jean-Baptiste-Siméon Chardin - French painter Jean-Baptiste-Siméon Chardin, whose famous still lifes and domestic scenes were remarkable for their intimate realism, tranquil atmosphere, and luminous quality, was born this day in 1699.
</Question>
<Choice>2 November</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Henri Matisse - Henri Matisse, who died this day in 1954 and is often regarded as the most important French painter of the 20th century, led the Fauvist movement about 1900 and pursued the expressiveness of colour throughout his career.
</Question>
<Choice>3 November</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Joseph Rotblat - Born this day in 1908 in Poland, British physicist Joseph Rotblat was a leading critic of nuclear weapons and joint winner with the Pugwash Conferences (of which he was a founding member) of the 1995 Nobel Prize for Peace.
</Question>
<Choice>4 November</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Eugene V. Debs - Eugene V. Debs, born this day in 1855, was a five-time Socialist candidate for U.S. president and won nearly one million votes in 1920 while in prison for his criticism of prosecutions under the 1917 Espionage Act.
</Question>
<Choice>5 November</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
James A. Naismith - James A. Naismith, born in Canada this day in 1861, was a physical education director and coach who in 1891 invented basketball in Springfield, Massachusetts, now home of the game's hall of fame, named in his honour.
</Question>
<Choice>6 November</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Marie Curie - Polish-born French physicist Marie Curie, famous for her groundbreaking work on radioactivity and winner of both the Nobel Prize for Physics and the Nobel Prize for Chemistry, was born in Warsaw this day in 1867.
</Question>
<Choice>7 November</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John Milton - John Milton, whose Paradise Lost is regarded as the greatest epic poem in the English language and who exerted a major influence on the history of English literature, culture, and libertarian thought, died this day in 1674.
</Question>
<Choice>8 November</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dylan Thomas - Welsh poet and prose writer Dylan Thomas, whose work is known for its comic exuberance, rhapsodic lilt, and pathos and whose personal bouts with drinking were notorious, died this day in 1953 of an alcohol overdose.
</Question>
<Choice>9 November</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
William Hogarth - William Hogarth, the first great English artist to attract admiration abroad, who was best known for moral and satirical engravings and paintings such as A Rake's Progress (begun 1732), was born this day in 1697.
</Question>
<Choice>10 November</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Maude Adams - American actress Maude Adams, born this day in 1872, was best known for her portrayals of Sir James Barrie's heroines and also played Joan of Arc, as well as the Shakespearean roles of Juliet, Viola, and Rosalind.
</Question>
<Choice>11 November</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nadia Comaneci - Born this day in 1961, Romanian Nadia Comaneci (who later defected to the U.S.) was the first gymnast to be awarded a perfect 10 in Olympic competition, scoring seven of them at the 1976 Summer Games in Montreal.
</Question>
<Choice>12 November</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Saint Augustine - St. Augustine—the author of the Confessions and City of God, the bishop of Hippo from AD 396 to 430, and perhaps the most significant Christian thinker after St. Paul—was born in Numidia (now in Algeria) this day in 354.
</Question>
<Choice>13 November</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Boutros Boutros-Ghali - Born this day in 1922, Egyptian scholar Boutros Boutros-Ghali, who served as secretary-general of the United Nations from January 1, 1992, to December 31, 1996, was the first Arab and first African to lead the UN.
</Question>
<Choice>14 November</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Georgia O'Keeffe - American painter Georgia O'Keeffe, whose subjects were frequently enlarged views of skulls and other animal bones, flowers and plant organs, shells, rocks, mountains, and other natural forms, was born this day in 1887.
</Question>
<Choice>15 November</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
W.C. Handy - Born this day in 1873, American composer W.C. Handy, among whose best-known works is the classic St. Louis Blues, changed the course of popular music by integrating the blues idiom into then-fashionable ragtime.
</Question>
<Choice>16 November</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Auguste Rodin - French sculptor Auguste Rodin, known for his bronze and marble figures, including The Thinker (1880) and The Kiss (1886), and considered one of the best portraitists in the history of sculpture, died this day in 1917.
</Question>
<Choice>17 November</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Wyndham Lewis - English artist and writer Wyndham Lewis, born this day in 1882, founded the abstract Vorticist movement, which, in painting and literature before World War I, sought to relate art to the industrial process.
</Question>
<Choice>18 November</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indira Gandhi - Indira Gandhi, born this day in 1917, was the daughter of the first prime minister of India, Jawaharlal Nehru, and served four terms as prime minister before being assassinated by Sikh extremists while in office in 1984.
</Question>
<Choice>19 November</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nathaniel Currier - Lithographer Nathaniel Currier, who died this day in 1888, and his partner James Merritt Ives published more than 7,000 prints between 1840 and 1890, which were among the most popular wall hangings in 19th-century America.
</Question>
<Choice>20 November</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Voltaire - One of the greatest French writers, famous for his critical capacity and satiric wit and still widely revered as a courageous crusader against tyranny, bigotry, and cruelty, Voltaire was born this day in 1694.
</Question>
<Choice>21 November</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Charles de Gaulle - French soldier, writer, and statesman Charles de Gaulle, born this day in 1890, commanded the Free French Forces during World War II and was France's first leader after the war and the architect of the Fifth Republic.
</Question>
<Choice>22 November</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Il Bronzino - Florentine painter Il Bronzino, whose portraits are prime examples of the Mannerist style and whose works are classic embodiments of the courtly ideal under the Medici dukes of the mid-16th century, died this day in 1572.
</Question>
<Choice>23 November</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scott Joplin - American composer and pianist Scott Joplin, born this day in 1868 and known as the “king of ragtime” at the turn of the 20th century, is remembered for his classic piano rags, notably Maple Leaf Rag and The Entertainer.
</Question>
<Choice>24 November</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Diego Rivera - Mexican painter Diego Rivera, whose bold, large-scale murals stimulated a revival of fresco painting in Latin America and whose wife, Frida Kahlo, was also an accomplished painter, died this day in 1957.
</Question>
<Choice>25 November</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Vreni Schneider - Born this day in 1964, Swiss Alpine skier Vreni Schneider won three Olympic gold medals and was the dominant female skier of her era and one of the greatest skiers in the history of the slalom and giant slalom events.
</Question>
<Choice>26 November</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jimi Hendrix - Born this day in 1942, American guitarist Jimi Hendrix altered the course of popular music in his brief career through his innovative playing of the electric guitar and his standing as a symbol of the 1960s youth movement.
</Question>
<Choice>27 November</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Berry Gordy, Jr. - Born this day in 1929, Berry Gordy, Jr., founded the Motown Record Corporation in Detroit in 1959, through which he developed many great rhythm-and-blues performers, including Diana Ross, Marvin Gaye, and Michael Jackson.
</Question>
<Choice>28 November</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jacques Chirac - French politician Jacques Chirac, born this day in 1932, was elected mayor of Paris in 1977, twice served as prime minister of France (1974–76, 1986–88), and was elected twice (1995, 2002) as the country's president.
</Question>
<Choice>29 November</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mark Twain - American writer Mark Twain, born this day in 1835, won worldwide acclaim for his stories of youthful adventures, especially The Adventures of Tom Sawyer, Life on the Mississippi, and The Adventures of Huckleberry Finn.
</Question>
<Choice>30 November</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Karl Schmidt-Rottluff - German artist Karl Schmidt-Rottluff, born this day in 1884 and noted for his landscapes and nudes, cofounded in 1905 Die Brücke, a group of German painters and printmakers who were pivotal to the development of Expressionism.
</Question>
<Choice>1 December</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Georges Seurat - Using the technique of pointillism, French Neo-Impressionist painter Georges Seurat, born this day in 1859, created huge, shimmering compositions comprising tiny, detached, colourful strokes indistinguishable from afar.
</Question>
<Choice>2 December</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Gilbert Stuart - American painter Gilbert Stuart, born this day in 1755, was one of his era's great portraitists, renowned for his portrait of George Washington and praised for his brushwork, luminous colouring, and psychological penetration.
</Question>
<Choice>3 December</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Wassily Kandinsky - Artist Wassily Kandinsky, born this day in 1866 in Moscow, was one of the first creators of pure abstraction in modern painting and cofounded the influential Munich group Der Blaue Reiter (“The Blue Rider”; 1911–14).
</Question>
<Choice>4 December</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Walt Disney - Walt Disney, born in Chicago this day in 1901, pioneered animated cartoon films, created such beloved characters as Mickey Mouse and Donald Duck, and founded what is now one of the world's largest entertainment conglomerates.
</Question>
<Choice>5 December</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
William S. Hart - Born this day in 1870, William S. Hart was an American stage and silent-film actor who was the leading hero of the early westerns, starring in films such as Hell's Hinges (1916) and Wild Bill Hickok (1923).
</Question>
<Choice>6 December</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Gian Lorenzo Bernini - Perhaps the greatest sculptor-architect of the 17th century, Italian Gian Lorenzo Bernini, born this day in 1598, created the Baroque style and refined it with such works as his masterpiece, The Ecstasy of St. Teresa.
</Question>
<Choice>7 December</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sammy Davis, Jr. - Singer, dancer, and actor Sammy Davis, Jr., born this day in 1925, was a member of the legendary “Rat Pack” with Frank Sinatra and Dean Martin and was among the first African American entertainers to gain wide popularity.
</Question>
<Choice>8 December</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Robert Hawke - Born this day in 1929, labour leader Robert Hawke was president of the Australian Council of Trade Unions and president of the Australian Labor Party before serving as prime minister of Australia from 1983 to 1991.
</Question>
<Choice>9 December</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Kenneth Branagh - Actor, director, and writer Kenneth Branagh, born this day in 1960 in Belfast, Northern Ireland, is best known for his film adaptations of Shakespearean plays and for his magnetic and often whimsical performances.
</Question>
<Choice>10 December</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn - Born this day in 1918, Russian writer Aleksandr Solzhenitsyn—best known for The Gulag Archipelago, which chronicles the U.S.S.R.'s vast system of prisons and labour camps—received the Nobel Prize for Literature for 1970.
</Question>
<Choice>11 December</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Edvard Munch - Norwegian artist Edvard Munch, whose painting The Scream (1893) can be seen as a symbol of modern spiritual anguish and whose works greatly influenced German Expressionism in the 20th century, was born this day in 1863.
</Question>
<Choice>12 December</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Moses Maimonides - Philosopher, jurist, and physician Moses Maimonides, the foremost intellectual figure of medieval Judaism, whose works, written in Hebrew and Arabic, influenced both Jewish and non-Jewish scholars, died this day in 1204.
</Question>
<Choice>13 December</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Tycho Brahe - Danish astronomer Tycho Brahe, born this day in 1546, developed astronomical instruments and measured and fixed the positions of stars in an era before the invention of the telescope, paving the way for future discoveries.
</Question>
<Choice>14 December</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Harold Abrahams - British athlete Harold Abrahams, born this day in 1899, won a gold medal in the 100-metre dash at the 1924 Olympic Games in Paris, a victory that became the subject of the Academy Award-winning film Chariots of Fire (1981).
</Question>
<Choice>15 December</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jane Austen - English writer Jane Austen, born this day in 1775, gave the novel its distinctly modern character through her treatment of ordinary people in everyday life and created comedies of contemporary middle-class manners in England.
</Question>
<Choice>16 December</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
W.L. Mackenzie King - W.L. Mackenzie King, born this day in 1874, served as prime minister of Canada (1921–26, 1926–30, 1935–48) and leader of the Liberal Party, helping preserve the unity of the country's English and French populations.
</Question>
<Choice>17 December</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Paul Klee - Born this day in 1879, Swiss painter Paul Klee, one of the foremost artists of the 20th century, used both representational and abstract approaches to produce some 9,000 paintings, drawings, and watercolours.
</Question>
<Choice>18 December</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Leonid Brezhnev - During his tenure as Soviet leader, Leonid Brezhnev, born this day in 1906, developed a doctrine that asserted the right of Soviet intervention in other socialist countries and ordered an invasion of Afghanistan in 1979.
</Question>
<Choice>19 December</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John Steinbeck - American writer John Steinbeck, winner of the Nobel Prize for Literature in 1962, whose protest novel The Grapes of Wrath (1939) offered hope in the face of the dispossession of the Great Depression, died this day in 1968.
</Question>
<Choice>20 December</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Florence Griffith Joyner - American sprinter Florence Griffith Joyner, considered one of the fastest women in track and holder from 1988 of the world record in the 100 metres (10.49 seconds) and 200 metres (21.34 seconds), was born this day in 1959.
</Question>
<Choice>21 December</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Giacomo Puccini - One of the greatest exponents of operatic realism, Italian composer Giacomo Puccini, born this day in 1858, imbued each of his works with a distinctive ambiance, including the classics La Bohème, Tosca, and Madama Butterfly.
</Question>
<Choice>22 December</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Akihito - Japanese emperor since 1989, Akihito—who was born this day in 1933, the eldest son of Hirohito, and whose reign is designated Heisei (“Achieving Peace”)—broke a 1,500-year-old tradition by marrying a commoner.
</Question>
<Choice>23 December</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
John - King John of England (1199–1216), born this day in 1167, lost Normandy and almost all his other French possessions in a war with France and was forced to seal the Magna Carta (1215) following an English baronial revolt.
</Question>
<Choice>24 December</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Anwar el-Sadat - Born this day in 1918, army officer and politician Anwar el-Sadat, who shared the 1978 Nobel Prize for Peace for his peace negotiations with Israel, served as president of Egypt from 1970 until his assassination in 1981.
</Question>
<Choice>25 December</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Henry Miller - American writer Henry Miller, born this day in 1891, was a perennial bohemian with a gift for comedy whose autobiographical novels achieved a candour that was considered liberating by many mid-20th-century readers.
</Question>
<Choice>26 December</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Louis Pasteur - French chemist and microbiologist Louis Pasteur, born this day in 1822, made many valuable contributions to the history of science, including originating vaccines for rabies and anthrax and developing pasteurization.
</Question>
<Choice>27 December</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Woodrow Wilson - The 28th U.S. president, Woodrow Wilson, born this day in 1856, was the creator and leading advocate of the League of Nations after World War I, for which he was awarded the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1919.
</Question>
<Choice>28 December</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pablo Casals - Born this day in Spain in 1876 was the virtuoso cellist and conductor Pablo Casals, a romantic who eschewed literal interpretations of modernism and was renowned for his innovative technique and consummate musicianship.
</Question>
<Choice>29 December</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Rudyard Kipling - Born this day in 1865, Rudyard Kipling, winner of the 1907 Nobel Prize for Literature, was an English short-story writer, poet, and novelist remembered for his celebration of British imperialism and his stories for children.
</Question>
<Choice>30 December</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sir Anthony Hopkins - Welsh actor Sir Anthony Hopkins, a performer of tremendous intensity born this day in 1937, is best remembered for his Academy Award-winning role as demented serial killer Hannibal Lecter in The Silence of the Lambs (1991).
</Question>
<Choice>31 December</Choice>
</item>
</topics>