<topics>
<item>
<Question>
Many religions have a literature that serves as a foundation for belief and practice among their followers. For Judaism and Christianity such a literature is found in the Bible—a term derived from the Greek meaning “book.” The Bible is a collection of many books by an unknown number of authors.
</Question>
<Choice>Bible</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Angkor means “capital,” and a wat is a monastery. The city of Angkor in northwestern Cambodia was for more than 500 years the capital of the Khmer Empire, a kingdom that once ruled most of the Indochinese peninsula. From the end of the 9th century until early in the 13th century, numerous large construction projects made Angkor one of the most...
</Question>
<Choice>Angkor Wat</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the middle of the 19th century, there emerged in Persia (now Iran) a new religion—the Baha?i faith, which had its roots in Islam (see Islam). Orthodox members of the Shi?ah sect of Islam believe that the 12th and last imam, or successor of Muhammad, disappeared in the year 878 and will one day reappear to save the world. For a short time after...
</Question>
<Choice>Baha'i Faith</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(flourished c. 6th–4th century BC). Hundreds of years before Jesus was born—and at about the same time that Confucius was teaching the Chinese how to lead the good life—a prince named Siddhartha Gautama (or Gotama) became famous in India for his holiness and love for all creatures. He was called the Buddha, meaning “the Enlightened One,” a title...
</Question>
<Choice>Buddha</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Buddhism is the name for a complex system of beliefs developed around the teachings of the Buddha. Though used by many religious groups in ancient India, the title Buddha (meaning “the Enlightened One”) became associated with the founder of Buddhism, Siddhartha Gautama, who lived between the 6th and the 4th centuries BC. There are now dozens of...
</Question>
<Choice>Buddhism</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1509–64). When John Calvin was a boy in France, Martin Luther launched the Protestant Reformation in Germany (see Luther). Two decades later Calvin became the second of the great 16th-century reformers. His work and teachings had a profound impact on the development of Christianity.
</Question>
<Choice>Calvin, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Early in the Middle Ages when Latin was still the language of religious and political life in western Europe, a Christian church that contained the official “seat” or throne (cathedra) of a bishop was known as the ecclesia cathedralis, or “church of the throne.” As time went on ecclesia cathedralis was shortened into “cathedral,” the modern word...
</Question>
<Choice>cathedral</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The beliefs and practices of Christianity are based on the teachings of Jesus Christ. Christianity is divided into three main denominations: Roman Catholic, Eastern Orthodox, and Protestant. There are more Christians in the world (some 2 billion at the beginning of the 21st century) than followers of any other single religion. (See also Jesus...
</Question>
<Choice>Christianity</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(551–479 BC). For more than 2,000 years the Chinese people were guided by the ideals of Confucianism. Its founder and greatest teacher was Confucius, whose humane philosophy also influenced the civilization of all of eastern Asia.
</Question>
<Choice>Confucius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the Middle Ages the Roman Catholic church considered all the Christians of Europe to be within its fold. That unity and inclusiveness were shattered by the Protestant Reformation of the 16th century. In response to the Reformation, the church launched a major effort to reform itself, to combat the Protestant movement and reclaim lost...
</Question>
<Choice>Counter-Reformation</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
To Tibetan Buddhists, a Dalai Lama is the incarnation of the lord of compassion who takes earthly forms in order to help humankind. The title is often translated as “Ocean of Wisdom.” The Dalai Lama is the head of the religious order called Dge-lugs-pa (or Yellow Hat). Since the order achieved supremacy in Tibet in the mid-17th century, the Dalai...
</Question>
<Choice>Dalai Lama</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the Chinese language the word dao, which is also spelled tao, means “way,” indicating a way of thought or life. There have been several such ways in China's long history, including Confucianism and Buddhism. In about the 6th century BC, under the influence of ideas credited to a man named Laozi, or Lao-tzu, Daoism became “the way” (see Laozi...
</Question>
<Choice>Daoism</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the year 1054 a major split occurred in Christianity. The churches in Western Europe, under the authority of the pope at Rome, separated from the churches in the Eastern Roman (or Byzantine) Empire, under the authority of the patriarch (bishop) of Constantinople. The churches of the Eastern Empire have come to be known by the collective term...
</Question>
<Choice>Eastern Orthodox Churches</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The name God has been applied to the supreme being who is variously understood in the many different religious traditions. Even within a single tradition, there is often great diversity of thought about God, which has resulted from changing conceptions of God's nature as they have evolved over the centuries.
</Question>
<Choice>God</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The major religion of the Indian subcontinent is Hinduism. The term Hinduism was first used in the 19th century by European scholars and derives from an ancient Sanskrit term meaning “dwellers by the Indus River,” a reference to the location of India's earliest known civilization in what is now Pakistan (see Indus Valley civilization). Although...
</Question>
<Choice>Hinduism</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A major world religion, Islam is based on the revelations of the Prophet Muhammad and was first established in Mecca (now in Saudi Arabia). From the Atlantic Ocean across North Africa, the Middle East, and South and Central Asia to the Pacific Ocean, the world's predominantly Muslim nations form a long, continuous band. (Muslims are those who...
</Question>
<Choice>Islam</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Along with Hinduism and Buddhism, Jainism is one of the major religions that developed within the ancient civilization of India. The name of the religion derives from the term Jina, meaning “victor” or “conqueror.” The goal of Jainism explains this term. It is the spiritual progress of the individual through a succession of stages until he is...
</Question>
<Choice>Jainism</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nearly all that is known about the life of Jesus, also called Jesus Christ, after whom Christianity is named, is contained in the four Gospels of the New Testament, particularly those of Mark, Matthew, and Luke. These accounts were written 60 to 100 or more years after the birth of Christ by men of different temperaments. They differ in some...
</Question>
<Choice>Jesus Christ</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1412?–31). One of the most romantic figures in European war history was Joan of Arc, a peasant girl who saved the kingdom of France from English domination. She has also been called the Maid of Orléans and the Maid of France. When she was only 17 years old, Joan inspired a French army to break the English siege of the French city of Orléans and...
</Question>
<Choice>Joan of Arc</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Along with Christianity and Islam, Judaism is one of the three major monotheistic religions of the world. It shares with them the belief in one God who is the creator and ruler of the universe and the lord of human history. Of the three, Judaism is much the oldest. According to biblical tradition, the origins of the faith can be traced back at...
</Question>
<Choice>Judaism</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
“We have revealed the Koran in the Arabic tongue that you may grasp its meaning. It is a transcript of Our eternal book, sublime, and full of wisdom.” The speaker was Allah (God), and the one who received the message was Muhammad, Allah's chosen prophet to the Arab peoples. The message is contained in the holy book of Islam, the Koran. The word...
</Question>
<Choice>Koran</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1483–1546). The Protestant Reformation in Germany was inaugurated by Martin Luther in 1517. It was his intent to reform the medieval Roman Catholic church, but the firm resistance of the church to Luther's challenge led instead to permanent divisions in the structure of Western Christianity (see Reformation).
</Question>
<Choice>Luther, Martin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Through the many centuries of church history, the mother of Jesus achieved a status second only to Jesus himself in the Roman Catholic, Eastern Orthodox, and other churches. She has been the focus of much debate and the subject of some of the greatest art in the Western world. Many of the finest medieval cathedrals are dedicated to her—including...
</Question>
<Choice>Mary</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Most Christians, Hindus, Muslims, and members of other religions are ordinary citizens. They raise families, work, play, and are otherwise involved in their societies. In most major religions there are also numerous individuals who devote themselves full-time to the quest for salvation—however that term may be defined. The term used to describe...
</Question>
<Choice>monk and monasticism</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Church of Jesus Christ of Latter-day Saints, more commonly known as the Mormons, was founded by Joseph Smith in 1830 (see Smith, Joseph). Some scholars of religion argue that Smith combined elements of Judaism and Christianity with Native American myths and several distinctive features of his own creation. The organization that grew out of...
</Question>
<Choice>Mormons</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Revered as a prophet but even more importantly as a teacher and a lawgiver, Moses was the leader of the Israelite people 3,300 years ago during their journey from slavery in Egypt to freedom as a nation in the land of Israel (see Israel). For 40 years Moses led the people through the desert on their way to Israel and helped shape them into a...
</Question>
<Choice>Moses</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(570?–632). “There is no God but Allah, and Muhammad is the Prophet of Allah.” This is the fundamental statement of faith in Islam, and it declares that Muhammad is the founder of one of the world's major religions. He was also the founder of a state by his unification of Arabia. Within decades after his death his followers sent out armies that...
</Question>
<Choice>Muhammad</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Roman Catholic church is governed by a leader known as the pope. The word pope is the English form of the Latin word papa, meaning “father.” The institution by which the pope governs the church is called the papacy. As a result of a long historical development, the pope claims jurisdiction over the universal church. This means that he...
</Question>
<Choice>papacy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
When the snows of winter have melted and April rains bring forth the flowers of spring, wrote Geoffrey Chaucer, “then do folk long to go on pilgrimage?.?.?.?to distant shrines well known in sundry lands.” The opening lines of the ‘Canterbury Tales' state what has been an ancient custom in all of the major world religions: making a journey at...
</Question>
<Choice>pilgrimage</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Today the word Protestantism is used to refer to most Christian denominations and sects that do not form part of the Roman Catholic or Eastern Orthodox groups. Included within the framework of Protestantism are the Anglican Communion, Adventists, Baptists, Brethren, the Church of God, Disciples of Christ, Friends (or Quakers), Lutherans...
</Question>
<Choice>Protestantism</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In 1652 George Fox, standing on high Pendle Hill in England, had a vision. This was the beginning of the Christian denomination known as the Religious Society of Friends (or simply the Society of Friends). Its members are commonly called Friends or Quakers. A magistrate first used the name Quaker in Derby in 1650, when Fox was on trial for his...
</Question>
<Choice>Quakers</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the greatest of all revolutions was the 16th-century religious revolt known as the Reformation. This stormy, often brutal, conflict separated the Christians of Western Europe into Protestants and Catholics. So far-reaching were the results of the separation that the Reformation has been called a turning point in history. It ushered in the...
</Question>
<Choice>Reformation</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The largest of the Christian denominations is the Roman Catholic church. As an institution it has existed since the 1st century AD, though its form, extent, and teachings have been significantly modified over the centuries. The headquarters of the church is Vatican City, an independent nation-state and enclave within Rome, Italy. The head of the...
</Question>
<Choice>Roman Catholicism</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The word saint has undergone a significant change in meaning during the approximately 2,000 years of Christianity. In the Hebrew Bible (Old Testament) it applies to any Israelite. In the New Testament its meaning is similar, referring to any Christian. Basically, as Paul the Apostle noted in his Epistle to the Romans, the word refers to anyone...
</Question>
<Choice>saint</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Religions such as Buddhism and Christianity were brought into Japan, but Shinto seems to be as old as the Japanese people and nation. Shinto is a loose system of beliefs and attitudes held by most Japanese about themselves, their families and clans, and their ruling powers. The word itself means “the way of kami,” and while there is no precise...
</Question>
<Choice>Shinto</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Punjab region of northern India is home to Sikhism, a religion founded in the 15th century. When the Indian subcontinent was partitioned into India and Pakistan in 1947, many Sikhs emigrated to Punjab from Muslim-dominated Pakistan. Since then, they have turned the Punjab into the breadbasket of India. Because they desire to establish a...
</Question>
<Choice>Sikhism</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Found at sites sacred to Buddhism, stupas are commemorative monuments that were originally built to house the earthly remains or relics of the Buddha and his associates. Later the concept of a relic was extended to include the sacred texts.
</Question>
<Choice>stupa</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The basic scripture of Judaism is the Hebrew Bible, the most significant portion of which is the first five books. Because these books contain the laws of Moses, they are usually referred to collectively as the Torah, or Law (see Bible; Judaism; Moses; Torah). Ancient Israel, however, had many other laws, customs, and traditions not found in the...
</Question>
<Choice>Talmud</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1910–97). One of the most highly respected women in the world, Mother Teresa was internationally known for her charitable work among the victims of poverty and neglect—particularly in the slums of Calcutta, India. In 1979 she was awarded the Nobel peace prize in recognition of her humanitarian efforts. She also received the Jewel of India, India...
</Question>
<Choice>Teresa, Mother</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Judaism, the word Torah in its narrowest sense refers to the first five books, or Pentateuch, of the Hebrew Bible. These books, traditionally credited to Moses, are Genesis, Exodus, Leviticus, Numbers, and Deuteronomy (see Bible; Judaism; Moses). This written Torah is preserved in all Jewish synagogues on handwritten scrolls of parchment...
</Question>
<Choice>Torah</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The ancient Iranian (or Persian) religion was reformed during the 7th and 6th centuries BC by a legendary figure named Zoroaster, or Zarathustra. Despite the furious onslaughts of Islam, beginning in the 7th century, Zoroastrianism has survived into the 20th century. The majority of its adherents live in India and are known as Parsis, which...
</Question>
<Choice>Zoroastrianism</Choice>
</item>
</topics>