<topics>
<item>
<Question>
Descendants of the Germanic peoples who invaded and conquered Britain in the 5th and 6th centuries are generally known as Anglo-Saxons. The term Anglo-Saxon was most likely first used in the late 8th century to distinguish the Saxons of Britain from those of the European continent. Following the Norman Conquest, however, the term simply came to...
</Question>
<Choice>Anglo-Saxon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Beginning on July 21, 1588, a great fleet of ships from Spain engaged English forces in combat in English waters. This was the Invincible Armada, sent by Philip II, king of Spain. The Armada was made up of 130 ships, not more than 50 of them real men-of-war. They carried 30,493 men, of whom 18,973 were soldiers.
</Question>
<Choice>Armada, Spanish</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(born 1953). British Labour party leader Tony Blair became the United Kingdom's prime minister in 1997, ending 18 years of Conservative party rule. Blair pushed his party to the political center with a “New Labour” agenda, which embraced a mixed economy, supported the United Kingdom's integration into the European Union, and stressed aggressive...
</Question>
<Choice>Blair, Tony</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
South Africa's Cape of Good Hope was colonized in the 17th century by Dutch Boers (farmers). The Boers used African slaves on their farms. Britain occupied the Cape during the Napoleonic wars and took complete control after the Congress of Vienna. Slavery was abolished throughout the British Empire in 1833. Many of the Boers then decided that...
</Question>
<Choice>Boer War</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1869–1940). In the hope of preventing war, Neville Chamberlain made concessions to the German dictator Adolf Hitler in 1938. The war started the following year, however, and ever since then the British prime minister's name has been linked to the failed policy of “appeasement.”
</Question>
<Choice>Chamberlain, Neville</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Two British kings were named Charles. Both were of the Scottish house of Stuart (see Stuart).
</Question>
<Choice>Charles, Kings of England, Scotland…</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1874–1965). Once called “a genius without judgment,” Sir Winston Churchill rose through a stormy career to become an internationally respected statesman during World War II. He was one of Britain's greatest prime ministers.
</Question>
<Choice>Churchill, Winston</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The terms colonialism and imperialism belong together. Imperialism refers to the practice of extending political power, especially through the acquisition of conquered territory. The territories that are acquired are called colonies. The Roman Empire, for example, began as a small city-state. Gradually, by force, it extended its control...
</Question>
<Choice>colonialism and imperialism</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The largest, richest, and most powerful empire in the world's history was the British Empire. At its zenith, Great Britain ruled broad lands on every continent and islands in every ocean. It was a common saying that the sun never set on Britain's dominions. As one after another of these lands have become independent states, they have joined...
</Question>
<Choice>Commonwealth of Nations</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1728–79). The English navigator Captain Cook became an explorer because of his love of adventure and curiosity about distant lands and their people. He surveyed a greater length of coastline than any other man and remade the map of the Pacific. His explorations gave Britain the lands now occupied by Australia and New Zealand.
</Question>
<Choice>Cook, James</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Crimean War was named for the Crimean peninsula, in what is now Ukraine, which was the main site of the war. The immediate cause of the war was a religious quarrel. In 1853 Czar Nicholas I of Russia demanded the right to protect Christian shrines in Jerusalem, then part of the Turkish empire. As a first step, his troops moved into the...
</Question>
<Choice>Crimean War</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1599–1658). The chief leader of the Puritan Revolution in England was Oliver Cromwell, a soldier and statesman. He joined with the Puritans to preserve Protestantism and the law against the tyranny of King Charles I. Cromwell was made lord protector of the Commonwealth of England, Scotland, and Ireland in December 1653 and held that office...
</Question>
<Choice>Cromwell, Oliver</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1804–81). A clever novelist and a brilliant statesman, Disraeli led the Conservative political party in Great Britain for more than a quarter century, twice holding the post of prime minister. Widely considered the founder of British imperialism, Disraeli was largely responsible for securing British control of the Suez Canal and India.
</Question>
<Choice>Disraeli, Benjamin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1543?–96). The first Englishman to sail around the world was Sir Francis Drake. He also took a leading part in defeating the Great Armada sent by Spain to invade England.
</Question>
<Choice>Drake, Francis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Two 11th-century kings of Scotland bore the name Duncan. Both were killed after brief reigns in rivalries for the throne.
</Question>
<Choice>Duncan, kings of Scotland</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Three Anglo-Saxon kings bore the name of Edward before the Norman Conquest in 1066. Eight Edwards have reigned since then. As the numbering of English rulers of the same name began after the Conquest, the three earlier Edwards have only distinguishing nicknames.
</Question>
<Choice>Edward, kings of england</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1533–1603). Popularly known as the Virgin Queen and Good Queen Bess, Elizabeth Tudor was 25 years old when she became queen of England. The golden period of her reign is called the Elizabethan Age.
</Question>
<Choice>Elizabeth I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Like Elizabeth I of England's Golden Age, Elizabeth II came to the throne when she was 25 years old. “A fair and youthful figure,” said Winston Churchill, “princess, wife, and mother, is heir to all our traditions and glories.” The young queen had already won the affection of the British people by her charm and thoughtfulness, her modesty and...
</Question>
<Choice>Elizabeth II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The largest and most populated part of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland is England. By world standards, it is neither large nor particularly rich in natural resources, yet in the past, as the heart of the vast British Empire, its political and economic power was virtually unrivaled. Today England's influence on the...
</Question>
<Choice>England</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
To understand the natural world and humankind's place in it solely on the basis of reason and without turning to religious belief was the goal of the wide-ranging intellectual movement called the Enlightenment. The movement claimed the allegiance of a majority of thinkers during the 17th and 18th centuries, a period that Thomas Paine called the...
</Question>
<Choice>Enlightenment</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1570–1606). November 5 is Guy Fawkes Day in England. It is the anniversary of the Gunpowder Plot to blow up King James I and Parliament in 1605.
</Question>
<Choice>Fawkes, Guy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Six kings of the United Kingdom have borne the name George. The first four were also German princes of the House of Hanover. George V and George VI belonged to the House of Saxe-Coburg-Gotha. This royal house was renamed Windsor by George V during World War I because of strong anti-German feeling in Britain.
</Question>
<Choice>George, Kings of England, Scotland…</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1809–98). After his graduation from Oxford in 1831, William Gladstone wanted to become a clergyman in the Church of England. But his strong-willed father, Sir John Gladstone, insisted that he enter politics. For 60 years William Gladstone served the government of the United Kingdom almost continuously, achieving one of the most brilliant state...
</Question>
<Choice>Gladstone, William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Great Britain is one of the two main islands that make up the British Isles. By this definition it includes England, Scotland, and Wales. However, the name Great Britain is commonly used to refer to the United Kingdom as a whole, which also includes Northern Ireland and some offshore islands.
</Question>
<Choice>Great Britain</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
United States President Franklin D. Roosevelt, in his first inaugural address, made some attempt to assess the enormous damage: “The withered leaves of industrial enterprise lie on every side; farmers find no markets for their produce; the savings of many years in thousands of families are gone. More important, a host of unemployed citizens face...
</Question>
<Choice>Great Depression</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Only two kings of England were named Harold. Both of them reigned before the Norman Conquest, which took place in 1066.
</Question>
<Choice>Harold, kings of england</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Norman Conquest, which brought tremendous changes to England, began with the decisive battle of Hastings on Oct. 14, 1066. Harold II, the last of the Saxon kings of England, was killed in this battle. On Christmas Day William, duke of Normandy, was crowned king. He became known as William the Conqueror (see William, Kings of England).
</Question>
<Choice>Hastings, Battle of</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Eight of the kings of England have been named Henry. The first of these, Henry I, was the youngest son of the Norman conqueror, William I. The most recent one was the notorious Henry VIII, who ruled in the 1500s.
</Question>
<Choice>Henry, kings of England</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1337–1453). The struggle between France and England called the Hundred Years' War was the longest war in recorded history. It lasted, with some interruptions, through the reigns of five English kings (Edward III to Henry V) and five French kings (Philip VI to Charles VII).
</Question>
<Choice>Hundred Years' War</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Most products people in the industrialized nations use today are turned out swiftly by the process of mass production, by people (and sometimes, robots) working on assembly lines using power-driven machines. People of ancient and medieval times had no such products. They had to spend long, tedious hours of hand labor even on simple objects. The...
</Question>
<Choice>Industrial Revolution</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Only two rulers of England have borne the name James. The hatred felt for the second of these, because of his attempts to rule despotically and to restore the Roman Catholic religion, is probably the most important reason why the name fell into disuse.
</Question>
<Choice>James, Kings of England</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1167–1216). Vicious, shameless, and ungrateful, King John has been called the worst king ever to rule England. Yet the very excesses of his reign proved positive in that they provoked such a violent reaction that his subjects revolted and forced him to put his seal on the Magna Carta. This document became the safeguard of English liberty. John...
</Question>
<Choice>John of England</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A basic document that states the liberties guaranteed to the English people, the Magna Carta proclaims rights that have become a part of English law and are now the foundation of the constitution of every English-speaking nation. The Magna Carta, which means “great charter” in Latin, was drawn up by English barons and churchmen, who forced the...
</Question>
<Choice>Magna Carta</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(born 1943). Rising above his humble background, John Major became prime minister of the United Kingdom in 1990. He was the youngest person to hold the post since the Earl of Rosebery in 1894. Major served as prime minister until May 1997, when his Conservative party suffered its worst loss in 165 years in national elections and was ousted by...
</Question>
<Choice>Major, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Four kings of medieval Scotland ruled under the name Malcolm. Their reigns were characterized by continuous warfare with England and bloody competition for the Scottish throne. (See also Scotland.)
</Question>
<Choice>Malcolm, kings of Scotland</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Only six English rulers have been women. Two bore the name Mary. The first, Mary I, attempted to restore England to Roman Catholicism. The other, Mary II, was brought in to guarantee that England would remain Protestant.
</Question>
<Choice>Mary, Queens of England</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The medieval period, or the Middle Ages, was a time in European history before the modern era. In the 4th century AD Germanic peoples began crossing the frontiers of the Roman Empire, in part because of the advance of ferocious warriors from the east—the Huns. The movement of the Germanic peoples contributed to the so-called fall of the Roman...
</Question>
<Choice>Middle Ages</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1208?–65). Although he was born into the French aristocracy, Simon de Monfort moved to England during the reign of Henry III to claim an inherited title. Simon was the most notable English statesman of his era and is remembered in history as a political reformer. He led a movement to limit the king's governing powers and, after an armed revolt...
</Question>
<Choice>Montfort, Simon de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Edward the Confessor, king of England, died childless on Jan. 5, 1066. It is possible that Edward had promised William, duke of Normandy, the throne. As William was Edward's cousin, it is likely that William had been given some encouragement about the succession. Nevertheless, when Edward died, Harold, the powerful earl of Wessex, had himself...
</Question>
<Choice>Norman Conquest</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The North Atlantic Treaty Organization is a political and military alliance between the United States, Canada, and numerous European countries. Established in 1949 as a defense against the Soviet Union and its eastern European allies, NATO changed its membership and its goals following the breakup of the Soviet Union in 1991. NATO headquarters...
</Question>
<Choice>North Atlantic Treaty Organization</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The northeastern part of the island of Ireland is occupied by Northern Ireland, a part of the United Kingdom. It covers only one sixth of the total area of the island but has about one third of the population. The rest of the island is occupied by the Republic of Ireland. The capital and largest city of Northern Ireland is Belfast.
</Question>
<Choice>Northern Ireland</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sea robbers, or men who attack and rob ships at sea, are called pirates. Many of the romantic stories that have been written about them are imaginative pieces of fiction. Nevertheless, their actual adventures often changed the course of history.
</Question>
<Choice>pirates</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
“I will make them conform or I will harry them out of the land.” This was the threat that King James I of England made to the Puritans when they asked him to “purify” the state church of England of certain ceremonies and usages derived from the Roman Catholic church, which they disliked. These Puritans were not dangerous revolutionists but...
</Question>
<Choice>Puritans</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The 13 American colonies revolted against their British rulers in 1775. The war began on April 19, when British regulars fired on the Minutemen of Lexington, Mass. The fighting ended with the surrender of the British at Yorktown on Oct. 19, 1781. In 1783 Great Britain signed a formal treaty recognizing the independence of the colonies.
</Question>
<Choice>Revolution, American</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Three of the kings of England have been named Richard. Of the three, only Richard I succeeded his father as king. Richard II succeeded Edward III, his grandfather, because his father, called the Black Prince, had died the year before. Richard III succeeded his nephew Edward V, whom Richard may have had killed.
</Question>
<Choice>Richard, Kings of England</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
When the ancient Greeks were reaching the height of their glory, the power of Rome, to the west, was slowly rising. The genius of the Greeks lay in art, literature, science, and philosophy. The Romans were best in warfare, engineering, and government.
</Question>
<Choice>Roman Empire</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A quarrel between the families of York and Lancaster over the right to occupy the English throne brought on a series of cruel civil wars in England in the years 1455 to 1485. The emblem of the Yorkists was a white rose and that of the Lancastrians a red rose. Because of this the wars were called the Wars of the Roses.
</Question>
<Choice>Roses, Wars of the</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A part of the United Kingdom, Scotland occupies the northern part of the island of Great Britain. Rugged uplands separate it from England to the south. Within this border territory north of England the Scots fought many wars to keep their independence. In 1707, however, Scotland was joined to England, and the entire island became a single kingdom...
</Question>
<Choice>Scotland</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1756–63). During the early part of the 18th century, both France and England sought undisputed supremacy of the seas. Each nation tried to outdo the other in forming military alliances. Diplomatic intrigues stemming from these alliances created bitter rivalries among European powers. The political atmosphere was so tense that even a small...
</Question>
<Choice>Seven Years' War</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The prehistoric monument known as Stonehenge includes a circular arrangement of massive, upright stones surrounded by a large circular earthen embankment. It was built between about 3100 and 1500 BC and is located about 8 miles (13 kilometers) northwest of Salisbury, in southern England. There are hundreds of similar structures throughout Britain...
</Question>
<Choice>Stonehenge</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(born 1925). The first woman to be elected prime minister of the United Kingdom was Margaret Thatcher, who was also the first woman to hold such a post in the history of Europe. The first prime minister since the 1820s to win three consecutive elections, Thatcher held office longer than any other 20th-century British leader.
</Question>
<Choice>Thatcher, Margaret</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The House of Tudor ruled England from the late 15th century through the 16th century. Henry VII, who came to the throne in 1485, was the first Tudor monarch. His successor was his son, Henry VIII (reigned 1509–47). The other Tudor sovereigns were Henry VIII's son, Edward VI (1547–53), and his daughters, Mary I (1553–58) and Elizabeth I...
</Question>
<Choice>Tudor, House of</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1819–1901). On June 22, 1897, as cheering throngs massed in the streets, cannon roared, and the bells of London rang, a carriage pulled up to the steps of St. Paul's Cathedral. The greatest empire on Earth was paying tribute to Victoria, the queen-empress, on her Diamond Jubilee.
</Question>
<Choice>Victoria, Queen</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the 9th century AD, seafaring warriors known as Vikings began raiding the coasts of Europe, burning, plundering, and killing as they went. These marauders, or pirates, came from Scandinavia—what is now Denmark, Norway, and Sweden. The people who lived there were Norsemen, or Northmen. Their expression for these campaigns of swift, cruel raids...
</Question>
<Choice>Vikings</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Though a part of the United Kingdom, Wales has retained a character of its own—the result of its Celtic culture and its rugged landscape. In the Welsh language, Wales is called Cymru. Much of Wales is still a land of picturesque mountains and valleys. However, the existence of large coalfields in the south brought industry and urbanization. The...
</Question>
<Choice>Wales</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Since the United States became a nation, it has fought in eight major wars. The War of 1812 with Great Britain was one of three wars (the others were the Korean War and the Vietnam conflict) that did not end in unmistakable victories. It was tragic in its loss of life, money, and property, but otherwise it was almost a comedy of cross-purposes...
</Question>
<Choice>War of 1812</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Four kings of England were named William. The first was William I of Normandy, who conquered England in 1066. Every king and queen who has sat on the throne in England since the Norman Conquest can claim descent from this king.
</Question>
<Choice>William, Kings of England</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A major international conflict fought from 1914 to 1918, World War I was the most deadly and destructive war the world had ever seen to that time. More than 25 countries eventually participated, aligned with either the Allied or the Central powers. The Allies—who won the war—included primarily France, Great Britain, Russia, Italy, Japan, and...
</Question>
<Choice>World War I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Some 20 years after the end of World War I, lingering disputes erupted in an even larger and bloodier conflict—World War II. The war began in Europe in 1939, but by its end in 1945 it had involved nearly every part of the world. The opposing sides were the Axis powers—consisting mainly of Germany, Italy, and Japan—and the Allies—primarily France...
</Question>
<Choice>World War II</Choice>
</item>
</topics>