<topics>
<item>
<Question>
From June 19 to July 11, 1754, an intercolonial conference was held at Albany, N.Y. Present were 23 delegates from the English colonies of New York, Pennsylvania, New Hampshire, Connecticut, Massachusetts, Rhode Island, and Maryland, along with 150 members of the Iroquois Indian federation. The Albany Congress had been called by the English Board...
</Question>
<Choice>Albany Congress</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
During the 15th century, the European nations of Spain and Portugal began a series of explorations to find trade routes to the Far East. An accidental outcome of this search was the discovery by Christopher Columbus in 1492 of land in the Western Hemisphere. Although he and his immediate successors failed to recognize it, he had found another...
</Question>
<Choice>Americas, Discovery and Exploration of the</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1567–1635). Called the Father of New France, Samuel de Champlain founded Quebec, the first permanent French settlement in North America. He also kept the struggling community alive during its early years. He explored New France (now part of Canada) as far west as Lake Huron and also discovered the lake in New York that bears his name.
</Question>
<Choice>Champlain, Samuel de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1451–1506). On the morning of Oct. 12, 1492, Christopher Columbus stepped ashore on an island in what has since become known as the Americas. The arrival of his ships in the Western Hemisphere was one of the pivotal events in world history. It opened up a new world for Europeans and initiated the spread of Western civilization to a new hemisphere...
</Question>
<Choice>Columbus, Christopher</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1510?–54). One of the strangest journeys ever made in search of gold was led by the Spaniard Francisco Coronado. His army of several hundred Spaniards, Indians, and slaves was accompanied by herds of cattle, pigs, and sheep. Instead of the cities filled with treasure that he expected to find in the wilderness north of Mexico, Coronado found...
</Question>
<Choice>Coronado, Francisco</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1496?–1542). One of the most famous gold seekers in history was Hernando De Soto. He was born in about 1496 in Jerez de los Caballeros, Spain. In 1514 he sailed to the New World with Pedro Arias Dávila, governor of Darien (now Panama). He became a ruthless soldier whose men feared his temper but admired his horsemanship.
</Question>
<Choice>De Soto, Hernando</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1754–63). The struggle between France and England for North America was finally ended by the French and Indian War. Three earlier wars—King William's War, from 1689 to 1697; Queen Anne's War, from 1702 to 1713; and King George's War, from 1744 to 1748—had failed to bring a settlement of the bitter contest.
</Question>
<Choice>French and Indian War</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1575?–1611). Because of the thriving trade in spices and silk between the Far East and Europe, Henry Hudson and other explorers made a number of difficult and dangerous voyages searching for a northeast or northwest passage. Such a passage—a shortcut northward from the east coast of Europe and thence either eastward over the top of Europe and...
</Question>
<Choice>Hudson, Henry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first permanent English colony in America was founded on May 14, 1607, on a peninsula of the James River in what is now the state of Virginia. The colony was named after King James I of England. Here the first representative government in America was begun, and here the first black people were brought to the American Colonies.
</Question>
<Choice>Jamestown</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1645–1700). Two men share the honor of discovering and exploring the upper Mississippi River—Father Jacques Marquette and Louis Jolliet. They were the first Europeans to travel the upper reaches of the giant river after the Spaniard Hernando de Soto explored the lower Mississippi in 1541.
</Question>
<Choice>Jolliet, Louis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1639?–76), Native American leader of the Wampanoag. Also known as Metacom and as Metacomet, he was the second son of Massasoit, who had been the grand sachem, or chief, of the Wampanoag Confederacy and oversaw a lifetime of peaceful relations with the Pilgrims and other settlers. Massasoit died in 1661, and Metacom's older brother Alexander was...
</Question>
<Choice>King Philip</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the most tragic of all the conflicts between the American colonists and the Indians was King Philip's War. In 1662 Metacomet, or Philip, younger son of the Pilgrims' friend Massasoit, succeeded his father as chief of the Wampanoags. He tried for some years to keep peace and to meet the demands of the white settlers, but the settlers...
</Question>
<Choice>King Philip's War</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1643–1687). The father of the great Louisiana Territory was the French explorer René Robert Cavelier, sieur de La Salle. He was the first to voyage down the Mississippi River to the Gulf of Mexico. As a result of this exploration France laid claim to the entire Mississippi Valley under the name of Louisiana.
</Question>
<Choice>La Salle, Sieur de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1637–75). Traveling with his fellow adventurer Louis Jolliet, Father Jacques Marquette explored the upper Mississippi River and reported the first accurate data on its course. The story of the long and dangerous journey of Marquette and Jolliet is one of the most interesting chapters in the history of the exploration of the New World.
</Question>
<Choice>Marquette, Jacques</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(also called Wasamegin) (1580?–1661), Native American chief of the Wampanoag in Massachusetts. Massasoit was the intertribal chief, or grand sachem, of the Wampanoag of Massachusetts and Rhode Island. From the early days after the arrival of the Pilgrims, Massasoit sought to develop peaceful relations. He became their steadfast friend and signed...
</Question>
<Choice>Massasoit</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A storm-tossed, 66-day voyage across the wintry Atlantic Ocean in 1620 carried the small, slow merchant vessel Mayflower into an honored place in American history. Crowded on board were the men, women, and children who founded Plymouth, the first permanent colony in North America settled by families. These people, now called the Pilgrims, were...
</Question>
<Choice>Mayflower</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1644–1718). The most famous colony builder in early America was a wealthy Englishman, William Penn. His province, or colony, of Pennsylvania (meaning “Penn's woods”) had an area of more than 50,000 square miles (130,000 square kilometers). A Quaker, Penn welcomed to his colony members of all religious faiths and also those who had no religion...
</Question>
<Choice>Penn, William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Pilgrim leaders chose the site at Plymouth for their new home because it had a broad, sheltered harbor and a large brook providing fresh water. There were also wooded hills to supply timber and stretches of cleared ground for farming. The Pilgrims landed at what is now Provincetown, Mass., on Nov. 21, 1620. A month later, on December...
</Question>
<Choice>Plymouth</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1595?–1617). A familiar story about colonial days in America recounts the way in which Pocahontas, daughter of the Indian chief Powhatan, saved the life of Captain John Smith. According to the story, Powhatan's warriors had captured Smith and were about to put him to death. When Pocahontas pleaded with her father to spare him, Powhatan relented...
</Question>
<Choice>Pocahontas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
“I will make them conform or I will harry them out of the land.” This was the threat that King James I of England made to the Puritans when they asked him to “purify” the state church of England of certain ceremonies and usages derived from the Roman Catholic church, which they disliked. These Puritans were not dangerous revolutionists but...
</Question>
<Choice>Puritans</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
proceedings held in 1692 in Salem, Massachusetts Bay Colony, that led to the hanging of 19 suspected witches and the imprisonment of many others; started in May with accusations by a few young girls against women in the community; special court was convened; trials quickly grew into mass hysteria implicating even the governor's wife; by October...
</Question>
<Choice>Salem witch trials</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1580–1631). The story of the life of Captain John Smith, as told by himself, reads more like an adventure novel than like a true autobiography. He was baptized on Jan. 6, 1580, in Willoughby, Lincolnshire, England. In about 1600 he ran away from home and, traveling through France and at sea, survived some fantastic adventures. Then he fought in...
</Question>
<Choice>Smith, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(died 1622). Soon after the Pilgrims arrived in Massachusetts on the Mayflower in 1620, they met an Indian of the Pawtuxet tribe named Squanto. Squanto befriended them, taught them how to survive in their new wilderness home, showed them how to plant crops, and acted as an interpreter with the Wampanoag tribe and its chief, Massasoit. Squanto...
</Question>
<Choice>Squanto</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1584?–1656). Before the Pilgrims sailed for America in 1620, they were joined by Miles Standish, an English soldier born in Lancashire who had been fighting in the Low Countries. He and his wife, Rose, sailed on the Mayflower on its voyage to the New World. What led this military man to cast his lot with this little band will never be known...
</Question>
<Choice>Standish, Miles</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
As first vice president and second president of the United States, John Adams was one of the founding fathers of the new nation. He was a delegate of the Continental Congress from 1774 to 1777 and one of only two presidents whose signature appears on the Declaration of Independence. Adams also participated in negotiating the 1783 Treaty of Paris...
</Question>
<Choice>Adams, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1722–1803). One of the firebrands of the American Revolution was Sam Adams. He helped to start it and he helped to keep it going—by speeches, newspaper articles, and behind-the-scene maneuvers. He combined great ideals with shrewd politics, and he worked hard to help America change from a British colony into an independent nation.
</Question>
<Choice>Adams, Sam</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The administration of President John Adams drew sharp criticism from newspaper editors and public speakers. To check these attacks Congress passed four measures in 1798 called the Alien and Sedition Acts.
</Question>
<Choice>Alien and Sedition Acts</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1738–89). One of the first heroes of the American Revolution was Ethan Allen. He was especially famed for leading a small force against the British at Fort Ticonderoga and winning a bloodless surrender on May 10, 1775.
</Question>
<Choice>Allen, Ethan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first constitution of the United States was known as the Articles of Confederation. The Articles were written in 1776–77, after independence from Great Britain had been declared and while the American Revolution was in progress. As a constitution, the Articles had a short life. The document was not fully ratified by the states until March...
</Question>
<Choice>Articles of Confederation</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1731–1806). A story about Benjamin Banneker—African-American mathematician, astronomer, and inventor—suggests to what degree he had trained his memory. Appointed to the District of Columbia Commission by President George Washington in 1790, he worked with Pierre L'Enfant, Andrew Ellicott, and others to plan the new capital of Washington, D.C...
</Question>
<Choice>Banneker, Benjamin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A written statement that spells out the rights of citizens and the limitations of government is commonly called a “bill of rights.” The term rights is used, basically, in two senses: natural rights and civil rights. Natural rights are those rights that any person can claim by virtue of his or her humanity; the right to life is most basic of...
</Question>
<Choice>Bill of Rights</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1734–1820). At a time when most Americans were content to live along the Atlantic coast, Daniel Boone was one of the restless pioneers who pushed westward through the wilderness. Often accompanied by their families, these men and women explored, cut trails, and sometimes established new communities.
</Question>
<Choice>Boone, Daniel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first major battle of the American Revolution was fought at Bunker Hill in Massachusetts on June 17, 1775. Two months had passed since the skirmishes at Lexington and Concord (see Lexington and Concord, Battles of). The British had increased their force in Boston and put Maj. Gen. William Howe in command. Thousands of colonial troops had...
</Question>
<Choice>Bunker Hill, Battle of</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
From 1774 to 1789 there was a group of men who spoke and acted for the people of the 13 British North American colonies that in 1776 became the United States of America. This body of delegates, called the Continental Congress, came into existence to deal with complaints that the colonies had against Great Britain, particularly the Coercive Acts...
</Question>
<Choice>Continental Congress</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On July 4, 1776, the members of the Continental Congress assembled at the State House in Philadelphia to take up a matter of vital importance. Two days earlier the Congress had voted to declare the 13 American colonies to be “free and independent states,” with no ties to Great Britain. Now they were considering how to announce that fact to the...
</Question>
<Choice>Declaration of Independence</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1745 or 1750?–1818). The first settler in what is now Chicago was a black man named Jean Baptist Point du Sable. Of French and African parentage, he was probably born in what is now Haiti in about 1745 or 1750. After attending school in France, he went to New Orleans as a member of a French trading firm. He soon went up the Mississippi River to...
</Question>
<Choice>Du Sable, Jean-Baptist-Point</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the United States presidential election of 1876, the Democratic candidate, Samuel J. Tilden, received 4,284,020 votes; the Republican Rutherford B. Hayes received 4,036,572 votes; but Hayes became president (see Hayes, “The Disputed Presidential Election”). Similarly, Benjamin Harrison got fewer popular votes than did Grover Cleveland in the...
</Question>
<Choice>electoral college</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Few men have done as much for the world as Benjamin Franklin. Although he was always proud to call himself a printer, Franklin had many other talents as well. He was a diplomat, a scientist, an inventor, a philosopher, an educator, and a public servant.
</Question>
<Choice>Franklin, Benjamin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1765–1815). The man who did the most to make steamboats a commercial success was Robert Fulton. Other inventors pioneered in steam navigation before him, but it was Fulton who proved that their vision and designs were practical. (See also Steamboat.)
</Question>
<Choice>Fulton, Robert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1755?–1804). One of the youngest and brightest of the founders of the United States, Alexander Hamilton favored strong central government. As the nation's first secretary of the treasury he established responsible financial policies that helped the country prosper.
</Question>
<Choice>Hamilton, Alexander</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1737–93). The man whose name heads the list of signers of the Declaration of Independence, John Hancock was a Boston patriot and a leader of the American Revolution. His prominent signature is familiar to anyone who has seen a picture of that document. (See also Declaration of Independence; Revolution, American.)
</Question>
<Choice>Hancock, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1736–99). Fearless and eloquent, Patrick Henry became the spokesman of the Southern colonies during the stirring period that led to the American Revolution. His words, which expressed the feelings and hopes of the patriots, helped inspire them to make those dreams into reality.
</Question>
<Choice>Henry, Patrick</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The author of the Declaration of Independence in 1776, Thomas Jefferson was the third president of the United States, serving from 1801 to 1809. During his presidency the territory of the United States doubled with the Louisiana Purchase. To investigate the vastness of this newly acquired land in the West, he dispatched two of the most famous...
</Question>
<Choice>Jefferson,Thomas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1747–92). The first great American naval hero was Captain John Paul Jones. Strong, resourceful, and skilled in seamanship, he loved a battle almost as much as he loved freedom. His words, “I have not yet begun to fight,” are famous throughout the world.
</Question>
<Choice>Jones, John Paul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1757–1834). Among the heroes of the American Revolution only the name of Washington ranks above that of Lafayette. He was a gallant Frenchman who generously placed his life and his fortune at the disposal of the American colonists.
</Question>
<Choice>Lafayette, Marquis de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The American Revolution began on April 19, 1775, with the Battles of Lexington and Concord. Some time before, Gen. Thomas Gage, the military governor of Massachusetts, had received orders from England to arrest Samuel Adams and John Hancock, accused of stirring up rebellion in the colony. On the night of April 18 Gage sent a detachment of...
</Question>
<Choice>Lexington and Concord, Battle of</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The giant statue titled Liberty Enlightening the World has become a symbol of the United States and of freedom to oppressed people everywhere. It stands on Liberty Island in New York Harbor. The statue was a gift from the people of France to the people of the United States commemorating the alliance of the two nations during the American...
</Question>
<Choice>Liberty, Statue of</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1735–1818). On the night of April 18, 1775, Paul Revere rode to warn American patriots northwest of Boston that the British intended to raid Lexington and Concord. The ride of this Revolutionary War folk hero was immortalized in Henry Wadsworth Longfellow's 1863 ballad, ‘Paul Revere's Ride'.
</Question>
<Choice>Revere, Paul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The 13 American colonies revolted against their British rulers in 1775. The war began on April 19, when British regulars fired on the Minutemen of Lexington, Mass. The fighting ended with the surrender of the British at Yorktown on Oct. 19, 1781. In 1783 Great Britain signed a formal treaty recognizing the independence of the colonies.
</Question>
<Choice>Revolution, American</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
After the American Revolution the young nation was torn by unsettled economic conditions and a severe depression. Paper money was in circulation, but little of it was honored at face value. Merchants and other “sound money” men wanted currencies with gold backing. In Massachusetts the “sound money” men controlled the government. Most of those...
</Question>
<Choice>Shays' Rebellion</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The French and Indian War (1754–63) doubled the debt of the British government and at the same time greatly increased British possessions in America. The British government therefore decided to station British troops in the colonies to prevent the French from recovering Canada and to defend the colonies against the Indians. Most Englishmen...
</Question>
<Choice>Stamp Act</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the judicial systems of most countries, there is one high court whose decisions are final. Beyond it no appeal can be made. In several countries this body is called the Supreme Court. The Supreme Court of the United States dates from 1789, at the foundation of the republic. Canada's Supreme Court was established in 1875, but it was not made...
</Question>
<Choice>Supreme Court</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Many people think of the United States as a young country. Yet it has the oldest written constitution among the major nations of the world. Moreover, it was, for the first time in history, a constitution that specifically limited the powers that the federal government would be able to exercise over its citizens.
</Question>
<Choice>United States Constitution</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The federal government of the United States was created by the Constitution, which went into operation in 1789 when the first Congress convened and George Washington took the oath of office as president. The government is called federal because it was formed by a compact (the Constitution) among 13 political units (the states). These states...
</Question>
<Choice>United States government</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An area about 20 miles (32 kilometers) northwest of Philadelphia, Pa., Valley Forge served as the headquarters of General George Washington and the encampment of the Continental Army in the winter of 1777–78, during the American Revolution. The major portions of the original camp are now part of Valley Forge National Historical Park, along the...
</Question>
<Choice>Valley Forge</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Many United States presidents were honored for their great achievements, and George Washington's achievements distinguished him as the Father of His Country. Washington was commander in chief of the Continental Army during the American Revolution, chairman of the convention that wrote the United States Constitution, and the first president of the...
</Question>
<Choice>Washington, George</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The official home of the president of the United States is the White House at 1600 Pennsylvania Avenue N.W., Washington, D.C., 20500. It is also called the Executive Mansion. The stately, white stone home is almost as old as the United States. Americans have a deep regard for it as a symbol of the nation's history and unity.
</Question>
<Choice>White House</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1765–1825). Best remembered as the inventor of the cotton gin, Eli Whitney also developed the concept of mass production of interchangeable parts and the assembly line.
</Question>
<Choice>Whitney, Eli</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The last battleground of the American Revolution was at Yorktown. This small tidewater village on the south shore of the deep York River is the site where Gen. George Cornwallis's British troops were besieged in 1781 by allied French and American forces under George Washington. Yorktown Day is celebrated annually on October 19, the anniversary...
</Question>
<Choice>Yorktown</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Beginning in the 1780s—during the time of the American Revolution—there arose in Western Europe and the United States a movement to abolish the institution of slavery and the slave trade that supported it. Advocates of this movement were called abolitionists.
</Question>
<Choice>abolitionist movement</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An old mission-fort, the Alamo, in San Antonio, has been called the “cradle of Texas liberty.” Its defense and the deaths of the more than 180 men who defended it inspired the cry, “Remember the Alamo!” Texas soldiers shouted this at the battle of San Jacinto, which brought Texas its independence from Mexico. (See also Texas.)
</Question>
<Choice>Alamo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
ship on which a successful revolt by black Africans occurred in 1839. The revolt drew considerable international attention and made many in the United States take a closer look at the issue of slavery.
</Question>
<Choice>Amistad</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1767–1838). The American Indian chief of the Sauk tribe, Black Hawk was the leader of the last war against white settlers in the Northwest Territory. He had a band of about 1,000 followers, many of whom were women, old men, and children.
</Question>
<Choice>Black Hawk</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1770–1838). With Meriwether Lewis, William Clark led the famous Lewis and Clark Expedition of 1804 to 1806 from St. Louis to the mouth of the Columbia River. Lewis was chief in command, but Clark had had more frontier experience. More than once he saved the party from disaster. (See also Lewis and Clark Expedition.)
</Question>
<Choice>Clark, William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1777–1852). For 40 years Henry Clay exercised a leadership in the politics of the United States that has seldom been equaled. He was a man of charming personal traits, powerful emotional oratory, and brilliant statesmanship. He was greatly loved and honored by his many followers. Nevertheless, like his great contemporaries John C. Calhoun and...
</Question>
<Choice>Clay, Henry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1786–1836). In history and in folklore Davy Crockett represents the spirit of the American frontier. As a young man he was a crafty Indian fighter and a hunter. For many years he was nationally known as a political representative of the frontier. He served two terms in the Tennessee legislature and three terms as a representative in Congress...
</Question>
<Choice>Crockett, Davy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1818?–95). An escaped slave, Frederick Douglass became one of the foremost black abolitionists and civil rights leaders in the United States. His powerful speeches, newspaper articles, and books awakened whites to the evils of slavery and inspired blacks in their struggle for freedom and equality.
</Question>
<Choice>Douglass, Frederick</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The controversial 1857 ruling of the U.S. Supreme Court in the case of Dred Scott made slavery legal in all the territories. Dred Scott was a black slave who belonged to an officer in the United States Army. His master had taken him from the slave state of Missouri to the free state of Illinois and then to Wisconsin Territory, which had been...
</Question>
<Choice>Dred Scott decision</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American settlers knew little about western North America when the Lewis and Clark Expedition set out in 1804. Twelve years earlier Capt. Robert Gray, an American navigator, had sailed up the mouth of the great river he named the Columbia. Traders and trappers reported that the source of the Missouri River was in the mountains in the Far West. No...
</Question>
<Choice>Lewis and Clark Expedition</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1774–1809). The name of Meriwether Lewis is closely linked with that of another American explorer, William Clark. Together they led the expedition named for them (see Clark, William; Lewis and Clark Expedition).
</Question>
<Choice>Lewis, Meriwether</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In 1803 United States President Thomas Jefferson set the example of getting new territory by purchase rather than by war. He did so by buying from France the vast tract of land known as Louisiana. The United States did not differ from Old World countries in wanting to expand its control to its “natural boundaries.” It did differ in the method...
</Question>
<Choice>Louisiana Purchase</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The 19th-century political and philosophical belief that it was America's divinely assigned mission to expand westward across the North American continent and to establish democratic and Protestant ideals was known as Manifest Destiny.
</Question>
<Choice>Manifest Destiny</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
“Mexico has passed the boundary of the United States, has invaded our territory and shed American blood upon American soil. War exists, and, notwithstanding all our efforts to avoid it, exists by the act of Mexico herself.” So President James K. Polk said in his message to Congress in May 1846.
</Question>
<Choice>Mexican War</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In February 1819 the slavery issue in the United States was dramatically brought to everyone's attention. People were awakened to the gravity of the issue, in the words of elder statesman Thomas Jefferson, “as though a fire bell had rung in the night.”
</Question>
<Choice>Missouri Compromise</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
First expressed by President James Monroe in his message to Congress on Dec. 2, 1823, the Monroe Doctrine states that the United States will not permit any European nation to extend its holdings or use armed force on the two American continents. The Monroe Doctrine has been a keystone of American foreign policy since then.
</Question>
<Choice>Monroe Doctrine</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
“The grass is up!” Each spring in the 1840s and 1850s the excited shout arose from emigrants camped at the big bend of the Missouri River. When the prairie began to show green, they rushed to head their wagon trains northwestward to the Oregon country. For the next four to six months these brave travelers would plod some 2,000 miles...
</Question>
<Choice>Oregon Trail</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1804?–38). The leader of the Seminole Indians in their second war against the United States was Osceola. He was born about 1804 along the Tallapoosa River in Georgia. When he was 4 his family moved to Florida. As a boy he may have fought against Andrew Jackson in the First Seminole War.
</Question>
<Choice>Osceola</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1786?–1812?). In 1804 the Lewis and Clark Expedition arrived among the Mandan Indians of North Dakota (see Lewis and Clark Expedition). They hired the French fur trapper Toussaint Charbonneau and his Indian wife, Sacagawea, to guide them to the West coast. In the Northwest, Sacagawea has become a legend. Memorials have been raised in her honor...
</Question>
<Choice>Sacagawea</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1768?–1813). The most dramatic of the Indians' struggles to hold their lands against the white man was the one led by the great Shawnee chief Tecumseh. He was born on Mad River, near the present city of Springfield, Ohio, in about 1768. From his earliest childhood he saw suffering brought to his people by the whites.
</Question>
<Choice>Tecumseh</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
For more than four decades before the American Civil War, there existed an organized system in the Northern states established to help escaped slaves reach places of safety in the North and in Canada. This system was called the Underground Railroad because its activities were carried on in secret and because railway terms were used to describe...
</Question>
<Choice>Underground Railroad</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Since the United States became a nation, it has fought in eight major wars. The War of 1812 with Great Britain was one of three wars (the others were the Korean War and the Vietnam conflict) that did not end in unmistakable victories. It was tragic in its loss of life, money, and property, but otherwise it was almost a comedy of cross-purposes...
</Question>
<Choice>War of 1812</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1820–1906). For more than half a century Susan B. Anthony fought for women's right to vote. Many people made fun of her. Some insulted her. Nevertheless, she traveled from county to county in New York and other states making speeches and organizing clubs for women's rights. She pleaded her cause with every president from Abraham Lincoln to...
</Question>
<Choice>Anthony, Susan B.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1838–65), U.S. actor. John Wilkes Booth was born in Hartford County, Md., in 1838, into a well-known acting family that included Edwin Booth, his brother. He too became an outstanding Shakespearean actor, but he is best known for having assassinated President Abraham Lincoln on April 14, 1865. Booth served briefly under General Robert E. Lee and...
</Question>
<Choice>Booth, John Wilkes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1800–59). The ideological differences between the North and the South that festered before the American Civil War were reflected in their views of the abolitionist John Brown. To Northerners he was a martyr to the cause of freeing African Americans from slavery. To Southerners he was an insane criminal. As for historians he was a man obsessed...
</Question>
<Choice>Brown, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At 4:30 AM on April 12, 1861, Confederate artillery in Charleston, S.C., opened fire on Fort Sumter, which was held by the United States Army. The bombardment set off a savage four-year war between two great geographic sections of the United States. One section was the North—23 Northern and Western states that supported the federal government...
</Question>
<Choice>Civil War, American</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At the close of the Mexican War, in 1848, the United States owned vast stretches of territory without local government. All the land now included in New Mexico, Arizona, and California was then unsettled.
</Question>
<Choice>Compromise of 1850</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Between Dec. 20, 1860, and Feb. 1, 1861, six southern states declared their withdrawal (secession) from the United States. On February 4, at Montgomery, Ala., they organized a separate and independent government called the Confederate States of America. The states that set up this government were South Carolina, Mississippi, Florida, Alabama...
</Question>
<Choice>Confederate States of America</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1842?–77). Carved out of a mountain near Custer, S.D., there is a large memorial to Crazy Horse, chief of the Oglala Sioux Indians. He was one of the ablest warriors to lead American Indians in their attempt to stop the white man's invasion of the northern Great Plains. In 1866 he participated in the massacre of Captain William J. Fetterman and...
</Question>
<Choice>Crazy Horse</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1808?–89). During the American Civil War, Jefferson Davis was president of the Confederate States of America. A hero of the Mexican War and former U.S. war secretary, he also took an active role in dictating Confederate military strategy during the Civil War.
</Question>
<Choice>Davis, Jefferson</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1813–61). The author of the Kansas-Nebraska Act of 1854 was Stephen Douglas, a United States senator from 1847 until his death. He also gained national fame from a series of debates with Abraham Lincoln (see Lincoln-Douglas Debates).
</Question>
<Choice>Douglas, Stephen</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The controversial 1857 ruling of the U.S. Supreme Court in the case of Dred Scott made slavery legal in all the territories. Dred Scott was a black slave who belonged to an officer in the United States Army. His master had taken him from the slave state of Missouri to the free state of Illinois and then to Wisconsin Territory, which had been...
</Question>
<Choice>Dred Scott decision</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On Sept. 22, 1862, United States President Abraham Lincoln issued a proclamation that he later called “the central act of my administration, and the greatest event of the 19th century.” The proclamation promised freedom for slaves held in any of the Confederate states that did not return to the Union by the end of the year.
</Question>
<Choice>Emancipation Proclamation</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1829–1909). A formidable leader of the Chiricahua Apache in the defense of their homeland against the invasion of white settlers, Geronimo today is considered a genuine legend of the Old West. Embittered at the slaughter and displacement of his people, he displayed exceptional courage and skill in leading attacks on both the Mexican and the U.S...
</Question>
<Choice>Geronimo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the two major battles of the American Civil War was fought at the crossroads town of Gettysburg, Pa., from July 1 to 3, 1863. The defeat of the Southern forces at Gettysburg and their surrender of Vicksburg the next day foreshadowed Gen. Robert E. Lee's eventual surrender at Appomattox Court House.
</Question>
<Choice>Gettysburg, Battle of</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
From humble beginnings, Ulysses S. Grant rose to command all the Federal armies in the Civil War and lead them to victory. So great was his popularity that the people twice elected him to the presidency.
</Question>
<Choice>Grant, Ulysses S.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Harpers Ferry is located in the Blue Ridge Mountains on a strip of land at the junction of the Shenandoah and Potomac rivers where West Virginia, Virginia, and Maryland meet. It is famous as the site of John Brown's ill-fated raid on a United States armory, an incident that preceded the outbreak of the American Civil War (see Brown, John).
</Question>
<Choice>Harpers Ferry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1824–63). No leader in the American Civil War was more skilled or gallant than Stonewall Jackson. His earnestness of purpose, determination to do right as he saw it, and military genius made him admired by friend and foe alike.
</Question>
<Choice>Jackson, Stonewall</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Passed by Congress in 1854, the Kansas-Nebraska Act has been called the most momentous piece of legislation in the United States before the American Civil War. It set in motion events that led directly to the conflict over slavery.
</Question>
<Choice>Kansas-Nebraska Act</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1807–70). The Confederacy's greatest soldier, Robert E. Lee, was descended from an old and honored family. Several of Lee's forebears had played distinguished roles in Virginia's history. His father was the Revolutionary War hero Light-Horse Harry Lee, a friend of George Washington.
</Question>
<Choice>Lee, Robert E.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The 16th president of the United States, Abraham Lincoln not only ranks among the greatest of all American statesmen. Many historians also place him among the greatest men of all time. Lincoln came to the presidency at a time of great crisis, with the country at the brink of a civil war that threatened to split North from South. Combining his...
</Question>
<Choice>Lincoln, Abraham</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In 1858 the Republican party nominated Abraham Lincoln for United States senator from Illinois. His Democratic opponent was Senator Stephen A. Douglas.
</Question>
<Choice>Lincoln-Douglas Debates</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The victory of the North in the American Civil War put an end to slavery and to the South's effort to secede from the Union. However, for more than a decade after the Civil War the status of the liberated slaves and the terms on which the defeated states would be restored to the Union—that is, the way in which the South and the Union would be...
</Question>
<Choice>Reconstruction Period</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1820–91). Ranked second only to General Ulysses S. Grant as the greatest Northern commander in the American Civil War, Gen. William Tecumseh Sherman was a master of modern warfare. Like Grant, Sherman was born in Ohio when it was a frontier state. He was named Tecumseh for the Shawnee Indian chief who had terrorized that region a few years...
</Question>
<Choice>Sherman, William Tecumseh</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1831?–90). The Hunkpapa Sioux Indian chief and medicine man Sitting Bull was respected by the Plains Indians for his courage and wisdom and feared by settlers and the United States Army for his determination to rid Indian tribal lands of white people. Under him the Sioux tribes united in their struggle for survival on the Great Plains.
</Question>
<Choice>Sitting Bull</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The most common form of forced labor in the history of civilization is slavery. Servitude is the general term used to describe all types of forced labor. It is derived from the Latin noun servus, which really means “slave,” though it is recognizable as the source of “servant” as well. Throughout the ancient world, anyone who functioned as a...
</Question>
<Choice>slavery and serfdom</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the summer of 1898, the United States fought Spain in one of the shortest and most pathetically one-sided wars in modern history. The war represented a powerful resurgence of the same doctrine of Manifest Destiny that had led the United States to expand westward by defeating Mexico in 1846–48. This impulse toward imperialism took place as...
</Question>
<Choice>Spanish-American War</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Governmental rights granted to individual states in a country by a federal constitution are called states' rights. On Feb. 19, 1985, the United States Supreme Court ruled that federal minimum wage laws apply to employees of state and local governments. The case, Garcia vs. San Antonio Metropolitan Transit Authority, was one in a long series of...
</Question>
<Choice>States' Rights</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1820?–1913). A runaway slave herself, Harriet Tubman helped so many blacks escape to freedom that she became known as the “Moses of her people.” During the Civil War she served the Union Army as a nurse, cook, scout, and spy.
</Question>
<Choice>Tubman, Harriet</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1860–1935). An early concern for the living conditions of 19th-century factory workers led Jane Addams to assume a pioneering role in the field of social work. She brought cultural and day-care programs to the poor, sought justice for immigrants and blacks, championed labor reform, supported women's suffrage, and helped to train other social...
</Question>
<Choice>Addams, Jane</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1875–1955). A pioneer in African American education in the United States was Mary McLeod Bethune. Born to parents who had been slaves until the American Civil War, she rose to become president of her own college. Under President Franklin D. Roosevelt, she headed the Division of Negro Affairs of the National Youth Administration and was an...
</Question>
<Choice>Bethune, Mary McLeod</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1846–1917). A folk hero was created in the late 1860s when a dime novelist listened to the wild West tales of a young Indian scout. The writer was Ned Buntline (the pen name of E.Z.C. Judson), and the subject of many of his pulp stories was the bigger-than-life figure he nicknamed Buffalo Bill. The scout's legendary feats as a frontiersman rank...
</Question>
<Choice>Buffalo Bill</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1864?–1943). American agricultural chemist George Washington Carver helped to modernize the agricultural economy of the South. He developed new products derived from peanuts and soybeans and promoted the planting of these legumes as a way of liberating the South from its dependency on cotton.
</Question>
<Choice>Carver, George Washington</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1868–1963). For more than 50 years W.E.B. Du Bois, an African American editor, historian, and sociologist, was a leader of the civil rights movement in the United States. He helped found the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) and was its outstanding spokesman in the first decades of its existence.
</Question>
<Choice>Du Bois, W.E.B.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1897–1937). One of the most intriguing mysteries of the 20th century is: What happened to Amelia Earhart? In June 1937 she and her copilot, Lieutenant Commander Fred J. Noonan, left Miami, Fla., on an around-the-world flight attempt in a twin-engine Lockheed aircraft. On July 2 the plane vanished near Howland Island in the South Pacific. The...
</Question>
<Choice>Earhart, Amelia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1863–1947). In 1896 a horseless carriage chugged along the streets of Detroit, with crowds gathering whenever it appeared. Terrified horses ran at its approach. The police tried to curb this nuisance by forcing its driver, Henry Ford, to get a license. That car was the first of many millions produced by the automotive pioneer.
</Question>
<Choice>Ford, Henry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
United States President Franklin D. Roosevelt, in his first inaugural address, made some attempt to assess the enormous damage: “The withered leaves of industrial enterprise lie on every side; farmers find no markets for their produce; the savings of many years in thousands of families are gone. More important, a host of unemployed citizens face...
</Question>
<Choice>Great Depression</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
After World War I Americans enjoyed a period of economic growth that produced a popular faith in lasting peace and prosperity. The austerity of the war gave way to a general relaxation of standards, which had a profound effect on the social, sexual, and cultural values of Americans. A new feminism arose after women gained the right to vote in...
</Question>
<Choice>Jazz Age</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1880–1968). “Once I knew only darkness and stillness.?.?.?. My life was without past or future.?.?.?. But a little word from the fingers of another fell into my hand that clutched at emptiness, and my heart leaped to the rapture of living.” This is how Helen Keller described the beginning of her “new life,” when despite blindness and deafness...
</Question>
<Choice>Keller, Helen</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1902–74). On May 20–21, 1927, Charles A. Lindbergh flew a small silvery monoplane, called the Spirit of St. Louis, nonstop from New York City to Paris. It was the first one-man flight across the Atlantic Ocean. The daring, skill, and endurance of “Lucky Lindy” won him world acclaim. After his flight Lindbergh devoted his career to aviation and...
</Question>
<Choice>Lindbergh, Charles</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The code name for the United States program to develop an atomic bomb during World War II, the Manhattan Project was the largest scientific effort undertaken to that time. It involved 37 installations throughout the country; at least 13 university laboratories; and 100,000 people, including the Nobel prizewinning physicists Arthur Holly Compton...
</Question>
<Choice>Manhattan Project</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
When Franklin D. Roosevelt assumed the presidency of the United States in 1933, the nation's economy was in a state of turmoil. Following the stock market crash of 1929 that signaled the onset of the Great Depression, the Dow Jones Industrial Average went on to lose an additional 80 percent of its value through the early 1930s. Industrial...
</Question>
<Choice>New Deal</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On the morning of Sunday, Dec. 7, 1941, Japanese bombers, fighter planes, and torpedo planes attacked the American naval base at Pearl Harbor. This sneak attack brought the United States into World War II. The first wave, consisting of 183 planes, arrived at approximately 7:50 AM. They had taken off from aircraft carriers about 200 miles...
</Question>
<Choice>Pearl Harbor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Herbert Hoover called it a “noble experiment.” Organized crime found it to be the opportunity of a lifetime. And millions of Americans denounced it as an infringement of their rights. For nearly 14 years—from Jan. 29, 1920, until Dec. 5, 1933—the manufacture, transportation, and sale of alcoholic beverages was illegal in the United States. The...
</Question>
<Choice>Prohibition</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Everyone had strong feelings about Franklin D. Roosevelt during his 12 years as president. Many people hated him. They thought he was destroying the country and the American way of life. Most people loved him. They believed he was a great president, truly interested in people.
</Question>
<Choice>Roosevelt, Franklin Delano</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1884–1962). Great reformer and humanitarian Eleanor Roosevelt strove to improve the lives of people all over the world. As the wife of Franklin Delano Roosevelt, 32nd president of the United States, she had the distinction of being first lady longer than any other presidential wife—slightly more than 12 years (1933–45)—and her defense of the...
</Question>
<Choice>Roosevelt, Eleanor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the summer of 1898, the United States fought Spain in one of the shortest and most pathetically one-sided wars in modern history. The war represented a powerful resurgence of the same doctrine of Manifest Destiny that had led the United States to expand westward by defeating Mexico in 1846–48. This impulse toward imperialism took place as...
</Question>
<Choice>Spanish-American War</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Although it was considered “unsinkable” by its builders and the general public, the British ocean liner Titanic of the White Star Line sank on her maiden voyage in 1912, resulting in the death of more than 1,500 men, women, and children—more casualties than in any other marine disaster in peacetime history. The magnitude of this tragedy, combined...
</Question>
<Choice>Titanic</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1856–1915). The first African American whose face appeared on a United States postage stamp was Booker T. Washington, who was thus honored a quarter century after his death. (In 1946 he also became the first black with his image on a coin, a 50-cent piece.) His ten-cent stamp went on sale in 1940 at Tuskegee Institute, which Washington had...
</Question>
<Choice>Washington, Booker T.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A major international conflict fought from 1914 to 1918, World War I was the most deadly and destructive war the world had ever seen to that time. More than 25 countries eventually participated, aligned with either the Allied or the Central powers. The Allies—who won the war—included primarily France, Great Britain, Russia, Italy, Japan, and...
</Question>
<Choice>World War I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Some 20 years after the end of World War I, lingering disputes erupted in an even larger and bloodier conflict—World War II. The war began in Europe in 1939, but by its end in 1945 it had involved nearly every part of the world. The opposing sides were the Axis powers—consisting mainly of Germany, Italy, and Japan—and the Allies—primarily France...
</Question>
<Choice>World War II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1926–90), U.S. clergyman and civil rights leader, born in Linden, Ala.; Alabama State University 1950; Baptist clergyman; close associate of Martin Luther King, Jr., he was a founder and president of Southern Christian Leadership Conference 1975–90; took part in civil rights marches during 1960s, led bus boycott in Montgomery, Ala. 1956–57.
</Question>
<Choice>Abernathy, Ralph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1904–1971). One of the great contributions to peace after World War II was made by the grandson of an ex-slave. He was Dr. Ralph Bunche, a former teacher.
</Question>
<Choice>Bunche, Ralph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1927–93), U.S. labor leader. Hailed by Senator Robert F. Kennedy as “[o]ne of the heroic figures of our time,” César Chávez was instrumental in changing the working conditions of migrant workers on American farms. An inspirational leader, he organized poor farm laborers into the nation's first successful union of agricultural workers, the...
</Question>
<Choice>Chávez, César</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The mass movement for racial equality in the United States known as the civil rights movement started in the late 1950s. Through nonviolent protest actions, it broke through the pattern of racial segregation, the practice in the South through which black Americans were not allowed to use the same schools, churches, restaurants, buses, and other...
</Question>
<Choice>The civil rights and black power movements</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In 1946 Sir Winston Churchill gave an address on foreign affairs at Westminster College in Fulton, Mo. In it he uttered this ominous sentence: “From Stettin in the Baltic to Trieste in the Adriatic, an iron curtain has descended across the Continent [of Europe].” These words marked the beginning of the Cold War. The term was first used again by...
</Question>
<Choice>Cold War</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1929–68). Inspired by the belief that love and peaceful protest could eliminate social injustice, Martin Luther King, Jr., became one of the outstanding black leaders in the United States. He aroused whites and blacks alike to protest racial discrimination, poverty, and war. A champion of nonviolent resistance to oppression, he was awarded the...
</Question>
<Choice>King, Martin Luther, Jr.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Early in the morning of June 25, 1950, the armed forces of Communist North Korea smashed across the 38th parallel of latitude in an invasion of the Republic of Korea (South Korea) that achieved complete surprise. Although attacks came all along the border, the major North Korean thrust was in the west of the Korean peninsula, toward Seoul, the...
</Question>
<Choice>Korean War</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1925–65). A black militant, Malcolm X championed the rights of African Americans and urged them to develop racial unity. He was known for his association first with the Nation of Islam, sometimes known as the Black Muslims, and later with the Organization of Afro-American Unity, which he founded after breaking with the Nation of Islam.
</Question>
<Choice>Malcolm X</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1908–93). U.S. lawyer Thurgood Marshall became the first African American justice of the Supreme Court of the United States. He was a champion of civil rights, both as a lawyer and later as a judge.
</Question>
<Choice>Marshall, Thurgood</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1908–57). The term McCarthyism will probably long endure in American politics as a synonym for “witch-hunt,” for making serious but unsubstantiated charges against people in public life. Joseph R. McCarthy served as United States senator from Wisconsin from January 1947 until his death on May 2, 1957. His career in the Senate was rather quiet...
</Question>
<Choice>McCarthy, Joseph R.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The North Atlantic Treaty Organization is a political and military alliance between the United States, Canada, and numerous European countries. Established in 1949 as a defense against the Soviet Union and its eastern European allies, NATO changed its membership and its goals following the breakup of the Soviet Union in 1991. NATO headquarters...
</Question>
<Choice>North Atlantic Treaty Organization</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
“The liberation of Kuwait has begun.” With that announcement, White House Press Secretary Marlin Fitzwater broke the news to the American public that war against Iraq had been launched by armed forces of the United Nations. The date was Jan. 16, 1991. The war began about 2:40 AM on January 17 Iraq time, or 6:40 PM EST on January 16 in the...
</Question>
<Choice>Persian Gulf War</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(born 1937). A four-star U.S. general and statesman, Colin Powell was the first African American to serve as chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff (1989–93) and secretary of state (2001–05). He was highly regarded by both the public and fellow politicians for his integrity and dedication to service.
</Question>
<Choice>Powell, Colin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
There were four countries that were divided during the years after World War II as the result of global Communist strategy: China, Germany, Korea, and Vietnam. Until formal reunification in 1976, Vietnam was split at the 17th parallel of latitude into North Vietnam, with a Communist government, and South Vietnam, with a republican government...
</Question>
<Choice>Vietnam War</Choice>
</item>  
<item>
<Question>
As first vice president and second president of the United States, John Adams was one of the founding fathers of the new nation. He was a delegate of the Continental Congress from 1774 to 1777 and one of only two presidents whose signature appears on the Declaration of Independence. Adams also participated in negotiating the 1783 Treaty of Paris...
</Question>
<Choice>Adams, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Eldest son of John Adams, the second president of the United States, John Quincy Adams followed in his father's footsteps to serve as the sixth president of the United States, from 1825 to 1829. The younger Adams achieved very few of his plans for improvements within the country. From the outset of his presidency, he faced unmerciful scrutiny...
</Question>
<Choice>Adams, John Quincy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1829–86). On the evening of Sept. 19, 1881, Vice-President Chester A. Arthur was in his home at 123 Lexington Avenue in New York City. Through the open windows he could hear newsboys shouting, “President Garfield is dying!” Around midnight he received a telegram from the members of James A. Garfield's Cabinet informing him of the president's...
</Question>
<Choice>Arthur, Chester</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
When James Buchanan became president in 1857 he had a record of 42 years of almost continuous public service. Even with this long experience, he was not a successful leader in a time of great crisis for the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>Buchanan, James</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
After serving two terms as vice president under Ronald Reagan, George Bush was elected the 41st president of the United States in 1988. For the first time since Martin Van Buren won in 1836, a sitting vice president succeeded directly to the presidency through an election rather than through the death or resignation of the incumbent. Bush, the...
</Question>
<Choice>Bush, George</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
George W. Bush, the oldest son of former U.S. President George Bush, emerged from the shadow of his famous father to be elected president himself in 2000. As a popular governor of Texas, Bush had won national attention as a so-called “new Republican” who combined traditional Republican party values with a self-described “compassionate conservative...
</Question>
<Choice>Bush, George W.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In November 1976 Jimmy Carter was elected the 39th president of the United States. His emphasis on morality in government and his concern for social welfare appealed to voters who were disturbed by corruption in government and economic problems.
</Question>
<Choice>Carter, Jimmy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Democrats from all parts of the country crowded into Washington to witness the presidential inauguration of March 4, 1885. The party was jubilant. For the first time since the Civil War a Democrat had won the presidency. Grover Cleveland, a powerful personality, had revived the party. He was a man of strong common sense, simple honesty, and...
</Question>
<Choice>Cleveland, Grover</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Emphasizing change and a “new covenant” between citizens and government, Governor Bill Clinton of Arkansas was elected the 42nd president of the United States in 1992. He was one of the youngest men and the first Democrat since 1976 to be elected to the country's highest office.
</Question>
<Choice>Clinton, Bill</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The sixth vice-president to become president at the death of the chief executive was Calvin Coolidge. He took the oath of office as the 30th president at 2:47 AM, on Aug. 3, 1923, a few hours after President Warren G. Harding died.
</Question>
<Choice>Coolidge, Calvin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In World War II Gen. Dwight D. Eisenhower became one of the most successful commanders in history. After the war he added to his military reputation by his work as Army chief of staff. Later he became the first head of the armies of the North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO). Turning to politics in 1952, Eisenhower proved to be a successful...
</Question>
<Choice>Eisenhower, Dwight D.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In 1850 the United States was close to civil war over the thorny problems of slavery. A proposed compromise had touched off the greatest political storm in the nation's history. Amid this bitter struggle President Zachary Taylor suddenly died on July 9, 1850. Succeeding to the presidency was Vice-President Millard Fillmore, a Whig from New York...
</Question>
<Choice>Fillmore, Millard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
When Gerald R. Ford became the 38th president of the United States on Aug. 9, 1974, the nation had for the first time in its history an appointed chief executive. He took leadership of the country when his predecessor, Richard M. Nixon, became the first United States president to resign.
</Question>
<Choice>Ford, Gerald R.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Born in a log cabin, James Abram Garfield rose by his own efforts to become a college president, a major general in the Civil War, a leader in Congress, and finally president of the United States. Four months after his inauguration, he was shot by an assassin. After weeks of suffering he died.
</Question>
<Choice>Garfield, James A.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
From humble beginnings, Ulysses S. Grant rose to command all the Federal armies in the Civil War and lead them to victory. So great was his popularity that the people twice elected him to the presidency.
</Question>
<Choice>Grant, Ulysses S.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
"Back to normalcy" was the campaign slogan of Warren G. Harding, 29th president of the United States. War-weary American voters of 1920 liked the idea so much that they elected this Ohio newspaper publisher by a plurality of 7 million votes.
</Question>
<Choice>Harding, Warren G.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nearly half a million people stood in the rain to watch the inauguration of Benjamin Harrison in 1889. This was the nation's centennial inauguration. Just 100 years earlier George Washington had become the first president of the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>Harrison, Benjamin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On March 4, 1841, General William Henry Harrison rode briskly down Pennsylvania Avenue in Washington, D.C., to be inaugurated ninth president of the United States. Slender and slightly stooped, the victor of the battle of Tippecanoe was 68 years old—the oldest man to be elected president in the 19th century. Just one month later, on April 4, he...
</Question>
<Choice>Harrison, William Henry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The presidential election of 1876 between Rutherford B. Hayes and Samuel Tilden was the most bitterly contested in United States history. Both the Democrats and the Republicans accused each other of fraud. Not until March 2, two days before President Grant's term expired, was the issue at last settled. The electoral commission decided in favor of...
</Question>
<Choice>Hayes, Rutherford B.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
When United States voters elected Herbert Hoover 31st president in 1928, the country was enjoying an industrial and financial boom. Within seven months of his taking office, however, the country was swallowed up in a depression that swept the entire world. He devised emergency measures in both the domestic and the foreign fields. Conditions...
</Question>
<Choice>Hoover, Herbert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
With a humble political background, Andrew Jackson introduced a new type of democracy in the country when he became the seventh president of the United States in 1829. Rather than winning an election through the traditional backing of a strong political party, Jackson triumphed by a direct appeal to a mass of people. He was the first president...
</Question>
<Choice>Jackson, Andrew</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The author of the Declaration of Independence in 1776, Thomas Jefferson was the third president of the United States, serving from 1801 to 1809. During his presidency the territory of the United States doubled with the Louisiana Purchase. To investigate the vastness of this newly acquired land in the West, he dispatched two of the most famous...
</Question>
<Choice>Jefferson, Thomas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Andrew Johnson became a public figure during the nation's greatest crisis—the American Civil War. Although he came from the slave state of Tennessee, Johnson refused to resign as United States senator when the state seceded; instead, he worked to preserve the Union. For his efforts he won the vice-presidency, taking office in March 1865. Six...
</Question>
<Choice>Johnson, Andrew</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At 2:38 PM, on Nov. 22, 1963, Lyndon B. Johnson took the oath of office as 36th president of the United States. On his right stood his wife, Lady Bird. On his left stood Jacqueline Kennedy, stony-faced with shock. Less than two hours earlier, President John F. Kennedy had died in a Dallas hospital from an assassin's bullets. He had been shot...
</Question>
<Choice>Johnson, Lyndon B.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1917–63). In November 1960, at the age of 43, John F. Kennedy became the youngest man ever elected president of the United States. Theodore Roosevelt had become president at 42 when President William McKinley was assassinated, but he was not elected at that age. On Nov. 22, 1963, Kennedy was shot to death in Dallas, Tex., the fourth United...
</Question>
<Choice>Kennedy, John F.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The 16th president of the United States, Abraham Lincoln not only ranks among the greatest of all American statesmen. Many historians also place him among the greatest men of all time. Lincoln came to the presidency at a time of great crisis, with the country at the brink of a civil war that threatened to split North from South. Combining his...
</Question>
<Choice>Lincoln, Abraham</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Father of the Constitution, James Madison was the fourth president of the United States, serving from 1809 to 1817. Succeeding Thomas Jefferson as president, Madison was confronted with British naval threats overseas and hostile Native Americans stirred by British resentment of the United States. These factors contributed to the War of...
</Question>
<Choice>Madison, James</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The 25th president of the United States was William McKinley. He was the leader of the nation when, at the end of the 19th century, it suddenly became a world power by making territorial acquisitions overseas following the Spanish American War.
</Question>
<Choice>McKinley, William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The fifth president of the United States was James Monroe, whose most celebrated achievement during his administration (1817–25) was the proposal of the Monroe Doctrine in 1823. It was a basic policy for the defense of North and South America against foreign intrusion. His two terms as president brought growing national wealth, strong westward...
</Question>
<Choice>Monroe, James</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first president of the United States to resign from office was Richard M. Nixon. Before his mid-term retirement in 1974, he had been only the second president to face impeachment.
</Question>
<Choice>Nixon, Richard M.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(born 1961). In only four years Barack Obama made an improbable rise from the state legislature of Illinois to the highest office of the United States. The first African American to win the presidency, he made history with his resounding victory in the election of 2008. His eloquent message of hope and change attracted voters across the country...
</Question>
<Choice>Obama, Barack</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In 1852 the Democrats could not agree on one of their party leaders for a presidential nomination. They finally turned to a little-known New Hampshire lawyer, Franklin Pierce, as their candidate.
</Question>
<Choice>Pierce, Franklin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
“Who is James K. Polk?” people asked when he was nominated for president by the Democrats. It was a reasonable question, for Polk was the first “dark horse”—compromise candidate—to be nominated.
</Question>
<Choice>Polk, James K.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In a stunning electoral landslide, Ronald Reagan was elected the 40th president of the United States in 1980. A former actor known for his folksy charm and confident ease as a public speaker, the Great Communicator, as he was sometimes called, won the votes of divergent groups who had not traditionally supported the Republican party. He defeated...
</Question>
<Choice>Reagan, Ronald</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Everyone had strong feelings about Franklin D. Roosevelt during his 12 years as president. Many people hated him. They thought he was destroying the country and the American way of life. Most people loved him. They believed he was a great president, truly interested in people.
</Question>
<Choice>Roosevelt, Franklin D.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The youngest president of the United States was Theodore Roosevelt. He had been vice-president under William McKinley. He came into office in 1901, just before his 43rd birthday, when McKinley was killed by an anarchist. He was elected in his own right in 1904.
</Question>
<Choice>Roosevelt, Theodore</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The only man in the nation to hold its two highest offices was William Howard Taft. He was the 27th president of the United States and later (1921–30) the chief justice of the United States Supreme Court. No man was better fitted for these posts by long years of experience. He had been in public office almost continuously since 1881. He was the...
</Question>
<Choice>Taft, William Howard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first United States president elected after the Mexican War was a popular hero of that war, General Zachary Taylor. After 40 years in the army, he became the first man to occupy the nation's highest office without previous political experience. The biggest problem he faced was how to organize the large Southwest territory acquired from Mexico...
</Question>
<Choice>Taylor, Zachary</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
It was late afternoon of a warm spring day. Vice-President Harry S. Truman had just finished listening to a Senate debate. He was given a telephone message. It asked him to get to the White House as soon as possible. President Franklin D. Roosevelt had died at Warm Springs, Ga. That evening, April 12, 1945, at 7:09 P.M., Harry S. Truman took the...
</Question>
<Choice>Truman, Harry S.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Tall, soft-spoken John Tyler was never expected to be president of the United States. When he was elected vice-president in 1840, with William Henry Harrison as president, he was just a political pawn. Harrison, however, died after only a month in office, and Tyler became president—the first vice-president to succeed to the presidency by the...
</Question>
<Choice>Tyler, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first president born as a United States citizen was Martin Van Buren, who was the eighth president of the United States and one of the founders of the Democratic party. Before his term in 1837–41, the first seven presidents had been born prior to the signing of the Declaration of Independence, making them British subjects at birth.
</Question>
<Choice>Van Buren, Martin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Many United States presidents were honored for their great achievements, and George Washington's achievements distinguished him as the Father of His Country. Washington was commander in chief of the Continental Army during the American Revolution, chairman of the convention that wrote the United States Constitution, and the first president of the...
</Question>
<Choice>Washington, George</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The president who led the nation through the hard years of World War I was Woodrow Wilson. He was probably the only president who was a brilliant student and teacher as well as a statesman. He had been a college professor, president of Princeton University, and the author of books on American government. He had also been governor of New Jersey...
</Question>
<Choice>Wilson, Woodrow</Choice>
</item>
</topics>