<topics>
<item>
<Question>
Two groups of chemical compounds called acids and bases have many members that react together to produce new products. Acids, bases, and the products of their reactions are vital to many life processes and are valuable to industry.
</Question>
<Choice>acids and bases</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
During the Middle Ages there existed a kind of primitive science called alchemy. Its objective was to discover a substance called the philosophers' stone. This elusive material was thought to transform common metals such as lead into silver or gold. Another objective of the alchemists' researches was the “elixir of life”—a potion that would cure...
</Question>
<Choice>alchemy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Any substance that cannot be decomposed into simpler substances by ordinary chemical processes is defined as a chemical element. Only 94 such substances are known to exist in nature. They are found either chemically free, such as the oxygen in air, or combined with other elements, such as the hydrogen and oxygen in water. About 20 additional...
</Question>
<Choice>chemical elements</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Minerals are essential to the life of plants and animals. Most plants get minerals from the soil. Animals, including humans, obtain them from plants, vegetables, and fruits or from the milk, eggs, and meat of plant-eating animals (see food and nutrition). Industry is equally dependent upon an abundant supply of minerals. The science of mineralogy...
</Question>
<Choice>minerals</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The smallest units into which a compound can be divided without changing its physical and chemical properties are molecules. They are formed from combinations of atoms, the basic building blocks of all matter (see Atomic Particles).
</Question>
<Choice>molecule</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Throughout recorded history human beings have marveled at the universe and have tried to describe and to understand it and their place within it. Furthermore, every culture has tried to explain the universe and to give a unified picture of natural phenomena.
</Question>
<Choice>atomic particles</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1885–1962). One of the foremost scientists of the 20th century, the Nobel prizewinning physicist Niels Bohr was the first to apply the quantum theory to atomic structure. His interpretation of the meaning of quantum physics was to become a basic tenet of the science. (See also Quantum Mechanics.)
</Question>
<Choice>Bohr, Niels</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1627–91), British scientist, seventh son of Richard Boyle, first earl of Cork, born in Lismore Castle at Lismore, Ireland, in present county of Waterford; settled at Oxford 1654 and did much of his work there; to London 1668; elected president of Royal Society 1680 but declined honor because of scruple against taking oaths
</Question>
<Choice>Boyle, Robert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1811–99). The gas-burning stoves and the common blowtorch of today are both monuments to Robert Wilhelm Bunsen, a German chemist. He also helped develop the method of spectrum analysis which yields clues to the constitution and the motions of the stars. At the outset of his career he discovered that hydrated ferric (iron) oxide is an antidote...
</Question>
<Choice>Bunsen, Robert Wilhelm</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A substance able to increase the rate of a chemical reaction without itself being consumed or changed by the reacting chemicals is called a catalyst. The action of a catalyst is called catalysis. Catalysts are used by chemists to speed up chemical reactions that otherwise would be inconveniently slow. The exact mechanisms of catalytic actions are...
</Question>
<Choice>catalyst</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Many common substances consist of solid particles, liquid droplets, or gas bubbles much bigger than ordinary molecules but much too small to be seen, even with the aid of most microscopes. Such particles range in size from about 0.00000004 to 0.0004 inch. Usually these tiny bits of matter, called colloids, are dispersed throughout another...
</Question>
<Choice>colloid</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The ancient Greeks used the word krystallos to mean both ice and quartz. They thought that quartz was simply another form of ice that had become permanently solid. In today's world a crystal is commonly considered to be a solid object with symmetrically arranged flat surfaces that meet in straight lines and sharp corners. Everyone has seen...
</Question>
<Choice>crystal</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
It is an unusual distinction for four members of one family to win Nobel prizes in science. The family to whom these honors came was that of the Curies, four individuals whose lives and work form a significant part of the history of nuclear physics in the 20th century.
</Question>
<Choice>Curie family</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1791–1867). The English physicist and chemist Michael Faraday made many notable contributions to chemistry and electricity. When the great scientist Sir Humphry Davy was asked what he considered his greatest discovery, he answered, “Michael Faraday.”
</Question>
<Choice>Faraday, Michael</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The modern idea of the nature of a chemical compound—a single substance containing fixed proportions of two or more elements—was adopted early in the 19th century. The number of known compounds then was growing fast as chemists learned to separate and analyze the substances found in nature. To organize and simplify the facts concerning these...
</Question>
<Choice>inorganic chemistry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1743–94). One of the most honored men in the history of science is the Frenchman Antoine Laurent Lavoisier. For more than a century before his day, chemists had been hampered by a false theory about fire and the burning of matter. By revealing the truth about fire and burning, Lavoisier helped chemistry make its remarkable advance from that...
</Question>
<Choice>Lavoisier, Antoine Laurent</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Carbon unites with many elements to form a great variety of compounds that are found in such substances as coal, petroleum, fabrics, plastics, and rubber. Other carbon compounds include plant and animal tissues, sugars, proteins, starches, and cellulose. About 1 million carbon compounds are known. The substances that contain carbon are called...
</Question>
<Choice>organic chemistry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1822–95). The French chemist Louis Pasteur devoted his life to solving practical problems of industry, agriculture, and medicine. His discoveries have saved countless lives and created new wealth for the world. Among his discoveries are the pasteurization process and ways of preventing silkworm diseases, anthrax, chicken cholera, and rabies.
</Question>
<Choice>Pasteur, Louis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The arrangement of chemical elements started with Dmitri Mendeleev, a Russian chemist. In 1869 he arranged all the known chemical elements in the order of increasing atomic weights. He found that, for the first 20, each one resembled the eighth element following it in appearance, properties, and activity. Thus lithium, sodium, and potassium are...
</Question>
<Choice>periodic table</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1733–1804). A clergyman who at one time was driven from his home because of his liberal politics, Joseph Priestley is remembered principally for his contributions to science. For his best-known accomplishment—the discovery of oxygen—he must share the credit with the Swedish chemist Carl Wilhelm Scheele, who is believed to have made the same...
</Question>
<Choice>Priestley, Joseph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The word protein comes from the Greek work proteios, meaning “primary.” Proteins are large organic compounds essential to life. They are made up of complex combinations of amino acids and are the most common macromolecules found in cells.
</Question>
<Choice>protein</Choice>
</item>
</topics>