<topics>
<Chapter>Mathematics</Chapter>
<item>
<Question>
(1802–29). The Norwegian mathematician Niels Henrik Abel made a remarkable series of contributions that were not fully recognized during his lifetime. He is known for his work with integral equations—mathematical expressions that are used to compute the area beneath a curve. Integral equations have broad practical application in surveying and...
</Question>
<Choice>Abel, Niels Henrik</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An important branch of mathematics, algebra today is studied not only in high school and college but, increasingly, in the lower grades as well. Taught with insight and understanding of the new mathematics programs, it can be an enjoyable subject. Algebra is as useful as all the other branches of mathematics—to which it is closely related. For...
</Question>
<Choice>algebra</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(262?–190 BC). Admiring friends called him “The Great Geometer” for his numerous accomplishments in the field of geometry. Specifically, it was his theory of conic sections, elaborated in his major work, ‘Conics', that earned Apollonius of Perga the plaudits of his contemporaries.
</Question>
<Choice>Apollonius of Perga</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(287–212 BC). The first scientist to recognize and use the power of the lever was Archimedes. This gifted Greek mathematician and inventor once said, “Give me a place to stand and rest my lever on, and I can move the Earth.” He also invented the compound pulley and Archimedes' screw. Archimedes was a brilliant mathematician who helped develop the...
</Question>
<Choice>Archimedes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The foundation of all other branches of mathematics is arithmetic, the science of calculating with numbers. Without the ability to use numbers, it would not be possible to measure distance or tell time. People would not be able to figure out how many gallons per mile they get with an automobile; they would not be able to judge how tall they are...
</Question>
<Choice>arithmetic</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The field of mathematics called calculus deals with change in processes or systems. In science many quantities change as we deal with them. The heat in a billet of steel begins to lessen the instant the billet is poured from molten metal. The number of bacteria in a culture changes measurably every fraction of a second. So, likewise, does the...
</Question>
<Choice>calculus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1596–1650). Both modern philosophy and modern mathematics began with the work of René Descartes. He attempted to justify certain basic beliefs about human beings, the world, and God using a technique of systematic doubt that he invented. He also developed the first modern theory that mind and body are essentially different substances, a...
</Question>
<Choice>Descartes, René</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
It has been said that, next to the Bible, the ‘Elements' of Euclid is the most-translated, -published, and -studied book in the Western world. Of the author himself almost nothing is known. It is recorded that he founded and taught at a school of mathematics in Alexandria, Egypt, during the reign of Ptolemy I Soter, who ruled from 323 to about...
</Question>
<Choice>Euclid</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1707–83). The Swiss mathematician and physicist Leonhard Euler not only made important contributions to the subjects of geometry, calculus, mechanics, and number theory but also developed methods for solving problems in observa- tional astronomy. A founder of pure mathematics, he also demonstrated useful applications of mathematics in...
</Question>
<Choice>Euler, Leonhard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1601–65). One of the leading mathematicians of the 17th century was the Frenchman Pierre de Fermat. His work was all the more remarkable because mathematics was only his hobby. His profession was law. Independently of his great contemporary, René Descartes, he discovered the fundamental principles of analytic geometry. He is also regarded as...
</Question>
<Choice>Fermat, Pierre de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1777–1855). The German scientist and mathematician Carl Friedrich Gauss is frequently called the founder of modern mathematics. His work in astronomy and physics is nearly as significant as that in mathematics. He also contributed much to crystallography, optics, biostatistics, and mechanics.
</Question>
<Choice>Gauss, Carl Friedrich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The ancient branch of mathematics known as geometry deals with points, lines, surfaces, and solids—and their relationships. In particular, geometry may be thought of as offering (1) precise definitions of many different figures; (2) construction methods for drawing figures; (3) a wealth of facts about the figures; and, most important, (4) ways to...
</Question>
<Choice>geometry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1736–1813). By the time he was a teenager, the mathematical genius of Lagrange was already apparent. In his lifetime he became one of the preeminent mathematicians of the time, one who excelled in all areas of the subject, especially analysis, number theory, and analytical and celestial mechanics. His major work, ‘Analytical Mechanics...
</Question>
<Choice>Lagrange, Joseph-Louis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1646–1716). Although he was not an artist, Leibniz was in many other ways comparable to Leonardo da Vinci. He was recognized as the universal genius of his time, a philosopher and scientist who worked in the fields of mathematics, geology, theology, mechanics, history, jurisprudence, and linguistics.
</Question>
<Choice>Leibniz, Gottfried Wilhelm</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1642–1727). The chief figure of the scientific revolution of the 17th century was Sir Isaac Newton. He was a physicist and mathematician who laid the foundations of calculus, extended the understanding of color and light, studied the mechanics of planetary motion, and discovered the law of gravitation. His work established the commonly held...
</Question>
<Choice>Newton, Isaac</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
More than 5,000 years ago an Egyptian ruler recorded, perhaps with a bit of exaggeration, the capture of 120,000 prisoners, 400,000 oxen, and 1,422,000 goats. This event was inscribed on a ceremonial mace which now is in a museum in Oxford, England.
</Question>
<Choice>numbers and numeration sys</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1854–1912). An honored French mathematician, theoretical astronomer, and philosopher of science, Henri Poincaré was also a gifted writer. He wrote about science and mathematics in language that was easy for his readers to understand.
</Question>
<Choice>Poincaré, Henri</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hundreds of years ago mathematicians devised a way of measuring the uncertainties found in things such as games of chance and created a new branch of mathematics—probability. The principles of probability are widely used. In genetics, for example, probability is used to estimate the likelihood for brown-eyed parents to produce a blue-eyed child...
</Question>
<Choice>probability</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(580? BC–500? BC). The man who played a crucial role in formulating principles that influenced Plato and Aristotle was the Greek philosopher and mathematician Pythagoras. He founded the Pythagorean brotherhood, a group of his followers whose beliefs and ideas were rediscovered during the Renaissance and contributed to the development of...
</Question>
<Choice>Pythagoras</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Anyone who listens to the radio, watches television, and reads books, newspapers, and magazines cannot help but be aware of statistics, which is the science of collecting, analyzing, presenting, and interpreting data. Statistics appear in the claims of advertisers, in predictions of election results and opinion polls, in cost-of-living indexes...
</Question>
<Choice>statistics</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The building of the Egyptian pyramids may seem to have little in common with devising modern radar and H-bombs. But certain principles of mathematics enter into all such activities, because they are fundamentals of the physical universe. Many are used in the division of mathematics called trigonometry.
</Question>
<Choice>trigonometry</Choice>
</item>
</topics>