<topics>
<item>
<Question>
What do these seemingly unrelated experts have in common: the scientist studying the transmission of sound under water, the physician using ultrasonics to study the condition of an unborn child, the engineer developing techniques for quieting a noisy truck or providing good listening conditions for a concert hall, and the audiologist evaluating...
</Question>
<Choice>acoustics</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The study of matter at temperatures much colder than those that occur naturally on Earth is called cryogenics. In the cryogenic temperature range, air becomes a liquid or even a solid and living tissues freeze instantly. At the very lowest temperatures of the cryogenic temperature range, matter behaves strangely—liquids run uphill and electric...
</Question>
<Choice>cryogenics</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
It is an unusual distinction for four members of one family to win Nobel prizes in science. The family to whom these honors came was that of the Curies, four individuals whose lives and work form a significant part of the history of nuclear physics in the 20th century.
</Question>
<Choice>Curie family</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1879–1955). Any list of the greatest thinkers in history will contain the name of the brilliant physicist Albert Einstein. His theories of relativity led to entirely new ways of thinking about time, space, matter, energy, and gravity. Einstein's work led to such scientific advances as the control of atomic energy and to some of the...
</Question>
<Choice>Einstein, Albert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Electricity is a form of energy associated with the atomic particles called electrons and protons. In particular, electricity involves the movement or accumulation of negatively charged electrons in relation to positively charged protons. The world's modern economies, with their industrial, transportation, and communication systems, were made...
</Question>
<Choice>electricity</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A rock falling off a cliff is different from the same rock lying on the ground below. The lively child eager to join his playmates after a night's rest and a hearty breakfast is different from the child who can barely keep his eyes open after dinner. A glowing light bulb is different from the same bulb when the electricity is switched off. In...
</Question>
<Choice>energy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1901–54). On Dec. 2, 1942, the first man-made and self-sustaining nuclear chain reaction was achieved, resulting in the controlled release of nuclear energy. This feat took place in a squash court beneath the stands of an unused football stadium at the University of Chicago. The scientist who led the achievement was Enrico Fermi. The first...
</Question>
<Choice>Fermi, Enrico</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
When cavemen learned to make and use fire, they could start to live in civilized ways. With fire, they were able to cook their food so that it was easier to eat and tasted better. By the light of torches, men could more easily find their way at night. They could also improve their wooden tools by hardening the points in fire. With fire to keep...
</Question>
<Choice>fire</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1564–1642). Modern physics owes its beginning to Galileo, who was the first astronomer to use a telescope. By discovering four satellites of the planet Jupiter, he gave visual evidence that supported the Copernican theory (see Astronomy). Galileo thus helped disprove much of the medieval thinking in science.
</Question>
<Choice>Galileo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The force that causes objects to drop and water to run downhill is the same force that holds the Earth, the sun, and the stars together and keeps the moon and artificial satellites in their orbits. Gravitation, the attraction of all matter for all other matter, is both the most familiar of the natural forces and the least understood.
</Question>
<Choice>gravitation</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
All living things need heat. Heat is a form of energy that is transferred from one body to another because of a difference in temperature. It is the cause of certain natural changes which occur in an endless cycle.
</Question>
<Choice>heat</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1901–76). For his work on quantum mechanics, the German physicist Werner Heisenberg received the Nobel prize for physics in 1932. He will probably be best remembered, however, for developing the uncertainty (or indeterminacy) principle, the concept that the behavior of subatomic particles can be predicted only on the basis of probability (see...
</Question>
<Choice>Heisenberg, Werner</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1629–95). The shape of the rings of Saturn was discovered by Christiaan Huygens, a Dutch astronomer, mathematician, and physicist. Huygens also developed the wave theory of light and made significant contributions to the science of dynamics and the use of the pendulum in clocks. His reputation in mathematics as well as his wealth and parentage...
</Question>
<Choice>Huygens, Christiaan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first men to land on the moon left a quartz reflector—the lunar laser reflector. Later, a beam of light was sent from Earth all the way to the moon, where it bounced off the reflector and returned to Earth. The instrument that produced this intense beam of light was a laser (from light amplification by stimulated emission of radiation).
</Question>
<Choice>laser and maser</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
For thousands of years humans could observe only the things that could be seen with unaided eyes. Today millions of people use lenses as eyeglasses and contact lenses to correct defective vision. In telescopes lenses help astronomers to study the stars and planets; however, the most advanced telescopes now use curved mirrors rather than glass...
</Question>
<Choice>lens</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the most familiar and important forms of energy is light. Nothing is visible to humans when light is totally absent. But light is even more important for other reasons. Many scientists believe that millions of years ago light from the sun triggered the chemical reactions that led to the development of life on Earth. Without light the...
</Question>
<Choice>light</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In ancient times men knew of a special kind of rock that could pull other rocks of the same kind and pieces of iron toward itself. Such rocks were called lodestones. In modern times man uses the same force exerted by the ancient lodestones to generate electric power, to store information in computers, and to study the secrets of the universe. The...
</Question>
<Choice>magnets and magnetism</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1874–1937). The brilliant man who transformed an experiment into the practical invention of radio was Guglielmo Marconi. He shared the 1909 Nobel prize in physics for the development of wireless telegraphy.
</Question>
<Choice>Marconi, Guglielmo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An electron, a grain of sand, an elephant, and a giant quasar at the edge of the visible universe all have one thing in common—they are composed of matter. A beam of light, the motion of a falling stone, and the explosion of a stick of dynamite all have one thing in common—they are expressions of energy. Energy and matter together make up the...
</Question>
<Choice>matter</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1831–79). Scientists of the Royal Society of Edinburgh must have been stunned to discover that the paper submitted to them in 1845 was the work of a 14-year-old boy. James Clerk Maxwell's first scientific paper, “On the Description of Oval Curves,” marked the beginning of an impressive career in science.
</Question>
<Choice>Maxwell, James Clerk</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The acceleration of an automobile, the recoil of a fired gun, the motion of a space rocket, and the action of a spinning top—all can be analyzed and understood through the science of mechanics. In all these actions, certain general principles, or laws of nature, hold true. These principles make up the science of mechanics. Mechanics deals with...
</Question>
<Choice>mechanics</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1642–1727). The chief figure of the scientific revolution of the 17th century was Sir Isaac Newton. He was a physicist and mathematician who laid the foundations of calculus, extended the understanding of color and light, studied the mechanics of planetary motion, and discovered the law of gravitation. His work established the commonly held...
</Question>
<Choice>Newton, Isaac</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Energy is produced when the nuclei of atoms are either split (fission) or united (fusion). Fission occurs when a heavy nucleus splits into two or more lighter segments. Fusion is the combining of two light nuclei to form a single, heavier nucleus. The energy released by the fission or the fusion of nuclei, in the form of heat, light, or other...
</Question>
<Choice>nuclear energy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The world is made up of exceedingly small units called atoms and of groups of atoms called molecules that exist in dazzling variety. At the center of each atom is a tiny core called a nucleus that is surrounded by a cloud of electrons—electrically charged particles that move in the outer regions of the atom. Nuclear physics is the study of the...
</Question>
<Choice>nuclear physics</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Rainbows, mirrors, and holograms are manifestations of the properties of light. Optics, the study of light, is a diverse field of science concerned with how light is produced and transmitted and how it interacts with matter. Light sometimes behaves like a particle and sometimes like a wave. When it is emitted or absorbed by atoms, light behaves...
</Question>
<Choice>optics</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1858–1947). Awarded the Nobel prize for physics in 1918, German physicist Max Planck is best remembered as the originator of the quantum theory (see Quantum Mechanics). His work helped usher in a new era in theoretical physics and revolutionized the scientific community's understanding of atomic and subatomic processes.
</Question>
<Choice>Planck, Max</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
When a gas is heated by many thousands of degrees, the individual atoms collide with enough violence to knock electrons free, resulting in a collection of positively charged ions and free, negatively charged electrons. The gas is said to be ionized, and when a sizable number of the atoms become ionized, the gas is called a plasma.
</Question>
<Choice>plasma and plasma physics</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Classical physics, the body of physics developed until about the turn of the 20th century, cannot account for the behavior of matter and light at extremely small scales. The branch of physics concerned with atomic and subatomic systems is known as quantum mechanics. Its aim is to account for the properties of molecules and atoms and their even...
</Question>
<Choice>quantum mechanics</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The warmth of the sun, an X ray taken in a doctor's office, the sound of a guitar, and electricity generated in a nuclear power plant all have one thing in common. They are results of radiation. Radiation is the movement, or propagation, of energy from one place to another. From a human perspective, some radiation is directly useful, some...
</Question>
<Choice>radiation</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Among the outstanding advances in science will always stand Albert Einstein's theories of relativity—the problem of how physical laws and measurements change when considered by observers in various states of motion. These theories forced revision of all fundamental thinking about time and space. They brought changes in many statements of natural...
</Question>
<Choice>relativity</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Computers, spaceships, color television sets, telephones, satellites, and hearing aids all owe many of their recent advances to the young science of solid state physics. Solid state physicists study the internal structures of solids. They try to understand how the behavior of atoms and molecules within solids gives the solids their observed...
</Question>
<Choice>solid state physics</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On freezing winter days, a pail of water left outdoors soon changes in the way it looks and feels. Its chemical structure—H2O—remains the same, but its physical state is different. It has frozen and turned to ice. It has changed from a liquid to a solid.
</Question>
<Choice>solids</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Every kind of sound is produced by vibration. The sound source may be a violin, an automobile horn, or a barking dog. Whatever it is, some part of it is vibrating while it is producing sound. The vibrations from the source disturb the air in such a way that sound waves are produced. These waves travel out in all directions, expanding in...
</Question>
<Choice>sound</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A total, or perfect, vacuum would be a space from which all matter has been removed. This includes solids, liquids, and gases (including air). It would be a space that contains “nothing.” Since there is no method or device that can remove all matter from an enclosed space, a perfect vacuum is unknown and has only theoretical meaning. It was once...
</Question>
<Choice>vacuum</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The earliest units of weights and measures were derived from the human body and from natural surroundings. The cubit, for example, was defined as the distance between a man's elbow and the tip of his middle finger. This unit, which probably originated as early as 3000 BC, was standardized so precisely by the Egyptians that they could use it in...
</Question>
<Choice>weights and measures</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Since their discovery in 1895, X rays have proved a vital tool of science, making it possible to examine previously hidden worlds ranging from the tiniest of atoms to the most distant galaxies in space. Like light and radio waves, X rays are a type of electromagnetic radiation—oscillating electric and magnetic fields traveling at the speed of...
</Question>
<Choice>x rays</Choice>
</item>
</topics>