<topics>
<item>
<Question>
One reason human beings can thrive in all kinds of climates is that they can control the qualities of the air in the enclosed spaces in which they live. Air conditioning is the use of mechanical systems to achieve that control in such places as homes, offices, theaters, institutions, factories, airplanes, and automobiles. The most familiar type...
</Question>
<Choice>air conditioning</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
When Wilbur and Orville Wright mastered the secret of flight, they did not try to imitate the flight of birds but they built a machine for flying. That is exactly what an airplane is, a flying machine. An airplane is heavier than air and yet it flies. It does this by propelling itself through the air and by supporting itself on wings so shaped...
</Question>
<Choice>airplane</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Soon after automobiles were mass-produced early in the 20th century, they began to change styles of living. The automobile is still causing changes. Easy access by passenger car or by truck helps to determine where people build homes, buy food, seek recreation, and locate businesses. The term automotive means “self-propelling.” It generally...
</Question>
<Choice>automobile</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
For centuries people have sought ever more convenient and fast ways to travel. The development of the airplane in the 20th century was a major milestone in that search, allowing much faster travel than past generations thought possible (see airplane). It also led to the new industry of aviation, which deals with the development and operation of...
</Question>
<Choice>aviation</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1792–1871). Although he was a 19th-century mathematician, Charles Babbage is credited with inventing the modern computer. He also designed a type of speedometer and the cowcatcher (a sloping frame on the front of a locomotive that tosses obstacles off the railroad tracks).
</Question>
<Choice>Babbage, Charles</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
All Europe was excited in June 1783. The Montgolfier brothers of Annonay, France, had sent a large paper bag sailing upward 6,000 feet (1,800 meters) into the air. They had filled it with hot smoke from a straw fire. To most people of that day, the soaring bag seemed a miracle. Yet within 50 years inventors had developed most of the principles...
</Question>
<Choice>balloon and airship</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1847–1922). Other people before Bell had tried to transmit the human voice across distances. Others since have helped improve and perfect Bell's inventions. But Alexander Graham Bell will always be remembered as the father of the electric telephone (see Telephone).
</Question>
<Choice>Bell, Alexander Graham</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
When he was 21 years old, Thomas Edison took out his first patent. It was for an electric vote counter to be used in the United States House of Representatives. The machine worked perfectly, but the congressmen would not buy it. They did not want vote counting to be done quickly. Often the roll call was used for purposes of delay (filibustering).
</Question>
<Choice>Edison, Thomas Alva</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Television, stereophonic recording and playback, the computer, robots, and space probes are all products of electronics. Electronics is the branch of physics concerned with the generation and behavior of electrons, as in transistors and electron tubes. It is especially concerned with their use in electronic devices, in which electricity is used...
</Question>
<Choice>electronics</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A large, international computer network, the Internet links tens of millions of users around the world. It is used daily by many individuals for the main purposes of sending and receiving electronic mail (e-mail), obtaining mountains of information on almost any subject, or communicating with coworkers on projects. An Internet address is needed...
</Question>
<Choice>Internet</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Many objects too small to be seen with the unaided eye can be viewed through a microscope, an instrument that produces magnified images of such objects. The development of the microscope greatly affected human life. Before it was invented, little was known about tiny organisms such as bacteria and protozoa.
</Question>
<Choice>microscope</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The word photography comes from two ancient Greek words: photo, for “light,” and graph, for “drawing.” “Drawing with light” is a way of describing photography. When a photograph is made, light or some other form of radiant energy, such as X rays, is used to record a picture of an object or scene on a light-sensitive surface. Early photographs...
</Question>
<Choice>photography</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Today sea captains can guide their ships safely through a crowded harbor in dense fog, and pilots can land their planes through a thick overcast. An electronic system called radar makes this possible.
</Question>
<Choice>radar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The word “radio” evokes the broadcast stations this entry discusses, but in fact the term covers a huge spectrum of services and businesses. At its most basic, radio means the wireless transmission of information in any form—data, audio, or video.
</Question>
<Choice>radio</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The railroad is a form of land transportation that is found in almost every country in the world. Railroads serve many thousands of communities, from big cities in highly developed nations to tiny villages in remote areas. Railroads carry travelers to and from neighboring communities or on trips across whole continents. They carry raw materials...
</Question>
<Choice>railroad</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The cooling of substances or enclosed spaces to low temperatures is called refrigeration. Refrigeration is used most often to keep foods or medicines from spoiling, since bacterial growth is slowed at lower temperatures. A common example is the home refrigerator, in which foods can be stored for days at temperatures of around 40°?F (4°?C). Foods...
</Question>
<Choice>refrigeration</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The image usually conjured up by the word robot is that of a mechanical being, more or less human in shape. Common in science fiction, robots are generally depicted as working in the service of humanity, but often escaping the control of their human masters and doing them harm.
</Question>
<Choice>robot</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The development of advanced rocket technology in the 20th century transformed modern warfare and helped usher in the space age. Rockets are a special form of jet-propulsion device. They propel guided missiles, spacecraft launch vehicles, and firework skyrockets; the vehicles themselves are commonly called rockets, too. Sounding rockets carry...
</Question>
<Choice>rocket</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Of all the various telecommunications services in existence today, the one most used is the telephone. Although there have been striking advances in the way telephone messages are transmitted over long distances, the basic operation has remained little changed over many decades.
</Question>
<Choice>telephone</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Light and other kinds of electromagnetic radiation coming from the universe outside the Earth must travel enormous distances through space and time to reach observers. Only the brightest and nearest stars can be seen with the unaided eye. To see farther and to clarify and measure what is seen, a telescope is needed. The word telescope is derived...
</Question>
<Choice>telescope</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The idea of television existed long before its realization as a technology. The dream of transmitting images and sounds over great distances actually dates back to the 19th century, becoming an increasingly common aspiration of scientists and inventors in the United States, Europe, and Japan after the first telegraph line opened up the modern...
</Question>
<Choice>television</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Generally, a computer is any device that can perform numerical calculations—even an adding machine, an abacus, or a slide rule. Currently, however, the term usually refers to an electronic device that can perform automatically a series of tasks according to a precise set of instructions. The set of instructions is called a program, and the tasks...
</Question>
<Choice>computer</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1736–1819). It is sometimes said that James Watt got the idea for a steam engine while still a boy, watching steam lift the lid of his mother's teakettle. The truth is that Watt did not invent the steam engine; however, he made major improvements on the inefficient steam engine of his time.
</Question>
<Choice>Watt, James</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On a coastal sand dune near Kitty Hawk, N.C., on Dec. 17, 1903, two brothers, Orville and Wilbur Wright, realized one of mankind's earliest dreams: they flew. Although gliders were in existence, the Wright brothers made the world's first successful sustained and controlled flight of a motor-driven aircraft, the culmination of years of...
</Question>
<Choice>Wright, Orville and Wilbur</Choice>
</item>
</topics>