<topics>
<item>
<Question>
Four hundred million years ago the most advanced forms of life on Earth, the fishes, lived in the water. Plants and insects alone occupied the land until the appearance of the amphibians more than 350 million years ago. Almost all amphibians have features that fall between those of fishes and those of reptiles. The most commonly known amphibians...
</Question>
<Choice>amphibian</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Corals are small, marine animals that remain in one place throughout their adult lives and produce a hard skeleton made of calcium carbonate (CaCO3), or limestone. The skeletal material, which can be either internal or external, is also called coral. After the coral animal dies, the skeleton remains. Many species of corals grow in colonies that...
</Question>
<Choice>coral</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
There are more than 31,300 known species of animals included among the crustaceans. Crustaceans are covered by hard shells, called exoskeletons, as are all other members of their phylum, Arthropoda, which includes insects, centipedes, and spiders. The exoskeleton is composed of a tough, flexible substance called chitin and is jointed at many...
</Question>
<Choice>crustacean</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The largest ecosystem on Earth, and also the least explored, is the vast realm of the ocean known as the deep sea. It is home to billions of organisms adapted to its extreme conditions: profound to total darkness, crushing pressures, and cold temperatures. Deep-sea life also clusters around oceanic hot springs that spew extremely hot, mineral...
</Question>
<Choice>deep-sea life</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Although there were about 65,000 black rhinoceroses in the world in 1970, at the start of the 21st century there were fewer than 3,000 left. Even rarer was the mandrinette, a shrub from Mauritius with bright red flowers. Fewer than 50 of the plants were known in the wild. The black rhinoceros and the mandrinette are endangered species—they face a...
</Question>
<Choice>endangered species</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Among the most unusual of sea animals are the jellyfishes. Cousins of the jellyfishes are the corals and sea anemones. These three belong to the phylum of animals known as Coelenterata.
</Question>
<Choice>jellyfish</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The simple, animal-like organisms that make up the kingdom Protista are called protozoans. They were once thought to be the first animals to appear on Earth. The term protozoan comes from the Greek words protos, meaning “first,” and zoion, meaning “animal.” Although protozoans are often called one-celled animals, many biologists prefer to call...
</Question>
<Choice>protozoan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
From tidal pools on rocky shores to the depths of the oceans live beautiful flowerlike animals—the sea anemones. When the tide is out they look like sodden lumps of jelly, but as the water flows over them they expand into strange and lovely forms. Many kinds are found on both coasts of North America, but those in tropical waters are the most...
</Question>
<Choice>sea anemone</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
It would be quite a feat for a person to drink 64 glasses of water every day, but in effect that is just what some sponges do. They filter that much water through their bodies every 24 hours, absorbing oxygen from the water and feeding on waterborne food particles.
</Question>
<Choice>sponge</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Among the most widespread of marine animals, starfishes and sea urchins inhabit all seas except those of the polar regions. Despite their name, starfishes (also called sea stars) are not really fishes at all.
</Question>
<Choice>starfish and sea urchin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Adult animals that have soft, elongated, often tubelike bodies and that lack backbones are commonly called worms. Worms are so different from one another that zoologists do not classify them together in a single group; they place them in about a dozen different and often unrelated taxonomic groups called phyla. In everyday language the name worm...
</Question>
<Choice>worm</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
No other dinosaur has inspired more terror, awe, and imagination than Tyrannosaurus rex.
</Question>
<Choice>tyrannosaurus rex</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Elephants, the largest living land animals, belong to the scientific family Elephantidae.
</Question>
<Choice>elephant</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The word cattle was once used to describe all animals raised by humans.
</Question>
<Choice>cattle</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Flamingos are tall, brightly colored birds.</Question>
<Choice>flamingo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An African mammal, the giraffe is the tallest living animal.
</Question>
<Choice>giraffe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Bears loom large in legends and folk tales.</Question>
<Choice>bear</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The grasshopper is a leaping insect that is closely related to the cricket.
</Question>
<Choice>grasshopper</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Many people confuse rabbits with hares because the two look rather similar.
</Question>
<Choice>rabbit and hare</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>The hawk is a small to medium-sized bird of prey.</Question>
<Choice>hawk</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The jackal is a wolflike, meat-eating animal related to the dog.
</Question>
<Choice>jackal</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The kangaroo is possibly the best known of the marsupials, or animals that carry their young in a pouch.
</Question>
<Choice>kangaroo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Kangaroos, koalas, and opossums--these unique animals are all marsupials.
</Question>
<Choice>marsupial</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The dinosaur known as Triceratops somewhat resembled a modern rhinoceros.
</Question>
<Choice>triceratops</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Corals are small marine animals that stay in one place throughout their adult lives.
</Question>
<Choice>coral</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The leopard is a member of the cat family that is known for its spotted coat.
</Question>
<Choice>leopard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The lynx is a short-tailed cat of the family Felidae.
</Question>
<Choice>lynx</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Manatees are slow-moving, seal-shaped mammals.</Question>
<Choice>manatee</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Allosaurus was a fierce dinosaur that roamed the Earth before the similar but more well-known Tyrannosaurus rex appeared.
</Question>
<Choice>Allosaurus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The name mouse is used for many small rodents, or gnawing animals.
</Question>
<Choice>mouse</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Most members of the parrot family can be told apart from other birds by their noisy calls, colorful feathers, and curved beaks.
</Question>
<Choice>parrot family</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
For thousands of years people have had a unique relationship with the horse.
</Question>
<Choice>horse</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
With a huge fan of colorful tail feathers, the peacock is famous as an ornamental bird.
</Question>
<Choice>peacock</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Penguins are the only birds that can swim but cannot fly.
</Question>
<Choice>penguin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Stegosaurus was a heavily armored dinosaur.</Question>
<Choice>Stegosaurus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>The falcon is a member of the hawk family.</Question>
<Choice>falcon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The spiders called tarantulas were named after the city of Taranto, Italy, where the first tarantula bites were reported centuries ago.
</Question>
<Choice>tarantula</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The raccoon is a nocturnal omnivore, which means it is active at night and it eats both plants and animals.
</Question>
<Choice>raccoon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The term beetle refers to thousands of different insects.
</Question>
<Choice>beetle</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The rhinoceros, or rhino, is a bulky, hoofed animal.
</Question>
<Choice>rhinoceros</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The armored dinosaur known as Ankylosaurus had a tail that ended in a large, bony club.
</Question>
<Choice>Ankylosaurus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
With their long necks and graceful movements, swans are often described as stately or majestic as they swim on lakes, ponds, and rivers.
</Question>
<Choice>swan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The spider is the most common and varied of all the land predators.
</Question>
<Choice>spider</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Feared and misunderstood, snakes belong to a class of animals known as reptiles.
</Question>
<Choice>snakes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Fossils show that the first fish that can be identified as sharks lived about 300 million years ago.
</Question>
<Choice>shark</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Woodpeckers are best known for making holes in trees to find insects to eat.
</Question>
<Choice>woodpecker</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A member of the horse family, the zebra is known for its striking pattern of black and white stripes.
</Question>
<Choice>zebra</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Known for their brightly or strikingly colored wings, butterflies and moths are flying insects that come from caterpillars.
</Question>
<Choice>butterfly and moth</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The unusual mammal called the aardvark was named by South Africans in the early 19th century. In the local language, Afrikaans, 'aardvark' means 'earth pig'.
</Question>
<Choice>aardvark</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Famous for its supposed head-butting behavior, Pachycephalosaurus is considered by some to be the bighorn sheep of the dinosaur world.
</Question>
<Choice>Pachycephalosaurus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Closely related to crocodiles, alligators are large lizard-like animals with long, rounded snouts and powerful tails.
</Question>
<Choice>alligator</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An anaconda is a giant water-loving snake that is found in tropical South America.
</Question>
<Choice>anaconda</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The name panda is used for two mammals that live in Asia.
</Question>
<Choice>panda</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Baboons are large monkeys that move about both on the ground and in trees.
</Question>
<Choice>baboon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Birds that pursue other animals for food are called birds of prey.
</Question>
<Choice>birds of prey</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
For thousands of years eagles have held a special place in the human imagination because of their size, strength, and bold appearance.
</Question>
<Choice>eagle</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Humans have long been fascinated by monkeys, both as interesting creatures in their own right and as a source of information about the human species.
</Question>
<Choice>monkey</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The owl is a bird of prey that is nocturnal, or active at night
</Question>
<Choice>owl</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The so-called American buffalo that used to roam by the millions on the North American plains is actually a bison.
</Question>
<Choice>bison</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Although the North American bison is often called a buffalo, true buffalo come from much warmer lands in Asia and Africa.
</Question>
<Choice>buffalo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The name blackbird applies to several kinds of small birds in which the males are largely black.
</Question>
<Choice>blackbird</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Feared and misunderstood, snakes belong to a class of animals known as reptiles.
</Question>
<Choice>snakes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the earliest voices of spring in North America is that of the bluebird.
</Question>
<Choice>bluebird</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Oviraptor can be described as a dinosaur with the head of a parrot.
</Question>
<Choice>Oviraptor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first dinosaur in history to be described and named by scientists was Megalosaurus.
</Question>
<Choice>Megalosaurus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
For at least 4,000 years honeybees have been kept for their honey and for beeswax, a substance used to make candles, ointments, and many other products.
</Question>
<Choice>bee</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The coyote is the most common and widespread native North American relative of the dog.
</Question>
<Choice>coyote</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sometimes called the 'ship of the desert,' the camel is a large mammal that is well suited to living and working in hot, dry deserts.
</Question>
<Choice>camel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Cats have fascinated humans for thousands of years.
</Question>
<Choice>cat</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A group of various unrelated invertebrates, worms have soft, elongated bodies.
</Question>
<Choice>worm</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Long-necked birds with a loud, honking call, geese are equally at home on the land, on the water, or in the air.
</Question>
<Choice>goose</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The most humanlike of all animals, the ape is often termed anthropoid, meaning, 'resembling a human.'
</Question>
<Choice>Ape</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>The chimpanzee is an African great ape.</Question>
<Choice>Chimpanzee</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The second dinosaur ever to be discovered was Iguanodon.
</Question>
<Choice>Iguanodon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Cobras are deadly, poisonous snakes known for their ability to flatten their necks into the shape of a hood when threatened.
</Question>
<Choice>cobra</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>The crane is a tall, graceful, wading bird.</Question>
<Choice>crane</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The birds known as cuckoos are named for the sounds they make.
</Question>
<Choice>cuckoo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The dog is one of the most popular animals in the world.
</Question>
<Choice>Dog</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Known for their intelligence, playfulness, and friendliness toward humans, dolphins can often be seen swimming alongside boats or performing at aquariums.
</Question>
<Choice>Dolphin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The weasel family is one of the largest groups of meat-eating mammals on Earth.
</Question>
<Choice>Weasel family</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ants are social insects who live in organized colonies.
</Question>
<Choice>Ant</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A massive dinosaur, the Apatosaurus weighed as much as five adult elephants.
</Question>
<Choice>Apatosaurus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Stories about legendary animals abounded when much knowledge of the natural world was based on travelers' tales and rumor.
</Question>
<Choice>legendary animals</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Turtles are an ancient group of reptiles that developed when the dinosaurs were still alive.
</Question>
<Choice>turtle</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Among the many striking birds of the American tropics, the toucans stand out because of their enormous, brightly colored bills.
</Question>
<Choice>toucan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
With their distinctive, saberlike snouts, swordfish always seem ready for an underwater fencing match.
</Question>
<Choice>swordfish</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Despite their reputation, pigs are neither filthy nor stupid.
</Question>
<Choice>pig</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The most commonly displayed dinosaur in museums is Diplodocus.
</Question>
<Choice>Diplodocus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Closely related to spiders, ticks and mites are tiny creatures that usually live on other creatures.
</Question>
<Choice>tick and mite</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The journey of the salmon has fascinated people for centuries.
</Question>
<Choice>salmon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The sea animals known as whales are among the most fascinating members of the animal kingdom.
</Question>
<Choice>whale</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A popular pet, the guinea pig is also a valuable animal for medical research purposes.
</Question>
<Choice>guinea pig</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Crows are named after their typical call, which sounds like 'caw' or 'crah'.
</Question>
<Choice>crow</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Barracudas are among the most ferocious fish in tropical waters.
</Question>
<Choice>barracuda</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Antelopes are plant-eating animals known for their beauty, grace, and speed in running.
</Question>
<Choice>antelope</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Heavyset animals with a piglike appearance, the tapirs are actually related to horses and rhinoceroses.
</Question>
<Choice>tapir</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sloths are mammals that hang from tree branches and move very slowly.
</Question>
<Choice>sloth</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Otters are intelligent, friendly, and curious.</Question>
<Choice>otter</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The large, meat-eating dinosaur Ceratosaurus can be recognized by the large horn on its snout.
</Question>
<Choice>ceratosaurus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Related to frogs and toads, salamanders are tailed amphibians that look something like lizards.
</Question>
<Choice>salamander</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The amphibians known as toads are familiar to people all over the world.
</Question>
<Choice>toad</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
More than 30 different kinds of sea mammals are called seals.
</Question>
<Choice>seal</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Most of the animals known as amphibians can live on land or in the water.
</Question>
<Choice>amphibians</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>Lampreys are water creatures that resemble eels.</Question>
<Choice>lamprey</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the tallest of all dinosaurs, Brachiosaurus was built something like an enormous elephant with an extremely long neck.
</Question>
<Choice>Brachiosaurus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The wapiti is a North American deer that is often called the American elk.
</Question>
<Choice>wapiti</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A canary is a type of bird that belongs to the finch family.
</Question>
<Choice>canary</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A songbird of the finch family, the cardinal is sometimes called the redbird because of its striking color.
</Question>
<Choice>cardinal</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sheep are timid creatures that tend to graze in flocks.
</Question>
<Choice>sheep</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The boa constrictor is a large snake that kills its prey by coiling around it so tightly that it cannot breathe.
</Question>
<Choice>boa constrictor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The goldfinch is a songbird named for the yellow in its feathers.
</Question>
<Choice>goldfinch</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The rattlesnake is a kind of snake known as a viper.
</Question>
<Choice>rattlesnake</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>The only mammal that flies is the bat.</Question>
<Choice>bat</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The coelacanth is a rare fish thought to have been extinct for hundreds of millions of years.
</Question>
<Choice>coelacanth</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question/>
<Choice>Arachnids</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A robin hops about the lawn. It stops with its head tipped to one side. Suddenly it jabs at the ground and pulls out a worm. As the robin flies off you see its brick-red breast. It is carrying the worm to a nest full of hungry young robins.
</Question>
<Choice>Birds</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Many animals that live in water are called fish. Perch, crayfish, cuttlefish, jellyfish, starfish, and even whales and dolphins all live in water. Yet, of these animals, only the perch is a true fish. Whales and dolphins are warm-blooded mammals. The others belong to the great group of animals without backbones, called invertebrates.
</Question>
<Choice>Fish</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The world's most abundant creatures are the insects, whose known species outnumber all the other animals and the plants combined. Insects have been so successful in their fight for life that they are sometimes described as the human race's closest rivals for domination of the Earth. Entomologists, the scientists who study insects, have named...
</Question>
<Choice>Insects</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Despite their size differences, the great blue whale and the pygmy shrew have something in common: they are both members of a warm-blooded, air-breathing class of vertebrate (backboned) animals known as Mammalia, or mammals. In many ways mammals are the most highly developed of all creatures.
</Question>
<Choice>Mammals</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The large group of animals called mollusks live on land and in both fresh and salt water. They constitute the phylum Mollusca, a major group of animals known to have as many as 100,000 living species and more than 50,000 fossil forms. Most mollusks, including snails, clams, oysters, and mussels, have shells. A major group called the cephalopods...
</Question>
<Choice>Mollusks</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
According to fossil records, reptiles first appeared on Earth more than 300 million years ago. In fact, birds and mammals evolved from reptilian ancestors. Reptiles are distinguished from other vertebrates by the fact that they have dry scales covering their bodies. Reptiles are further distinguished from vertebrates lower on the evolutionary...
</Question>
<Choice>Reptiles</Choice>
</item>
</topics>