<topics>
<item>
<Question>
The many small bodies called asteroids are chunks of rock and metal that orbit the Sun. Most are found in the main asteroid belt, a doughnut-shaped zone between the orbits of Mars and Jupiter. Jupiter is the largest planet by far. Astronomers think that when the solar system was forming, the immense pull of gravity from the object that became...
</Question>
<Choice>asteroid</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An aurora is a display of colored light in the night sky that occurs primarily in high latitudes of both hemispheres. Auroras in the Northern Hemisphere are called the northern lights, or aurora borealis. In the United States they are most frequent and spectacular in Alaska and other Northern states. They are seen approximately 25 times a year...
</Question>
<Choice>aurora</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Some regions of space exert such powerful gravity that they suck in any matter that comes too close. That matter—whether it is a comet, a planet, or a cloud of gas—is crushed to infinite density. The gravity is so intense that it tugs at time and space, slowing down time and stretching out space. Not even light can escape the fierce gravitational...
</Question>
<Choice>black hole</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
When near the Sun, the small bodies called comets develop a hazy cloud of gases and dust. They also often develop long, glowing tails. However, a comet exists as only a small core of ice and dust for most or even its entire orbit around the Sun. Comets can be easily seen from Earth only when they approach the Sun closely. Even then, most are...
</Question>
<Choice>comet</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
For untold thousands of years men have traced the outlines of familiar things among the stars. These patterns in the night sky are called constellations, from Latin words meaning together and stars.
</Question>
<Choice>constellation</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1473–1543). The Polish astronomer Nicolaus Copernicus is often considered the founder of modern astronomy. His study led to his theory that the Earth rotates on its axis and that the Earth and the other planets revolve around the sun.
</Question>
<Choice>Copernicus, Nicolaus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Throughout recorded history, humankind has asked big questions about the universe: How large is it? Is it finite, or does space go on forever? How old is it, or has it always been here, and will it last forever? Where in the universe are we—the center? Or does it even have a center? Is the universe fundamentally chaotic or orderly? If it is...
</Question>
<Choice>cosmology</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
When three celestial objects become aligned, an eclipse is said to occur. The many eclipse events known to astronomers are of two different types. In the first, the eclipsing body comes between an observer and the eclipsed object. The eclipsed object appears to the observer to be totally or partially covered by the eclipsing object. Eclipses of...
</Question>
<Choice>eclipse</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1564–1642). Modern physics owes its beginning to Galileo, who was the first astronomer to use a telescope. By discovering four satellites of the planet Jupiter, he gave visual evidence that supported the Copernican theory (see Astronomy). Galileo thus helped disprove much of the medieval thinking in science.
</Question>
<Choice>Galileo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The fifth planet from the Sun and the solar system's largest planet by far is Jupiter. More than 1,300 Earths would fit inside it. The planet is one of the brightest objects in the night sky, and even a small telescope can reveal its multicolored stripes. These stripes are bands of clouds being pushed around the planet by strong east-west winds...
</Question>
<Choice>Jupiter</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1571–1630). The Renaissance astronomer and astrologer Johannes Kepler is best known for his discovery that the orbits in which the Earth and the other planets of the solar system travel around the sun are elliptical, or oval, in shape. He was also the first to explain correctly how human beings see and to demonstrate what happens to light when...
</Question>
<Choice>Kepler, Johannes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The fourth planet from the Sun is Mars. Easily visible from Earth with the naked eye, it has intrigued stargazers since ancient times. It often appears quite bright and reddish in the night sky. Babylonians mentioned Mars in records from about 3,000 years ago, associating the blood-red planet with their god of death and disease. The name Mars is...
</Question>
<Choice>Mars</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The planet that orbits closest to the Sun is Mercury. It is also the smallest of the eight planets in the solar system. These features make Mercury difficult to view from Earth, as the small planet rises and sets within about two hours of the Sun. Observers on Earth can only ever see the planet during twilight, when the Sun is just below the...
</Question>
<Choice>Mercury</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A flaming streak flashes across the night sky and disappears. On rare occasions the flash of light plunges toward Earth, producing a boom like the thundering of guns and causing a great explosion when it lands. When ancient peoples witnessed such displays, they believed they were seeing a star fall from the sky, and so they called the object a...
</Question>
<Choice>meteor and meteorite</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The most prominent feature in the night sky is Earth's natural satellite, the Moon. Because of its nearness to Earth, the Moon is second only to the Sun in apparent brightness among celestial objects. It also appears roughly the same size as the Sun, though the Sun is actually about 400 times larger and 400 times more distant. In astronomical...
</Question>
<Choice>moon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The eighth and farthest planet from the Sun is Neptune. It is always more than 2.5 billion miles (4 billion kilometers) from Earth, making it too far to be seen with the unaided eye. It was the second planet, after Uranus, to be discovered through a telescope but the first planet to be found by people specifically searching for one. In the mid...
</Question>
<Choice>Neptune</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1642–1727). The chief figure of the scientific revolution of the 17th century was Sir Isaac Newton. He was a physicist and mathematician who laid the foundations of calculus, extended the understanding of color and light, studied the mechanics of planetary motion, and discovered the law of gravitation. His work established the commonly held...
</Question>
<Choice>Newton, Isaac</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The relatively large natural bodies that revolve in orbits around the Sun or other stars are called planets. The term does not include small bodies such as comets, meteoroids, and asteroids, many of which are little more than pieces of ice or rock.
</Question>
<Choice>planet</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The distant rocky and icy body named Pluto is a dwarf planet. For 76 years, however, from its discovery in 1930 until 2006, it was considered the ninth and outermost planet of the solar system. Pluto is on average about 39.5 times farther from the Sun than is Earth. As a result, very little sunlight reaches Pluto, so it must be a dark, frigid...
</Question>
<Choice>Pluto</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(100?–170?). Claudius Ptolemaeus (Ptolemy) was an eminent astronomer, mathematician, and geographer who lived in the 2nd century AD. Although his work has survived, almost nothing is known about his life. Ptolemy published his astronomical data in an encyclopedic volume known as Almagest. It synthesized Greek astronomical knowledge and provided...
</Question>
<Choice>Ptolemy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In 1967, at the Cavendish Laboratories in Cambridge, England, two astrophysicists happened upon something completely unexpected. Their radio telescope picked up short pulses of energy. At first dismissed as some sort of man-made interference, the pulse was found to recur at regular intervals, much like a “light clock” ticking in space. This was...
</Question>
<Choice>pulsar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Since their discovery in the early 1960s, quasars, or quasi-stellar radio sources, continue to baffle astronomers. It is now generally accepted that quasars are the highly luminous cores, or nuclei, of distant galaxies. What is still uncertain about quasars is how they produce their vast energy. They are up to a thousand times as bright as the...
</Question>
<Choice>quasar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The sixth planet from the Sun is Saturn. Dusty chunks of ice—some the size of a house, others of a grain of sand—make up its extraordinary rings. The other outer planets also have rings, but Saturn's are much larger and more complex. The planet is a popular target for amateur astronomers, because even a small telescope can reveal the dazzling...
</Question>
<Choice>Saturn</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
As the Sun rushes through space at a speed of roughly 150 miles (240 kilometers) per second, it takes many smaller objects along with it. These include the planets and dwarf planets; their moons; and small bodies such as asteroids, comets, and meteoroids. All these objects orbit, or revolve around, the Sun. Together, the Sun and all its smaller...
</Question>
<Choice>solar system</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(or solar plasma), the stream of atomic particles entitled from a thermonuclear explosion in the sun; the particles are mostly electrons and the positive nuclei of ionized hydrogen gas and other elements; their temperature near the Earth is about 1 million degrees F (1.1 million degrees C); their ultrahigh speed, about 3 million mi (4.8 million km...
</Question>
<Choice>solar wind</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
From earliest times the rainbow had delighted and puzzled observers. Men invented myths to explain the beautiful arc of multicolored light that appeared after the rain. But a scientific answer to the puzzle of the rainbow did not come until 1666. In that year Sir Isaac Newton began investigating the problem of eliminating the color fringes in...
</Question>
<Choice>spectrum and spectroscope</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
People of the ancient world thought that stars were tiny lights on the inner side of a great, hollow globe. They made up stories about them and gave names to the patterns that they saw in the sky night after night and year after year (see constellation). Only with the birth of the modern science of astronomy did the true nature of the universe...
</Question>
<Choice>star</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Although the Sun is a rather ordinary star, it is very important to the inhabitants of Earth. The Sun is the source of virtually all Earth's energy. It provides the heat and light that make life on Earth possible. Yet Earth receives only about half a billionth of the energy that leaves the Sun. The Sun is a huge ball of hot gases. Like other stars...
</Question>
<Choice>sun</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Light and other kinds of electromagnetic radiation coming from the universe outside the Earth must travel enormous distances through space and time to reach observers. Only the brightest and nearest stars can be seen with the unaided eye. To see farther and to clarify and measure what is seen, a telescope is needed. The word telescope is derived...
</Question>
<Choice>telescope</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The seventh planet from the Sun is Uranus. It is one of the giant outer planets with no solid surfaces. Although Uranus is not as big as Jupiter or Saturn, more than 60 Earths would fit inside it. The planet is most similar in size and composition to Neptune, its outer neighbor. Like Neptune, Uranus is blue-green because of the small amount of...
</Question>
<Choice>Uranus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The second planet from the Sun is Venus. After the Moon, Venus is the most brilliant natural object in the nighttime sky. It is the closest planet to Earth, and it is also the most similar to Earth in size, mass, volume, and density. These similarities suggest that the two planets may have had similar histories. Scientists are thus intrigued by...
</Question>
<Choice>Venus</Choice>
</item>
</topics>