<topics>
<item>
<Question>
Gliding on tireless and apparently motionless wings, the albatross may follow a ship for days. The great ocean bird used to hold a strange spell over sailors who believed that it had unnatural power, and that killing one brought bad luck. The famous poem by Samuel Taylor Coleridge, The Rime of the Ancient Mariner, is based on this old superstition.
</Question>
<Choice>albatross</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The seabirds of the family Alcidae nest on the barren islands of the Arctic Sea and on the islands off the far northern coasts of North America, Europe, and Asia. In North America a few kinds nest as far south as northern California and Maine. In the winter they move southward to central California and Long Island.
</Question>
<Choice>auk, murre, and puffin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
During the course of evolution, some birds lost the power of flight as they adapted to new environmental circumstances. Most flightless birds belong to the order Struthioniformes—more commonly known as the ratites—which includes the ostrich, rhea, emu, and cassowary. Two extinct ratites are the elephant bird and the moa. Also flightless, but...
</Question>
<Choice>bird, flightless</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Many birds are carnivorous—that is, they prey upon other animals for food. All such birds could be considered birds of prey, even a robin in pursuit of a worm. However, the term “bird of prey” is used more precisely for only those birds in either of two orders: Falconiformes and Strigiformes. Falconiformes includes hawks, eagles, vultures, falcons...
</Question>
<Choice>birds of prey</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Various relatives of the meadowlarks and orioles are known as blackbirds. The grackles, the cowbirds, and the red-winged, yellow-headed, rusty, and Brewer's blackbirds are members of this large group. Most blackbirds are found in North America, where they nest in marshes, on dry prairies, or in dense evergreen forests. The redwings have musical...
</Question>
<Choice>blackbird</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the early voices of the northern spring is the bluebird's. In spite of its sad song, this brilliantly colored bird is the symbol of happiness. It is found in common places, such as fields, orchards, and gardens.
</Question>
<Choice>bluebird</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Northerners love the bobolink for its beautiful song. They protect it because it eats insects and weed seeds. In the South, however, it is considered an enemy of the rice crop. The males even look different in the South. The spring plumage of the male is black underparts, black face and top of the head, black and white back, and buff back of the...
</Question>
<Choice>bobolink</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the most popular pet songbirds all over the world is the canary. In the wild, this member of the finch family measures about 5 12 inches (14 centimeters) in length. It is dull green above, with a yellow breast.
</Question>
<Choice>canary</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The cardinal, or redbird, is a North American songbird found mostly east of the Rocky Mountains and belonging to the family Fringillidae. Its scientific name is Cardinalis cardinalis. The cardinal is about 8 inches (20 centimeters) long, a little smaller than a robin. It has a high crest of feathers on its head. The throat and area around the...
</Question>
<Choice>cardinal</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Through the still waters of open marshlands the sandhill crane wades on stiltlike legs. Its long neck erect, it scans the countryside with keen eyes for signs of danger. Then it lowers its head and searches the water. Out darts its neck, and its long daggerlike beak holds a frog or a salamander, which it swallows in one or two gulps. At other...
</Question>
<Choice>crane</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Crows, ravens, and jays belong to the family Corvidae. Also included in this family are the magpies, jackdaws, and rooks and many lesser-known forms such as the bush-crow of Africa and notch-tailed tree pie of Southeast Asia.
</Question>
<Choice>crow</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Cuckoos are members of the bird family Cuculidae. The family consists of more than 125 species, including the roadrunners and anis. More than a third of all cuckoo species are brood parasites; that is, they lay their eggs in the nests of other birds and the young cuckoos are reared by foster parents. Most cuckoos live in the tropics, but cuckoo...
</Question>
<Choice>cuckoo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Of the nearly 150 species of waterfowl known as ducks, geese, and swans, most are strong swimmers with powerful wings for long-distance migrations. The birds of this family, Anatidae, have stout bodies, short legs, webbed feet, and somewhat flattened bills. The largest waterfowl are the swans, and the smallest are the ducks. Geese are...
</Question>
<Choice>duck, goose, and swan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Since ancient times the eagle has been used as a symbol of strength and courage. This large bird of prey has been admired for its powerful appearance and majestic, soaring flight. The Sumerians chose it as their emblem of power 5,000 years ago. So did imperial Rome many centuries later. Today the bald eagle is the national bird of the United...
</Question>
<Choice>eagle</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Small, stout birds with conical bills adapted to crushing seed make up the finch group. They are closely related to the grosbeaks, sparrows, and buntings. All of them are members of the family Fringillidae, the largest of all the bird families. Its members are found in most of the world. (See also birds; cardinal; goldfinch; grosbeak; sparrow.)
</Question>
<Choice>finch</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
This long-legged bird is usually a rich vermilion color, shading on the underparts to rose and pale pink. It stands between 3 to 6 12 feet (0.9 to 2 meters) tall. The bird's neck curves, looking very much like a letter S. Its head is small, and its beak is flat and downcurved. The flamingo flies with its neck and legs outstretched. The sight of a...
</Question>
<Choice>flamingo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The “man-o'-war bird,” as the frigate bird is sometimes called, is like a feathered airplane. Seemingly without effort it floats high in the air for hours at a time, altering its course by movements so slight as to be almost invisible.
</Question>
<Choice>frigate bird</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
This game bird is hunted eagerly. In some regions it has almost been exterminated. It is the habit of these dull-plumaged birds to lie hidden in the grass until the hunter's dogs are upon them; then, with a sudden, loud whirring sound and with almost the speed of an arrow, they rise before the startled hunter, who must remain both cool and quick...
</Question>
<Choice>grouse</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Among the most common water birds of ocean and coastal zones worldwide are gulls and terns. Species live inland on every continent and in all major bodies of water.
</Question>
<Choice>gull</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Many of the long-legged wading birds living in the marshes of saltwater lagoons, freshwater lakes, and rivers are herons. Included in the heron family, Ardeidae, are bitterns, boatbills, and egrets. The word egret usually refers to the beautiful white-plumed birds. They are famous for the long plumes, or aigrettes, that are worn by the males...
</Question>
<Choice>heron</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Portuguese call it beija-flôr, meaning “kiss-flower.” The Aztecs adorned Montezuma's ceremonial cloaks with its feathers. The dazzling hummingbird still captures people's fancy.
</Question>
<Choice>hummingbird</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The kingfisher family, Alcedinidae, includes some 90 species, distributed over the greater part of the globe. They are known for their swift dives. From its perch the kingfisher can swoop like an arrow to seize a fish underwater or an insect on land. An ancient name for the kingfisher was halcyon.
</Question>
<Choice>kingfisher</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The lark is primarily a bird of the Old World. Only one species, the horned lark, is native to North America. The meadowlark and the titlark, sometimes called pipit, are not true larks (see Pipit).
</Question>
<Choice>lark</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
“As crazy as a loon” is an expression that comes from the strange, laughterlike notes that the common loon sends ringing across the waters of North American inland lakes. This bird and three other species make up the family Gaviidae.
</Question>
<Choice>loon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Of all North American birds, by far the most famed for its vocal imitations is the mockingbird. Besides its own rapturous song, the common mockingbird's repertoire has been known to include the songs of 39 other species of birds, 50 different call notes, the cackling of a hen, and the barking of a dog.
</Question>
<Choice>mockingbird</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Few birds are as celebrated in literature as the nightingale, but residents of the Americas must go abroad to hear this famous bird, for it does not live in the New World. Its relatives, the thrushes, are the only birds in the Americas that approach the nightingale in beauty of song. The nightingale is found throughout Europe, most abundantly in...
</Question>
<Choice>nightingale</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In their topsy-turvy search for insects and grubs hiding in the bark of trees, nuthatches are upside down as often as they are right side up. In fact, among birds that forage in tree trunks, they are the only ones that regularly feed moving head downward, often finding food in bark crevices overlooked in their upward search.
</Question>
<Choice>nuthatch and creeper</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Few birds can rival the gorgeous, often bizarre plumage of the male birds of paradise. They may have iridescent neck ruffs, brightly colored, flowing tail feathers, or long, thin, wirelike projections growing from their heads. Courting males will perform for hours. In their efforts to distinguish themselves, they may wave their tail feathers over...
</Question>
<Choice>paradise, birds of</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The tiniest pygmy parrot, largest macaw, and all the variously sized parakeets and cockatoos in between belong to the family Psittacidae of parrots and related birds. The family also includes the lories, lovebirds, keas, cockatiels, lorikeets, parrotlets, budgerigars, rosellas, conures, and amazons. The birds of this family range in length from...
</Question>
<Choice>parrot family</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
“As proud as a peacock,” this male bird struts as he displays his resplendent plumage. His feathers shine in metallic shades of bronze, blue, green, and gold, and a crest adorns his head. His chief glory is the 60-inch (150-centimeter) train of brilliantly marked plumes, each tipped with an iridescent “eye” ringed with blue and bronze. In the...
</Question>
<Choice>peacock</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
“A wonderful bird is the pelican, His bill will hold more than his belican.” So begins a well-known limerick on the pelican's comical appearance. The bird is large-bodied and short-legged and has a bill that is longer than its head with an enormous pouch of skin fastened to the lower mandible. The pouch does in fact hold more than the pelican's...
</Question>
<Choice>pelican</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Seen from a distance, a colony of penguins might easily be taken for a group of little men. These sea birds stand erect and flat-footed and are often drawn up in long regular files like soldiers. They walk with a tread so stately and dignified that the sight is very comical. In the species known as the king penguin, the resemblance to man is...
</Question>
<Choice>penguin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Some of the most beautiful birds in the world are classed in the pheasant family, including the elegant peacock and the Lady Amherst's pheasant (see Peacock). The argus pheasants of southeastern Asia have a chain of eye spots running down the center of their long secondary wing feathers. They are named for Argus of Greek mythology, who had a...
</Question>
<Choice>pheasant</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Taxonomically, pigeons and doves are the same. Both are members of the order Columbiformes, family Columbidae. The term dove is generally used for smaller species with pointed tails. “Pigeon” refers to the larger species with square or rounded tails.
</Question>
<Choice>pigeon and dove</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The fowl-like birds known as quail and partridge are members of the pheasant family, Phasianidae, which also includes the pheasants and peacocks. Some scientists also consider turkeys and chickens to be part of the same family. Quail are native to both the Eastern and Western hemispheres, while partridge are native only to the Eastern Hemisphere...
</Question>
<Choice>quail and partridge</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
For gorgeous plumage, few birds surpass the quetzal. Found in rainforests from southern Mexico to Bolivia, the quetzal was the sacred bird of the ancient Mayas and Aztecs; today it is the national emblem of Guatemala (whose monetary unit is the quetzal).
</Question>
<Choice>quetzal</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A familiar and amusing bird, the roadrunner lives in the deserts of the southwestern United States and Mexico. It flies very little: it was named for its habit of dashing along desert roads in search of cover or in pursuit of lizards, insects, or snakes. Its speed has been timed at greater than 15 miles (24 kilometers) per hour. The roadrunner...
</Question>
<Choice>roadrunner</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the best known of American birds is the robin. It nests from the limit of trees in northern Alaska and Canada to southern Mexico. Its musical warble, cheerily, cheer up, cheerily, cheerily, is one of the early signs of spring in the north. It seems to have little fear of people.
</Question>
<Choice>robin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Most of the small brown shorebirds seen along the edges of seas, lakes, marshes, and mud flats are sandpipers and their relatives. The sandpiper family includes the sanderlings, the snipes, and the woodcocks. However, the name sandpiper refers particularly to several species of small to middle-sized birds that throng at the water's edge.
</Question>
<Choice>sandpiper</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the world's best known and probably most abundant small birds is the house, or English, sparrow. It is found worldwide around homes and on farms. A native of the British Isles, Eurasia, and northern Africa, it is more robust than the native New World sparrows. The house sparrow was introduced into North America in the early 1850s, and...
</Question>
<Choice>sparrow</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The large birds called storks have long necks and legs. They make up the scientific family Ciconiidae and are related to herons, flamingos, and ibises. In some parts of Europe the white stork is believed to bring such good luck that people fix platforms and baskets to their rooftops to encourage the birds to nest there. When a child is born, some...
</Question>
<Choice>stork</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Flying aces of the avian world, swifts feed, drink, bathe, court, and sometimes mate on the wing. They often spend the entire night flying and are the fastest of small birds. Their strong claws are used to cling to vertical surfaces, but their legs are small and weak. Consequently, if a swift lands on flat ground, it may have great difficulty...
</Question>
<Choice>swift</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the large thrush family of birds are some of the finest singers—the robin, the bluebird, and the nightingale, as well as those commonly known as thrushes. Although most of them are feathered in browns and buffs, some thrushes—such as the robin and the bluebird—have bright colors.
</Question>
<Choice>thrush</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
any of about 40 species of large-billed, tropical American birds constituting family Ramphastidae; mainly black body with bold breast color; saw-edged, distinctly colored bill; short, rounded wings; long tail; grow to 2 ft (0.6 m) long; nest in noisy treetop colonies in tree holes; lay 2 to 4 glossy white eggs in unlined cavity; feed on fruit...
</Question>
<Choice>toucan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The wild turkey is native only to North and Central America. When the Spaniards conquered Mexico, they found domesticated birds. They introduced the bird into Europe, and it was well established by 1530. Later the English colonists brought it back to North America. All domestic turkeys are descendants of the Mexican subspecies.
</Question>
<Choice>turkey</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Named for the scarlet flecks resembling sealing wax that tip the secondary feathers of their wings, the waxwings are nomadic birds with unpredictable migration patterns. They are particularly handsome, with soft brown crests and black masks. The plumage is a delicate fawn color, blending into ashy gray, the short, square tail has a lemon yellow...
</Question>
<Choice>waxwing</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The nocturnal whippoorwill won its name by its call. As the whippoorwill swoops across the sky hunting insects, it keeps calling three whistled notes—whip-poor-will, whip-poor-will— which may be repeated 400 times without stopping.
</Question>
<Choice>whippoorwill</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
When a woodpecker drums a tree, it is usually searching for food. Once it has detected the sounds of insects gnawing or moving within the bark or wood, it begins to hammer persistently in pursuit of its prey. Trees are not injured by these birds; the disfigured bark soon heals. In fact woodpeckers save many trees from injury by insects.
</Question>
<Choice>woodpecker</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
This quick, excitable bird is often scolding and seems to rush from one task to another all day long. Wrens are among the easiest of birds to attract to the home garden with the offer of a birdhouse (see Birds). Wrens belong to the wren family Troglodytidae (meaning “cave dweller”), which comprises 59 species. They originated in the Western...
</Question>
<Choice>wren</Choice>
</item>
</topics>