<topics>
<item>
<Question>
When fossil fuels such as coal, gasoline, and fuel oils are burned, they emit oxides of sulfur, carbon, and nitrogen into the air (see oxygen). These oxides combine with moisture in the air to form sulfuric acid, carbonic acid, and nitric acid. The term acid rain is also applied to other forms of precipitation—snow, hail, sleet, and fog—that are...
</Question>
<Choice>acid rain</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In countless tasks, from running blast furnaces to inflating tires, people use air. Airplanes and kites need it to fly. The sound of thunder or a clap of hands requires air to be heard. Humans and animals would die without air. Trees, flowers, and grass also need it to live.
</Question>
<Choice>air</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Earth and other planets of the solar system are each enclosed in a thin shell of gas called an atmosphere. Only the Earth's atmosphere will be dealt with in this article. (For information about the atmospheres of the other planets see Planets.)
</Question>
<Choice>atmosphere</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The aggregate, long-term weather—or state of the atmosphere—of any place is known as its climate. For example, a description of weather might be “It rained yesterday in Phoenix,” while “Phoenix gets only 10 inches of rain per year” would be a statement about climate. Descriptions of climate include such weather elements as temperature...
</Question>
<Choice>climate</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Though they may look fairly solid, clouds are only collections of water droplets, ice crystals, or mixtures of both. Since early times people have observed the infinite shapes of the clouds in the sky and watched their ceaseless formation and disappearance. Poets and artists have interpreted their beauty in rhyme and picture. But farmers, sailors...
</Question>
<Choice>cloud</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the most important natural fuels, coal was formed from plant life buried in the Earth millions of years ago. Like petroleum and natural gas, it is a carbon-based fossil fuel. (See also gas, natural and manufactured; petroleum.)
</Question>
<Choice>coal</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Conservation is the responsible stewardship of the environment to preserve natural ecosystems while insuring that balanced consideration is also given to human needs for production and recreation. People vary in their opinions on the levels of importance of the various components and on how much emphasis should be placed on each. Thus, some...
</Question>
<Choice>conservation</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The sudden shaking of the ground that occurs when masses of rock change position below the Earth's surface is called an earthquake. The shifting masses send out shock waves that may be powerful enough to alter the surface of the Earth, thrusting up cliffs and opening great cracks in the ground.
</Question>
<Choice>earthquake</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
To the 19th-century fishermen who coined the term, El Niño was a warm Pacific Ocean current that affected their catch off the coast of Peru. They named the current El Niño, Spanish for “the Christ child,” because it usually arrived around Christmas. Later, scientists noted that every few years an especially strong current brought unusually warm...
</Question>
<Choice>El Niño</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Fires must be fought every day in most countries. Millions of fires start each year and cause great destruction of property and much human suffering. In the United States alone, in 1981, 6,800 people died in some of the almost 3 million fires that occurred and the cost of damaged or destroyed property was estimated at nearly 7 billion dollars.
</Question>
<Choice>fire fighting</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Water overflowing onto normally dry land is known as flooding. It has always been a part of human life. Stories of great floods in ancient times—for example, the Bible story of Noah and the Ark—have come down from many early peoples (see flood legends). To obtain access to transportation routes, fishing, and water for drinking, farming, and...
</Question>
<Choice>flood</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Perhaps the most widely used product refined from petroleum is gasoline. Gasoline is burned in an internal-combustion engine to provide energy to power automobiles, airplanes, and other machinery. In some English-speaking countries, such as the United Kingdom, gasoline is referred to as petrol. Gasoline is a complex mixture containing hundreds...
</Question>
<Choice>gasoline</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The science of the Earth—geology—is perhaps the most varied of all the natural sciences. It is concerned with the origin of the planet Earth, its history, its shape, the materials forming it, and the processes that are acting and have acted on it (see Earth). Geology is one of several related subjects commonly grouped as the Earth sciences, or...
</Question>
<Choice>geology</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In many of the world's high mountains, the heat of summer is not sufficient to melt all the snow that falls in winter. Whenever this occurs year after year, there is a gradual accumulation of snow in the upper ends of mountain valleys. These areas where the snow lasts from year to year are known as snowfields. In the sunny days of summer the...
</Question>
<Choice>glacier</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The rise of air temperatures near Earth's surface over the past century is known as global warming. Earth has experienced periods of gradual warming and cooling throughout its existence due to natural causes, such as volcanic eruptions and variations in the Sun's output. However, scientists have attributed the current increase in global...
</Question>
<Choice>global warming</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The warming of Earth's surface and lower atmosphere due to the presence of certain gases in the air is known as the greenhouse effect. The gases involved are collectively termed greenhouse gases; the most significant of these are water vapor, carbon dioxide, methane, and nitrous oxide. The greenhouse effect is so named because it resembles the...
</Question>
<Choice>greenhouse effect</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Floating icebergs are at once the dread of sailors and the wonder of all who see them for the first time. They are the broken-off ends of glaciers that slide into the sea. They vary in size from small, flat “growlers” to mountains of ice a mile or more across and more than 200 feet above the water.
</Question>
<Choice>iceberg</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Irrigation is the artificial supply of water to agricultural land. It is practiced by more than half the farmers in the world because they need more water for their crops than is available from rainfall. Irrigation projects must also allow for removal of excess water. Modern irrigation and the associated practice of drainage, together with the...
</Question>
<Choice>irrigation</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Molten, or hot liquefied, rock located deep below the Earth's surface is called magma. When a volcano erupts or a deep crack occurs in the Earth, the magma rises and overflows. When it flows out of the volcano or crack, usually mixed with steam and gas, it is called lava. Fresh lava ranges from 1,300° to 2,200°? F (700° to 1,200° ?C) in...
</Question>
<Choice>lava and magma</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Since earliest times people have needed devices to help them see after sundown and to illuminate places of shelter. Light from the sun and the moon is free, but it is undependable, difficult to control, and impossible to move. The development of artificial lighting has been marked by the invention of light sources with ever-increasing efficiency...
</Question>
<Choice>lightning</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Atmospheric conditions, particularly variations in the weather and their effects on the Earth, are the subject of meteorology. This science uses physics and chemistry to unravel the dynamics of the Earth's atmosphere in an attempt to understand, predict, and control atmospheric actions.
</Question>
<Choice>meteorology</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Stories are often told of thirsty desert travelers being lured by a “mirage” of an oasis with green trees and quiet water. The traveler runs forward, according to the common version of the story, and tries to throw himself into the shady pool. At this moment the vision disappears, leaving him once more on the desert sand under the burning sun...
</Question>
<Choice>mirage</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Next to their vastness, the most striking feature of the oceans and other large bodies of water is the constant motion of their surfaces. Waves—ripples, ridges, and hollows moving over the water are the cause of this choppy, rolling, or otherwise disturbed appearance.
</Question>
<Choice>ocean waves and tides</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Petroleum is crude oil, a naturally occurring liquid that can be refined to make gasoline (or petrol), diesel fuel, jet fuel, home heating oil, lubricating oil, wax, asphalt, and many other valuable products. Crude oil usually occurs in subsurface deposits, but in some areas it leaks onto the surface in oil seeps. The word petroleum comes from...
</Question>
<Choice>petroleum</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The modern theory of the motions of Earth's outer layers is called plate tectonics. It provides a framework for understanding many of Earth's features, such as mountains, earthquakes, and volcanoes, as well as the distribution of fossils and the ages of rocks. It also helps scientists reconstruct ancient climates and continental configurations.
</Question>
<Choice>plate tectonics</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Efforts to improve the standard of living for humans—through the control of nature and the development of new products—have also resulted in the pollution, or contamination, of the environment. Much of the world's air, water, and land is now partially poisoned by chemical wastes. Some places have become uninhabitable. This pollution exposes...
</Question>
<Choice>pollution, environmental</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The recovery and reuse of materials from spent products—called recycling or materials salvage—is an ancient practice with many modern applications. In recent years recycling has become a major part of environmental policy, largely owing to the increased costs of solid- and hazardous-waste disposal, the scarcity of natural resources, and the...
</Question>
<Choice>recycling</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the most important natural resources is soil. Like air and water, soil is necessary to life on Earth. Without it, plants could not grow and plant-eating animals could not live; meat-eating animals would also perish. Civilizations depend on the quality of their soil to grow their food and to serve as a living filter that purifies the...
</Question>
<Choice>soil</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A storm is simply a disturbed state of the atmosphere. The term strongly implies destructive or unpleasant weather conditions characterized by strong winds, heavy rain, snow, sleet, hail, lightning, or a combination of these occurrences. Each type of storm follows a particular life cycle and occurs in specific seasons when atmospheric conditions...
</Question>
<Choice>storm</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nearly three fourths of the Earth's surface is covered with water. Perhaps the most important liquid in the world, water is usually easy to get from rain, springs, wells, streams, rivers, ponds, and lakes. It fills the vast ocean beds. As vapor, water is also present in the air, where it often condenses into clouds. The bodies of most living...
</Question>
<Choice>water</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The weather concerns everyone and has some effect on nearly every human activity. It occurs within the atmosphere, the mixture of gases that completely envelops Earth. Weather is defined as the momentary, day-to-day state of the atmosphere over any place on Earth's surface. Climate, on the other hand, refers to weather averaged over a long period...
</Question>
<Choice>weather</Choice>
</item>
</topics>