<topics>
<item>
<Question>
Every organization needs some way of keeping accounts—that is, of recording what it spends and receives. The person who maintains these records is called a bookkeeper. Bookkeeping is part of the larger field of accounting. People who work as accountants prepare financial statements, study an organization's costs, calculate its taxes, and...
</Question>
<Choice>accounting</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Banks are institutions that deal in money and its substitutes. They accept deposits, make loans, and derive a profit from the difference in the interest paid to lenders (depositors) and charged to borrowers, respectively. From these deposits the bank makes loans to individuals, businesses, government agencies, and other banks. Banks also profit...
</Question>
<Choice>bank and banking</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
When any person or business owes more money than is available for payment, a petition of bankruptcy may be filed in bankruptcy court. The court may appoint a trustee to take charge of the debtor's property and to sell it to pay the outstanding debts.
</Question>
<Choice>bankruptcy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Modern economies have alternated between periods of boom and bust. These are times of economic expansion and prosperity followed by economic downturns. Such periods of economic expansion followed by a contraction are called business cycles. During periods of expansion, employment remains high and prices remain stable or rise.
</Question>
<Choice>business cycle</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An economic system that features private ownership of the means of production (such as factories, offices, and shipping enterprises) and in which market forces determine the way in which goods are produced and the means by which income and profit are distributed is called capitalism.
</Question>
<Choice>capitalism</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
If a society's economy is to function efficiently, there must be some standard by which to measure the value of all goods and services. For many centuries in most societies this standard has been money. In the modern world money appears in two forms, paper and metal. Historically the metal has been mostly in flat, round pieces called coins.
</Question>
<Choice>coin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Communism is a political and economic system in which the major productive resources in a society—such as mines, factories, and farms—are owned by the public or the state, and wealth is divided among citizens equally or according to individual need. In its most common usage, the term communism refers to the type of ideal society envisioned by the...
</Question>
<Choice>communism</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Before the rise of national states in Western Europe, the people lived under a system called feudalism. This was a social system of rights and obligations based on land ownership patterns.
</Question>
<Choice>feudalism</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
National income accounting is a set of measures used to gauge the health of a nation's economy for a given period. One of these measures is the Gross Domestic Product (GDP). The government uses GDP as the best indicator of economic health because it represents the total market value of all goods and services during a given year. Unlike the better...
</Question>
<Choice>gross national product (GNP)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Most products people in the industrialized nations use today are turned out swiftly by the process of mass production, by people (and sometimes, robots) working on assembly lines using power-driven machines. People of ancient and medieval times had no such products. They had to spend long, tedious hours of hand labor even on simple objects. The...
</Question>
<Choice>Industrial Revolution</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The term industry covers all the businesses and factories that convert raw materials into goods or that provide useful services. Industry produces all the goods and services required by society and distributes them to consumers. The term is also used to describe a group of businesses that produce a similar product or service. All the factories...
</Question>
<Choice>industry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
What is now called international trade has existed for thousands of years—long before there were nations with specific boundaries. Speaking in strictly economic terms, international trade today is not between nations. It is between producers and consumers or between sets of producers in different parts of the world. Nations do not trade; only...
</Question>
<Choice>international trade</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1883–1946). An economist, journalist, and financier, Englishman John Keynes is best known for his revolutionary economic theory on the causes of prolonged unemployment. His enduring fame rests on a theory that recovery from a recession can best be achieved by a government-sponsored policy of full employment.
</Question>
<Choice>Keynes, John Maynard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the most general sense labor means work. Young children know that when they grow up they will get a job, earn money, and use that money to live. This appears to be a basic fact of life, as basic as growing up itself. Actually, however, this form of earning a living, exchanging hours of work for money, has become common only within the last...
</Question>
<Choice>labor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The term labor movement is often applied to any organization or association of wage earners who join together to advance their common interests. It more broadly applies, however, to any association of workers by geographical area, trade or industry, or any other factor. While labor unions have been the almost exclusive center of the modern labor...
</Question>
<Choice>labor movements</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1818–83). Known during his lifetime only to a small group of socialists and revolutionaries, Karl Marx wrote books now considered by Communists all over the world to be the source of absolute truth on matters of economics, philosophy, and politics. Most modern socialists also base their doctrines to a lesser or greater degree on Marx's theories.
</Question>
<Choice>Marx, Karl</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Every purchase in a store is an exchange. A product is traded for money. In preindustrial societies, goods and services were exchanged directly, without money, in a process called barter. Mr. A exchanged his product, shoes, for a shirt made by Ms. B. Or both exchanged their products, shoes and shirts, for ten pounds of wheat grown by Mr. and Mrs...
</Question>
<Choice>money</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Socialism is a political and economic system in which most forms of economically valuable property and resources are owned or controlled by the public or the state. The term socialism also refers to any political or philosophical doctrine that advocates such a system. In a strictly socialist economy, public agencies influence—and in some cases...
</Question>
<Choice>socialism</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
“Wall Street Lays an Egg,” a headline in Variety announced in October 1929. In that understated sentence the show-business newspaper was saying that the New York stock market had collapsed. Beginning on October 24—remembered as Black Thursday—and culminating in an even blacker Tuesday, October 29, the value of securities dropped more than...
</Question>
<Choice>stock market</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Governments can never create wealth. They must, therefore, support themselves by taking a portion of the wealth of their citizens. The chief means by which governments do this is taxation. Taxes are required payments of money that must be made regularly. Most of the money goes into a general pool of revenues from which all government expenses are...
</Question>
<Choice>taxation</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In its most obvious sense, unemployment means being without a job. As an economic definition, however, this is inadequate. The term unemployment is one description of the economic condition of a society at a given time. Low unemployment means most of the labor force has steady work. High unemployment is an indication of an economy in recession...
</Question>
<Choice>unemployment</Choice>
</item>
</topics>