<topics>
<item>
<Question>
A large carnivorous, or meat-eating, dinosaur, Allosaurus was a fierce predator that inhabited North America and probably Africa, Australia, and Asia during the late Jurassic period, approximately 144 to 159 million years ago. Allosaurus is classified as a member of the family Allosauridae, which belongs to the order Saurischia (the lizard-hipped...
</Question>
<Choice>Allosaurus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
a large herbivorous, or plant-eating, dinosaur that inhabited North America approximately 65 to 98 million years ago during the late Cretaceous period. Ankylosaurus is classified as a member of the family Ankylosauridae, which contains heavily armored dinosaurs. Ankylosaurus and Euoplocephalus are the only known ankylosaurids from North America...
</Question>
<Choice>Ankylosaurus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
a large, herbivorous, or plant-eating, dinosaur that inhabited North America during the late Jurassic period, approximately 144 to 163 million years ago. Apatosaurus is classified as a member of the family Diplodocidae, which contains dinosaurs with exceptionally long necks and tails. The Diplodocidae belong to the order Saurischia (the lizard...
</Question>
<Choice>Apatosaurus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
a massive, herbivorous, or plant-eating, dinosaur that inhabited North America and Africa during the late Jurassic period, about 144 million to 163 million years ago. Brachiosaurus is classified as a member of the family Brachiosauridae, which contains enormous dinosaurs with long necks and relatively short tails. The Brachiosauridae belong to...
</Question>
<Choice>Brachiosaurus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
a large carnivorous, or meat-eating, dinosaur that inhabited North America about 144 to 163 million years ago during the late Jurassic period. Ceratosaurus is classified as a member of the family Ceratosauridae, which belongs to the order Saurischia, the lizard-hipped dinosaurs.
</Question>
<Choice>Ceratosaurus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
To see the fossilized bones of ancient dinosaurs, go to a museum. To see living descendants of dinosaurs, just find some birds. Some scientists consider birds to be the feathered crown of the dinosaur family tree. While a bird may not fit the common notion of a dinosaur (the word dinosaur means “terrifying lizard”), many scientists are certain...
</Question>
<Choice>dinosaur</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
an enormous, herbivorous, or plant-eating, dinosaur that inhabited North America during the late Jurassic period, approximately 144 to 163 million years ago. Diplodocus is classified as a member of the family Diplodocidae, which contains dinosaurs with exceptionally long necks and tails, slender bodies and limbs, and tiny heads. The Diplodocidae...
</Question>
<Choice>Diplodocus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An early carnivorous, or meat-eating, dinosaur, Eoraptor inhabited South America during the late Triassic period, approximately 223 to 228 million years ago. Eoraptor belongs to the order Saurischia (the lizard-hipped dinosaurs) and to the suborder Theropoda. It is among the oldest known dinosaurs and is an ancestor of larger theropods, such as...
</Question>
<Choice>Eoraptor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
a large, herbivorous, or plant-eating, dinosaur that inhabited North America, Europe, Africa, and Asia during the early Cretaceous period, about 98 to 144 million years ago. Iguanodon is classified as a member of the family Iguanodontidae, which contains bulky, fairly slow-moving dinosaurs. The Iguanodontidae belong to the suborder Ornithopoda of...
</Question>
<Choice>Iguanodon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Two million years ago, during the Pleistocene epoch, an immense beast with long, shaggy hair and huge, curved tusks lumbered around what are now Africa, Eurasia, and North America. This animal, the mammoth, was the ancestor of the modern elephant. Mastodons, similar in appearance to mammoths, were early distant relatives of the mammoths...
</Question>
<Choice>mammoth and mastodon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
a large, carnivorous, or meat-eating, dinosaur that inhabited Europe and possibly Africa about 144 to 208 million years ago during the Jurassic period. Megalosaurus is classified as a member of the family Megalosauridae, which belongs to the order Saurishcia (the lizard-hipped dinosaurs) and the suborder Theropoda. Theropoda is further divided...
</Question>
<Choice>Megalosaurus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
a small, carnivorous, or meat-eating, dinosaur that inhabited Asia during the late Cretaceous period, about 65 to 98 million years ago. Oviraptor is classified as a member of the family Oviraptoridae, a small family of toothless dinosaurs. The Oviraptoridae belong to the order Saurischia (the lizard-hipped dinosaurs), which is divided into two...
</Question>
<Choice>Oviraptor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An herbivorous, or plant-eating, dinosaur, Pachycephalosaurus inhabited North America during the late Cretaceous period, about 65 to 98 million years ago.Pachycephalosaurus is a member of the family Pachycephalosauridae, which comprises dinosaurs with thickened, dome-shaped skulls. This family—sometimes referred to as the boneheads—belongs to the...
</Question>
<Choice>Pachycephalosaurus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Stegosaurus was a massive herbivorous, or plant-eating, dinosaur that inhabited North America during the late Jurassic period, approximately 144 to 159 million years ago. Stegosaurus is classified as a member of the family Stegosauridae, which includes dinosaurs with triangular plates running along their backs. Stegosaurus belongs to the order...
</Question>
<Choice>Stegosaurus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Triceratops is a horned herbivorous, or plant-eating, dinosaur that inhabited North America during part of the late Cretaceous period, approximately 65 to 70 million years ago. Triceratops is classified as a member of the family Ceratopsidae, which includes dinosaurs with large neck frills and great horns on their heads. Triceratops belongs to...
</Question>
<Choice>Triceratops</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
large, carnivorous, or meat-eating, dinosaur that inhabited North America approximately 65 to 98 million years ago during the late Cretaceous period. The most widely recognized of all the dinosaurs, Tyrannosaurus rex has inspired much speculation about how it lived, as well as what and how it ate. Even before it was featured as the chief villain...
</Question>
<Choice>Tyrannosaurus rex</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Velociraptor was an agile carnivorous, or meat-eating, dinosaur that inhabited Asia during the late Cretaceous period, approximately 65 to 99 million years ago. Velociraptor is classified as a member of the family Dromaeosauridae, which includes dinosaurs with an especially large and deadly sickle-shaped claw. Velociraptor belongs to the order...
</Question>
<Choice>Velociraptor</Choice>
</item>
</topics>