<topics>
<item>
<Question>
The term angelfish is applied to several unrelated fishes of the order Perciformes. The angelfishes, or scalares, popular in home aquariums are members of the genus Pterophyllum of the cichlid family. They are thin, deep-bodied fishes with elongated dorsal, anal, and pelvic fins. Depending on the authority, one to three species may be recognized...
</Question>
<Choice>angelfish</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the fiercest of fishes is the barracuda, found in the warmer parts of the Atlantic and the Pacific. It has the savage appearance of the fresh-water pike—a narrow muscular body, a long cruel mouth with undershot jaw, and yellowish green eyes. It is, however, no relative of the pike and differs from it in having two fins on the back...
</Question>
<Choice>barracuda</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Fish of the bass family are found in both fresh and salt water. They range from the 6-inch (15-centimeter) rock bass of the Mississippi River basin to the sea bass and jewfish that may grow 8 feet (2.5 meters) long and weigh more than 700 pounds (318 kilograms). The smallmouth black bass of the Great Lakes region is prized by sports fishermen...
</Question>
<Choice>bass</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Fishes having a conspicuous set of feelers surrounding the mouth are called catfish. The feelers, called barbels, are sensory structures that look like whiskers and serve as organs of touch and taste. All catfishes are either smooth or armored with bony plates; none has scales.
</Question>
<Choice>catfish</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Among the most abundant of all freshwater fishes are the dace and minnows. These names are applied to various small, slender, active fishes in the carp family, Cyprinidae (see carp). (The term minnow can also refer to some small fishes in other families or to the young of larger fish in general). Most species grow to about 2–12 inches...
</Question>
<Choice>dace and minnow</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
There are more than 500 species of eels, long, snakelike fishes that live in major oceans, freshwater lakes, and rivers. Eels belong to about 20 different families, most of which are relatively unknown. They live in tropical seas or deep in the ocean. Freshwater eels are members of the family Anguillidae. They live in the waters of almost every...
</Question>
<Choice>eel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Among the most commercially valuable groups of fishes in the world are the flatfishes, a collective name applied to a large number of species with similar, distinctive features. One of the most notable characteristics of the flatfish is the location of the eyes: Both of them are on the same side of the head. Some species have both eyes on the...
</Question>
<Choice>flatfish</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The fish that can “fly” through the air for long distances is called the flying fish. It takes to the air with two winglike fins that are attached to either side of its body. These are known as pectoral fins. They are really elastic membranes that, when spread, serve as “wings.”
</Question>
<Choice>flying fish</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ancestors of the goldfish were dull-colored carp. Ornamental breeds of carp were developed by the Chinese, at least as early as the Song Dynasty, which ruled from 960 to 1279. Although it is native to East Asia, the goldfish is also found in many other places in the world.
</Question>
<Choice>goldfish</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In AD 240 the Roman historian Solinus wrote that the people of the Hebrides islands, located off Scotland's northwest coast, lived on fish and milk. That fish was herring. Herring and related fishes in the Clupeidae family have been economically significant for hundreds of years to countries bordering the Atlantic and Pacific oceans. In addition...
</Question>
<Choice>herring</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The only living representatives of the most primitive vertebrates are the eellike lampreys. Their ancestors can be traced back some 400 to 450 million years. The lampreys have no bones or jaws. The fish's skeleton is made of cartilage, and the mouth is a funnellike disk lined with horny teeth. Parasitic species attach themselves to other fishes...
</Question>
<Choice>lamprey</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the fastest fishes is the sailfish. It can swim at speeds of up to 68 miles (109 kilometers) per hour in short spurts and is known for its spectacular leaps above the water's surface. Its powerful streamlined body is dark blue above and white or silver below and can reach lengths of up to 12 feet (3.7 meters). The sailfish gets its name...
</Question>
<Choice>sailfish</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Chinook Indians arranged their lives by the annual run of the salmon. In spring and summer they gathered along the Columbia River to spear them as the fish swam upstream in tremendous shoals. The Chinook then dried them and stored them for winter food. Today the Pacific salmon is the most valuable of all the commercial fishes of North America...
</Question>
<Choice>salmon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nothing more unlike a fish could be imagined than the sea horse. In fact it looks much like the knight in a chess game. The sea horse has a head and neck shaped like a horse, and it swims in an upright position. The body is encased in bony, ringlike plates studded with spines. The long tail curls forward at the tip. Like a monkey's tail, the sea...
</Question>
<Choice>sea horse</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Fossil records indicate that the first sharks lived some 300 million years ago, and by about 100 million to 70 million years ago, most of the modern sharks had evolved. Sharks are among the oldest living things, and they have remained essentially the same since the modern sharks first appeared.
</Question>
<Choice>shark</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the finest of all game and food fishes is the tuna, a giant relative of the mackerel. For beauty, strength, and speed, many sportsmen and commercial fishermen call the great bluefin tuna (Thunnus thynnus) the king of ocean game. It grows to a length of 14 feet (4 meters) and a weight of 1,800 pounds (800 kilograms). Its average weight...
</Question>
<Choice>tuna</Choice>
</item>
</topics>