<topics>
<item>
<Question>
Among the most widely cultivated of all flowers are carnations. Sometimes called clove pinks because of their spicy fragrance, carnations are often used in bouquets, corsages, and boutonnieres. These flowers are native to the Mediterranean region, where they have been cultivated for more than 2,000 years. The scientific name of the carnation is...
</Question>
<Choice>carnation</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The name chrysanthemum means “golden flower” in Latin. Actually, the colors range from pale yellow to chestnut or from pink to crimson, and many varieties are white. The flower heads may be single, like daisies, or double. In size they range from tiny pompons to immense hothouse flowers. The plants are rather coarse and strongly scented. They...
</Question>
<Choice>chrysanthemum</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The “day's eye,” as the daisy was known in Old English, is a flowering plant of the Asteraceae family. The common field, or oxeye, daisy looks like a tiny sun surrounded by white rays. It is a species of chrysanthemum native to Europe. Its scientific name is Chrysanthemum leucanthemum. Tradition says that it was carried to America in hay brought...
</Question>
<Choice>daisy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the most familiar wild plants is the dandelion. Children like to whistle through its hollow stem, make braided necklaces of its golden yellow blossoms, or blow the fluff off a head that has gone to seed. Many people, however, consider it a weed in lawns and gardens.
</Question>
<Choice>dandelion</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
All the familiar garden flowers of today have been developed from wild flowers. They were chosen for cultivation because of their beauty. By careful selection and cross-pollination of the finest plants, their blooms have been made even more beautiful. Some of them now bear little resemblance to their wild ancestors.
</Question>
<Choice>flowers, garden</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Whether grown indoors in pots or outdoors in beds and borders, geraniums are durable and popular plants. Selective breeding for more than two centuries has produced showy flowers, from deep red or pink to white in color, and fancy leaf shapes. The entire family is called Geraniaceae, from the Greek word geranos, meaning “crane.” The genus...
</Question>
<Choice>geranium</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The largest group of plants in the mallow (Malvaceae) family is the genus Hibiscus, which includes about 250 species of herbs, shrubs, and small trees. Some are delicate tropical blooms; others are hardy and grow almost anywhere.
</Question>
<Choice>hibiscus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
There are about 200 species of honeysuckles found throughout the Northern Hemisphere. They are usually deciduous, sometimes more or less evergreen, and may be climbers, tall bushes, or trailers. Most have two-lipped flowers and red, orange, or black berries. Birds and insects relish the honeysuckle's colorful, juicy berries, and the sweetly...
</Question>
<Choice>honeysuckle</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
True lilies belong to the genus Lilium of the family Liliaceae. The genus contains between 80 and 100 species, all native to the Northern Hemisphere. Lilies have six-part flowers—three petals and three sepals (modified leaves) colored alike—and usually six stamens. The flowers of some species are quite fragrant, and they occur in a wide variety...
</Question>
<Choice>lily</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Because of their lustrous foliage and large blossoms, the magnolias are some of the handsomest flowering trees. There are about 200 species of magnolias, including both trees and shrubs. The magnolias are native to Asia, ranging from the Himalayas to Japan, and are cultivated in many parts of Central and North America. Some hybridized Chinese...
</Question>
<Choice>magnolia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
So disagreeable is the smell of the common marigold that many 16th-century gardeners regarded it as poisonous, and one proclaimed that “few care to handle it, and most choose to admire its charms at a distance only.” Nevertheless, the plant's hardiness and the variety and bright colors of its flowers have succeeded in gaining the favor of...
</Question>
<Choice>marigold</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The graceful narcissus flower takes its name from a Greek myth. Narcissus was a beautiful youth who refused the love of a nymph named Echo. In punishment the gods condemned him to fall in love with his own image. Forced to gaze constantly at his reflection in a clear pool, he pined away and died. In pity the gods changed Narcissus into a lovely...
</Question>
<Choice>Narcissus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Extraordinary prices have been paid for a single rare specimen of the remarkable orchid family of plants. These flowers are so exquisite in their delicate colorings of rose, lilac, yellow, white, and green, so pleasing in their fragrance of violet or orrisroot, and so graceful in many of their forms that they have become the favorites of flower...
</Question>
<Choice>orchid</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
With its shiny, dark green foliage and showy masses of brilliant blooms, the peony is a popular garden flower. It thrives in any soil and has been cultivated since the days of the ancient Romans.
</Question>
<Choice>peony</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Found in gardens and in the wild, phlox plants are admired for their clustered flowers. The blossoms' bright colors—blue, purple, pink, crimson, salmon, and white—inspired phlox's name, the Greek word for “flame.” The individual flowers that make up the clusters are tubular with five flaring lobes. There are about 65 species of phlox; all but one...
</Question>
<Choice>phlox</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The brightly colored papery flowers of the stately poppies make them a favorite in rock gardens and borders. The single-blossomed kinds range in color from white, pink, and rose to yellow, orange, and scarlet. There are also double varieties, some with fringed petals.
</Question>
<Choice>poppy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Throughout June and July the colorful flowers and shining foliage of the rhododendron beautify the mountain slopes of North America. The tubular, funnel-shaped flowers are white, pink, lilac, or purple; the leaves, usually evergreen, are thick and leathery.
</Question>
<Choice>rhododendron</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Among the best-loved and most widely grown flowers is the rose, the national flower of the United States. Its clear, delicate colors, its often rich fragrance, and the beauty of its form have made the rose a favorite garden flower since ancient times. Indeed, the ancient Greek lyric poet Sappho labeled the rose the Queen of Flowers. As early as...
</Question>
<Choice>rose</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
When the French explorer Samuel de Champlain visited the American Indians on the eastern shore of Lake Huron some 300 years ago, he found them cultivating the common sunflower. The parts of the plant furnished the Indians with a wide variety of useful products.
</Question>
<Choice>sunflower</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The tulip is a member of the lily family. By crossbreeding, florists have produced thousands of varieties. There are the single and double early tulips. There are also the taller late types, which bloom in a wide variety of bright colors.
</Question>
<Choice>tulip</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The native flowering plants of a region are its wild flowers. They originated there and grow wild year after year under natural conditions if they are undisturbed by humans.
</Question>
<Choice>wild flowers</Choice>
</item>
</topics>