<topics>
<item>
<Question>
Because of the apple's fine qualities, it is sometimes called the king of fruits. The hardy apple flourishes over more parts of the Earth than any other fruit tree. Because the fruit keeps for months in cool storage, it was a dependable winter fruit supply before cold storage was developed.
</Question>
<Choice>apple</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the earliest cultivated fruits, the banana is known for its high nutritional value. It is consumed extensively throughout the tropics, where it is grown, and is also valued in the temperate zone.
</Question>
<Choice>banana</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Strawberries, raspberries, blackberries, mulberries, and similar small fruits that grow on a bush or small tree fit the popular notion of berries. To a botanist, however, these are not true berries. They are classified scientifically as either aggregate fruits or multiple fruits. True berries are simple fruits that develop from a single, entire...
</Question>
<Choice>berry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The plants of the cabbage group include not only the common head cabbage but also broccoli, cauliflower, kale, and other familiar vegetables. Members of the mustard family, cabbages are among the oldest of vegetables grown for human consumption. Homer, nearly 3,000 years ago, wrote in the Iliad that Achilles washed cabbages.
</Question>
<Choice>cabbage</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The fruit of the cherry tree may be eaten fresh or prepared in pies, other desserts, sauces, preserves, brandies, and liqueurs. Like peaches, apricots, nectarines, plums, and almonds, cherries belong to the genus Prunus of the rose family. The cherry tree's pink and white blossoms look much like those of the wild rose. The small roundish fruits...
</Question>
<Choice>cherry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Members of the rue family (Rutaceae), citrus trees make up the genus Citrus. All citrus fruits are considered by botanists to be a special type of berry called a hesperidium. The fruit has a leathery peel and a fleshy, edible interior. The interior flesh, or pulp, is divided into eight or more sections that contain many tiny juice sacs and the...
</Question>
<Choice>citrus fruit</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the United States, Canada, and Australia the term corn refers to maize, or what is sometimes known as Indian corn. The rest of the world calls this grain maize. (This grain is known in South Africa, however, as mealies.) In England the word corn refers to wheat, and in Scotland and Ireland it refers to oats. This article uses the word corn to...
</Question>
<Choice>corn</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An important part of a well-balanced diet, fresh fruit contains large quantities of water and is not a substantial food. Fruits are important mainly for the vitamins and minerals they contain. Acids they contain also help digestion.
</Question>
<Choice>fruit</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the most popular cooking ingredients and a bulbous vegetable plant that grows beneath the ground, garlic belongs to the lily family, Liliaceae. It is closely related to the onion. Each bulb contains several sections, called cloves, which are covered by a thin papery skin. The cloves—peeled, pounded and dried, minced or crushed—are the...
</Question>
<Choice>garlic</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Fossilized leaves, seeds, and stems of grapes, some of them perhaps 40 million years old, have been found throughout the Northern Hemisphere. The grape is native to the north temperate zone. There are about 60 species and more than 8,000 varieties of grape. The mature fruit of most species can be eaten fresh or dried. Dried grapes are known as...
</Question>
<Choice>grape</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The more than 18,000 kinds of plants belonging to the pea family (Leguminosae) are known as legumes. The Leguminosae is the third largest family of flowering plants, being exceeded in numbers of species only by the Compositae (sunflower family) and Orchidaceae (orchid family). The word legume means seed pod and refers to the case that encloses...
</Question>
<Choice>legume</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The world's most popular salad green is lettuce. It originated in western Asia and was popular with the ancient Persians, Greeks, and Romans.
</Question>
<Choice>lettuce</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
For many centuries the sweet fragrant flesh of melons has been relished. Melons are usually eaten as fresh fruits, though they are sometimes pickled or preserved. They are good sources of vitamins A and C and are low in calories and sodium. The fruits are round or oval-shaped with protective outer rinds that cover the fleshy pulp. The pulp in...
</Question>
<Choice>melon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Prized since ancient times, the evergreen olive tree and its fruit have enjoyed a venerable history. The tree, believed to be a native of Asia Minor, may live for 1,500 years or more and is among the oldest trees known in Europe. It is frequently mentioned in the Bible, and it was cultivated on the island of Crete as early as 3500 BC. Around the...
</Question>
<Choice>olive</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The spherical bulb of the onion was regarded by the ancient Egyptians as a symbol of the universe. It is thought that the onion gets its name from the Latin unus, meaning “one.” The onion has been used as a cure for a variety of ailments, but it is best known for its use in cooking.
</Question>
<Choice>onion</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In spite of the peach tree's short life, its fruit was a symbol of immortality to the ancient Chinese. They exchanged the fruit as a token of affection and placed bowls of peaches in the tombs of loved ones to prevent the bodies from decaying. Peaches are believed to have originated in China then to have spread westward through Asia to the...
</Question>
<Choice>peach</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The pear, which is probably of European origin, has been cultivated since at least 2000 BC. The common pear was introduced into the New World by Europeans when the colonies were established.
</Question>
<Choice>pear</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The edible, pungent fruits called garden peppers have been known since ancient times. They have been found in prehistoric remains in Peru and were widely grown in Central and South America in pre-Columbian times. Pepper seeds were carried to Spain in 1493, and from there the plants spread rapidly throughout Europe.
</Question>
<Choice>peppers</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Once a rare delicacy, the pineapple has become a familiar fruit in many parts of the world. It was found in the West Indies by Christopher Columbus and other early explorers and apparently was disseminated largely by the Portuguese. Now it is grown in most tropical lands.
</Question>
<Choice>pineapple</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The most widely distributed of the stone fruits, plums exist in great variety throughout much of Europe, Asia, and North America. They range in size from as small as a cherry to as large as a hen's egg and vary in color from purple or dark blue to red, yellow, or green. Their texture may be firm or soft and their flavor bitter or sweet.
</Question>
<Choice>plum</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Considered by most botanists to be a native of the Peruvian-Bolivian Andes, the potato is one of the main food crops of the world. The edible part of a potato plant is the tuber, the swollen ends of its underground stems.
</Question>
<Choice>potato</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On Halloween night, porches are lit with the orange glow of jack-o'-lanterns—carved pumpkins that grin, grimace, and scowl by the light of a flickering candle within their walls. The pumpkin is a versatile fruit commonly grown in North America, Great Britain, and Continental Europe for human food and livestock feed. In the United States and...
</Question>
<Choice>pumpkin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The long, juicy leaf stalks of the garden rhubarb, or pie plant, are among the earliest contributions of the garden in spring. These stalks are tart, having a high acid content, and are cooked with sugar for use in pies, compotes, and preserves. Sometimes the stalks are used as the base of a wine or aperitif. The leaves, however, contain a toxic...
</Question>
<Choice>rhubarb</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
South America is the home of the tomato, a fruit that is commonly called a vegetable. Indians of the Andes Mountains grew it for food in prehistoric times. Migrations carried it to Mexico more than 3,000 years ago. The Spaniards introduced the tomato to Europe in the 16th century. It was first grown in Italy about 1550.
</Question>
<Choice>tomato</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The watermelon plant is a trailing annual with long running stems and tendrils. Small lemon-yellow flowers grow in the axils of the large, deeply notched leaves. The number of fruits per vine varies from two or three to 15.
</Question>
<Choice>watermelon</Choice>
</item>
</topics>