<topics>
<item>
<Question>
The process by which a government counts its people is called a census. Censuses—sometimes called enumerations—are also used to find out what kinds of people a country has, how they live, what they possess, how their economy functions, and much more.
</Question>
<Choice>census</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
It is no coincidence that the words citizenship and city are similar. Both are derived from the Latin word for “city.” In ancient Greece and Rome citizens were the free inhabitants of a city, or, more properly, of a city-state. The city-state was a self-governing community that came many centuries before the development of nations (see city-state).
</Question>
<Choice>citizenship</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At the dawn of Western civilization, in the Tigris-Euphrates river valley of the Middle East, there arose more than a dozen self-governing communities called city-states. These societies were the first attempts of people to create independent political structures for themselves. The chief characteristic of the city-state was geographical: it...
</Question>
<Choice>city-state</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The study of a person's rights and duties as a citizen is known as civics. It is a combination of many subjects, including history, political science, and social sciences.
</Question>
<Choice>civics</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Human rights traditionally have been put in two categories, natural rights and civil rights. Natural rights are those that belong to individuals by virtue of their humanity: the right to remain alive, to sustain life with food and shelter, and to follow the dictates of their conscience. Civil rights are based on positive law; they are derived...
</Question>
<Choice>civil rights</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The largest, richest, and most powerful empire in the world's history was the British Empire. At its zenith, Great Britain ruled broad lands on every continent and islands in every ocean. It was a common saying that the sun never set on Britain's dominions. As one after another of these lands have become independent states, they have joined...
</Question>
<Choice>Commonwealth of Nations</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Every government has an organizational structure that defines the specific responsibilities of its public officials. Some officials make the laws, others see to their enforcement. Taxes must be collected and revenues spent. There must be provision for preserving the domestic peace and providing for national defense. The fundamental written...
</Question>
<Choice>constitution</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
If it is against criminal law, it is a crime. It is societies acting through their governments that make the rules declaring what acts are illegal. Hence, war is not a crime. Although it is the most violent of human activities, it has not been declared illegal by governments or their agencies. But petty theft—the stealing of a loaf of bread—is a...
</Question>
<Choice>crime</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the chief purposes of government, according to the United States Constitution, is to insure domestic tranquillity. Helping keep such promises of peace and order within nations is the primary function of every court system in every nation. The courts are the branch of government that must make decisions about problems of civil and criminal...
</Question>
<Choice>court of justice</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The word democracy literally means “rule by the people.” It is derived from a Greek word coined from the words demos (“people”) and kratos (“rule”) in the middle of the 5th century BC as a name for the political system that existed at the time in some of the cities of Greece, notably Athens. As a form of government, democracy contrasts with...
</Question>
<Choice>democracy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The single most vital issue confronting the world after World War II was the prevention of nuclear warfare. During the decades-long Cold War this task was the focus of diplomatic discussions between the United States and the Soviet Union and a leading item on the agenda of the United Nations.
</Question>
<Choice>disarmament</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the major forms of government of the 20th century is called fascism. The name is derived from the Latin fasces, a symbol of authority in ancient Rome. The fasces was a bundle of rods strapped together around an axe, and it represented the unbreakable power of the state. Fascism, along with Communism (and to some extent, Socialism), holds...
</Question>
<Choice>fascism</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Since early times people have displayed flags and various other objects to show their nationality or their allegiances. Today, in addition to representing nations and other political entities, flags are used to represent youth groups, such as the Boy Scouts and Girl Scouts; political alliances, such as the North Atlantic Treaty Organization...
</Question>
<Choice>flags</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A right may be defined as something to which an individual has a just claim. The American Declaration of Independence states that “all men?.?.?.?are endowed by their Creator with certain unalienable Rights, that among these are Life, Liberty, and the pursuit of Happiness.” This is a brief statement about human rights in contrast to civil rights...
</Question>
<Choice>human rights</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The most significant military figure of the European Middle Ages was the knight. Knighthood emerged as a distinct order in around the year 1000, and the knight came to be defined as a warrior mounted on a horse and dressed in a suit of armor. The word knight is derived from the Old English word cniht, the equivalent of the Latin word caballarius...
</Question>
<Choice>knighthood</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
All the rules requiring or prohibiting certain actions are known as law. In the most general sense, there are two kinds of law—natural law and positive law. Natural law has been recognized since the ancient world to be a general body of rules of right conduct and justice common to all mankind. This concept grew from the observation of the...
</Question>
<Choice>law</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A basic document that states the liberties guaranteed to the English people, the Magna Carta proclaims rights that have become a part of English law and are now the foundation of the constitution of every English-speaking nation. The Magna Carta, which means “great charter” in Latin, was drawn up by English barons and churchmen, who forced the...
</Question>
<Choice>Magna Carta</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A nation is a unified territorial state with a political system that governs the whole society. A nation may be very large with several political subdivisions—such as the United States, China, Canada, or Australia—or it may be a small unit like the city-state of Singapore. A nation need not consist of a single, continuous geographical unit. The...
</Question>
<Choice>nation and nationalism</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The legislature, or lawmaking body, of the United Kingdom, Canada, Australia, India, and most other Commonwealth nations is called a parliament. The legislative assembly of the European Union is called the European Parliament. Many individual European nations and Japan also have parliamentary-type legislatures, though they use other names. Japan...
</Question>
<Choice>parliament</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Government policy is made by elected officials who are members of political parties. In the United States most elected officials are members of either the Democratic or Republican party, though occasionally members of smaller parties are also elected.
</Question>
<Choice>political party</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One meaning of the Greek word politeia is “government.” The word was used in ancient Greece as a general term to describe the way city-states were ruled, and it is derived from the word polis, which means “city-state.” Today the word politics refers to all aspects and types of government. Political science is a more specific term. It means the...
</Question>
<Choice>political science</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
During 1831 and 1832 two Frenchmen, Alexis de Tocqueville and Gustave de Beaumont, toured the United States. After their visit each wrote a book. Beaumont's volume is about slavery. Tocqueville's is the classic ‘Democracy in America'. Publication of the books obscured the original purpose of their visit. The two men had been sent to the United...
</Question>
<Choice>prison and punishment</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The most common form of forced labor in the history of civilization is slavery. Servitude is the general term used to describe all types of forced labor. It is derived from the Latin noun servus, which really means “slave,” though it is recognizable as the source of “servant” as well. Throughout the ancient world, anyone who functioned as a...
</Question>
<Choice>slavery and serfdom</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Geographic and political subdivisions of large nations are often called states or provinces. In the former Soviet Union they were republics; in Germany the term is Länder (singular, Land); and in Switzerland the divisions are called cantons. Sometimes—as in France, where the subdivisions are called departments—these units may be entirely subject...
</Question>
<Choice>state government</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Governmental rights granted to individual states in a country by a federal constitution are called states' rights. On Feb. 19, 1985, the United States Supreme Court ruled that federal minimum wage laws apply to employees of state and local governments. The case, Garcia vs. San Antonio Metropolitan Transit Authority, was one in a long series of...
</Question>
<Choice>states' rights</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The right to vote is called suffrage. It is from the Latin word suffragium, which has several meanings, including “vote,” “ballot,” and “voting rights.” Suffrage—also called the franchise—is a civil right enjoyed by citizens of a democratic state. (See also citizenship; civil rights.)
</Question>
<Choice>suffrage</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
It is the “total” in totalitarianism that gives the best clue to its meaning. The term refers to the type of government that attempts to assert total control over the lives of its citizens. This form of tyranny was a 20th-century development that was instituted to serve the goal of transforming society according to socialist principles...
</Question>
<Choice>totalitarianism</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
“Every age, however destitute of science or virtue, sufficiently abounds with acts of blood and military renown.” This judgment by the historian Edward Gibbon was echoed in the 20th century by one of the great generals of World War II, Sir Bernard Law Montgomery: “As man became more and more civilized, so wars became more and more frequent...
</Question>
<Choice>warfare</Choice>
</item>
</topics>