<topics>
<item>
<Question>
The process of changing from a child into an adult is called adolescence. During this period of change young people mature physically, begin to take responsibility for themselves, and start to deal with the world on their own. For most young people, adolescence is a time in which pleasure and excitement are mixed with confusion and frustration...
</Question>
<Choice>adolescence</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The disease called acquired immunodeficiency syndrome, but better known as AIDS, is a complicated illness that may involve several phases. It is caused by the human immunodeficiency virus (HIV), which can be passed from person to person. AIDS impairs the human body's immune system—the system responsible for warding off disease—and leaves the...
</Question>
<Choice>AIDS</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Some people suffer from hay fever when pollen is in the air. Others develop skin rashes when they touch certain substances. Still others experience stomach cramps after eating particular foods. These ailments are all caused by allergic reactions to various substances. In most cases, an allergy causes relatively mild symptoms such as sneezes...
</Question>
<Choice>allergy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
To understand the human body it is necessary to understand how its parts are put together and how they function. The study of the body's structure is called anatomy; the study of the body's function is known as physiology.
</Question>
<Choice>anatomy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The life fluid of the body is blood. It makes up about 113 of the total weight of the human body. A person who weighs 154 pounds (70 kilograms), for example, has about 12 pounds (5.4 kilograms) of blood. Since blood is fluid, however, it is easier to talk about it in terms of volume instead of weight: a 154-pound person has about 12 pints...
</Question>
<Choice>blood</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The most commonly used system of writing by and for blind persons is called Braille. Named after its French inventor, Louis Braille (1809–52), it is a code of 63 characters. Each character is composed of six dots arranged in a cell that is three dots long and two dots wide. The characters are embossed in lines on heavy paper, and they are read...
</Question>
<Choice>Braille</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The human brain is a miraculous organ. It regulates thought, memory, judgment, personal identity, and other aspects of what is commonly called mind. It also regulates aspects of the body—including body temperature, blood pressure, and the activity of internal organs—to help the body respond to its environment and to maintain the body's health. In...
</Question>
<Choice>brain and spinal cord</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Of all the words in the English language, probably no other inspires as much dread as the word cancer. Although commonly thought of and conveniently referred to as a single disease, cancer is not just one disease. It is a group of more than 100 diseases caused by abnormal cells that cannot be repaired, and thus grow and spread uncontrollably...
</Question>
<Choice>cancer</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The infectious disease known as chicken pox (or varicella) is characterized by a slight fever and small red bumps on the skin. Most people contract it during childhood—when it is usually in its most mild form—but when it occurs in an adult, it is severe. The disease is transmitted by a herpes virus, Varicella zoster, which is found in airborne...
</Question>
<Choice>chicken pox</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Although cholera is usually not life-threatening, the symptoms it produces can be extremely uncomfortable. Cholera is an acute infection of the small intestine resulting in a profuse, watery diarrhea, vomiting, and dehydration. Infection always occurs by ingesting food or water that has been contaminated with the bacterium Vibrio cholerae...
</Question>
<Choice>cholera</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The waxy substance called cholesterol is present in blood plasma and in all animal tissues. Cholesterol is an organic compound belonging to the steroid family; its molecular formula is C27H46O. In its pure state it is a white, crystalline substance that is odorless and tasteless.
</Question>
<Choice>cholesterol</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
microscopic, threadlike part of the cell that carries hereditary information in the form of genes; among simple organisms, such as bacteria and cyanobacteria (formerly called blue-green algae), chromosomes consist entirely of DNA and are not enclosed within a membrane; among all other organisms chromosomes are contained in a membrane-bound cell...
</Question>
<Choice>chromosome</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The cardiovascular, or circulatory, system in humans is composed of the heart and the blood vessels—arteries, veins, and capillaries. Its purpose is to provide nutrients and oxygen to the tissues and to remove wastes from them. It is also where the body fights infections.
</Question>
<Choice>circulatory system</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
What happens to food after it is eaten? The body uses various kinds of food for energy and growth. To be used, however, food must be converted into nutrients that can be carried through the bloodstream and absorbed by the organism's cells. This conversion process is called digestion.
</Question>
<Choice>digestive system</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A disease is a condition that impairs the proper function of the body or of one of its parts. All living things can succumb to disease. People, for example, are often infected by bacteria, but bacteria, in turn, can be infected by certain viruses.
</Question>
<Choice>disease, human</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Physicians use special chemical compounds to diagnose, prevent, or treat certain kinds of diseases. These compounds are drugs. A more scientific name for them is pharmaceuticals. (See also anesthesia; antibiotic; antiseptic; antitoxin; disease, human; medicine; pharmacy; vaccine.)
</Question>
<Choice>drugs</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Vibrations of air molecules moving through the air are received and translated into messages that the brain recognizes as sound by a complex organ—the ear. The ear has two important, but different, functions: hearing and sensing the body's equilibrium, or balance. The mechanisms for these processes are located within a hollow space in the skull...
</Question>
<Choice>ear</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The physical training of the human body to improve the way it functions is known as exercise. Exercise can be categorized as either active or passive. Exercise involving voluntary physical effort such as walking, swimming, bicycling, and jogging is known as active exercise. Passive exercise involves a machine or the action of another person. It...
</Question>
<Choice>exercise</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The human eye is a complex part of the body that is used for seeing. Eyes enable people to perform daily tasks and to learn about the world that surrounds them. Sight, or vision, is a rapidly occurring process that involves continuous interaction between the eye, the nervous system, and the brain. When someone looks at an object, what he really...
</Question>
<Choice>eye</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nutrition begins with food. It is the process by which the human body nourishes itself by transforming food into energy and body tissues. The science of nutrition concerns everything the body does with food to carry on its functions. Food provides essential substances called nutrients. The body needs these nutrients to help it make energy; grow...
</Question>
<Choice>food and nutrition</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A slender, flexible structure found on the surface of mammals, as well as on some insects and plants, is hair. One of the characteristics by which mammals are distinguished from other members of the animal kingdom is the presence of hair. Plant hairs called trichomes occur on roots, stems, and leaves.
</Question>
<Choice>hair</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A muscular, pear-shaped organ slightly larger than a clenched fist, the human heart is the center of the circulatory system. The human heart pumps blood through the body at a rate of more than about 4 quarts (3.8 liters) per minute.
</Question>
<Choice>heart</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The transmission of biological traits from one generation to the next is governed by the process of heredity. Heredity determines certain specific characteristics of plants and animals. Plants inherit traits that affect their physical and metabolic processes. Animals can inherit behavioral, mental, and physical traits. Some traits characteristic...
</Question>
<Choice>heredity</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A system of medical treatment, homeopathy is based on the principle that “likes are cured by likes.” According to this law of similars, drugs that cause disease symptoms in healthy individuals can also be used to cure illnesses that produce the same symptoms in sick individuals.
</Question>
<Choice>homeopathy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
All living organisms are continuously exposed to substances that are capable of causing them harm. Most organisms protect themselves against such substances in more than one way—with physical barriers, for example, or with chemicals that repel or kill invaders. Animals with backbones, called vertebrates, have these types of general protective...
</Question>
<Choice>immune system</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A viral infection of the respiratory passages known as influenza, or flu, may be accompanied by symptoms of fever, chills, headache, muscle ache, sore throat, and weakness. It is spread by breathing airborne droplets infected with one of three influenza viruses—A, B, or C. The incubation period is two to three days. In general, type A is more...
</Question>
<Choice>influenza</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
All active forms of life must get rid of the waste matter left after they have used what they need from the outside environment. They must also keep up a constant internal environment, a sort of inland sea with the right amount of water and dissolved chemicals. In most land animals, including humans, the kidney is the main organ for performing...
</Question>
<Choice>kidney</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The liver is the largest and heaviest organ within the body. It also has the most tasks to perform. Nestled in the upper abdomen behind the right lung, the liver seems to be a uniform blob of reddish-brown tissue, but it is the body's chief chemical factory, blood-purifying and tune-up station, poison detoxification center, and food storage and...
</Question>
<Choice>liver</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
All living animals must take in oxygen and get rid of carbon dioxide. In the vertebrates—animals with backbones—that get their oxygen from the air, both tasks are performed by special gas-exchange organs called lungs. The lungs provide a place where oxygen can reach the blood and carbon dioxide can be removed from it. They are equipped with...
</Question>
<Choice>lung</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The lymphatic, or lymphoid, system consists of tissues and organs designed to protect the body from damage by foreign materials. The major parts of the system are the lymph nodes, tonsils, thymus, spleen, and lymphatic vessels; additional lymphatic tissue is found in isolated patches in the gastrointestinal tract, lungs, and bone marrow. The...
</Question>
<Choice>lymphatic system</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(or rubeola), highly contagious viral infection characterized by a fever, cough, spots on the gums, and a red rash that usually begins at the head and neck and slowly moves down to cover the entire body. The measles virus Morbillivirus is spread by inhalation of airborne droplets of infected nasal discharge. The incubation period is 7 to 14 days...
</Question>
<Choice>measles</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The practice of medicine—the science and art of preventing, alleviating, and curing disease—is one of the oldest professional callings. Since ancient times, healers with varying degrees of knowledge and skills have sought to restore the health or relieve the distress of the sick and injured. Often, that meant doing little more than offering...
</Question>
<Choice>medicine</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In vertebrate animals, including humans, the mouth is the entrance to the long and uninterrupted tube called the digestive tract (see Digestive System). It is composed, on the outside, of lips and cheeks; on the inside are the mouth's roof, floor, tongue, teeth, and gums. (See also Teeth and Gums; Tongue.) In humans the mouth has two primary...
</Question>
<Choice>mouth</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(or infectious parotitis), contagious disease characterized by inflammation and swelling of the parotid (salivary) glands on one or both sides of the jaw. One attack of mumps provides lifelong immunity. The mumps virus, Paramyxovirus, is spread by contact with an infected person's saliva. The virus incubates for two to three weeks before symptoms...
</Question>
<Choice>mumps</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
All animal movement depends on the use of muscles. Whether the movement is as simple as opening the eyes or as complex as running the high hurdles at a track event, each is the result of a complex series of electric, chemical, and physical interactions involving the brain, the central nervous system, and the muscles themselves. However, movement...
</Question>
<Choice>muscle</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Information about the outside world as well as the inner workings of the human body speeds to and from the brain and spinal cord through nerves. Nerves are bundles of the long, tubelike extensions of nerve cells. Impulses fired through them uniquely convey information throughout the body.
</Question>
<Choice>nervous system</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
It was in part the development of internal nostrils in ancient fishes that paved the way for our evolutionary ancestors' migration from sea to land millions of years ago. Nostrils provide a means of air intake for lung-breathing animals and have developed into structures that exist today in great variety in the animal kingdom.
</Question>
<Choice>nose</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the larger organs of the digestive tract, the pancreas is found in all vertebrates. The term also refers to a gland found in many invertebrates, the primary purpose of which is the secretion of digestive enzymes. The pancreas in vertebrates secretes digestive enzymes and produces the hormones insulin and glucagon.
</Question>
<Choice>pancreas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Great events make fascinating history, but commonplace occurrences quite often have a greater influence on society. The total number of persons killed in World War I was a little more than 8.5 million. The war provided material for countless books. The influenza epidemic of 1918–19, coming on the heels of the war, killed more than 20 million...
</Question>
<Choice>plague and epidemic</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Human beings are surrounded by poisons, though not all of these poisons are deadly. Some exist in the air and water as environmental pollutants; others are in the form of hazardous chemicals in the workplace; many others can be found in the home in cleaning-supply cabinets and medicine chests. This article will discuss primarily animal and...
</Question>
<Choice>poison</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The study of the way people think and behave is called psychology. The field of psychology has a number of subdisciplines devoted to the study of the different levels and contexts of human thought and behavior. Social psychology, for example, deals with human thought and action in a social context, while physiological psychology is concerned with...
</Question>
<Choice>psychology</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The science and art of preventing disease, prolonging life, and promoting physical and mental health and well-being through organized community efforts is known as public health. Public-health efforts are directed toward the health of a community, whereas private-health efforts are directed toward the health of individuals.
</Question>
<Choice>public health</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Reproduction is the process by which a living organism creates a likeness of itself. The process may be either asexual—meaning that an organism reproduces by itself alone—or sexual—which requires both male and female sex cells. The organs, glands, and other structures that enable an organism to reproduce are known as the reproductive system...
</Question>
<Choice>reproductive system</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
All living things need oxygen. Oxygen enables them to metabolize, or burn, nutrients, releasing the energy required to grow, reproduce, and maintain life. In the metabolic process, oxygen combines with the carbon in food and forms carbon dioxide as a waste product. The respiratory system is an organism's apparatus for taking in oxygen and...
</Question>
<Choice>respiratory system</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The bones of the body form a framework called the skeleton. This framework supports and protects the softer tissues. All the higher animals have an internal skeleton (endoskeleton) with a central spine, or backbone. Many lower animals, such as insects and shellfish, carry their skeletons on the outside (exoskeleton). Other creatures of still...
</Question>
<Choice>skeleton</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The human body's largest organ is the skin. All vertebrates (animals with backbones) have skin, though the covering in each species has different features, such as scales, feathers, or fur (see Feather; Hair; Leather).
</Question>
<Choice>skin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Once one of the world's most dreaded plagues, smallpox is an acute infectious disease caused by the virus Variola major, a member of the orthopoxvirus family. The disease has been known for thousands of years—it was described as early as 1122 BC in China and is referred to in the ancient Sanskrit texts of India. Evidence of smallpox was found on...
</Question>
<Choice>smallpox</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The saclike expansion of the alimentary canal between the esophagus and the small intestine is called the stomach. It is a hollow, muscular organ that stores food and passes it along in small amounts to the intestines for digestion. In some animals, including humans, the stomach also partially digests the food.
</Question>
<Choice>stomach</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The treatment of injury and disease by manual or operative procedures is called surgery. Its counterpart, medicine, treats disease with drugs, diet, irradiation, and other means. The two fields are closely related. The surgeon must be familiar, in general, with medical means of treatment, and a physician practicing medicine must have a general...
</Question>
<Choice>surgery</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
By cutting, tearing, and grinding food and by helping to mix it with saliva, teeth carry out the first step in digestion. This is known as mastication (see Digestive System). The teeth of human beings also help to form the sounds of speech, and they participate in facial expression.
</Question>
<Choice>teeth and gums</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The various activities of the body create waste by-products that must be expelled in order to maintain health. To excrete certain fluid wastes, the body has a specialized filtering and recycling system known as the urinary system. Solid wastes are ultimately expelled through the large intestine (see Digestive System).
</Question>
<Choice>urinary system</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In 1921 there were 206,939 cases of diphtheria reported in the United States, mostly among children. In 1983 only five people came down with the disease. In 1941 measles claimed 894,134 victims; in 1983 there were only 1,497 cases. The main reason for the dramatic decline in these serious diseases has been the development and use of vaccines.
</Question>
<Choice>vaccines</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
All living things, plant or animal, need vitamins for health, growth, and reproduction. Yet vitamins are not a source of calories and do not contribute significantly to body mass. The plant or animal uses vitamins as tools in processes that regulate chemical activities in the organism and that use basic food elements—carbohydrates, fats, and...
</Question>
<Choice>vitamins</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the systems of orthodox Hindu philosophy, Yoga, which is Sanskrit for “union,” seeks the union of the individual with the divine by means of exercise, breathing, posture, diet, and meditation. The most popular form of yoga is a type called hatha-yoga. Those who practice hatha-yoga seek to improve their health and sense of well-being by...
</Question>
<Choice>yoga</Choice>
</item>
</topics>