<topics>
<item>
<Question>
Mankind is not alone in living in organized communities, working cooperatively and efficiently, creating a clear division of labor, waging war, and occasionally capturing slaves. The most common of the social insects, the ant, also exhibits these behaviors. Ants do not have the power of reason, however, by which humans err and experience freedom...
</Question>
<Choice>ant</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
People have known ever since ancient times that the insects called bees make delicious honey from the nectar of flowers. There are more than 20,000 species of bees, and they are found all over the world except in Antarctica. Most people throughout the world recognize honeybees, and people in temperate regions know bumblebees as well (in some...
</Question>
<Choice>bee</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
There are more species of beetles than of any other kind of insect. They constitute the largest order of insects—Coleoptera—which includes more than a third of a million recognized species. In fact, the beetle order is the largest order in the entire animal kingdom. About a quarter of all known species of animals in the world are beetles. These...
</Question>
<Choice>beetle</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
To a poet butterflies and moths are like fluttering flowers. Scientists know them as a group of insects that make up the order Lepidoptera, meaning “scale wings.” They are so named because their wings and certain portions of their bodies are covered with a fine dust. Under a microscope the dust is seen to be made up of millions of finely ridged...
</Question>
<Choice>butterfly and moth</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Butterflies and moths in the larval stage of development are called caterpillars, from the Latin catta pilosa, meaning “hairy cat.” Not all caterpillars are hairy, however. Bare-skinned caterpillars—which are popularly called worms—include such types as the cabbageworm and the armyworm.
</Question>
<Choice>caterpillar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
After 17 years of dormancy underground, the best known of the 1,500 species of cicada emerges for five weeks of lively activity in the sunlight, and then dies. With the possible exception of the termite queen, this cicada may be the longest living insect.
</Question>
<Choice>cicada</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The cockroach is considered one of the most obnoxious of household pests. This brown or black insect can be found in houses, apartment and office buildings, ships, trains, and airplanes in many parts of the world. Domestic cockroaches, which are also called roaches, have a disagreeable odor. They live in warm, dark areas. Their broad, flat...
</Question>
<Choice>cockroach</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Crickets, grasshoppers, and katydids are among the most musical of insects. More than 10,000 species live throughout the world.
</Question>
<Choice>cricket, grasshopper, and katydid</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Among the most beautiful and useful of all insects is the dragonfly. It has thin silvery wings. Its body may be steel blue, purple, green, or copper. The dragonfly eats mosquitoes, flies, and other insects harmful to man.
</Question>
<Choice>dragonfly</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Fireflies are not really flies. They are members of the beetle order. The males have wings and are relatively good fliers. The females of most species have short wings or are wingless. The wingless females and the long, flat firefly larvae, which these females resemble, are often called glowworms. Most fireflies are visible at night because of...
</Question>
<Choice>firefly and glowworm</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The flea is one of the most troublesome of insects and one of the most dangerous. Rat fleas carry the germs of bubonic plague from rats to man. They also spread the germs of a type of typhus fever.
</Question>
<Choice>flea</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
While some flies are beneficial to humans as parasites of insect pests or as scavengers and many others are important as plant pollinators, flies are also known to be carriers of such serious diseases as cholera, typhoid, and dysentery. In most species of fly the body and padded feet are covered with bristling hairs and the tongue is coated with...
</Question>
<Choice>fly</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The name locust is popularly given to two different kinds of insects—the short-horned grasshopper and the cicada. Both kinds do great damage to trees and crops when they swarm in huge numbers.
</Question>
<Choice>locust</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The predatory mantis is well adapted for catching the living insects on which it feeds. It is often called the praying mantis because of the way it holds its prehensile front legs while waiting to make a kill. The mantis remains motionless or sways gently back and forth, with head raised and front legs outstretched in an apparent attitude of...
</Question>
<Choice>mantis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
More than just annoying insects, some mosquitoes are responsible for transmitting diseases that can result in serious illness and even death. Mosquitoes were once viewed merely as a nuisance because of the itching and irritation that resulted from their bites. In the early 1900s, however, they were recognized as carriers of yellow fever, malaria...
</Question>
<Choice>mosquito</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Although they are closely related to cockroaches, termites are sometimes called “white ants” because their general appearance and social organization are like those of the ants. Termites, however, are distinguished from ants by their soft bodies and lighter color. Ants have hard bodies and are usually dark (see Ant). Furthermore, the termite's...
</Question>
<Choice>termite</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Most people think of wasps only as bugs with bad tempers and sharp stings. Actually, wasps exhibit remarkably sophisticated behavior and are often helpful, especially to farmers, because they help to check the population of other insects that may be harmful to crops. The many species that feed on nectar travel from flower to flower just as bees...
</Question>
<Choice>wasp</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Even though they breathe air, several kinds of insects can also live underwater and are able to fly, crawl, or swim at will. Called water bugs, such insects belong to the order of true bugs—Hemiptera.
</Question>
<Choice>water bug</Choice>
</item>
</topics>