<topics>
<item>
<Question>
Certain animals and plants develop characteristics that help them cope better than others of their species with their environment. This natural biological process is called adaptation. Among the superior traits developed through adaptation are those that may help in obtaining food or shelter, in providing protection, and in producing and...
</Question>
<Choice>adaptation</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At first glance, the green stain on damp rocks and tree trunks, the fine scum on quiet ponds, and the massive seaweeds of the oceans seem so different that the casual observer would assume they have no relationship to one another. However, these organisms, and thousands like them, are algae. Approximately 27,000 marine and freshwater species of...
</Question>
<Choice>algae</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
All living organisms, from protozoa to plants and animals, have in common the fact that they synthesize protein by using the same 20 amino acids, even though more than 100 amino acids occur in nature. If proteins are the bricks from which the body is made, then amino acids are the grains of sand and clay that make up those bricks. Chemists...
</Question>
<Choice>amino acid</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A tiny blob of colorless jelly with a dark speck inside it—this is what an amoeba looks like when seen through a microscope. The colorless jelly is cytoplasm, and the dark speck is the nucleus. Together they make up a single cell of protoplasm, the basic material of all living things (see cell).
</Question>
<Choice>amoeba</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The one-celled organisms called bacteria live on, in, and around most living and nonliving things. Most bacteria can be seen only with the aid of a microscope, and millions of them would fit on the head of a pin.
</Question>
<Choice>bacteria</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scientists in the field of biochemistry study the chemical basis of life's activities. They have shown that all living things—amoebas and elephants alike—share many similarities at the level of atoms and molecules. Without exception, all animals and plants operate on the basis of a few unvarying biological principles. These principles are: all...
</Question>
<Choice>biochemistry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The scientific study of living things is called biology. Biologists strive to understand the natural world and its inhabitants—plants, animals, fungi, protozoa, algae, bacteria, and viruses—by asking why and how the processes of life occur. Why do living organisms interact with each other in particular ways? When did they evolve? How are...
</Question>
<Choice>biology</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Plants are found throughout the world, on land, in water, and even floating in the air. They are extremely important organisms, essential to the continuation of all life on Earth. Because of both their crucial role and their own interesting variations, plants are the subjects of the science of botany. Botany is the study of not only the so...
</Question>
<Choice>botany</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The smallest unit of living matter that can exist by itself is the cell. Some organisms, such as bacteria, consist of only a single cell. Others, such as humans and oak trees, are composed of many billions of cells.
</Question>
<Choice>cell</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1809–82). The theory of evolution by natural selection that was developed by Charles Darwin revolutionized the study of living things. In his Origin of Species (1859) he provided a scientific explanation of how the diverse species of plants and animals have descended over time from common ancestors. His theory remains central to the foundations...
</Question>
<Choice>Darwin, Charles</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The study of the ways in which organisms interact with their environment is called ecology. The word ecology was coined in 1869 by the German zoologist Ernst Haeckel, who derived it from the Greek oikos, which means “household.” Economics is derived from the same word. However, economics deals with human “housekeeping,” while ecology concerns the...
</Question>
<Choice>ecology</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
All animals and plants, except for the most primitive types, begin their journey toward independent life when an egg is fertilized. An egg is a single female germ cell, or reproductive cell. It eventually develops into a new organism after it has been fertilized by a male germ cell (see Biology; Genetics). The egg cells of plants, when...
</Question>
<Choice>egg</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
People have always wondered how life originated and how so many different kinds of plants and animals arose. Stories of a supernatural creation of life developed among many peoples. The Bible, for example, tells of God's creation of humans and other higher animals over several days. Many people also believed that insects, worms, and other lower...
</Question>
<Choice>evolution</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A chemical change in animal and vegetable matter brought about by microscopic yeasts, bacteria, and molds is called fermentation. Examples of fermentation are the souring of milk, the rising of bread dough, and the conversion of sugars and starches to alcohol. Many industrial chemicals and a number of antibiotics used in modern medicine are...
</Question>
<Choice>fermentation</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
It is hard to imagine a resource that provides more benefits for humans than do forests. Food, shelter, tools, and fuels are all products of this natural treasury. The forest is also home to many animals and plants. Its trees help clear the air of pollution while enriching it with oxygen and slow down the sometimes destructive forces of wind and...
</Question>
<Choice>forest and forestry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Deep beneath one's own backyard may be the remains of plants and animals unlike any alive today. In many areas of the United States, if one digs long enough and deep enough, one may come across some ancient clamshells, a fragment of a big bone, a piece of petrified wood, or a leaf print.
</Question>
<Choice>fossils</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Fungi (singular, fungus) are everywhere in the environment—in the soil; in lakes, rivers, and the seas; in the air (some are so tiny that they are carried by currents of wind or on the bodies of insects); and in and on plants and animals, including humans. Along with bacteria, fungi are responsible for the decay of organic matter and the release...
</Question>
<Choice>fungus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Why do offspring resemble their parents? Such resemblances are passed on relatively unaltered from generation to generation through a process called heredity. The units of heredity are deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) segments called genes. Encoded in every gene are biochemical instructions that determine the characteristics, or traits, of an organism...
</Question>
<Choice>genetics</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Before northern winters begin many birds travel south to warmer climates. Some four-footed animals go southward too. Hardy creatures such as rabbits and foxes stay where they are and live as actively as they do in summertime.
</Question>
<Choice>hibernation</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The study of human origins is the study of how modern human beings evolved from earlier humanlike species and other nonhuman primates that are now extinct. Since ancient times, human beings have generally recognized that they are members of the animal world. It was only relatively recently, in the middle of the 19th century, however, that Charles...
</Question>
<Choice>human origins</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1707–78). The Swedish naturalist and physician Linnaeus brought into general use the scientific system of classifying plants and animals that is now universally used. This is the binomial (two-name) system, in which each living thing is assigned a name consisting of two Latin words. The first word is the name of the genus and the second the...
</Question>
<Choice>Linnaeus, Carolus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Living things include the plants, animals, fungi, and algae that we can see, as well as tiny organisms such as bacteria and protozoa, which can be seen only with a microscope. These organisms live on every type of habitat on Earth—on land and in the lakes, rivers, and seas; some organisms, such as some worms and certain bacteria and protozoa...
</Question>
<Choice>living things</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1822–84). The laws of heredity on which the modern science of genetics is based were discovered by an obscure Austrian monk named Gregor Mendel. Yet Mendel's discoveries remained virtually unknown for more than 30 years after he completed his experiments—in spite of the fact that his papers reached the largest libraries of Europe and the United...
</Question>
<Choice>Mendel, Gregor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A fascinating result of evolution is the phenomenon of mimicry, the superficial resemblance of one organism to another that gives the mimicking organism some advantage or protection from predators. Many plants and animals have evolved such resemblances in order to increase their own chances of survival. A walkingstick, for example, is an insect...
</Question>
<Choice>mimicry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Earth is the only one of the eight planets in the solar system that is known to have an appreciable amount of water on its surface (see planet). About 71 percent of the Earth's surface is covered by the oceans, and half of the world is covered by a layer of water more than two miles in depth. More than 98 percent of the water on Earth is in the...
</Question>
<Choice>oceanography</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Without photosynthesis, the replenishment of the Earth's fundamental food supply would halt, and the planet would become devoid of oxygen. During photosynthesis the radiant energy from the sun is harnessed and converted to the chemical energy stored in green plants and certain bacteria. In green plants this energy is used to convert carbon...
</Question>
<Choice>photosynthesis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The pollen produced by seed plants is essential to the plants' reproduction. Pollen grains are fertilizing bodies—they produce male sex cells, or sperm—and are formed in the stamen, or male apparatus, of seed-bearing plants. Pollination is the process by which these grains are transferred to the flower's pistil, or female structure, and unite...
</Question>
<Choice>pollen and pollination</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
As animals evolved, most of them developed body colors and markings that improved their chances of surviving. This adaptive mechanism, known as protective coloration, may serve any number of functions. Coloring can help protect an animal by making it hard to see. For an animal that spends much of its life trying to avoid dangerous enemies, this...
</Question>
<Choice>protective coloration</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A highly valued animal fiber, silk has long been used for the production of luxurious textiles of the finest quality. Silk, the “Queen of the Fibers,” is produced by silkworms. The silkworm is not really a worm at all; it is a caterpillar that spins a protective cocoon for use as a shelter while it changes from a caterpillar into a moth. This...
</Question>
<Choice>silk</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A park where captive animals, often from all over the world, live and are exhibited to visitors is a zoo or zoological garden. The word zoo comes from the Greek word zoion, which means “animal.”
</Question>
<Choice>zoo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Anyone who likes to visit a zoo or an aquarium, who collects butterflies, or who enjoys fishing or hunting shows an interest in zoology. The word zoo is from the Greek word zoion, which means “animal.” Zoology is the science of animals as botany is the science of plants. Together they make up biology, the science of all living things (see Living...
</Question>
<Choice>zoology</Choice>
</item>

</topics>