<topics>
<item>
<Question>
The aardvark, or “earth pig,” is one of Africa's strangest animals. Its thick body is thinly covered with stiff hair. Its back is arched. The animal's strong legs are short and stumpy. Its head has huge donkeylike ears, a long snout, and drooping eyelids with long lashes. Its naked tail tapers to a point from a thick base.
</Question>
<Choice>aardvark</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
As their name implies, anteaters are insect-eating animals belonging to the family Myrmecophagidae, which itself is part of the order Edentata (meaning “toothless”). The anteaters live in tropical grasslands and forests from southern Mexico to northern Argentina and Paraguay. They are densely furred, long-tailed animals with long skulls. Their...
</Question>
<Choice>anteater</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The term “antelope” is zoologically somewhat imprecise. It refers to a variety of animals with similar characteristics but belonging to different families. The only true antelope is the North American antelope, also called the pronghorn or prongbuck. It belongs to the family Antilocapridae. The other antelopes belong to the family Bovidae, which...
</Question>
<Choice>antelope</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Humans share more characteristics with the apes than with any other living organisms, and that may explain people's fascination with these animals. Both apes and humans are members of the order Primates, which also includes the monkeys and the prosimians. The apes are usually divided into two subgroups: the lesser apes—gibbons—and the great apes...
</Question>
<Choice>apes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Native to Central and South America, the armadillo is a piglike creature with bony armor. Jointed plates, which cover the back and sides of the animal, look like the armor worn by medieval knights. They protect the armadillo from attacks by enemies and from thorns and cactus. When danger threatens, some species are able to roll up into tight...
</Question>
<Choice>armadillo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
large monkey belonging to the genus Papio. Inhabiting much of sub-Saharan Africa, baboons are highly intelligent, noisy, and often ferocious members of the order Primates. With their exceptional adaptability, baboons are able to live in a wide range of habitats, including open woodland, savannah, grassland, and rocky hills. While other primates...
</Question>
<Choice>baboon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Because they fly, bats are often mistaken for birds. Bats are mammals, however, not birds. They have soft fur and large ears, and as babies they drink milk from their mothers. They are distinguished by their ability to navigate at night by using a system of sound vibrations (echolocation). This allows them to chase insects through thick forests...
</Question>
<Choice>bat</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Although it has a reputation for being fierce and aggressive, the bear is more often a peaceful and solitary creature. The largest of the carnivores—animals classified in an order of flesh-eating land mammals—and the least carnivorous, or flesh-eating. It is closely related to the dog and the raccoon.
</Question>
<Choice>bear</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A mammal belonging to the order of rodents, or gnawing animals, the beaver has been recognized as a master engineer. By using teeth and paws, beavers construct lodges, storehouses, dams, and canals. The animal is also known for its aquatic lifestyle as well as for its beautiful fur.
</Question>
<Choice>beaver</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The American bison (Bison bison), more commonly called buffalo, is the largest North American land mammal. Originally great herds ranged from Mexico to the region of the Great Slave Lake in Canada and from Pennsylvania and the Carolinas to west of the Rockies.
</Question>
<Choice>bison</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
African great ape. Known also as the pygmy chimpanzee, the bonobo was considered a subspecies of the chimpanzee until 1933, when it was classified as a separate species. Both species belong to the genus Pan, which is part of the great ape family, Pongidae, in the order Primates. The scientific name of the bonobo is Pan paniscus.
</Question>
<Choice>bonobo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
True buffalo are natives of Asia and most parts of Africa. They do not belong to the same genus as the American “buffalo,” or bison. The Asian water buffalo, or carabao, is still to be found in wild herds, though as a rule it is domesticated. This animal is large and powerful. A fully grown bull may stand 6 12 feet (2 meters) tall at the shoulders...
</Question>
<Choice>buffalo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The camels and their relatives, such as the llama and the vicuña, were domesticated about 4,000 to 6,000 years ago. Ever since, they have provided meat, milk, wool, and hides to various desert- and mountain-dwelling peoples of the Eastern and Western Hemispheres.
</Question>
<Choice>camel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Cats—domestic and wild—have intrigued humans for thousands of years, and throughout that time the relationship of these animals with humans has varied widely. People have valued cats as hunters, worshiped them as gods, and sacrificed them as demons. Many of the 37 species of cats have often been used as symbols of beauty, grace, mystery, and power...
</Question>
<Choice>cat</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In many areas of the world, cattle have long been among the most important domestic animals. Their meat is called beef—or veal, when taken from young animals—and is eaten by many people. Their milk is drunk and is used to make dairy products such as butter, cheese, and yogurt. Their hides are used to make leather. Their dung is used in fertilizer...
</Question>
<Choice>cattle</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
African great ape. The best studied of the great apes, the chimpanzee is considered by most authorities to be the closest living relative to humans. Although the degree of the relationships between humans and each of the great ape genera has long been debated, molecular analysis has verified that humans and chimpanzees share more than 98 percent...
</Question>
<Choice>chimpanzee</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The lively, chattering chipmunk looks like its relative the squirrel but is smaller and has a striped back. The rusty brown eastern chipmunk has five dark and two light stripes; the gray western, five dark and four light stripes. They are from 8 to 11 inches (20 to 28 centimeters) long.
</Question>
<Choice>chipmunk</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(or prairie wolf), animal. Viewed as a pest by some and surrounded by legend, the coyote is one of the most familiar of the North American wild canids. The image of a lone coyote howling at the moon is a staple of movie and television Westerns. Like its close relative the wolf, the coyote belongs to the family Canidae and genus Canis; the...
</Question>
<Choice>coyote</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Members of the deer family are found throughout the Western Hemisphere, Europe, and Asia. They are not native to Australia nor to most of Africa. Included among the approximately three dozen species in the deer family are moose; wapiti, or red deer; and caribou, or reindeer. The males of nearly all species of deer grow solid horns, called antlers...
</Question>
<Choice>deer</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The dog is one of the most popular pets in the world. Its loyalty and devotion are legendary, and because of this the dog has been called man's best friend. Class distinctions between people have no part in a dog's life. It can be a faithful companion to either rich or poor.
</Question>
<Choice>dog</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dolphins are small members of the whale order, Cetacea. Although the terms dolphin and porpoise are sometimes used interchangeably to refer to any member of the group, biologists recognize three distinct families: the true porpoises, with six marine species; the river dolphins, with five freshwater species; and the true dolphins, with more than...
</Question>
<Choice>dolphin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The largest living land animals are the elephants. Mammals of Africa and Asia, they live in habitats ranging from thick rain forests to savannas. The great size of elephants and the thickness and toughness of their skins protect them from most other animals. Since they have few enemies to fear, elephants are usually peaceful and easygoing. They...
</Question>
<Choice>elephant</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Foxes are closely related to dogs and jackals. They live in North America, Europe, Asia, and Africa. Some close relatives live in South America. In most regions where the fox has forest cover, it has survived in spite of hunting, trapping, and poisoning.
</Question>
<Choice>fox</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The hardy, gentle little gerbil that became a popular household pet in the United States during the 1960s is a burrowing rodent native to desert and near-desert regions of Africa and Asia. Also known as sand rats, they generally live in dry, sandy areas, but some of them prefer grasslands, cultivated fields, or forests. The gerbil is one of...
</Question>
<Choice>gerbil</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
primate belonging to the family Hylobatidae, also known as the lesser apes. Remarkably agile, gibbons move so swiftly through the tropical rain forests of their native Southeast Asia that they appear to fly. They demonstrate a specialized form of locomotion known as brachiation, using their long arms to swing from branch to branch and traverse...
</Question>
<Choice>gibbon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The tallest of all living animals is the giraffe. Even more peculiar than the size of this African animal is its shape, which has inspired amazement since ancient times. The male giraffe may grow to be from about 16 to 20 feet (5 to 6 meters) tall. The female is somewhat shorter. The giraffe's height comes mostly from its legs and neck, for its...
</Question>
<Choice>giraffe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The animals known as goats are hoofed mammals with hollow horns. They are closely related to sheep. Like sheep, they are ruminants, or cud-chewing animals, and eat grasses and shrubs. Some goats are wild, while others are raised by humans for their milk, cheese, wool, meat, and leather. They can live on coarse, thin plant growth and are often...
</Question>
<Choice>goat</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
African great ape. The largest of the great apes, gorillas have frequently been portrayed in fictional tales as ferocious creatures. In reality, however, gorillas are peaceful animals that subsist almost entirely on plant matter. Although they can appear intimidating when they encounter an outsider—either gorilla or human—they are rarely...
</Question>
<Choice>gorilla</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The guinea pig is not a pig, nor does it come from Guinea. It is a rodent, and its proper name is cavy. It is native to South America from Colombia and Venezuela to Brazil and northern Argentina. It lives at the edges of forests and swamps and in rocky regions. Domesticated strains are bred in Europe and North America for pets and for use in...
</Question>
<Choice>guinea pig</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
When the spiny hedgehog is frightened or attacked, it rolls itself into a ball to protect its vulnerable face and underparts, exposing only its sharp prickly spines. Hedgehogs belong to the family Erinaceidae and are divided into two types: the spiny hedgehogs and their spineless, soft-furred relatives, the hairy hedgehogs. Both kinds are found...
</Question>
<Choice>hedgehog</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An African folk tale describes how God created the hippopotamus and told it to cut grass for the other animals. When the hippo discovered how hot Africa was, however, it asked God if it could stay in the water during the day and cut grass at night when the weather was cool. God agreed, though He was reluctant because He feared the hippo might eat...
</Question>
<Choice>hippopotamus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Of all the animals, the horse has probably most closely shared in human adventures and has been most intimately allied with human progress. For thousands of years, the horse has participated in the pleasures, the dangers, and the hard work that have marked human life. Perhaps because of this long relationship, the horse holds a special place in...
</Question>
<Choice>horse</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Widely mistaken as a pure scavenger, the hyena is actually a brave nocturnal hunter in its own right. The animals' famous laughing sounds are uttered as they seize prey and fight among themselves for food. The cry often draws lions and other large carnivores, which may then try to steal the food.
</Question>
<Choice>hyena</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
wolflike, nocturnal, carnivore of dog genus Canis, family Canidae, found in open country of Asia, eastern Europe, and Africa; grows from 34 to 37 in. (86 to 94 cm) long and weighs from 15 to 24 lbs (7 to 11 kg); feeds on small animals, plant material, and carrion; travels alone, in pairs, or in packs; follows lions to finish carcasses left over...
</Question>
<Choice>jackal</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The largest member of the cat family found on the American continents is the jaguar. Its average length is between 6 and 7 feet (about 2 meters). It has a large head and massive legs. Jaguars vary in color, but usually they are yellowish brown, with black spots like those of the leopard. The jaguar's spots, however, are larger and more angular...
</Question>
<Choice>jaguar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
When Capt. James Cook was exploring the coast of Australia in 1770, his men were amazed by a strange animal. At times the creature stood upright, braced firmly on its hind legs and huge tail. It moved by great leaps. Thus Europeans first met the gray kangaroo, or forester, often called the “boomer” or “old man” of Australia.
</Question>
<Choice>kangaroo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Contrary to popular belief, lemmings do not plunge into the sea in a deliberate, suicidal death march. These small rodents of the far north normally hesitate to enter water and generally try to avoid swimming across rivers and other bodies of water. Lemmings are noted for the regular fluctuations of their populations and for their periodic...
</Question>
<Choice>lemming</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
common name given to various species of primitive primates. The name lemur comes from the Latin word lemures, meaning “ghosts.” It was given to these animals because of the silent, ghostlike way they move about. Although some lemurs are active during the day, the observers who assigned the name probably witnessed the eerily shining eyes of...
</Question>
<Choice>lemur</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
This spotted animal of the cat family lives in Africa, Asia Minor, Central Asia, and the Far East. It is a large cat, closely related to the lion and tiger. Leopards vary greatly in size and markings. They weigh, on average, from 60 to 200 pounds (27 to 90 kilograms) and are about 84 inches (213 centimeters) long, excluding the 36-inch...
</Question>
<Choice>leopard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On the plains of Africa, from South Africa to the Sahara, lions continue to thrive. They do their best hunting on the plateaus of eastern Africa and in the vast grasslands of the south. Their roar is the most terrifying voice of the grasslands. Lions live in rocky dens, in thorn-tree thickets, or in tall grasses at the edges of streams.
</Question>
<Choice>lion</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The wild cats called lynx have such sharp eyesight that people of ancient times believed they could see even through a stone wall. That is why sharp-sighted people are still referred to as “lynx-eyed.”
</Question>
<Choice>lynx</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Because it is sometimes mistaken for a swimming person, the manatee may have given rise to the folklore of mermaids. A slow-moving, seal-shaped mammal, the manatee lives in shallow coastal waters or rivers with rich plant life. All three species—the Caribbean (found off Florida and Georgia), Amazonian, and African manatees—are declining in...
</Question>
<Choice>manatee</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mammals that carry their young in an abdominal pouch during their early development are called marsupials. Soon after the marsupial ovum, or egg, is fertilized, the young are born in a premature state and crawl into the mother's pouch. There, nursing on milk from their mother's nipples, they complete their development.
</Question>
<Choice>marsupial</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The mole spends most of its life in darkness. It lives in an underground burrow and tunnels through soil to find its food of earthworms and other invertebrates. A mole may consume more than its weight in food daily. A long ridge of earth that zigzags across lawn and field is probably the roof of a mole's tunnel.
</Question>
<Choice>mole</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The playful little mongoose is renowned as a skilled and courageous snake fighter. It relies on speed, agility, and a growth of dense, loose hair into which the snake may inject venom without breaking the mongoose's skin.
</Question>
<Choice>mongoose</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
From the tiny, playful marmosets of the Amazon rain forest to the formidable, cunning baboons of the African savannah, monkeys hold a particular appeal for humans. Along with apes, monkeys are a popular attraction in zoos, where their antics and their reputation for cleverness endear them to visitors. More controversial is the extensive use of...
</Question>
<Choice>monkeys</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A small, scampering creature, the mouse relies on its senses of smell and hearing rather than sight to find its way around. It uses its nose to track down food and to follow scent paths. Its hearing is particularly attuned to high tones.
</Question>
<Choice>mouse</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A large, shaggy animal of the Arctic regions, the musk-ox is not an ox at all but a close relative of the sheep and goat. The first part of its name derives from the strong scent given off by the bulls during mating season.
</Question>
<Choice>musk-ox</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The dome-shaped mounds of mud and cattails scattered over a marsh or a pond are a muskrat “town.” Cut through the plant growth are “streets”—narrow channels along which the animals can be seen swimming. Muskrats look like small beavers and share some of the beaver's industrious habits.
</Question>
<Choice>muskrat</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A native of the tropical rain forest on the islands of Borneo and Sumatra, the orangutan is the only extant Asian great ape and the only species in the genus Pongo. In the Pleistocene period (2 million–8000 BC) the genus had a much greater distribution; fossils have been found in southern China, northern Vietnam, Laos, and Java. Some evidence...
</Question>
<Choice>orangutan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Two mammals native to the bamboo forests of East Asia are called pandas: the giant panda and the much smaller red panda. They are both members of the order Carnivora (the carnivores) but have been difficult to classify further. They were once thought to be closely related to each other and to either bears or raccoons. Through genetic studies...
</Question>
<Choice>panda</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Few animals have such economic importance to mankind yet suffer from such a deplorable image as does the pig. As a domestic animal it is a source of a wide variety of meats, high-quality leather, durable bristles for many kinds of brushes, and hundreds of medical products. At the same time, the pig is frequently regarded as unclean and even...
</Question>
<Choice>pig</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Native only to Tasmania and eastern and southern Australia, the platypus is the sole member of the mammal family Ornithorhynchidae. It is one of two animals that form the order Monotremata (egg-laying mammals), the other being the echidnas of Australia and New Guinea. The name platypus is derived from the Greek platys meaning “broad” and pous...
</Question>
<Choice>platypus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
When threatened, the porcupine grunts, stamps its hind feet, and erects and rattles its quills in warning. The offender would do well to retreat, for the quills detach easily from the porcupine and can become painfully embedded in the enemy's skin. (Contrary to common belief, the porcupine cannot shoot its quills.) Not only do the barbed quills...
</Question>
<Choice>porcupine</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
diverse order of mammals comprising the suborders Strepsirhini (prosimians) and Haplorhini (monkeys, apes, and humans). The prosimians, which include the lemurs, lorises, and tarsiers, are sometimes called the lower primates. They evolved long before monkeys, apes, and humans—the higher primates—and therefore exhibit more primitive characteristics.
</Question>
<Choice>primate</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Next to the jaguar, the graceful puma is the largest of the New World cats. A male may grow to 6 12 feet (2 meters) long from nose to rump, yet despite its size, the animal is remarkably agile. Its powerful limbs allow it to jump to heights of 18 feet (5.5 meters) or more.
</Question>
<Choice>puma</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Among the best-known wild animals are the cottontails and jackrabbits. These rabbits and hares are abundant in the brushy woods and gardens of eastern North America, on the western plains and deserts, on mountains, and even in the Arctic snows.
</Question>
<Choice>rabbit and hare</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Inquisitive, methodical, and intelligent, the raccoon looks constantly for something new to do. The common raccoon of North America is easily recognized by the black mask across its eyes and the black bands ringing its bushy tail. Because of these bands, the raccoon is often referred to by its nickname, the ringtail. Its stout body is covered...
</Question>
<Choice>raccoon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nearly all people associate rats with dirt, disease, and destruction, yet of the approximately 80 species of true rats, only seven may be said to deserve this reputation. Even animals that do not belong to the same order but that have “rat” in their common names— such as the rat kangaroo and the rat opossum, which are actually marsupials—suffer...
</Question>
<Choice>rat</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nearly all species of rhinoceroses are threatened, and some are close to extinction. Despite protective laws, they continue to be hunted because parts of their bodies are credited with some medicinal value in folk medicine. Most are killed for their horns, believed by some East Asian peoples to be an aphrodisiac, or sexual stimulant. Yet the...
</Question>
<Choice>rhinoceros</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Probably more than half of the mammals living on Earth are rodents. Rodents, gnawing animals of the order Rodentia, are found on all the major landmasses except Antarctica and on most islands. The order includes various species of rats and mice, squirrels, chipmunks, voles, gerbils, hamsters, lemmings, beavers, pocket gophers, guinea pigs, and...
</Question>
<Choice>rodents</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
With streamlined bodies, thick layers of fat, flippers for limbs, flattened feet with webbed digits, and hairy coats for protection from sand and rocks, seals, sea lions, fur seals, and walrus are adapted for life in and out of the water. These animals make up the suborder Pinnipedia of aquatic, fin-footed mammals. The pinnipeds evolved from land...
</Question>
<Choice>seal, sea lion, and walrus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Among the most valuable of all the domestic animals are the sheep. They provide humans with meat. They also give wool for cloth. Young sheep or lambs provide lamb pelts which are used for fur. In some lands the people drink sheep's milk. Other people use the milk to make delicious cheese.
</Question>
<Choice>sheep</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Small and mouselike, shrews are among the most abundant mammals in the world. The family of true shrews, Soricidae, includes more than 300 species. About two fifths of these species live in Africa, but shrews are also found throughout the Northern Hemisphere and in northwestern South America. Shrews belong to a larger group of insect-eating...
</Question>
<Choice>shrew</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The curious mammals called sloths derive their name from the fact that they usually appear lazy and sluggish, though at times they show considerable agility. Sloths live in the forests of tropical America. (Their now-extinct relatives, the huge prehistoric ground sloths, once ranged into what is now North America.) The animals have rounded heads...
</Question>
<Choice>sloth</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Probably no wild animal is more commonly known than the eastern gray squirrel. It is now found as often in city parks and gardens as in its native forests. The gray squirrel is a member of the squirrel family, a group of rodents that includes the ground squirrels and flying squirrels, woodchucks and other marmots, prairie dogs, and chipmunks.
</Question>
<Choice>squirrel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The harmless, plant-eating tapirs are relatives of the rhinoceros and the horse. They are found in two tropical regions on opposite sides of the world—southern Myanmar, Thailand, Malaysia, and Sumatra; and Central and South America.
</Question>
<Choice>tapir</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The largest of the cats is the tiger. It is as strong and fierce as it is big. The tiger's coat is often a bright golden color. It has black stripes on the head, body, limbs, and tail. Stripes like these are sometimes found on the domestic cat, or house cat, which is a distant relative of the tiger. On the domestic cat the stripes are called...
</Question>
<Choice>tiger</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(or morse, in Aleut, amak or amaghak; in Inuit, aivik), large, heavy-bodied, seallike mammal (Odobenus rosmarus); sole living member of family Odobenidae; up to 12 ft (3.7 m) long; grayish skin; long tusks used for digging and defense; found in Arctic seas of Eurasia and North America .
</Question>
<Choice>walrus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
More than 60 species of carnivorous mammals, distributed throughout the world, are included in the weasel family Mustelidae. They are placed in five major groups, or subfamilies: true weasels, which include ermine, minks, ferrets, martens, and wolverines; honey badgers; badgers; skunks; and otters.
</Question>
<Choice>weasel family</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
It weighs as much as 20 elephants but lives beneath the sea. The blue whale is Earth's largest animal. Larger than the largest of ancient dinosaurs, blue whales can grow to be more than 100 feet (30 meters) long and weigh nearly 150 tons. Not all whales are so large. The much smaller pilot whale grows to about 28 feet (8.5 meters) in length, and...
</Question>
<Choice>whale</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Believed to be an ancestor of the domestic dog, the wolf is a highly intelligent and courageous hunter. Its remarkable powers of endurance are legendary. Although it is not a fast runner, it can maintain a loping run for many miles, running throughout the night if necessary.
</Question>
<Choice>wolf</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On the high plateaus of Tibet lives a massive member of the bovine family Bovidae—the yak. It has long hair that hangs from its sides like a curtain, sometimes touching the ground.
</Question>
<Choice>yak</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On grassy African tablelands, from Ethiopia south to the Cape of Good Hope, graze the fleet and wary zebras, the striped members of the horse family Equidae. All zebra species have decreased in number because of human activities, and some are considered endangered. Because they readily breed in captivity, there is still hope of maintaining zebra...
</Question>
<Choice>zebra</Choice>
</item>
</topics>