<topics>
<item>
<Question>
The plants known as cactuses, or cacti, are well suited for life in the desert. Their unique ability to store water allows them to flourish in arid conditions in which other plants could not survive. The cacti are flowering plants that belong to the scientific family Cactaceae, which includes some 1,700 species.
</Question>
<Choice>cactus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Rest periods set aside for snacks and small talk are called coffee breaks or coffee hours, no matter what kinds of refreshments are enjoyed. Coffee has become one of the most popular hot drinks because it combines good taste and aroma with caffeine, a stimulant. It is prepared by brewing the roasted and ground beans of the coffee tree in water.
</Question>
<Choice>coffee</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
People use cotton in some form every day. In summer cotton clothes are worn because they are cool and easy to clean. For all seasons there are cotton towels, sheets, rugs, draperies, gloves, and countless other products that range from sewing thread to cooking oils. Despite the increasing use of synthetic fibers, such as rayon and nylon, cotton...
</Question>
<Choice>cotton</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In damp places in woods, ravines, and rocky crevices grow the feathery green ferns. They may be recognized by the shape of their leaves, known as fronds. These have a single midrib, with small leaflets branching off from either side. The leaflets may be delicately cut into toothed or lobed edges. Most of the familiar ferns grow from a creeping...
</Question>
<Choice>fern</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Members of the grass family that yield starchy seeds suitable for food are called grains. Grains are also known as cereal, or cereal grains. The grains most commonly cultivated are barley, corn (maize), millet, oats, rice, rye, sorghum, and wheat.
</Question>
<Choice>grains</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Records of the use of herbs date from ancient Egypt and Biblical times. The Greeks and Romans studied and wrote about herbs and their uses in medicine and cooking. Early physicians used hundreds of herbs to treat a variety of ailments. Herbs were also used to mask unpleasant household odors and to enhance the taste of dull food.
</Question>
<Choice>herb</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Several different kinds of climbing or creeping plants are known by the name of ivy. All are hardy shrubs or vines, growing in moderately cool, moist regions of the Northern Hemisphere. They climb by means of suckerlike disks, which attach themselves to walls and trees, or by means of twining tendrils. Many are cultivated as ornamental plants...
</Question>
<Choice>ivy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Among the earliest plants to become adapted to living on dry land, the mosses were the first green plants to stand erect. They existed as early as the Permian Period, which began 280,000,000 years ago and lasted for 55,000,000 years, and more than 100 species were present during the Tertiary Period (65,000,000 to 2,500,000 years ago). Fossilized...
</Question>
<Choice>moss</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Physicians knew the medicinal value of mustard more than 2,000 years ago, and it was used as a condiment even earlier. Mustard plants belong to the genus Brassica of the mustard family Cruciferae, or Brassicaceae (see mustard family). Most commercial mustard is prepared from two mustard plants—one having black seeds (B. nigra) and the other white...
</Question>
<Choice>mustard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Many early peoples who had not yet learned to catch fish, hunt game, or till the soil undoubtedly lived chiefly on roots, berries, and nuts. Of these foods nuts were the most nourishing, for they are rich in oil and protein. Because the nutmeats were inside airtight shells, they could be stored through the long, cold winters when other foods...
</Question>
<Choice>nuts</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
“The staff of life” normally refers to bread, or specifically to wheat, in Europe and North America. For fully half the population of the world, however, it is rice upon which people depend for fundamental, daily nutrition. In East Asia, Central Asia, the islands of the western Pacific, and much of Latin America rice is the basic component of...
</Question>
<Choice>rice</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
a cereal grain. Where the climate and soil are relatively unfavorable for other cereals and where winter temperatures are too cold to grow winter wheat, rye (Secale cereale) is grown. Rye is used chiefly as flour for bread and as livestock feed. It is high in carbohydrates and provides small quantities of protein, potassium, and B vitamins. It is...
</Question>
<Choice>rye</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A free-floating meadow of seaweed almost as large as a continent lies between the United States and Africa in the North Atlantic Ocean. This is the famous Sargasso Sea. Christopher Columbus discovered it as he sailed toward the New World in 1492. Its presence suggested that land was near and encouraged him to continue.
</Question>
<Choice>seaweed</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
For centuries people have made bland foods more flavorful by adding spices—the dried parts of various plants cultivated for their aromatic or pungent properties. Although the terms spices, spice seeds, and herbs are often used interchangeably, the differences between them are clearly defined. Spices are the fragrant or pungent parts of plants...
</Question>
<Choice>spice</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the United States a short interruption in the workday is called a coffee break. In other parts of the world, it is more likely to be a tea break. In all of Asia, Europe, the Middle East, and North Africa, tea is the more popular drink of the two. On any busy afternoon in Istanbul, Cairo, or any of several other Muslim cities, runners can be...
</Question>
<Choice>tea</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Although several varieties of the thistle are handsome plants with soft silky flower heads of purple, pink, yellow, or white, most of them are troublesome weeds. For example, the Canada thistle—known also as corn thistle, creeping thistle, and Scotch thistle—is a great nuisance in agricultural areas of North America. Like all thistles, the flower...
</Question>
<Choice>thistle</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
When Christopher Columbus arrived in the Americas, he found the natives using tobacco much the same way as it is used in many parts of the world today. At least partly because it was thought to have medicinal value, it was soon carried to France, Spain, and Portugal and from there to the rest of Europe. By the 16th century Spaniards had...
</Question>
<Choice>tobacco</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
As a food crop essential to the making of bread, pastry, and pasta, wheat products are eaten by many people at every meal. Wheat products are valued for their taste and for their nutritional benefit. (See also agriculture; bread and baking; breakfast cereal; food and nutrition.)
</Question>
<Choice>wheat</Choice>
</item>
</topics>