<topics>
<item>
<Question>
Since early times, tales of horror have been woven around strange sea creatures, especially the giant squid and the fearsome octupus. They are among the largest, strongest, fastest, most cunning, and ferocious of all animals. Many of them, however, are quite harmless and are useful in a variety of ways. In southern European and Asian countries...
</Question>
<Choice>octopus, cuttlefish, and squid</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the most nourishing of all sea foods, the oyster is a bivalve—a shellfish having two shells—of the mollusk group (see mollusks). They live in quiet bays and river mouths and are found along the shores of all temperate and tropical oceans.
</Question>
<Choice>oyster</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
There are more than 40,000 different species of snails and slugs throughout the world, and they are remarkably well adapted to survival. They may be found almost everywhere—on land, in trees, in freshwater ponds and streams, and in salt water from shoreline to ocean depths. Snails have shells; slugs do not.
</Question>
<Choice>snails</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Humans have always feared large, flesh-eating reptiles, and with good reason. Alligators and crocodiles, in addition to being among the ugliest of all living creatures, can also be among the most dangerous.
</Question>
<Choice>alligator and crocodile</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
a giant snake, Eunectes murinus, of the boa family, Boidae. One of the two largest snakes in the world, adults measure up to 30 feet (9 meters) in length. The reticulated python, with a confirmed length of 32 feet (9.8 meters), is longer, but the anaconda is much heavier.
</Question>
<Choice>anaconda</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The boa constrictor is a large, thick-bodied snake of the boa family, Boidae. Its scientific name, Boa constrictor, is the same as its common name. Its range is wide, from Argentina to northern Mexico, and though it thrives in tropical rain forests, it also inhabits savannas, cane fields, and semiarid scrublands. The snake's adult length is about...
</Question>
<Choice>boa constrictor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
any of about 21 species of medium to large poisonous snakes inhabiting tropical and subtropical Asia and Africa that are known for a unique threat display in which they raise the front of the body straight up and pull the ribs of the neck sideways and forward, flattening the neck into a hood. Characterized by short, hollow, fixed fangs that...
</Question>
<Choice>cobra</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
any of numerous poisonous snakes of the cobra family, Elapidae, that typically have three strongly contrasting rings of black, yellow, and red. Variations are black with one other color, or white instead of yellow. Although coral snakes are small—most are less than 3 feet (0.9 meter) long—their hollow fangs transmit a deadly paralyzing venom.
</Question>
<Choice>coral snake</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The members of this family of lizards differ greatly in their looks and habits. Most of them are green. Some take on the color of their surroundings (see Protective Coloration). Many of them have unusual sawlike teeth. They also have large dewlaps, or pouches, under the head and neck and long scaly crests all along the back.
</Question>
<Choice>iguana</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
any of twelve species of medium-sized, poisonous snakes of the genus Bungarus. Kraits are related to cobras in the family Elapidae. They inhabit regions of Southeast Asia from Pakistan through Indonesia, usually in open woods and grassy meadows near water. Adult size averages 5 feet (1.5 meters).
</Question>
<Choice>krait</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The largest living group of reptiles, the lizards, is made up of more than 3,000 species. They make up 57 percent of the world's reptiles. Typical of reptiles, lizards have claws, lungs, and a tough outer skin of epidermal scales. Like all reptiles, they do not adjust their own body temperature. They assume the temperature of their environment...
</Question>
<Choice>lizards</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The family Pythonidae is composed of about 26 species of constricting snakes. Although sometimes classified as a subfamily of the boa family, Boidae, pythons are distinguished from boas in several ways. Pythons are Old World snakes, inhabiting Australasia, Southeast Asia, India, and Africa. Boas are mainly New World snakes, with a few...
</Question>
<Choice>python</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
a widespread, highly poisonous American pit viper of the family Viperidae; some scientists place it in the family Crotalidae. Unique to this group is a tail rattle that is vibrated as a threat or warning.
</Question>
<Choice>rattlesnake</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
any of about 50 species of poisonous snakes that live mainly in warm coastal seas and bays of the Indian and Pacific oceans, off the shores of Asia, Australia, western Pacific Islands, and coral reefs. Sea snakes are related to cobras in the family Elapidae. Like their terrestrial relatives, the sea snakes have short, fixed, hollow fangs that...
</Question>
<Choice>sea snake</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Of all the animals, snakes are among the best known but perhaps the most misunderstood. Snakes are characterized by their elongated limbless bodies. They are found in almost every part of the world except the polar regions. Although the greatest species diversity is found in the tropics, snakes occupy a wide range of habitats, from deserts to...
</Question>
<Choice>snakes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Along with snakes, lizards, and crocodiles, turtles belong to the class of animals called reptiles. The earliest fossils recognized as turtles are about 200 million years old and date from the time when dinosaurs roamed the Earth. Turtles have changed little in appearance since that time.
</Question>
<Choice>turtle</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
any poisonous snake belonging to the family Viperidae. Vipers are characterized by a pair of long, sharp fangs, each with a hollow center. The fangs, which are attached to the front of movable upper jaw structures called maxillae, lie folded back against the roof of the mouth until the snake swings them out to threaten or attack. When the viper...
</Question>
<Choice>viper</Choice>
</item>
</topics>