<topics>
<item>
<Question>
nut-bearing tree (Amygdalus communis) of the rose family; grows extensively in western Asia, in Mediterranean countries, and in California; related to plum and peach; grows to 20 to 30 ft (6 to 9 m) in height; delicate white or pink flowers bloom in early spring; oval, pointed leaves notched at edges; fruit has soft outer coat enclosing shell...
</Question>
<Choice>almond</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Among the finest forest and timber trees in North America are the ashes. About 65 species are found throughout the Northern Hemisphere. The most abundant and economically useful is the white ash (Fraxinus americana). Its tough, elastic, straight-grained wood can be used for baseball bats, skis, oars, tennis rackets, tool handles, and ladders.
</Question>
<Choice>ash</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the most valuable and widespread plants is bamboo. It is a tall treelike grass. There are more than 350 species. Most grow in Asia and on islands of the Indian and Pacific oceans. Although bamboo is a tropical plant, it can be grown in temperate zones.
</Question>
<Choice>bamboo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An important timber tree of genus Fagus of family Fagaceae, the beech is native to Europe and eastern North America. The wood is used for flooring, furniture, woodenware, handles, cooperage, railway ties, and building timber. It is the only wood used in the filtering process of vinegar manufacture and is distilled to make the finest creosote for...
</Question>
<Choice>beech</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Whitish bark, dainty leaves, and a slim, graceful trunk make the commonly known species of birch tree seem delicate. Actually, they are extremely hardy. Some birches flourish within the Arctic Circle. Others grow up mountainsides as far as the timberline.
</Question>
<Choice>birch</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The wood of the cedar tree has been highly valued since ancient times. It is easily worked, resists rot and insect attack, and has an attractive reddish color and a pleasing aroma. Cedars are also grown as ornamental trees.
</Question>
<Choice>cedar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the shade of majestic chestnut trees pioneer America worked and played. These beautiful trees lined the village streets of New England. From great chestnut forests came lumber for buildings, furniture, and fences. The wood was the chief source of tannin, used for curing hides. The sweet-flavored nuts, roasted in the fireplace on cool autumn...
</Question>
<Choice>chestnut</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the most durable of all woods, cypress resists insects and chemical corrosion as well as decay and has a smell resembling that of cedar. Cypress products include coffins, acid-holding tanks, docks, pilings, poles, and railroad ties. Cypress trees are also often grown as ornamentals.
</Question>
<Choice>cypress</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The trees of the elm family are valued for their strong wood, their attractive foliage, and the shade they provide. Elms are found mostly in the temperate parts of the Northern Hemisphere. There are about 18 species, all in the genus Ulmus of the scientific family Ulmaceae.
</Question>
<Choice>elm</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Next to the Douglas fir and the giant redwoods of the American West, the tallest tree in the world is the giant gum (Eucalyptus regnans) of Australia, which grows to more than 300 feet (90 meters) high. There are about 500 eucalyptus species in the world. It is native to Australia, New Zealand, Tasmania, and nearby islands. There are about...
</Question>
<Choice>eucalyptus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
To many people the word fir calls to mind the graceful, fragrant balsam fir so widely used as a Christmas tree. Some 40 other species of fir, however, are distributed throughout the world. Their wood is not as good as that of spruce and pine for building. It is used for lumber and pulpwood. Various foreign species of the fir tree have become...
</Question>
<Choice>fir</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
During the Christmas season, many people of North America and Europe decorate their homes with wreaths and sprays of holly. The bright red berries and dark green prickly leaves provide a traditional note of Christmas color.
</Question>
<Choice>holly</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Most trees cannot live on tide-drenched seashores because their roots cannot get air from the wet soil. The mangrove, however, does so easily because its vinelike roots take in air through their pores. These roots drop from both the tree's trunk and branches into the surrounding mud, where they establish supporting stilts and new trunks in a...
</Question>
<Choice>mangrove</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Its thick, shading foliage in summer and its brilliant coloring in autumn make the maple one of the most popular trees for parks and streets. It is also valued as the source of maple sugar and the maple wood used for furniture and building.
</Question>
<Choice>maple</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The majestic monarchs of the forest may take 100 years to reach maturity and then may live for another 900 years. Their wood provides one of the strongest and most durable of timbers.
</Question>
<Choice>oak</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Among the most useful of all plants, palms furnish food, shelter, clothing, fuel, building materials, starch, oils, and a host of minor products for peoples of the tropics. Palms are tall and stately in appearance and are often planted as ornamentals. The 18th-century Swedish naturalist Carolus Linnaeus termed them the princes of the plant...
</Question>
<Choice>palm</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Perhaps the most valuable commercial nut in the United States, the pecan has a distinctive flavor and texture. American Indians extracted a milky fluid from it that they used in making corn cakes.
</Question>
<Choice>pecan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The oldest living trees on Earth are thought to be the bristlecone pines. Representatives grow in Colorado, Utah, Nevada, and Arizona. The oldest known bristlecone is 4,900 years old, but they can live for as long as 6,000 years.
</Question>
<Choice>pine</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Many beautiful forest and ornamental trees are included among the poplars. The stately Lombardy poplar, cottonwood, and quaking aspen are among the most familiar. Western balsam poplar, up to 200 feet (60 meters) tall, is one of the largest deciduous trees of northwestern North America.
</Question>
<Choice>poplar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
It is for good reason that the massive sequoias—the redwood and the so-called big tree—have captured the imagination of those who have encountered them. The towering redwood is the tallest of all trees. During a lifetime of up to 2,000 years it may grow to nearly 400 feet (120 meters) high and more than 30 feet (9 meters) thick at the base. Its...
</Question>
<Choice>sequoia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The ornamental and timber trees known as spruces are native to the temperate and cold regions of the Northern Hemisphere. These cone-bearing evergreen trees are usually pyramid-shaped with whorled branches and thin, scaly bark. When the trees grow singly, their lower branches often touch the ground. The cones are egg-shaped or cylindrical. The...
</Question>
<Choice>spruce</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Among the most beautiful and most useful of all trees are the walnuts. For fine furniture, cabinets, and paneling, the beauty and quality of walnut wood are equaled only by mahogany and oak. In the United States and England, walnuts are among the most popular of all edible nuts.
</Question>
<Choice>walnut</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The generic name of the willows, Salix, comes from the Celtic sal, meaning “near,” and lis, meaning “water.” Most species grow near water or in moist ground in cold and temperate regions throughout the world, but a few are dry-soil plants. The willow often appears in Chinese art, and its beauty makes it a favorite ornamental tree in gardens and...
</Question>
<Choice>willow</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An ornamental evergreen, the yew is a very slow-growing and long-lived tree. The trunks of some English specimens are more than 10 feet (3 meters) in diameter and are estimated to be over 1,200 years old. The wood of the yew is highly valued for cabinetmaking because of its hardness and close grain.
</Question>
<Choice>yew</Choice>
</item>
</topics>