<topics>
<item>
<Question>
Australian Aborigines are indigenous people of Australia whose ancestors came from Asia at least 50,000 years ago. By the time Europeans began settling Australia in 1788, Aborigines had occupied the entire continent and had adapted successfully to Australia's often harsh climatic conditions.
</Question>
<Choice>aborigine</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Black people make up one of the largest of the many racial and ethnic groups in the United States. The black people of the United States are mainly of African ancestry, but many have nonblack ancestors as well.
</Question>
<Choice>African Americans, or Black Americans</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Descendants of the Germanic peoples who invaded and conquered Britain in the 5th and 6th centuries are generally known as Anglo-Saxons. The term Anglo-Saxon was most likely first used in the late 8th century to distinguish the Saxons of Britain from those of the European continent. Following the Norman Conquest, however, the term simply came to...
</Question>
<Choice>Anglo-Saxon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The science of the origins and development of human beings and their cultures is called anthropology. The word anthropology is derived from two Greek words: anthropos meaning “man” or “human” and logos, meaning “thought” or “reason.” Anthropologists investigate the whole range of human development and behavior, including biological variation...
</Question>
<Choice>anthropology</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The term Arab, in its most general application, refers to those who speak Arabic as their native language. Prior to the 7th century this word referred mainly to the inhabitants of Arabia, which today encompasses the nations of the Arabian Peninsula. Subsequent political and military expansion left Arabs as the dominant social group in most parts...
</Question>
<Choice>Arab</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The field of study called archaeology combines the excitement of treasure hunting with the investigative labor of detective work. Archaeology is the scientific study of the material remains of mankind's past. Its discoveries are the principal source of knowledge about prehistoric cultures.
</Question>
<Choice>archaeology</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
People of Asian descent who live in the United States are known as Asian Americans. Some were born in Asia and later migrated to the United States, while others are from families that have lived in the United States for several generations. The various Asian American ethnic groups should not be lumped together as if they were homogeneous. Their...
</Question>
<Choice>Asian Americans</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
When Hernando Cortez and his Spanish soldiers reached the Valley of Mexico in 1519, they found a splendid city standing on an island in a lake. Three wide causeways led to huge white palaces and ornate temples on pyramids.
</Question>
<Choice>Aztec</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The most ancient surviving ethnic group in Western Europe, the Basques settled along the coast of the Bay of Biscay from Bilbao, Spain, to Bayonne, France. There are more than 2.5 million Basques living in this region—the majority in four provinces in Spain. One of the most distinguishing features of the Basque people is their language, Euskara...
</Question>
<Choice>Basque</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Among the ancient European peoples were the warlike Celts—tall, fair-skinned wanderers who spoke an Indo-European language. Their ancestors probably came from the distant steppes near the Caspian Sea. By 500 BC they were living in northeastern France, southwestern Germany, and Bohemia. The Celts, who were also called Gauls, continued to migrate...
</Question>
<Choice>Celt</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1812?–74). Of all the Indian wars in the American West, none was more needless—or more destructive of life and property—than the one against the Apaches from 1861 to 1871. A treaty of peace and friendship had been signed with the Apaches in 1858. But it was broken by the United States Army in 1861, when Cochise, chief of the Chiricahua Apaches...
</Question>
<Choice>Cochise</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
During the 3rd century BC some of the earlier segments of the Great Wall of China were connected to keep out a fierce nomadic people from Mongolia to the north. These tribes were called the Hsiung-nu. In the West they became known as the Huns. They were a nonagricultural people—animal herders who became expert horsemen. Gradually they worked...
</Question>
<Choice>Huns</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first people to live in the Americas were the Indians. Their settlements ranged across the Western Hemisphere and were built on many of the sites where modern cities now rise. Indian families and traders used paths now followed by roads and railroads. Indian words dot the maps of the United States, Canada, and the rest of the Americas. In the...
</Question>
<Choice>Native Americans</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Although this people of the north are widely called Eskimos, the name they use for themselves is Inuit, which means simply “the people.” (The singular is Inuk.) It was apparently the Cree Indians of Canada who gave the Inuit the name Eskimo, which means “eaters of raw meat.” If so, it was a misnomer, because the Inuit care no more for meat that...
</Question>
<Choice>Inuit</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Throughout their long history, the Kurds have never had a country to call their own. Most Kurds live in a mountainous region of the Iranian Plateau called Kurdistan, an area where Turkey meets Iran, Syria, and Iraq. At least 20 million Kurds live in Kurdistan; hundreds of thousands inhabit other areas, including Armenia and the Caucasus region...
</Question>
<Choice>Kurds</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Maya of Mesoamerica, along with the Aztecs of Mexico and the Incas of Peru, made up the high civilizations of the American Indians at the time of the Spanish conquest. Both the Aztecs and the Incas were late empires (about AD 1300–1533), capstones of a sequence of civilizations in Central Mexico and the Andes in South America, respectively...
</Question>
<Choice>Maya</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
When the Arab armies swept across Northern Africa in the 7th century, they found indigenous tribespeople called Berbers living in the northwestern corner of the continent. After the Arabs converted many of the Berbers to Islam early in the 8th century, the Berbers and Arabs joined to conquer Spain. There they intermarried with the Spanish. Their...
</Question>
<Choice>Moors</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nomads are wanderers. The word nomad comes from the Greek nomados, which means “wandering around in search of pasture.” Today the term refers to all wandering peoples who move in cyclical or seasonal patterns during the year. There have traditionally been three types: hunters and gatherers; pastoral nomads, or herders of animals; and craftsmen...
</Question>
<Choice>nomad</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Anthropology, the study of humans, has two basic divisions. Physical anthropology studies human evolution and human biological variation, while cultural anthropology considers the social aspects of human life, such as language, behavior, and beliefs. Both fields have sought to establish classifications of human beings in order to further the...
</Question>
<Choice>race and ethnicity</Choice>
</item>
</topics>