<topics>
<item>
<Question>
(1904–83). Associated primarily with the New York City Ballet Company and its predecessors from 1934, George Balanchine became known as the most influential ballet choreographer in the 20th century. His more than 100 choreographic works developed a style unique in the world of dance.
</Question>
<Choice>Balanchine, George</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A product and pastime of royalty in 17th-century Europe, ballet has over the last three centuries been transformed into perhaps the most popular and pleasurable of the arts. Ballet creatively expresses the full range of human emotions through physical movements and gestures. Most ballets tell a story, using mime, music, costumes, and scenery to...
</Question>
<Choice>ballet</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1872–1929). As the founder of the legendary Ballets Russes, impresario Sergei Diaghilev revolutionized ballet in the early 20th century. He combined great music, painting, and drama with new types of choreography to form a dance company unlike any seen before.
</Question>
<Choice>Diaghilev, Sergei</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1877/78–1927). One of the first to raise the status of interpretive dance to that of creative art was Isadora Duncan. She helped free Western dance from its reliance on strict formulas and displays of mere technique, paving the way for the development of modern dance. She was controversial in both her professional and private lives.
</Question>
<Choice>Duncan, Isadora</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1880–1942). The Russian-born American ballet dancer and choreographer Michel Fokine was one of the most innovative forces in early 20th-century ballet. The revolutionary five principles of reform that he published in 1914 became accepted features of ballet. Fokine's liberation and reformation of ballet had its greatest impact in the United States...
</Question>
<Choice>Fokine, Michel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Young people of the United States or Canada doing square dances for the sheer fun of it are folk dancing. So are young people of Mexico performing their traditional dances before an audience of tourists in Mexico City. Yet if the people of these nations had always lived as they do today, they probably would not have any folk dances. The same...
</Question>
<Choice>folk dance</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1632–87). The foremost composer and musician of the 17th-century French court, Jean-Baptiste Lully, was born on Nov. 29, 1632, in Florence, Italy, as Giovanni Battista Lulli. He changed his name to its French form when he became a naturalized French subject in 1681.
</Question>
<Choice>Lully, Jean-Baptiste</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1890–1950). No more celebrated figure has ever graced the art of ballet than Vaslav Nijinsky. He was called “the god of the dance.” At age 17 he was already regarded throughout his native Russia as the greatest dancer in the world. When he retired 12 years later he left behind a record of unforgettable performances and brilliant new ballets...
</Question>
<Choice>Nijinsky, Vaslav</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1938–93). Known for his catlike leaps and rapid turns, Rudolf Nureyev was the most compelling dancer of his era. “When I dance with him, I see not Nureyev but the character of the ballet,” said Margot Fonteyn of her favorite partner.
</Question>
<Choice>Nureyev, Rudolf</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1881–1931). “She does not dance; she soars as though on wings.” That is what enchanted audiences the world over thought of Anna Pavlova. No dancer worked harder to perfect her art. Even at the height of her fame, the small, slender dancer practiced 15 hours a day.
</Question>
<Choice>Pavlova, Anna</Choice>
</item>
</topics>