<topics>
<item>
<Question>
The word Christmas comes from the Old English term Cristes maesse, meaning “Christ's mass.” This was the name for the festival service of worship held on December 25 (January 7 in many Eastern Orthodox or Eastern Rite churches) to commemorate the birth of Jesus. Although it is accepted that Jesus was born in the small town of Bethlehem a few...
</Question>
<Choice>Christmas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mexican holiday marking the defeat of French invaders. After Mexico's 1846–48 war with the United States, the French tried to establish a permanent presence in Mexico. On May 5, 1862, a small, ill-equipped army of Mexican soldiers defeated the vastly better-equipped French army sent by Emperor Napoleon III. The battle of Puebla pitted the liberal...
</Question>
<Choice>Cinco de Mayo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the major religious festivals in Hinduism, Diwali (or Divali) marks the beginning of the new year in the Hindu calendar. The festival usually falls in late October or November in the Gregorian calendar. Merchant communities observe the festival with special enthusiasm as it honors the goddess of wealth, Lakshmi.
</Question>
<Choice>Diwali</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The greatest festival of the Christian church commemorates the resurrection of Jesus. It is a movable feast; that is, it is not always held on the same date. In AD 325 the church council of Nicaea decided that it should be celebrated on the first Sunday after the first full moon on or after the vernal equinox of March 21. Easter can come as...
</Question>
<Choice>Easter</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Customs and superstitions gathered through the ages go into the celebration of Halloween, or All Hallows Eve, on October 31, the eve of the Christian festival of All Saints. It has its origins, however, in the autumn festivals of earlier times.
</Question>
<Choice>Halloween</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(or Chanukah), Jewish festival. The triumph of the few over the many and the weak over the strong, and the faith in one miracle-making god is celebrated on the Jewish festival of Hanukkah.
</Question>
<Choice>Hanukkah</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
African American festival. Celebrated around the world by millions of people of African descent, the week-long holiday of Kwanzaa was developed by the American scholar and activist Maulana Karenga in 1966. Kwanzaa celebrates African family, community, and culture. It is based on African harvest celebrations, and the name comes from the Swahili...
</Question>
<Choice>Kwanzaa</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A holiday celebrated in most industrialized nations is Labor Day. The first American Labor Day was celebrated in New York City in 1882. The holiday is similar to the May Day celebrations of labor and industrial production held since 1887 in socialist nations though it had a separate origin.
</Question>
<Choice>Labor Day</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(or Shrove Tuesday), the day preceding the Roman Catholic period of Lent. The term Mardi Gras has also come to be associated more generally with a prolonged festival celebrated in the pre-Lenten season. In many Roman Catholic countries the period of festivities marking the last days before Lent is known as carnival. The word is probably derived...
</Question>
<Choice>Mardi Gras</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the major festivals in Judaism is Passover. It is a holiday of rejoicing when Jews all over the world recall their deliverance from slavery in Egypt. The word Passover comes from the idea that God passed over the houses of the Israelites, who had marked their doorposts to signify that they were children of God. This way the firstborn sons...
</Question>
<Choice>Passover</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the basic institutions, or five pillars, of Islam, Ramadan is the Islamic holy month of fasting. It is the ninth month on the Islamic calendar, which is based on a lunar cycle. Ramadan begins and ends with the official sighting of the new moon. During the month-long fast, able-bodied adults and older children fast during the daylight hours...
</Question>
<Choice>Ramadan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Throughout the United States and Canada Thanksgiving Day is an annual legal holiday. It is celebrated on the fourth Thursday in November in the United States and on the second Monday in October in Canada. There are also Thanksgiving holidays celebrated every year in Japan, South Korea, the Philippines, Laos, Liberia, Puerto Rico, Guam, Grenada...
</Question>
<Choice>Thanksgiving</Choice>
</item>
</topics>