<topics>
<item>
<Question>
Drawing uses a kind of universal language. The word draw means to drag a pointed instrument such as a pen, pencil, or brush over a smooth surface, leaving behind the marks of its passage. The scribbles of children are drawings as truly as are the sketches of the masters. Children make marks on surfaces long before they learn to write. It is easy...
</Question>
<Choice>Drawing</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Art is as varied as the life from which it springs. Each artist portrays different aspects of the world. A great artist is able to take some aspect of life and give it depth and meaning. To do this he or she will make use of the many devices common to painting. These devices include composition (the arrangement of the objects within a picture...
</Question>
<Choice>Painting</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The word photography comes from two ancient Greek words: photo, for “light,” and graph, for “drawing.” “Drawing with light” is a way of describing photography. When a photograph is made, light or some other form of radiant energy, such as X rays, is used to record a picture of an object or scene on a light-sensitive surface. Early photographs...
</Question>
<Choice>Photography</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Burghers of Calais, a three-dimensional artwork, or sculpture, by Auguste Rodin, is a monument to a historic moment of French dignity and courage. The moment expressed through the six figures is one of trial and triumph. The year depicted in the masterpiece was 1347; the place, outside the gates of Calais, a much-invaded port town. The English...
</Question>
<Choice>Sculpture</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(525–456 BC). The first great tragic dramatist of Greece was Aeschylus. His plays focused on the conflicting concerns of political leaders for their people and for themselves.
</Question>
<Choice>Aeschylus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(died 564? BC). What little is known of Aesop, the legendary Greek teller of fables, is recounted by such ancient Greek authors as Herodotus, Aristotle, Aristophanes, and Plutarch. Even from the mentions of him in this literature it is difficult to separate fact from fiction and to get a true picture of his life.
</Question>
<Choice>Aesop</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1832–88). Based on Louisa May Alcott's recollections of her own childhood, Little Women describes the domestic adventures of a New England family of modest means but optimistic outlook. An immediate success when Alcott published it in 1868, the novel remains a classic of children's literature.
</Question>
<Choice>Alcott, Louisa May</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1924–2007), U.S. author. With lively novels and picture books that take characters through exciting physical and personal journeys, Lloyd Alexander has attracted attention from both critics and young readers, especially those interested in the fantasy genre.
</Question>
<Choice>Alexander, Lloyd</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1805–75). A native of Denmark, Hans Christian Andersen is one of the immortals of world literature. The fairy tales he wrote are like no others written before or since. ‘The Steadfast Tin Soldier', ‘The Snow Queen', ‘The Swineherd', ‘The Nightingale'—these are stories that have been translated into almost every language. All over the world...
</Question>
<Choice>Andersen, Hans Christian</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1775–1817). Through her portrayals of ordinary people in everyday life Jane Austen gave the genre of the novel its modern character. She began writing at an early age. At 15 she was writing plays and sketches for the amusement of her family, and by the time she was 21 she had begun to write novels that are among the finest in English literature.
</Question>
<Choice>Austen, Jane</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1799–1850). The great French novelist Honoré de Balzac wrote of life in France during his own time. His series of almost 80 novels and tales, which he called La Comédie humaine (The Human Comedy), forms a social history of France in the first half of the 1800s. In the works Balzac depicts more than 2,000 named characters, many of whom appear in...
</Question>
<Choice>Balzac, Honoré de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1821–67). Although his early childhood appears to have been happy, young Charles Baudelaire became sullen and withdrawn after his elderly father died in 1827 and his mother remarried. This experience may have produced the melancholy temperament that drove him to become an art critic and introspective poet.
</Question>
<Choice>Baudelaire, Charles</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1757–1827). “I do not behold the outward creation.…?it is a hindrance and not action.” Thus William Blake—painter, engraver, and poet—explained why his work was filled with religious visions rather than with subjects from everyday life. Few people in his time realized that Blake expressed these visions with a talent that approached genius. He...
</Question>
<Choice>Blake, William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(born 1938), U.S. author. As a youth, Judy Blume was discouraged by encountering a lack of books with characters whose feelings and actions resembled her own. She attempted to rectify this as an adult by creating juvenile fiction with people and situations identifiable to young readers. While her frankness, first-person narratives, and ability to...
</Question>
<Choice>Blume, Judy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The bleak, lonely moors of Yorkshire in England were the setting for two great novels of the 19th century. These were Charlotte Brontë's Jane Eyre and Emily Brontë's Wuthering Heights. Readers today are still enthralled by their tragic, romantic stories and by the sense of brooding mystery that shrouds the tales. The youngest sister, Anne, was...
</Question>
<Choice>Brontë family</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1917–2000). Her songs of life on Chicago's South Side warmly told it the way it was in the African American community. She was Gwendolyn Brooks, poet laureate of Illinois and the first African American winner of a Pulitzer prize for poetry. Her poems tell what she saw and heard and describe the desperate poverty and struggles of black people.
</Question>
<Choice>Brooks, Gwendolyn</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1806–61). The ethereal English poet Elizabeth Barrett seemed to be resigned to a life of isolation and invalidism until she met a younger poet, Robert Browning, when she was 39 years old. After her second volume of poetry was published in 1844, he had telegraphed, “I love your verses with all my heart.?.?.?. and I love you too.” In spite of...
</Question>
<Choice>Browning, Elizabeth Barrett</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1812–89). When Robert Browning died in 1889, he was ranked with Tennyson as the leading English poet of his time. Yet he wrote verse for more than 30 years before his talent was recognized, devoting half of that time to the care of his more famous wife, the poet Elizabeth Barrett Browning. He was to influence 20th-century poetry through his...
</Question>
<Choice>Browning, Robert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1860–1904). The stories and plays written by Anton Chekhov describe in almost sociological detail the Russian society of his day. However, modern readers value his works chiefly for their deep insight into human emotion. Such is his subtlety that it is often difficult to decide whether a particular work is a comedy or a tragedy.
</Question>
<Choice>Chekhov, Anton</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1857–1924). At the age of 20, Polish-born Joseph Conrad could speak no English; yet in his lifetime he would write outstanding novels and stories in that language. His tales of seafaring life depicted the concerns of all people: hazards in nature, the need for loyalty, and the danger in greed.
</Question>
<Choice>Conrad, Joseph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1789–1851). The first American novelist to achieve worldwide fame was James Fenimore Cooper. His stories were translated into foreign languages as soon as they were published. Robert Louis Stevenson called him “Cooper of the wood and wave,” because he wrote about American Indians and pioneers in the forest and sailors on the high seas.
</Question>
<Choice>Cooper, James Fenimore</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1916–90). Although British author Roald Dahl wrote many books for adults, he is best known for his action-packed children's books filled with memorable, magical and often bizarre characters. Many of his works feature children triumphing over cruel and beastly adults.
</Question>
<Choice>Dahl, Roald</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1821–81). The Russian writer Dostoevski is regarded as one of the world's great novelists. His works exerted a great influence on 20th-century fiction.
</Question>
<Choice>Dostoevski, Fedor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1888–1965). “I am an Anglo-Catholic in religion, a classicist in literature, and a royalist in politics.” T.S. Eliot so defined, and even exaggerated, his own conservatism. The ideas of this stimulating poet, playwright, and literary critic were perhaps traditional, but the way in which he expressed them was extremely modern. Eliot was one of...
</Question>
<Choice>Eliot, T.S.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(484?–406 BC). In 405 BC the comic dramatist Aristophanes staged his play ‘The Frogs'. It was based on the idea that Athens no longer had a great tragic poet. It was true. Euripides had died in 406. Along with Aeschylus and Sophocles, Euripides was one of the three great tragic poets of ancient Greece. Of his life very little is known. He was...
</Question>
<Choice>Euripides</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1821–80). Writing was not easy for the French novelist Gustave Flaubert. Because of his concern for form and precise detail, he often struggled for days searching for le seul mot juste (“the exactly right word”). He took five years to write ‘Madame Bovary', his best-known work.
</Question>
<Choice>Flaubert, Gustave</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
All over the world children have grown up with the Grimm brothers' Nursery and Household Tales. Almost everyone knows of the fairy tale characters Snow White and the Seven Dwarfs, Rumpelstiltskin, and Rapunzel of the long hair. The 200 stories commonly called Grimm's Fairy Tales have been translated into 70 languages.
</Question>
<Choice>Grimm brothers</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1840–1928). Essentially a tragic novelist, Thomas Hardy wrote books that strike many readers as overly gloomy and pessimistic. A great novelist of the Victorian era, Hardy was also an accomplished poet (see English Literature).
</Question>
<Choice>Hardy, Thomas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1804–64). Although his friends included a number of noted transcendentalists—such as Ralph Waldo Emerson, Henry David Thoreau, and Bronson Alcott—Nathaniel Hawthorne's works show little of the optimism and self-confidence that marked transcendentalism. Instead, he preferred themes drawn more from a Puritan preoccupation with guilt and the...
</Question>
<Choice>Hawthorne, Nathaniel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1862–1910). Famous for his short stories and a master of the surprise ending, O. Henry is remembered best for such enduring favorites as “The Gift of the Magi” and “The Ransom of Red Chief.” The combination of humor and sentiment found in his stories is the basis of their universal appeal.
</Question>
<Choice>Henry, O.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Apart from the historical writings of ancient Israel, the two major pieces of epic literature in Western civilization are the Iliad and the Odyssey, two books ascribed to the ancient Greek poet Homer. These two works represent a brilliant retelling of myths and legends. For the Greeks of the 7th century BC, however, these books were their history...
</Question>
<Choice>Homer</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1902–67). Known during his lifetime as “the poet laureate of Harlem,” Langston Hughes also worked as a journalist, dramatist, and children's author. His poems, which tell of the joys and miseries of the ordinary black man in America, have been widely translated.
</Question>
<Choice>Hughes, Langston</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1802–85). The great French novelist and poet Victor Hugo created two of the most famous characters in literature—Jean Valjean, the ex-convict hero of ‘Les Misérables', and the hunchback Quasimodo in ‘The Hunchback of Notre Dame'. Known for the vast range and immense quantity of his output, Hugo was able during much of his long life to write as...
</Question>
<Choice>Hugo, Victor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1783–1859). Essayist, historian, and writer of stories, Washington Irving was the first of the great American writers. Before his time Europe had regarded American authors chiefly as curiosities. It was quick to recognize this new writer, however, so graceful was his style and so fascinating and delicate his humor.
</Question>
<Choice>Irving, Washington</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1843–1916). One of the most productive and influential American writers, Henry James was a master of fiction. He enlarged the form, was innovative with it, and placed upon it the mark of a highly individual method and style.
</Question>
<Choice>James, Henry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1882–1941). The Irish-born author James Joyce was one of the greatest literary innovators of the 20th century. His best-known works contain extraordinary experiments both in language and in writing style.
</Question>
<Choice>Joyce, James</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1795–1821). “Here lies one whose name was writ in water.” This is the epitaph that the poet John Keats prepared for himself. He thought of it in the dark days when he felt death drawing near and despaired of winning fame. During his seven years of writing, he had written some of the greatest poems in the English language.
</Question>
<Choice>Keats, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1850–93). A great French master of the short story, Guy de Maupassant had a special gift for dramatic swiftness and naturalness. “The Necklace,” his most famous story, could be used as a model for short-story writers.
</Question>
<Choice>Maupassant, Guy de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1819–1891). During his four years as a sailor and beachcomber in the South Pacific, Herman Melville gathered rich material for several novels. One of them was Moby-Dick, the story of Captain Ahab's vengeful search for the white whale which had maimed him. On the surface Moby-Dick can be read as an exciting adventure story. At a deeper level it...
</Question>
<Choice>Melville, Herman</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1608–74). Next to William Shakespeare, John Milton is usually regarded as the greatest English poet. His magnificent ‘Paradise Lost' is considered to be the finest epic poem in the English language. In other epics and in shorter verse forms Milton showed further proof of his genius. Although they are not as well known, Milton's essays in prose...
</Question>
<Choice>Milton, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(born 1931). U.S. author Toni Morrison was noted for her examination of the African American experience (particularly female experience) within the black community. She was born on Feb. 18, 1931, in Lorain, Ohio. Morrison grew up in a poor family but graduated from Howard University in 1953 and received a master's degree in English from Cornell...
</Question>
<Choice>Morrison, Toni</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Although the name of Mother Goose is familiar to almost everyone, there is no certainty that any such person ever lived. According to one story a Mistress Elizabeth Goose (Vergoose, or Vertigoose), who lived in Boston, Mass., in the late 17th century, recited rhymes to her grandchildren. These were said to have been published in 1719 by her son...
</Question>
<Choice>Mother Goose</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(43 BC–AD 17). The ‘Metamorphoses' of Ovid is one of Western literature's classic works. A long poem in 15 books, it is a collection of mythological stories ranging from the creation of the world to the age of Augustus, the first Roman emperor.
</Question>
<Choice>Ovid</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1809–49). The greatest American teller of mystery and suspense tales in the 19th century was Edgar Allan Poe. In his mysteries he invented the modern detective story. In Poe's poems, like his tales, his characters are tortured by nameless fears and longings. Today Poe is acclaimed as one of America's greatest writers, but in his own unhappy...
</Question>
<Choice>Poe, Edgar Allan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(born 1965). British author J.K. Rowling captured the imagination of children and adults alike with her best-selling series of books about Harry Potter, a young sorcerer in training. The books were critically acclaimed as well as wildly popular and were credited with generating a new interest in reading among children, the books' intended audience.
</Question>
<Choice>Rowling, J.K.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(born 1928). “Children…live in both fantasy and reality; they move back and forth with ease, in a way that we no longer remember how to do.” Maurice Sendak, an artist best known for his illustrated children's books, had this to say about children, who were both his subject and a large part of his readership. His understanding of the role that...
</Question>
<Choice>Sendak, Maurice</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1904–91). In 1984 a special Pulitzer prize was awarded to Theodor Seuss Geisel—better known as Dr. Seuss—for his “special contribution over nearly half a century to the education and enjoyment of America's children and their parents.” This special prize honored one of the most beloved writers of children's books of the 20th century, even...
</Question>
<Choice>Seuss, Dr.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
For more than 350 years, William Shakespeare has been the world's most popular playwright. On the stage, in the movies, and on television his plays are watched by vast audiences. People read his plays again and again for pleasure. Students reading his plays for the first time are delighted.
</Question>
<Choice>Shakespeare, William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1932–99), U.S. author and illustrator. Shel Silverstein's books can be easily identified by the black-and-white cartoon-style drawings he created to accompany his writing, yet equally distinctive are the lasting impressions his poetry and prose leave on young minds.
</Question>
<Choice>Silverstein, Shel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(496?–406 BC). The second of the three great Greek writers of tragic drama during the 5th century BC was Sophocles. Of the other two, Aeschylus preceded him, and Euripides was his successor. Sophocles is believed to have written 123 dramas, but only seven have survived. The best known is ‘Oedipus Rex' (or, Oedipus the King). The others are...
</Question>
<Choice>Sophocles</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1552?–99). Virtuous knights, evil giants, beautiful ladies, and loathsome ogres walk through the fairyland of Edmund Spenser's great epic, ‘The Faerie Queene'. The poem is a long allegory of the struggle between Good and Evil. Spenser originally planned the work in 12 books, each to depict a particular moral virtue in a knight, but he...
</Question>
<Choice>Spenser, Edmund</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1850–1894). The history of English literature records few stories more inspiring than the life and work of Robert Louis Stevenson. He was a happy and gifted storyteller, poet, and essayist. Stevenson was born Nov. 13, 1850, in Edinburgh, Scotland. He spent much of his childhood in bed, always ill with lung trouble. He died at the early age of...
</Question>
<Choice>Stevenson, Robert Louis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1667–1745). When Jonathan Swift wrote Gulliver's Travels, he intended it as a satire on all of humankind. He proposed, in his own words, “to vex the world rather than divert it.” Instead, people enjoyed his story and gave it to children to read. Today most readers know this quite ferocious indictment of human nature only as an amusing tale for...
</Question>
<Choice>Swift, Jonathan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1828–1910). The great novels of the Russian writer Leo Tolstoi capture the vastness of the Russian landscape and the complexity of its people. His massive War and Peace is regarded as a milestone in the development of the Western novel and spread his social and moral ideals to all parts of the world.
</Question>
<Choice>Tolstoi, Leo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1835–1910). A onetime printer and Mississippi River boat pilot, Mark Twain became one of America's greatest authors. His Tom Sawyer, Huckleberry Finn, and Life on the Mississippi rank high on any list of great American books.
</Question>
<Choice>Twain, Mark</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1862–1937). The upper-class society into which Edith Wharton was born provided her with abundant material for plotting her novels and short stories. Her major literary model was Henry James, a close friend in her later years. Like him, she lived a great part of her life in Europe, rarely returning to the United States after 1907.
</Question>
<Choice>Wharton, Edith</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1819–92). When they first appeared, Walt Whitman's poems were considered formless, crude, and often immoral. Today many consider Whitman to be the greatest American poet.
</Question>
<Choice>Whitman, Walt</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1867–1957), U.S. author. When she was in her 60s, Laura Ingalls Wilder took her daughter's advice and began writing about her life as a pioneer child. The resulting “Little House” books became classics in children's literature not only for their insight into what it was like to grow up on the American frontier during the 1870s and 1880s, but...
</Question>
<Choice>Wilder, Laura Ingalls</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1882–1941). Virginia Woolf was born Virginia Stephen in London on Jan. 25, 1882, and was educated by her father, Sir Leslie Stephen. After his death she set up housekeeping in Gordon Square in the district of Bloomsbury in London. Beginning in about 1907 her home was frequently visited by the young intellectuals who later became known as the...
</Question>
<Choice>Woolf, Virginia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1770–1850). The poet of nature, as William Wordsworth is best known, served as Great Britain's poet laureate from 1843 until his death. His Lyrical Ballads (published in 1798), written with Samuel Taylor Coleridge, helped launch the Romantic movement in English literature.
</Question>
<Choice>Wordsworth, William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1840–1902). As a writer Émile Zola waged two great battles—a long struggle for the acceptance of his powerful novels and the courageous defense of Captain Alfred Dreyfus in the political-military scandal that divided France. Zola won both fights. The critics and the public both realized that his novels were serious studies of mankind, and...
</Question>
<Choice>Zola, Émile</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A narrative that records the actions and recreates the personality of an individual is called a biography (from a Greek term meaning “life-writing”). An individual who writes the story of his or her own life is creating an autobiography, meaning self-biography (see Autobiography).
</Question>
<Choice>biography</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Whodunit? The dogged quest for the perpetrator of a vile crime has become the definition of the detective story. The question of whodunit keeps challenging all kinds of detectives in novels, short stories, films, radio and television series, and stage plays.
</Question>
<Choice>detective story</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Drama comes from Greek words meaning “to do” or “to act.” A drama, or play, is basically a story acted out. And every play—whether it is serious or humorous, ancient or modern—tells its story through characters in situations that imitate human life. In a theater, under the spell of a fascinating play, we may forget ourselves for awhile and enter...
</Question>
<Choice>drama</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The nature of the literary form known as epic can be summed up by the title of James Agee's book ‘Let Us Now Praise Famous Men'. Most epics are legendary tales about the glorious deeds of a nation's past heroes. The term originally referred to long narrative poems of heroic deeds among ancient peoples. Today the word epic is often more loosely...
</Question>
<Choice>epic</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Stories that point out lessons are called fables. Nearly everyone knows the fable about the three little pigs. They leave home and go out into the world to make their fortunes. Of course, they have to build places in which to live. The first little pig makes his house of straw. The second little pig also takes things easily, building his house...
</Question>
<Choice>fable</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Like folklore, mythology, fables, tall tales, and other classic stories that have been handed down, fairy stories are part of the oral tradition of literature. What makes the fairy tale different from the others is its use of magic and fantasy. Contrary to popular belief, the supernatural characters in fairy stories are not always fairy...
</Question>
<Choice>fairy tale</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Before Superman, Batman, or the Terminator, people told tales of other heroes, of Hercules and Brer Rabbit, for example. These heroes of legend and fiction possessed exceptional characteristics—strength, determination, or cleverness—and used them to overcome obstacles, to save themselves from disaster, or to outwit villains.
</Question>
<Choice>folklore</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
There is a sea of language around us. From that sea comes a constant flow of messages in Brooklynese and Basque, teenybop and Tibetan. And all those messages are wrapped in sounds and silences and signals.
</Question>
<Choice>language</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Children's literature is literature that entertains or instructs children. Many stories, poems, and other types of literature have been written especially with the young in mind. These works have come to be known collectively as children's literature. But a large number of children's favorites were originally aimed at adults. These include such...
</Question>
<Choice>literature for children</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
For every age group, every interest, every specialty, and every taste there is a magazine. Magazines are often called periodicals, because they are published at fixed intervals—periodically—such as weekly, monthly, or quarterly. “Journal” is another term for such publications, but it is normally restricted to specialized or scholarly publications...
</Question>
<Choice>magazine</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
“Were it left to me to decide whether we should have a government without newspapers, or newspapers without a government, I should not hesitate a moment to prefer the latter.” So wrote Thomas Jefferson to a friend in January 1787.
</Question>
<Choice>newspaper</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
“The books that we do read with pleasure,” said Samuel Johnson, “are light compositions, which contain a quick succession of events.” Johnson spoke in 1783, but his claim has merit today. Most of the novels on a best-seller list in any given year fit his description. They appear, are read as a light entertainment, and are soon forgotten—replaced...
</Question>
<Choice>novel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In every country and in every time there have been rhymes and jingles sung or said to children to amuse or quiet them. Yet most of what are now called nursery rhymes had their origin in subject matter intended for adults. The young, however, have a way of taking to themselves what pleases them; and thus they have preserved the parodies, lampoons...
</Question>
<Choice>nursery rhyme</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The sounds and syllables of language are combined by authors in distinctive, and often rhythmic, ways to form the literature called poetry. Language can be used in several ways to tell a story, marvel at the wonders of nature, explain the universe, give advice, or ponder the mysteries of life and death. Among these ways are the novel, short story...
</Question>
<Choice>poetry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The tales told by minstrels in the courts during the Middle Ages are called romances. The nobles of Europe lived in lonely castles. There were few books to read, and travel was difficult. In such a life visitors were eagerly welcomed. Most welcome of all was the minstrel, or singer. The family would gather around the fireplace of the great hall...
</Question>
<Choice>romance</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Although less well known than other writings, the Icelandic sagas were some of the finest pieces of literature produced in Europe during the Middle Ages. The word saga is derived from the Old Norse verb meaning “to say” or “to tell.” A traditional form of household entertainment in medieval Iceland was reading stories aloud. In this saga...
</Question>
<Choice>saga</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The success of the motion picture Animal House (1978) depended on the ability of members of the audience to identify with life in a college fraternity house. The movie is a parody—a form of satire—in which real conditions are exaggerated to the point of absurdity. Humor directed at human folly, vice, pomposity, or nonsense is called satire...
</Question>
<Choice>satire</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On Oct. 30, 1938, the night before Halloween, Orson Welles performed a dramatization of H.G. Wells's 1898 novel, ‘The War of the Worlds', on his Mercury Theatre on the Air. Although it was announced at the beginning and middle of the radio program that the Martian invasion of New Jersey was only fiction, thousands of listeners panicked. They...
</Question>
<Choice>science fiction</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
As long as people have told stories, there have been short works of prose—and occasionally poetic—fiction. Today such works are called short stories, and their modern form was devised during the 19th century. But tales, sketches, fables, anecdotes, romances, myths, and other short narratives have been told and written down for more than...
</Question>
<Choice>short story</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Stories have always come in many forms. Drawings, paintings, and, in modern times, photographs, film, and video can tell very detailed stories, even when no words are spoken. Some kinds of music not only evoke an atmosphere or emotional response but also suggest to the imagination a progression of events paralleling the development of a story plot...
</Question>
<Choice>storytelling</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
People have always been interested in animals. Very early in the history of civilization hunters tracked down and domesticated the animals of their own surroundings. These remote peoples also listened eagerly to travelers from far places who told of strange beasts they had seen and even stranger ones they had only heard about.
</Question>
<Choice>animals, legendary</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In ancient Greek religion and mythology, the goddess of love, beauty, and fertility was Aphrodite. She was one of the 12 chief gods who lived on Mount Olympus. The Romans identified her with their goddess Venus.
</Question>
<Choice>Aphrodite</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the religion and mythology of ancient Greece, Apollo was one of the most widely revered and influential of the gods. He had numerous roles. He was the god of light, youth, beauty, poetry, and music. At the banquets held on Mount Olympus, he charmed the gods with his playing on the lyre, a harplike musical instrument. He was also worshipped as...
</Question>
<Choice>Apollo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The colorful tales called the Arabian Nights have come down through the centuries. Nobody knows who told them first or where, though they existed as early as the 10th century. Of Middle East origin, the tales have given to the world such interesting heroes or rogues as Sinbad the Sailor, Ali Baba and the story of the 40 thieves, and Aladdin and...
</Question>
<Choice>Arabian Nights</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The virtues of knighthood were more completely embodied in King Arthur, the legendary prince of the ancient Britons, than in any other figure in literature. According to legend, Arthur was the son of King Uther Pendragon. Immediately after his birth, Arthur was given into the keeping of Merlin, the magician. Merlin took him to Sir Hector, who...
</Question>
<Choice>Arthurian legend</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The war goddess of the ancient Greeks was Athena—often called Pallas Athena, or simply Pallas. She was worshiped also as the goddess of wisdom and of crafts, especially spinning and weaving. She was one of the most powerful of the 12 chief gods who ruled on Mount Olympus. The Romans identified their goddess Minerva with her.
</Question>
<Choice>Athena</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the most widely worshiped gods of Greek mythology was Dionysus. At first, he was considered only as the god of wine. Later he became the god of vegetation and warm moisture, and, eventually, the god of pleasures and of civilization.
</Question>
<Choice>Dionysus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Kept alive in plays, novels, and poems, the Don Juan legend centers around a fictitious character who is generally regarded as a symbol of libertinism. Libertinism is immoral behavior that is not restrained by conscience or conventions. The legend tells how Don Juan seduced a girl of noble family and then killed her father when he sought revenge...
</Question>
<Choice>Don Juan legend</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
According to a legend of the Middle Ages there once lived in a distant pagan land a dreadful monster called a dragon. The flapping of its great batlike wings could be heard for miles around. With a single blow of its terrible claws it could fell an ox. From its nostrils came clouds of smoke and flame that brought death to those who breathed it.
</Question>
<Choice>dragon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the early 16th century there sprang up in Germany tales of a magician, Dr. Johannes Faust, or Faustus, who was rumored to be in league with the devil. With his aid, Faust could supposedly perform remarkable feats. There seems little doubt that a soothsayer-magician of this name really existed. He is said to have died about 1540, but the...
</Question>
<Choice>Faust legend</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
According to Greek legend, Helen of Troy was the most beautiful woman in the world. She was the wife of Menelaus, king of Sparta. Aphrodite, the goddess of love, promised her to Paris, son of King Priam of Troy, to reward Paris for judging Aphrodite the fairest of the goddesses.
</Question>
<Choice>Helen of Troy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The strongest and most celebrated of the heroes of classical mythology, Hercules, called Heracles by the Greeks, was the son of the god Zeus and the mortal Alcmene. The goddess Hera, who hated the infant Hercules, sent two serpents to destroy him in his cradle, but Hercules strangled them. As a boy Hercules was trained by the centaur Chiron.
</Question>
<Choice>Heracles</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In ancient Greek religion and mythology, Hermes was the messenger of the gods and one of the 12 chief gods who lived on Mount Olympus. He had numerous roles, many of which were associated with the crossing of boundaries, with gain, or with trickery. One of his duties was to conduct the dead to the underworld. He was also the god of dreams...
</Question>
<Choice>Hermes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Greek mythology Daedalus was a clever craftsman. He later was said to be the first sculptor to make statues having open eyes and with arms standing out from the body. He was also credited with inventing the awl, the bevel, and other tools. In ancient times many wooden temples and statues in Greece and Italy were believed to be his work.
</Question>
<Choice>Daedalus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The most popular of the gods in ancient Egyptian mythology was Osiris, god of the sun, agriculture, and health. His queen was Isis, who was also his wife and sister. She represented the moon, as Osiris did the sun, and was believed to have taught Egyptians the arts of agriculture and medicine. She was also credited with instituting marriage.
</Question>
<Choice>Isis and Osiris</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Second in importance only to Jupiter among the ancient Roman gods, Mars was the god of war. Believed to be the father of Romulus and Remus, the legendary founders of Rome, Mars was worshipped with great honor as the guardian of Rome. In early times he was considered a god of nature and fertility as well as of war. March, the month when winter...
</Question>
<Choice>Mars</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
legendary bard, magician, and counselor in Arthurian romance; born of a human mother and a spirit father, from whom he inherited his supernatural abilities; aided kings of Britain, especially Arthur, by means of his magic art; through the treachery of Viviane, the Lady of the Lake, to whom he taught his magic, he disappeared and lived in an...
</Question>
<Choice>Merlin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A mythological king of Phrygia, Midas has become a symbol of foolish greed. He once did a favor for the god Dionysus, and Dionysus promised to grant him anything he wanted.According to the story, Midas asked that everything he touched might turn to gold. The request was granted, but the king soon regretted it when he found that even his food...
</Question>
<Choice>Midas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The origin of the universe can be explained by modern astronomers and astrophysicists, while archaeologists and historians try to clarify the origin of human societies. In the distant past, however, before any sciences existed, the beginnings of the world and of society were explained by mythology.
</Question>
<Choice>mythology</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The graceful narcissus flower takes its name from a Greek myth. Narcissus was a beautiful youth who refused the love of a nymph named Echo. In punishment the gods condemned him to fall in love with his own image. Forced to gaze constantly at his reflection in a clear pool, he pined away and died. In pity the gods changed Narcissus into a lovely...
</Question>
<Choice>Narcissus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(also called Othin, Wotan, Woden, Wuotan, Voden, or Votan), in Norse mythology, the principal Aesir god, ruler of heaven and Earth, and the god of war, wisdom, and poetry. With his brothers Vili and Ve he had killed the primordial frost giant Ymir and used Ymir's body to make all the different realms of the world, as well as the sea and sky. The...
</Question>
<Choice>Odin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
According to Greek mythology, the hero Orpheus was a poet and musician who sang and played music so beautifully that all who heard it were enchanted. Animals, trees, and even rocks moved about him in time to his music. Orpheus played the lyre, a harplike instrument that had been given to him by the god Apollo. Most legends relate that Orpheus...
</Question>
<Choice>Orpheus and Eurydice</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Greek mythology Pandora was the first woman on Earth. When it came time to populate Earth, the gods delegated the task to Prometheus and his brother Epimetheus. Epimetheus (whose name means “afterthought” or “hindsight”) began with the animals, to whom he gave all the best gifts—strength and speed, cunning, and the protection of fur and...
</Question>
<Choice>Pandora</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
According to Greek mythology the winged horse Pegasus sprang from the blood of the Gorgon Medusa as she was beheaded by the hero Perseus. Using Athena's gift of a golden bridle, Bellerophon caught and tamed Pegasus. Mounted on Pegasus, Bellerophon was invincible. He was able to kill the Chimera, a fire-breathing monster, and he succeeded in...
</Question>
<Choice>Pegasus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Greek mythology Perseus was the young hero who slew Medusa, one of the fearful Gorgons who turned to stone anyone who dared to look at them. Perseus was the son of Zeus, king of the gods, and Danaë, the beautiful daughter of Acrisius, king of Argos. Acrisius had banished mother and son because an oracle had said Danaë's son would one day kill...
</Question>
<Choice>Perseus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In ancient Greek religion and mythology, Hades was the god of the underworld, the underground dwelling place of the dead. He presided over the trial of all people after death and the punishment of those found wicked. Stern, pitiless, and aloof, he was said to be unmoved (like death itself) by prayer or sacrifice. It was thought to be unlucky to...
</Question>
<Choice>Pluto</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Greek mythology, Prometheus was one of the Titans, the supreme trickster, and a god of fire. His intellectual side was emphasized by the apparent meaning of his name, Foresight. In common belief he developed into a master craftsman, and in this connection he was associated with fire and the creation of man.
</Question>
<Choice>Prometheus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(also spelled Re or Phra), in Egyptian mythology, the supreme sun-god, father of all creation in the form of Atum (also called Ra-Tem or Ra-Atem). Ra, like Horus, encompassed numerous attributes and was often merged with other gods to form composite gods like Amen-Ra (or Amun-Re). Pharaohs claimed their legitimacy to the throne as descendents of...
</Question>
<Choice>Ra</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the romantic heroes of the Middle Ages was the outlaw Robin Hood of England. Whether he was a living man or only a legend is uncertain. Old ballads relate that Robin Hood and his followers roamed the green depths of Sherwood Forest, near Nottingham, in the center of England. There they lived a carefree life, passing the time playing games...
</Question>
<Choice>Robin Hood</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The greatest of the gods in ancient Greek religion and mythology was Zeus. He was often called the “father of gods and men,” meaning that he was their chief ruler and protector. He was the protector of kings in particular, the supporter of law and order, and the avenger of broken oaths and other offenses. He watched over the state and the family...
</Question>
<Choice>Zeus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Black Africa south of the Sahara has two distinct kinds of literature. Traditional poetry and folklore, which were transmitted orally, date back to early days of various tribal cultures. Written literature emerged much later and at different times among the diverse groups living in the region—in the 17th century in the Swahili language, for...
</Question>
<Choice>African literature</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Wherever there are people there will be a literature. A literature is the record of human experience, and people have always been impelled to write down their impressions of life. They do so in diaries and letters, in pamphlets and books, and in essays, poems, plays, and stories. In this respect American literature is like any other. There are...
</Question>
<Choice>American literature</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Before European settlers arrived in Australia late in the 18th century, the sole human inhabitants of the continent were the aborigines. These people had no written language. Their songs, myths, legends, and stories were part of an oral tradition handed down over centuries. Much of this tradition served to explain the origin of the land and of...
</Question>
<Choice>Australian literature</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Canada has two literatures—one in English and one in French. Both English and French are official languages of Canada. Each is spoken by millions of people and owes its use to historical circumstances. This article provides a brief account of each of these literatures. (See also Canada, sections on people and history.)
</Question>
<Choice>Canadian literature</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Caribbean islands are collectively called the West Indies, but each island has its distinctive history and culture (see West Indies). In contrast to most of the nations of Central and South America, only Haiti and the Dominican Republic became independent of their colonial rulers in the 19th century. When the islands began to express...
</Question>
<Choice>Caribbean literature</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
China is the only country in the world with a literature written in one language for more than 3,000 consecutive years. This continuity results largely from the nature of the written language itself. In a Western language such as English, the letters stand for sounds that make up words, so the written language is closely tied to the spoken...
</Question>
<Choice>Chinese literature</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The literature of England is one of the highest achievements of a great nation. It should not, however, be read simply as a national expression. It is a body of significant statements about abiding human concerns. The language in which it is written has evolved over hundreds of years and is still changing. Several nations, including Canada, the...
</Question>
<Choice>English literature</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Most French authors have believed that the artist should not write simply to express his moods and emotions. He should write instead of more general matters. French literature has thus tended to be more dramatic than lyric.
</Question>
<Choice>French literature</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Poetry and philosophy have been basic to the development of German literature. They are often found running together in a kind of literary counterpoint. As in the history of the literature of most peoples, poetry was the first literary expression of the Germans.
</Question>
<Choice>German literature</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The great British philosopher-mathematician Alfred North Whitehead once commented that all philosophy is but a footnote to Plato (see Plato). A similar point can be made regarding Greek literature as a whole.
</Question>
<Choice>Greek literature</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Infused with a spirit of self-determination and a belief in the power of art as an agent of change, a talented group of writers, artists, and musicians made Harlem—a predominantly black area of New York City—the home of an African American cultural movement during the 1920s. Philosopher Alain Locke proclaimed the movement in ‘The New Negro...
</Question>
<Choice>Harlem Renaissance</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The language of ancient Israel was Hebrew, one of the Semitic languages of the Middle East. It is the language in which most of the Hebrew Bible—what Christians call the Old Testament—was originally written (see bible). Literature in Hebrew has been produced continuously since at least the 12th century BC. Until about AD 200 Hebrew was a spoken...
</Question>
<Choice>Hebrew literature</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sometime in the first half of the 2nd millennium BC Aryan peoples from the northwest entered the Indian subcontinent and displaced the Indus Valley civilization of what is now Pakistan (see Indus Valley civilization). The language of the Aryans was Sanskrit, which eventually became the classic literary language of Hinduism, the leading religion...
</Question>
<Choice>Indian literature</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ireland is rich in its heritage of legendary stories that reach back to its ancient past more than 2,000 years ago. It is rich, too, in the realism and vitality of contemporary Irish writing that bridges the political divisions of the country. The dual nature of Irish literature is further reflected in its two distinct tongues—Gaelic and English.
</Question>
<Choice>Irish literature</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The cultural flowering of Islam began at the time when Europe, except for the Byzantine Empire, was in a state of disintegration—the Dark Ages. When Europe at last began to emerge from the doldrums, it was in great measure due to the efforts of Muslims, who had collected and translated into Arabic many of the ancient Greek philosophical and...
</Question>
<Choice>Islamic literature</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The history of Italian literature properly begins toward the end of the Middle Ages. It was then that writers began to abandon Latin as the language of literature and write in one of the Italian dialects used in common speech.
</Question>
<Choice>Italian literature</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Rich in sensitivity, quality, and variety, Japanese literature ranks as one of the great literatures of the world. Some of its collections of mythological history have survived for 1,300 years. Yet even the most ancient writings have a universal significance because they contain a sensory appeal that transcends the boundaries of time and cultural...
</Question>
<Choice>Japanese literature</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
There is an ancient Korean legend about Tangun, the son of a sky god and a she-bear, whose reign over the land that became Korea began in 2333 BC. The story was told and retold through the centuries, but it was not written down until the 13th century AD, and then it was written in Chinese characters.
</Question>
<Choice>Korean literature</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In 1539—less than 50 years after Christopher Columbus landed in the New World—the first printing press in the Americas was set up in Mexico City and the first Latin American book was published. Thus literature became deeply rooted in the history of the countries of Latin America.
</Question>
<Choice>Latin American literature</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A universal language existed for many centuries—from just before the dawn of the Christian Era almost to contemporary times. This world language was Latin. It was spread by the victorious Roman legions over Europe, Asia, and Africa. It finally became the speech of Western civilization. It was spoken in one form or another from the British Isles...
</Question>
<Choice>Latin literature</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian literature has a long and rich tradition. The term Russian literature is used to describe the literature of different areas at different periods, from the loose confederation of East Slavic tribes known as Kievan Rus that originated in the 10th century to the Russian Soviet Federated Socialist Republic of the Soviet Union to present-day...
</Question>
<Choice>Russian literature</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Writings in Norwegian, Swedish, Danish, Icelandic, and Faeroese are collectively called Scandinavian literature. This literature has existed for more than 1,000 years, beginning with Norwegian writings that very early became part of Icelandic literature. The Icelandic Eddas and sagas became world renowned and are outstanding literary works (see...
</Question>
<Choice>Scandinavian literature</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The literature of Spain owes its character largely to the country's geography. The Pyrenees separate Spain from the rest of continental Europe. The country is further set off from the world, on three sides, by water. Mountain ranges divide Spain into widely different regions. Partly as a result of this geographic isolation, Spanish literature...
</Question>
<Choice>Spanish literature</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
‘Fiddler on the Roof', one of the greatest of American musical comedies, opened in New York City in September 1964 and played continuously until July 1972. The movie version appeared in 1971. Most of those who have seen it are probably unaware that the plot is derived from the works of Sholem Aleichem, one of the world's master storytellers...
</Question>
<Choice>Yiddish literature</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1897–1993). The American contralto Marian Anderson was a pioneer in overcoming racial discrimination. After being prohibited from singing in Constitution Hall in Washington, D.C., be- cause of her race, she performed (1939) instead on the steps of the Lincoln Memorial to an audience of more than 75,000, thereby increasing public awareness of...
</Question>
<Choice>Anderson, Marian</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A German family of musicians and composers, the Bachs achieved the height of their fame in the 17th and 18th centuries. Seven Bach generations achieved greater or lesser prominence in music from 1580 to about 1800. Of the group, Johann Sebastian Bach has been acclaimed as one of the giants of musical history.
</Question>
<Choice>Bach family</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1770–1827). The composer of some of the most influential pieces of music ever written, Ludwig van Beethoven created a bridge between the 18th-century classical period and the new beginnings of Romanticism. His greatest breakthroughs in composition came in his instrumental work, including his symphonies. His work is characterized by great...
</Question>
<Choice>Beethoven, Ludwig van</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1803–69). “Passionate expression, inward intensity, rhythmic impetus, and a quality of unexpectedness,” in the words of the French composer Hector Berlioz, were the main characteristics of his work. A leading figure in the French Romantic movement, Berlioz expressed in musical terms the subject matter of Romantic literature, drama, and painting...
</Question>
<Choice>Berlioz, Hector</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1918–90). His accomplishments both in serious music and for the Broadway stage and his flair for teaching young people combined to make Leonard Bernstein a well-known conductor, composer, and teacher. The popularity of this American musical genius increased through his appearances on television, not only as conductor and pianist, but also as...
</Question>
<Choice>Bernstein, Leonard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1833–97). The “three B's” is a phrase often applied to the composers Bach, Beethoven, and Brahms. It was first used by Hans von Bülow, a critic and conductor who was also a friend of Johannes Brahms. In linking him with two of the world's greatest composers, Von Bülow expressed a judgment that is still accepted today.
</Question>
<Choice>Brahms, Johannes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1810–49). Perhaps the greatest of all composers for the piano was Chopin. Called a “musical genius” when he was a teenager, Chopin composed a remarkable variety of brilliant pieces—warlike polonaises, elegant waltzes, romantic nocturnes, and poetic ballades and études.
</Question>
<Choice>Chopin, Frédéric</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1685–1759). A musical giant of the late baroque period, George Frideric Handel was born in Germany but spent most of his adult life in England. He successfully combined German, French, Italian, and English musical styles in about 40 operas, 20 oratorios, and numerous other vocal pieces, instrumental works, and church music.
</Question>
<Choice>Handel, George Frideric</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1732–1809). Called the father of both the symphony and the string quartet, Joseph Haydn founded what is known as the Viennese classical school—consisting of Haydn, his friend Mozart, and his pupil Beethoven. He lived from the end of the baroque period to the beginning of the romantic and presided over the musical transition between them. His...
</Question>
<Choice>Haydn, Joseph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1811–86). The most brilliant pianist of his day, Franz Liszt was also a distinguished composer of great originality and a major figure in the whole of Romantic music. Liszt was born on Oct. 22, 1811, in Raiding, Hungary. His father was employed by the Esterházy family as a steward at Raiding and was himself an amateur musician. The Esterházy...
</Question>
<Choice>Liszt, Franz</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1809–47). The composer, pianist, and conductor Felix Mendelssohn was a pivotal figure of 19th-century romanticism. He was also a major force in the revival of the music of Johann Sebastian Bach.
</Question>
<Choice>Mendelssohn, Felix</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1756–91). A central figure of the Viennese classical school, Mozart is often considered the greatest musical genius of all time. His output—especially in view of his short life—was enormous, including 16 operas, 41 symphonies, 27 piano and five violin concerti, 25 string quartets, 19 masses, and other works in every form popular in his time...
</Question>
<Choice>Mozart, Wolfgang Amadeus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Although an opera is primarily a musical experience, it relies on all the other performing arts as well as on the arts of theatrical stagecraft. Opera is a drama sung to the accompaniment of an orchestra. Although the fabric of the opera may be interrupted by spoken dialogue or recitatives accompanied by a keyboard or by the orchestra, the...
</Question>
<Choice>opera</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An orchestra is an assembly of musicians who play a wide range of instruments: strings ranging in tone and timbre from the violin to the double bass; woodwinds from the piccolo to the double bassoon; brass from the trumpet to the tuba; and percussion of many shapes and sizes. A significant distinction among these players is that each string part...
</Question>
<Choice>orchestra</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1797–1828). One of the originators of the Romantic style, the Viennese composer Franz Schubert was also the greatest of the postclassicists. He served as a bridge between the two eras. As a composer of songs Schubert is without a rival. He turned poems into music effortlessly. He wrote eight songs in one day, 146 in a single year, more than...
</Question>
<Choice>Schubert, Franz</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Romantic movement in music had one of its greatest leaders in the German composer Robert Schumann. He was outstanding both as a composer and as a critic. Some of his best work was written for his wife, Clara Wieck Schumann, a talented concert pianist.
</Question>
<Choice>Schumann, Robert and Clara</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1813–83). Among the great composers for the theater, Richard Wagner was the only one who created plot, characters, text, and symbolism as well as the music. He raised the melodic and harmonic style of German music to its highest emotional intensity, changing the course of Western music by either the extension of his methods or the reaction...
</Question>
<Choice>Wagner, Richard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1900–71). The New Orleans trumpeter who became a world ambassador for jazz, Louis Armstrong learned to blow on a bugle in reform school when he was 13. His genius for improvisation changed the course of jazz, but after the 1940s he had his greatest success as a pop singer.
</Question>
<Choice>Armstrong, Louis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1904–84). U.S. jazz pianist, composer, and bandleader Count Basie was one of the outstanding organizers of big bands in jazz history. He transformed big-band jazz by the simplicity of his arrangements and secured his place in history with such classic numbers as “One O'Clock Jump” and “Basie Boogie.”
</Question>
<Choice>Basie, Count</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1903–31). The inspiration for Dorothy Baker's 1938 jazz novel, Young Man With a Horn, was Bix Beiderbecke, an outstanding jazz player, improviser, and composer. The baby-faced cornetist was the first white person to become a major jazz soloist. After his death, he also became one of the first cult celebrities of the 20th century.
</Question>
<Choice>Beiderbecke, Bix</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
form of U.S. music originated by black Americans in the South. As a music form, the blues is typified by a melancholy state of mind and 8-, 12-, or 32-bar harmonic progressions that form the basis for blues improvisation. Another characteristic element is the “blue note,” a lowered third, seventh, or sometimes fifth degree of what would otherwise...
</Question>
<Choice>blues</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(born 1930). What was called the New Thing was first blown out of the white plastic alto saxophone of Ornette Coleman. An inspiration for other young improvisers who believed in free music, the instrumentalist-composer's decision to do away with preset chord changes transformed the shape of jazz after the 1950s (see jazz, “Modern Era”).
</Question>
<Choice>Coleman, Ornette</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1926–67). Unending restlessness marked the career of John Coltrane, the jazz tenor saxophonist who began by playing bebop and ended by playing free jazz. A passionate player, he aroused strong audience responses and became the most imitated of modern jazz musicians.
</Question>
<Choice>Coltrane, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1926–91). The most important jazz bandleader after World War II was Miles Davis. Outstanding among trumpet soloists, he led many small ensembles, including three that were the original sources of major jazz idioms: cool jazz, modal jazz, and fusion.
</Question>
<Choice>Davis, Miles</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1899–1974). The A Train, part of the New York City subway system, ran to north Manhattan's Harlem area. There could be found the Cotton Club, a white-owned nightclub for white audiences but featuring African American entertainers. From 1927 to 1932 Duke Ellington was closely associated with the Cotton Club, so there is little wonder that his...
</Question>
<Choice>Ellington, Duke</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1918–96), U.S. singer. Composer Ira Gershwin once said, “I never knew how good our songs were until I heard Ella Fitzgerald sing them.” Such praise was often bestowed upon the “First Lady of Song,” a musical legend whose clear, sweet voice glided between low and high notes.
</Question>
<Choice>Fitzgerald, Ella</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1915–59). Lady Day, as she was usually called, was the finest jazz singer of her generation, and in the opinion of her followers and many critics she was the greatest jazz singer of the 20th century. The autobiography (1956) of Billie Holiday, written in collaboration with William Dufty, and the movie (1972) made from it, was called Lady Sings...
</Question>
<Choice>Holiday, Billie</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1868–1917). An African American composer and pianist, Scott Joplin has been known as the King of Ragtime since the turn of the 20th century. His classic ragtime pieces for the piano—including “Maple Leaf Rag” and “The Entertainer,” published from 1899 through 1909—made him famous. Musicians continued to perform his music for decades after his...
</Question>
<Choice>Joplin, Scott</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1922–79). He went beyond the trends of jazz with a personal style so distinctive that the trendsetters scrambled to catch up with him. In elevating the string bass from a mostly rhythmic to a solo instrument, the American musician Charles Mingus changed the way not only jazz, but also pop music, is played.
</Question>
<Choice>Mingus, Charles</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1917–82). “The high priest of bebop,” Thelonious Monk composed dozens of enduring songs and was one of the greatest jazz pianists. His music is marked by sudden chords, surprising rhythms, subtle melodies, and, mostly, by its swing.
</Question>
<Choice>Monk, Thelonious</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1920–55). The legendary jazzman known as Bird had a profound influence on an entire generation of jazz performers, and musicians still pay tribute to his innovative bop style. After the death of Charlie Parker, hipsters wrote BIRD LIVES graffiti on city sidewalks and walls. The celebrated nickname is short for Yardbird—a reference to his...
</Question>
<Choice>Parker, Charlie</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1894?–1937). One of the greatest of the blues singers, Bessie Smith sang of the cares and troubles she had known—of poverty and oppression, of love and indifference. Her art is known today through the more than 150 songs she recorded during her brief career.
</Question>
<Choice>Smith, Bessie</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1909–59). Singer Billie Holiday called Lester Young “the president of tenor saxophonists,” and the nickname Prez (or Pres) stuck. In his solos of the 1930s he reinvented the art of playing the saxophone and opened new doors to improvisation.
</Question>
<Choice>Young, Lester</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A quartet of talented musicians from Liverpool, England, the Beatles generated a phenomenal run of gold records that endured long after the rock group disbanded. Affectionately nicknamed the Fab Four, the band's fresh-faced appeal inspired a worldwide frenzy of fandom in the 1960s called Beatlemania. Their music, rooted in American rock and roll...
</Question>
<Choice>Beatles, The</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1933–2006). A skilled dancer and singer with an extraordinary sense of timing, U.S. entertainer James Brown played a major role in bringing rhythm to the foreground of popular music. Brown's ability to “scream” on key, to sing soulful ballads as well as electrifying up-tempo tunes, and to blend blues, gospel, jazz, and country vocal styles made...
</Question>
<Choice>Brown, James</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1930–2004). Terms such as genius, national treasure, and Father of Soul have been used to describe Ray Charles, a blind African American singer, pianist, bandleader, and composer. He was known for his husky, emotional voice and ability to perform many types of music.
</Question>
<Choice>Charles, Ray</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1903–77). The most successful entertainer in the early years of radio and talking motion pictures was the U.S. singer, actor, and songwriter Bing Crosby. His casual stage manner and mellow, relaxed singing style influenced two generations of pop singers.
</Question>
<Choice>Crosby, Bing</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(born 1941). From the early 1960s Bob Dylan was one of the most influential—and at times controversial—performers in American music. Dylan was known for his trademark nasal vocals and scores of compositions that were often made popular by other performers, including Blowin' in the Wind and Mr. Tambourine Man. He reinvented the folk music genre...
</Question>
<Choice>Dylan, Bob</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Since the term folk music was first used in the 19th century, it has had many shades of meaning. Certain general characteristics, however, help distinguish folk music from such kinds as popular music and art, or classical, music.
</Question>
<Choice>folk music</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The rock music movement known as grunge gave voice to the frustrations and disenchantment of the teenagers and young adults often referred to as Generation X. Growing out of the do-it-yourself, uncommercial legacy of punk rock, grunge favored straightforward musicianship and songwriting over superficial imagery and media hype.
</Question>
<Choice>grunge rock</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1943–70). One of the most popular female vocalists in rock music was Janis Joplin. Her singing had a power and depth of feeling that earned her comparison with the greatest performers in the blues tradition.
</Question>
<Choice>Joplin, Janis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A live theatrical production, a musical typically offers a simple but entertaining plot with spoken dialogue interspersed with music, song, and dance. It is also called musical comedy or musical theater.
</Question>
<Choice>musical comedy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1935–77). One of the most successful entertainers ever, Elvis Presley dominated popular music in the United States from the release of his first big record, Heartbreak Hotel, in 1956. His records, 45 of which sold more than a million copies each, his 33 motion pictures, and his appearances on television and in live concerts made the young singer...
</Question>
<Choice>Presley, Elvis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the early 1970s, a Jamaican deejay known as Kool Herc moved to the Bronx in New York and introduced the musical innovations that developed into the popular music style known as rap. Using two turntables, he manipulated records to create longer dance segments while shouting out comments to the dancers during the instrumental breaks. Soon urban...
</Question>
<Choice>Rap music</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Wild stage antics and brutal lyrics were the trademarks of one of the most durable rock music groups. The Rolling Stones, named after a Muddy Waters song, were formed in London, England, in 1962 and by the late 1960s called themselves the World's Greatest Rock and Roll Band.
</Question>
<Choice>Rolling Stones</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A blistering reaction to the 1970s rock and disco scene, punk music was raw, ugly, and noisy, an anarchistic mutiny against the popular music establishment. With punk, anger was an art form and anyone could be a star. Springing up simultaneously in the United Kingdom and in the United States, the movement was crystallized in the rise and fall of...
</Question>
<Choice>Punk rock</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1915–98). The term bobby-soxers was first used in 1943–44 to identify the young audiences who sighed, squealed, sobbed, and swooned over Frankie Boy—the original teen idol. Part of Frank Sinatra's appeal then was his vulnerable, slouchy look, and part was his way of caressing a lyric. He bent his voice like a trombone to develop an intimate...
</Question>
<Choice>Sinatra, Frank</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(born 1949). Known to his fans as the Boss, Bruce Springsteen became a music superstar and an unparalleled pop phenomenon in the mid-1980s. Springsteen's four-hour-long concerts sold out in outdoor stadiums around the world and his album Born in the U.S.A. sold more than 15 million copies.
</Question>
<Choice>Springsteen, Bruce</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(born 1950). U.S. singer, songwriter, producer, and musician Stevie Wonder, although blind since infancy, never lacked musical vision. Wonder's combination of soul, pop, funk, and rock earned him critical acclaim, including more than 20 Grammys and an Academy award, and commercial success. With millions of records sold, the multitalented...
</Question>
<Choice>Wonder, Stevie</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Musical instruments that produce or change sounds using electricity are called electronic instruments. Electricity was first applied to a musical instrument in 1761, when an electric harpsichord appeared. However, the first major wave of electronic instruments came between 1920 and the beginning of World War II.
</Question>
<Choice>electronic instrument</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The many types of stringed instruments, or chordophones, share a single characteristic. Their sound is produced when a slender length of material—usually wire, plastic, silk, or animal gut—is made to vibrate by being stroked with a bow, plucked with a finger or plectrum (pick), or struck with a harder object. The musical pitch of a string depends...
</Question>
<Choice>stringed instruments</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Percussion instruments date from the most ancient times. Two rocks struck together to beat time, or pebbles rattled rhythmically in a gourd, are some of the ancient instruments still used today in some form both in symphonic and popular music. Since the early 17th century the term percussion instruments has referred to two large groups of...
</Question>
<Choice>percussion instrument</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
According to the standard method of instrument classification introduced in the early 20th century, all wind instruments (that is, all instruments in which air is the primary vibrating medium for the production of sound) are called aerophones. Within the aerophone family there are four categories that are based on an instrument's manner of tone...
</Question>
<Choice>wind instruments</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Cartoons, whether in animated or print form, are a part of the daily lives of millions of people throughout the world. They encompass a broad range of subject matter that can be humorous or serious, realistic or fanciful, purely entertaining or bitingly satiric. People of all ages and backgrounds enjoy some form of cartoons.
</Question>
<Choice>cartoons</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1834–1917). The works of French impressionist artist Edgar Degas masterfully capture the human form in motion, especially female ballet dancers and bathers. Highly innovative, he found new and brilliant solutions to the problems of form, composition, and color. Degas favored pastels, but he also used a great variety of other media in his...
</Question>
<Choice>Degas, Edgar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1471–1528). The son of a goldsmith, Albrecht Dürer became known as the “prince of German artists.” He was the first to fuse the richness of the Italian Renaissance to the harsher northern European arts of painting, drawing, and engraving.
</Question>
<Choice>Dürer, Albrecht</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1697–1764). The English painter and engraver William Hogarth was primarily a humorist and satirist. His best-known works include several series of popular satiric engravings in which he ridiculed the viciousness and folly that he saw in the world around him.
</Question>
<Choice>Hogarth, William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1746–1828). For the bold technique of his paintings, the haunting satire of his etchings, and his belief that the artist's vision is more important than tradition, Goya is often called “the first of the moderns.” His uncompromising portrayal of his times marks the beginning of 19th-century realism.
</Question>
<Choice>Goya, Francisco de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1452–1519). The term Renaissance man was coined to describe the genius of Leonardo da Vinci. He was a man of so many accomplishments in so many areas of human endeavor that his like has rarely been seen in human history.Casual patrons of the arts know him as the painter of La Gioconda, more commonly called the Mona Lisa, and of the exquisite...
</Question>
<Choice>Leonardo da Vinci</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1684–1721). A French rococo artist whose charming and graceful paintings show his interest in theater and ballet, Antoine Watteau is probably best known for his fêtes galantes. These romantic and idealized scenes depict elaborately costumed ladies and gentlemen at play in fanciful outdoor settings.
</Question>
<Choice>Watteau, Antoine</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1450?–1516), Dutch painter. The works of Hieronymus Bosch are full of fantastic figures, expressions of the medieval belief in witchcraft and demons. Bosch specialized in religious allegories and satirical treatments of themes from everyday life. Despite a pessimism and stern morality, he influenced many later artists through his mastery of...
</Question>
<Choice>Bosch, Hieronymus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1839–1906).? Today many critics call Paul Cézanne the Father of Modern Painting, but during most of his life he seemed to be a failure. He sold few pictures and won no prizes. He had to be supported by his father and was also helped by the writer Émile Zola, his boyhood friend. Only in the last decade of his life was his greatness recognized.
</Question>
<Choice>Cézanne, Paul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1887–1985). In the whimsical world depicted by the Russian-born artist Marc Chagall, everyday objects seem to defy the laws of gravity. Cows and people float in space high above the rooftops of a distant village. Although he borrowed elements from cubism, impressionism, and fauvism, Chagall developed a style that cannot be classified with any...
</Question>
<Choice>Chagall, Marc</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1776–1837). Early in the 19th century, most English painters believed that “a good picture, like a good fiddle, should be brown.” John Constable, however, believed that nature should be shown in its own colors. He invented a technique to make this possible. Instead of using flat colors, he painted with thick daubs and flecks of many hues. He is...
</Question>
<Choice>Constable, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1904–89). Despite all that was written by and about him, Spanish surrealist artist Salvador Dalí remained a mystery as a man and as an artist. A curious blend of reality and fantasy characterized both his life and his works.
</Question>
<Choice>Dali, Salvador</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1834–1917). The works of French impressionist artist Edgar Degas masterfully capture the human form in motion, especially female ballet dancers and bathers. Highly innovative, he found new and brilliant solutions to the problems of form, composition, and color. Degas favored pastels, but he also used a great variety of other media in his...
</Question>
<Choice>Degas, Edgar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1471–1528). The son of a goldsmith, Albrecht Dürer became known as the “prince of German artists.” He was the first to fuse the richness of the Italian Renaissance to the harsher northern European arts of painting, drawing, and engraving.
</Question>
<Choice>Dürer, Albrecht</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1266?–1337). Outstanding as a painter, sculptor, and architect, Giotto was recognized as the first genius of art in the Italian Renaissance. Giotto lived and worked at a time when people's minds and talents were first being freed from the shackles of medieval restraint. He dealt largely in the traditional religious subjects, but he gave these...
</Question>
<Choice>Giotto</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1746–1828). For the bold technique of his paintings, the haunting satire of his etchings, and his belief that the artist's vision is more important than tradition, Goya is often called “the first of the moderns.” His uncompromising portrayal of his times marks the beginning of 19th-century realism.
</Question>
<Choice>Goya, Francisco de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1541?–1614). For centuries the vibrant colors, unusual perspectives, and strangely contorted figures of El Greco's paintings were widely misunderstood. While some critics attributed these characteristics to a defect in the artist's eyesight, others saw them as an expression of El Greco's unique artistic vision.
</Question>
<Choice>Greco, El</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1580?–1666). Now recognized as one of the greatest portrait painters of all time, the Dutch painter Frans Hals was generally ignored for two centuries. Then, in the 1800s, Édouard Manet, Vincent van Gogh, and others rediscovered his work and were influenced by his freedom of style, use of color, and technique that approached 18th-century...
</Question>
<Choice>Hals, Frans</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1697–1764). The English painter and engraver William Hogarth was primarily a humorist and satirist. His best-known works include several series of popular satiric engravings in which he ridiculed the viciousness and folly that he saw in the world around him.
</Question>
<Choice>Hogarth, William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1836–1910). One of the greatest of American painters, Winslow Homer is best known for his watercolors and oil paintings of the sea. These paintings often have great dramatic effect because of the way they show man's powerlessness in the face of the unfeeling forces of nature.
</Question>
<Choice>Homer, Winslow</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1452–1519). The term Renaissance man was coined to describe the genius of Leonardo da Vinci. He was a man of so many accomplishments in so many areas of human endeavor that his like has rarely been seen in human history.Casual patrons of the arts know him as the painter of La Gioconda, more commonly called the Mona Lisa, and of the exquisite...
</Question>
<Choice>Leonardo da Vinci</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1832–83). The French painter whose work inspired the impressionists was Édouard Manet. Manet also introduced the technique of lighting faces or figures from the front, almost eliminating shadows. This method, called peinture claire, is now considered one of the basic technical contributions of 19th-century art. Manet, who preferred to paint from...
</Question>
<Choice>Manet, Édouard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1401–28?). An Italian artist who worked in Florence during the Renaissance, Masaccio has been called the father of Renaissance painting. His use of light and shadow, the solidity and realism of his figures, and the use of the perspective in his paintings were entirely different from the work of the medieval and late Gothic artists who preceded...
</Question>
<Choice>Masaccio</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1869–1954). Widely regarded as the greatest French painter of the 20th century, Henri Matisse also excelled at sculpture, illustration, graphics, and scenic design. His final masterpiece, completed when he was more than 80 years old, was the complete decoration—including windows, furniture, vestments, and murals—for the Dominican Chapel of the...
</Question>
<Choice>Matisse, Henri</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1430?–94). Although he was known as a master of Flemish painting, Hans Memling was born in Seligenstadt, near what is today Frankfurt am Main, Germany. Memling, whose name is sometimes spelled Memlinc, first established himself as a painter in Brussels. In style and composition his work shows the strong influence of Rogier van der Weyden, the...
</Question>
<Choice>Memling, Hans</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1475–1564). Sculptor, painter, architect, and poet Michelangelo was the greatest artist in a time of greatness. He lived during the Italian Renaissance, a period known for its creative activity. Civilization made huge strides in science and invention, in literature, and in politics. In art, the age's great achievement, Michelangelo led all...
</Question>
<Choice>Michelangelo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1840–1926). The leader of the 19th-century impressionist art movement, Claude Monet continued throughout his long career to pursue its goals. Monet preferred to paint outdoors, directly from nature. Almost all his work shows his desire to capture on canvas the changing effects of light.
</Question>
<Choice>Monet, Claude</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1881–1973). The reaction in the late 19th century against naturalism in art led to a sequence of different movements in the 20th century. In each of these periods of innovation Pablo Picasso played an important part. He said that to repeat oneself is to go against “the constant flight forward of the spirit.” Primarily a painter, he also became a...
</Question>
<Choice>Picasso, Pablo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1912–56). Nicknamed Jack the Dripper for his unique style of painting, the American artist Jackson Pollock created his trademark murals by tacking a large canvas to the floor and using a stick to drip or splash paint from all four sides of the canvas. His style caused a critical controversy, and his use of painting for total personal expression...
</Question>
<Choice>Pollock, Jackson</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1483–1520). As a master painter and architect of the Italian High Renaissance, Raphael produced works that rivaled the well-known masterpieces of Leonardo da Vinci and Michelangelo. His later works used a new style that tended toward the baroque. His architecture displayed the exaggerated scale and abnormal forms of Mannerism.
</Question>
<Choice>Raphael</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1606–69). The greatest artist of the Dutch school was Rembrandt. He was a master of light and shadow whose paintings, drawings, and etchings made him a giant in the history of art.
</Question>
<Choice>Rembrandt</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1841–1919). The brilliant colors and beautiful, rounded figures of Renoir's paintings have never been equalled. He was one of the leaders of France's impressionist movement but later opted for a more formal style. His portraits, landscapes, and still lifes have a unique texture and light that places Renoir's work among that of the world's finest...
</Question>
<Choice>Renoir, Pierre-August</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1723–92). Not all artists have great difficulties and die unknown and unrewarded. Joshua Reynolds was the most successful portrait painter of his day in England as well as a distinguished member of London's intellectual society.
</Question>
<Choice>Reynolds, Joshua</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1577–1640). Regarded for more than three centuries as the greatest of Flemish painters, Peter Paul Rubens was nearly as famous during his lifetime for his adroit achievements as a diplomat. The master artist of his day, he was learned in science and politics as well and spoke seven languages fluently. His charm made him welcome in the courts...
</Question>
<Choice>Rubens, Peter Paul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1898–1969). Art, to Ben Shahn, was “one of the last remaining outposts of free speech.” He used art to express his social consciousness.
</Question>
<Choice>Shahn, Ben</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1755–1828). The most brilliant portrait painter in America after the Revolution, Gilbert Stuart is known especially for his paintings of George Washington. His “Athenaeum” portrait of Washington, which is reproduced on currency, is familiar to everyone who has looked at a dollar bill.
</Question>
<Choice>Stuart, Gilbert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1488/90?–1576). One of the master painters of the Italian Renaissance was Titian, an artist of the Venetian school. He was born Tiziano Vecellio at Pieve di Cadore, north of Venice, and tradition says that as a boy he painted with juices extracted from flowers. When he was about 10 years old, he went to Venice. There he studied under Giovanni...
</Question>
<Choice>Titian</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1775–1851). One of the finest landscape artists was J.M.W. Turner, whose work was exhibited when he was still a teenager. His entire life was devoted to his art. Unlike many artists of his era, he was successful throughout his career.
</Question>
<Choice>Turner, J.M.W.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1886–1957). Of the many controversies that embroiled the Mexican painter Diego Rivera because of the didactic character of his work, the removal in 1933 of his fresco Man at the Crossroads from Rockefeller Center in New York City is probably the best known. A Communist, the artist had included in his fresco a figure that resembled the Soviet...
</Question>
<Choice>Rivera, Diego</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1390?–1441). The Flemish painter who perfected the new technique of painting in oils, Jan van Eyck produced mostly portraits and religious subjects on wooden panels. His works often contain disguised religious symbols.
</Question>
<Choice>Van Eyck, Jan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1853–90). One of the four great Postimpressionists (along with Paul Gauguin, Georges Seurat, and Paul Cézanne), Vincent van Gogh is generally considered the greatest Dutch painter after Rembrandt. His reputation is based largely on the works of the last three years of his short ten-year painting career, and he had a powerful influence on...
</Question>
<Choice>Van Gogh</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1599–1660). Spain's greatest painter was also one of the supreme artists of all time. A master of technique, highly individual in style, Diego Velázquez may have had a greater influence on European art than any other painter.
</Question>
<Choice>Velasquez, Diego</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1632–75). One of the greatest 17th-century Dutch painters, Johannes Vermeer is known for his light-drenched genre pictures—scenes from everyday life. They are both realistic and poetic, conveying the sense that Vermeer saw beauty in the simplest object.
</Question>
<Choice>Vermeer, Jan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1928?–87). Pop art, according to its practitioners, is meant to create art that is indistinguishable from life. According to Andy Warhol, one of its most innovative producers, it is intended to bore the audience and to indicate the dehumanization of modern life. The creators of pop art have taken pleasure, if not pride, in exalting the...
</Question>
<Choice>Warhol, Andy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1738–1820). One of the first American artists to win a wide reputation in Europe, Benjamin West exerted considerable influence on the development of art in the United States through such young American painters as Gilbert Stuart, Charles Willson Peale, and John Singleton Copley. West abandoned the tradition of painting people in Greek and Roman...
</Question>
<Choice>West, Benjamin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1400?–64). A leading Flemish painter of the mid-15th century, Rogier van der Weyden added a new spiritual quality to the works of his time. He greatly influenced painting both in Flanders and throughout Europe.
</Question>
<Choice>Weyden, Rogier van der</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1834–1903). “If silicon had been a gas, I might have become a general in the United States Army,” remarked Whistler years after he had become a world-famous painter and etcher. James Abbott McNeill Whistler, who was born in Lowell, Mass., to an old military family, entered the United States Military Academy at West Point when he was 17. He liked...
</Question>
<Choice>Whistler, James McNeill</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1892–1942). A major artist of Midwestern regional themes, Grant Wood painted pictures that have become American classics. The Midwestern regional movement was a form of realism that was popular during the 1930s. It grew out of the desire of American artists to end their dependence on European culture.
</Question>
<Choice>Wood, Grant</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1898–1991). U.S. photographer Berenice Abbott is best known for preserving the works of French documentary photographer Eugène Atget and for her photographic documentation of New York City in the late 1930s. During the 1920s, she set up a Paris studio and made well-known portraits of Parisian expatriates, artists, writers, and aristocrats. She...
</Question>
<Choice>Abbott, Berenice</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1902–84). The American photographer Ansel Adams was well known for technical innovations and for his dramatic pictures of Western landscapes. He was a pioneer in the movement to preserve the wilderness and one of the first to promote photography as an art form.
</Question>
<Choice>Adams, Ansel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1856–1927). In more than 10,000 picturesque scenes of Paris, Eugène Atget—a failed painter who became an influential photographer—recorded moody black-and-white images of the city for others to put in color on canvas. The sign on the door of his studio read “Documents for Artists.” Among those who bought Atget's work for inspiration were set...
</Question>
<Choice>Atget, Eugène</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1823?–96). A pioneer in 19th-century photography, Mathew Brady was best known for his portraits of politicians and for his photographs of the American Civil War. In his early 20s he began carrying out a plan to photograph as many distinguished Americans as he could.
</Question>
<Choice>Brady, Mathew</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1815–79). The British photographer Julia Margaret Cameron is considered one of the greatest portraitists of the 19th century. Among her sitters were her friends the poets Alfred, Lord Tennyson, and Henry Wadsworth Longfellow; the astronomer Sir John Herschel; the writer Thomas Carlyle; and the scientist Charles Darwin.
</Question>
<Choice>Cameron, Julia Margaret</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1908–2004). With his Leica camera, French photographer Henri Cartier-Bresson traveled the world, recording the images he saw. His humane, spontaneous photographs helped establish photojournalism as an art form.
</Question>
<Choice>Cartier-Bresson, Henri</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1787–1851). The first practical photographic process that produced lasting pictures was invented by Louis-Jacques-Mandé Daguerre, a French painter and physicist. The photographs that result from his process are called daguerreotypes.
</Question>
<Choice>Daguerre, Louis-Jacques-Mandé</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1854–1932). The man who transformed photography from a complicated and expensive chore into an inexpensive hobby for millions of people was George Eastman. He was the founder of the Eastman Kodak Company and a philanthropist who gave about 75 million dollars to educational institutions and other causes. (See also Photography.)
</Question>
<Choice>Eastman, George</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1903–75), U.S. photographer. Born on Nov. 3, 1903, in St. Louis, Mo., Walker Evans was a master photographer noted for stark, black-and-white images of the American scene. Mainly self-taught, he first worked as a freelancer in New York City. During the Depression he worked for the Farm Security Administration, documenting the conditions of poor...
</Question>
<Choice>Evans, Walker</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1843–1942), U.S. photographer. William Henry Jackson was one of the best-known Western landscape and Native American portrait photographers in the 19th century. From 1870 to 1878 he was the official photographer for the United States Geological and Geographical Survey of the Territories. His photographs of Wyoming were instrumental in the...
</Question>
<Choice>Jackson, William Henry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1895–1965). The stark photographs of the victims of the Great Depression of the 1930s that were made by Dorothea Lange were a major influence on succeeding documentary and journalistic photographers. She has been called the greatest documentary photographer of the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>Lange, Dorothea</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1830–1904). To settle an argument, Eadweard Muybridge was hired to prove that a horse had all four feet simultaneously off the ground at one phase of a trot. He designed elaborate photographic systems that combined batteries of from 12 to 24 cameras with fast shutter mechanisms. The first successful sequential photographs of rapidly moving...
</Question>
<Choice>Muybridge, Eadweard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1917–2009). U.S. photographer Irving Penn is noted for his incisive portraits and sophisticated pictures for fashion magazines. He had highly acclaimed exhibits at the Museum of Modern Art in New York City in 1975 and at the Metropolitan Museum in 1977.
</Question>
<Choice>Penn, Irving</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1849–1914), U.S. social reformer, journalist, photojournalist, and author. Jacob Riis was known as the “Emancipator of the Slums” because he shocked the United States with his photographs of slum conditions. Born in Ribe, Denmark, Riis emigrated to the United States in 1870, where he became a police reporter in New York City. He was among the...
</Question>
<Choice>Riis, Jacob</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1879–1973). Some of the most familiar images of the personalities of the 1920s and '30s—names like Greta Garbo and Charlie Chaplin—stem from photographs taken by Edward Steichen. At that time Steichen was working as a photographer for the magazines Vanity Fair and Vogue, but he was never simply a portrait or fashion photographer. He and his...
</Question>
<Choice>Steichen, Edward</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1864–1946). The first photographer to have his work exhibited in American art museums, Alfred Stieglitz was also a devoted supporter of modern art, particularly modern American art. The Photo-Secession group he founded in 1902 contributed to the acceptance of photography as an art form. The group's gallery, which opened in 1905, was officially...
</Question>
<Choice>Stieglitz, Alfred</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1890–1976). Combining realism and abstraction in photographs of landscapes and close-ups of rocks and plants, Paul Strand achieved a synthesis in a style he described as organic realism. He was also one of the first photographers to use the candid-camera technique.
</Question>
<Choice>Strand, Paul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1886–1958). An artist obsessed with realism, the American photographer Edward Weston refused to manipulate his images in the darkroom. One of the most influential photographers of the 20th century, he preferred to work in abstract forms found in nature with high-resolution detail in his photographs.
</Question>
<Choice>Weston, Edward</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1598–1680). Perhaps the greatest sculptor of the 17th century and one of its outstanding architects, Gian Lorenzo Bernini created the baroque style of sculpture. He developed it to such an extent and it became so admired and popular that it continued for at least two more generations in various parts of Europe, and 18th-century Italian sculpture...
</Question>
<Choice>Bernini, Gian Lorenzo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1876–1957). The Romanian artist Constantin Brancusi was a simple man, and this simplicity is reflected in his sculptures. They do not represent natural objects so much as they embody the spirit and essence of those objects.
</Question>
<Choice>Brancusi, Constantin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1898–1976). The abstract constructions known as “stabiles” and “mobiles” were the creation of the American sculptor Alexander Calder. Trained as a mechanical engineer, Calder used his background to produce these new art forms.
</Question>
<Choice>Calder, Alexander</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1757–1822). Italian sculptor Antonio Canova was one of the greatest artists of the neoclassic movement (in art, a movement that imitated the classical art of ancient Greece and Rome). His work dominated European sculpture at the end of the 18th century and the beginning of the 19th century. He was made a marquess and given the title marchese d...
</Question>
<Choice>Canova, Antoinio</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1500–71). Benvenuto Cellini was the leading goldsmith of the Italian Renaissance and an accomplished sculptor as well. Despite these accomplishments, he owes much of his fame to an autobiography in which he describes in simple and direct language the details of his turbulent life.
</Question>
<Choice>Cellini, Benvenuto</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1386?–1466). One of the towering figures of the Italian Renaissance, Donatello was the greatest sculptor of the 15th century. He influenced both the realms of sculpture and painting throughout that century and beyond.
</Question>
<Choice>Donatello</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1887–1968). One of the leading spirits of 20th-century painting was the French artist Marcel Duchamp. He led the way to pop and op art with his famous cubist painting Nude Descending a Staircase, No. 2, through his “ready-mades,” and in the movement called dadaism.
</Question>
<Choice>Duchamp, Marcel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1378–1455). Sculptor, painter, and metalworker, Lorenzo Ghiberti was one of the great artists of the Italian Renaissance. Like many Renaissance artists, he was trained in gold working. His master was his stepfather, Bartoluccio, whom he sometimes claimed was his father. In 1400 Ghiberti left Florence to escape the plague. He returned to enter a...
</Question>
<Choice>Ghiberti</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1901–66). The Swiss sculptor Giacometti was one of the outstanding artists of the 20th century. Working in an era dominated by abstract art, he tried to achieve reality with a new approach to rendering distance. His elongated and textured figures are seen as in distance and in an imaginary space. Giacometti also produced paintings and drawings...
</Question>
<Choice>Giacometti, Alberto</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1891–1973). One of the first sculptors to create a style founded on the style of art called Cubism, Jacques Lipchitz was a pioneer of abstract sculpture in the first half of the 20th century. He produced numerous works in which a flamelike design is anchored to the Earth by the sheer massiveness of the material.
</Question>
<Choice>Lipchitz, Jacques</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1475–1564). Sculptor, painter, architect, and poet Michelangelo was the greatest artist in a time of greatness. He lived during the Italian Renaissance, a period known for its creative activity. Civilization made huge strides in science and invention, in literature, and in politics. In art, the age's great achievement, Michelangelo led all...
</Question>
<Choice>Michelangelo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1884–1920). An Italian painter and sculptor who worked mostly in Paris, Modigliani is best known for his portraits, which can easily be recognized because of their elongated noses and necks and their long slender faces.
</Question>
<Choice>Modigliani, Amedeo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1898–1986). Generally regarded as the greatest sculptor of the 20th century, Henry Moore was also one of the most prolific. His sculptures can be seen today in museums, private collections, and public spaces around the world.
</Question>
<Choice>Moore, Henry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(born 1929). An artist best known for his giant, soft sculptures of everyday objects, Claes Oldenburg was closely associated with the development of pop art in the United States during the 1960s.
</Question>
<Choice>Oldenburg, Claes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1861–1909). The painter and sculptor Frederic Remington created some of the most realistic portrayals of the American West in the late 19th century. He chose for his subjects men living close to nature: cowboys, Indians, frontiersmen, and soldiers. His works—especially his sculptures of bucking broncos—are alive with motion and vividly capture...
</Question>
<Choice>Remington, Frederic</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1840–1917). The French artist Auguste Rodin had a profound influence on 20th-century sculpture. His works are distinguished by their stunning strength and realism. Rodin refused to ignore the negative aspects of humanity, and his works confront distress and moral weakness as well as passion and beauty.
</Question>
<Choice>Rodin, Auguste</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1848–1907). The son of a French shoemaker, Augustus Saint-Gaudens was part of a new movement in the arts in the late 19th century. Before his time American sculptors merely followed the style of European artists or copied from the ancient Greeks and Romans. His monumental sculptures still stand in major United States cities.
</Question>
<Choice>Saint-Gaudens, Augustus</Choice>
</item>
</topics>