<topics> 
<item>
<Question>
The emergence of independent African American filmmakers such as Melvin Van Peebles in the late 1960s and 1970s paved the way for the mainstream success of an uncompromising black cinema in the late 1980s and 1990s. The leader of the movement was Spike Lee, an all-around talent who wrote, directed, edited, and often performed in his films. He...
</Question>
<Choice>African American filmmakers</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1899–1987). Highly popular for his graceful, seemingly effortless dancing and innovative choreography, American dancer Fred Astaire starred in numerous Broadway musicals and motion pictures. He is best known for his tap and ballroom numbers with Ginger Rogers in musical comedy films. Top hat, white tie, tails, and a formal cane epitomized the...
</Question>
<Choice>Astaire, Fred</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1918–2007). A collection of complex, searching films produced over a period of more than 40 years made the Swedish director Ingmar Bergman world famous. His versatile camera work, fragmented narrative style, and bleak depiction of human loneliness and weakness were his trademarks.
</Question>
<Choice>Bergman, Ingmar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1900–83), Spanish filmmaker. Born in Calanda, Spain, Buñuel was known for films that were characterized by surrealist humor and anarchistic contempt for conventional morality. He made films in Spain, France, the United States, and Mexico. Some of his most memorable films include ‘An Andalusian Dog' (1929), ‘The Golden Age' (1930), ‘Land Without...
</Question>
<Choice>Buñuel, Luis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1897–1991). American motion-picture director Frank Capra was noted for a series of highly popular films in the 1930s and '40s that included such classics as It Happened One Night (1934), Mr. Smith Goes to Washington (1939), and It's a Wonderful Life (1946).
</Question>
<Choice>Capra, Frank</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1889–1977). Start with a coat that is too small, trousers and shoes that are too large, a derby hat, a cane, and a ridiculous moustache. Put them together with the genius of Charlie Chaplin and the result is “the Little Tramp,” one of the most famous and best-loved characters ever created for the movie screen. Although he is best known as an...
</Question>
<Choice>Chaplin, Charlie</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. filmmakers. Meticulous craftsmen known for their unique juxtapositions, stylish visuals, and unsettling, though often humorous, stories, the Coen brothers attracted substantial critical notice beginning in the mid-1980s.
</Question>
<Choice>Coen, Joel and Ethan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(born 1939), U.S. film director. Born on April 7, 1939, in Detroit, Mich., Coppola grew up in a suburb of New York City. Coppola is best known for his trilogy of Godfather films, ‘The Godfather' (1972), ‘The Godfather Part II' (1974, for which he won an Academy award as best director), and ‘The Godfather Part III' (1990). Other critically...
</Question>
<Choice>Coppola, Francis Ford</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1881–1959). Film director and producer Cecil B. DeMille was often credited with making Hollywood, Calif., the motion picture capital of the world. He championed the making of feature-length films over short films. He also became known for his use of spectacle in large, often lurid productions of biblical and other epics.
</Question>
<Choice>De Mille, Cecil Blount</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1901–74). Italian film director Vittorio De Sica played a key role in Italy's neorealist movement following World War II. He also acted in more than 150 films over the course of his long career.
</Question>
<Choice>De Sica, Vittorio</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1901–92). The German-born American film actress and entertainer Marlene Dietrich developed an aura of sophistication and languid sensuality that made her one of the most glamorous of film stars.
</Question>
<Choice>Dietrich, Marlene</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1901–66). A cartoonist and master of motion picture animation, Walt Disney made the world fall in love with a large-eared mouse, a scheming duck, and dozens of other animal characters. Over the course of his remarkable career, Disney transformed the making of full-length animated films into an art form.
</Question>
<Choice>Disney, Walt</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
When he was 21 years old, Thomas Edison took out his first patent. It was for an electric vote counter to be used in the United States House of Representatives. The machine worked perfectly, but the congressmen would not buy it. They did not want vote counting to be done quickly. Often the roll call was used for purposes of delay (filibustering).
</Question>
<Choice>Edison, Thomas Alva</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1898–1948). He has been called the epic poet of the Soviet cinema, and many consider Sergei Eisenstein the finest craftsman ever to direct motion pictures. His films Potemkin, released in 1925, Alexander Nevsky (1938), and Ivan the Terrible (Part One, 1944; Part Two, completed 1946, released 1958) are classics of movie art.
</Question>
<Choice>Eisenstein, Sergei</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1883–1939). A motion-picture actor and producer, Douglas Fairbanks was one of the first and greatest of the boasting, daredevil screen heroes. His athletic skill, gallant romanticism, and natural sincerity made him “king of Hollywood” during the 1920s. He was the energetic go-getter who used his talents to achieve the classic goals of the...
</Question>
<Choice>Fairbanks, Douglas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1920–93). An outstanding Italian film director, Federico Fellini is known for freely structured films in which dreams and reality mingle. He wrote at least part of all his films, which are characterized by their emphasis on modern mankind's solitude and by their autobiographical elements. His most famous films are La Strada (The Road, 1954), La...
</Question>
<Choice>Fellini, Federico</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1880–1946). One of America's greatest comedians, W.C. Fields was a master mimic whose humor and mock pompousness was accompanied by a unique combination of a nasal drawl, wooden expression, and flawlessly timed gestures. He ad-libbed, or made up as he went along, many of his radio and movie scripts and maintained a cynic's role both on and off...
</Question>
<Choice>Fields, W.C.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1895–1973), U.S. motion picture director. Born in Cape Elizabeth, Me., Ford arrived in Hollywood in 1914 and worked as an actor and stuntman before becoming a director in 1917. Renowned for his Westerns and American epics starring movie legends John Wayne, Henry Fonda, and James Stewart, Ford won best director Academy awards for ‘The Informer...
</Question>
<Choice>Ford, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(born 1930). French film director Jean-Luc Godard came to prominence with the New Wave group of filmmakers during the late 1950s and the 1960s. Like other directors associated with the movement, Godard was known for his independent vision and his improvisatory filmmaking procedures.
</Question>
<Choice>Godard, Jean-Luc</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1875–1948). He was the first giant of the motion picture industry, the genius of film who is credited with making it an art form. Director D.W. Griffith never needed a script. He improvised new ways to use the camera and to cut the celluloid, redefining the craft for the next generation of directors.
</Question>
<Choice>Griffith, D.W.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1896–1977), U.S. film director. Hawks was born in Goshen, Ind., on May 30, 1896. He worked in silent films as a writer and producer before directing his first movie in 1925. Hawks made films in a variety of genres, such as dramas, Westerns, and comedies. His most memorable films include ‘Scarface: The Shame of a Nation' (1932), ‘Bringing Up Baby...
</Question>
<Choice>Hawks, Howard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1899–1980). The motion picture director Alfred Hitchcock was a master of suspense and horror films. His artistry, often coupled with humorous touches, was such that he himself became as notable as his movie work. He became well known to television audiences through his Alfred Hitchcock Presents, a series that was revived some years after his...
</Question>
<Choice>Hitchcock, Alfred</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A district within the city of Los Angeles, Calif., Hollywood served as the production center of the U.S. motion-picture industry for more than 30 years. Laid out as a real-estate subdivision in 1887, Hollywood existed as a separate town until 1910 when residents, faced with a chronic water shortage, voted to become part of Los Angeles. Hollywood...
</Question>
<Choice>Hollywood</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1928–99). U.S. motion-picture director Stanley Kubrick was known for his meticulous attention to detail and his detached, pessimistic view of life. Born in New York City on July 26, 1928, Kubrick became a staff photographer for Look magazine at age 17. His first film, The Day of the Fight (1951), is a short documentary about boxing. Fear and...
</Question>
<Choice>Kubrick, Stanley</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1910–98), Japanese film director. Born in Tokyo, Japan, Kurosawa began his film career as an assistant director in 1936. After making his debut film in 1943, he went on to direct such internationally renowned epic films as ‘Rashomon' (1950), ‘Seven Samurai' (1954), ‘Kagemusha' (1980), and ‘Ran' (1985). (See also Directing.)
</Question>
<Choice>Kurosawa, Akira</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1890–1976), Austrian-born U.S. film director. Born in Vienna, Austria, Lang began making films in Germany in 1919. His career flourished in the 1920s, but in 1934, he fled the Nazi regime and came to the United States. His films include ‘Metropolis' (1927), ‘M' (1931), ‘Fury' (1936), ‘You Only Live Once' (1937), ‘Hangmen Also Die...
</Question>
<Choice>Lang, Fritz</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1892–1947). German-born American motion-picture director and producer Ernst Lubitsch won critical and popular acclaim for his sophisticated comedies about upper-class life. His brilliant style, which became known as the “Lubitsch touch,” combined understatement and graceful wit.
</Question>
<Choice>Lubitsch, Ernst</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1864–1948). French chemist and industrialist Louis Lumière, along with his brother, Auguste, invented the first commercially successful motion-picture projector, which they used in 1895 to create the first motion picture.
</Question>
<Choice>Lumière, Louis Jean</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The comedy team of the Marx Brothers raised havoc on stage, screen, and radio for 30 years, making fun of the wealthy, pompous, and socially respectable. In vaudeville they created a skillful blend of visual and verbal humor that later became such movies as ‘The Cocoanuts' (1929), ‘Animal Crackers' (1930), ‘Monkey Business' (1931), ‘Duck Soup...
</Question>
<Choice>Marx Brothers</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1861–1938). An early French experimenter with motion pictures, Georges Méliès was the first to film fictional narratives. His techniques included multiple exposure and other in-camera manipulations to achieve special effects.
</Question>
<Choice>Méliès, Georges</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Famous for its logo of a roaring lion, Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer, Inc. (MGM), ranks as one of the world's most important film studios. MGM, based in Santa Monica, Calif., develops, produces, and distributes motion pictures for theatrical release and the home-video market as well as television programs. Founded in 1925, MGM became the world's most...
</Question>
<Choice>Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer, Inc.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Notorious for its iron-fisted business methods, the Motion Picture Patent Company (MPPC) attempted to gain complete control of the United States movie-making industry in the early 1900s. Ultimately unsuccessful, the company instead contributed to the rise of independent film producers and the establishment of Hollywood, Calif., as the nation's...
</Question>
<Choice>Motion Picture Patent Company</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1888–1931). A renowned German motion picture director of the silent era, F.W. Murnau revolutionized filmmaking by using the camera to interpret the emotional state of a character.
</Question>
<Choice>Murnau, F.W.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the late 1950s a group of French directors began making “New Wave” films. These movies were characterized by brilliant filming techniques that often overshadowed plot and character development and by rapid changes of scene called jump cuts. Among the New Wave directors were Louis Malle, Claude Chabrol, François Truffaut, Jean-Luc Godard, and...
</Question>
<Choice>New Wave</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1907–89). Acclaimed by critics and audiences alike as the greatest actor of his generation, Laurence Olivier pursued a distinguished career on stage and screen for more than 60 years.
</Question>
<Choice>Olivier, Laurence</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of Hollywood's oldest and most successful major motion picture studios, Paramount Communications (formerly Paramount Pictures Corporation) was founded in 1914. Soon afterward, Adolph Zukor became Paramount's president and built it into a leading motion picture studio. In the silent film era, Paramount boasted such directors as Cecil B...
</Question>
<Choice>Paramount Communications, Inc.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The experience of World War II brought about an increased appetite for films of social purpose made outside of Hollywood. One of the most notable developments in postwar cinema was the Italian neorealism movement of Luchino Visconti, Vittorio De Sica, and Roberto Rossellini, which emphasized simply shot stories filmed on location using...
</Question>
<Choice>Postwar world cinema</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1921–92). Indian filmmaker Satyajit Ray's influence on the movie industry was unparalleled in his native country. His Apu trilogy of films brought the world to India's doorstep. Ray presented scenes of everyday life in India in more than 30 feature-length films. He also influenced a generation of filmmakers including Ismail Merchant and Mira Nair...
</Question>
<Choice>Ray, Satyajit</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1902–2003). The legacy of German filmmaker, actress, photographer, and director Leni Riefenstahl was corrupted by her prominence as a filmmaker for Adolf Hitler. She was known chiefly for two documentaries she made during the Nazi regime that were later touted as some of the most successful propaganda pieces ever made. Triumph of the Will, which...
</Question>
<Choice>Riefenstahl, Leni</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1906–77). Italian motion-picture director Roberto Rossellini directed the first film created in the Italian style of filmmaking called neorealism, Open City (1945). Neorealist films featured natural settings in which actors either were or looked like ordinary people involved in commonplace situations.
</Question>
<Choice>Rossellini, Roberto</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(born 1942). U.S. filmmaker Martin Scorsese was known for his harsh, often violent depictions of U.S. culture. His films tend to be concerned with people rather than plots, and he was fond of placing his characters in volatile situations and allowing events to unfold naturally.
</Question>
<Choice>Scorsese, Martin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1880–1960). The father of slapstick comedy in motion pictures and one of the great pioneer Hollywood filmmakers was Canadian-born Mack Sennett. He was born Michael Sinnott in Richmond, Que., on Jan. 17, 1880. At age 20 he moved to New York City and became a performer in burlesque and vaudeville. In 1909 he went to work for D.W. Griffith at the...
</Question>
<Choice>Sennett, Mack</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(born 1947). U.S. filmmaker Steven Spielberg directed and produced some of the top-grossing movies of all time. His influence earned him the Irving G. Thalberg Award from the Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences in 1987 and a lifetime achievement award from the American Film Institute in 1995.
</Question>
<Choice>Spielberg, Steven</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Out of the international political and cultural changes of the 1960s emerged a new, socially conscious cinema in Latin America, Africa, and Asia. In the wake of decolonization and independence, activist filmmakers sought to create a cinema that could contribute to popular struggles against political oppression and economic dependency. The...
</Question>
<Choice>Third Cinema</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1932–84), French film director. François Truffaut created films that revealed the depth and complexity of human relationships. He and such contemporaries as Jean-Luc Godard and Eric Rohmer embodied what became known as the New Wave of French cinema. As a young film critic Truffaut was unmerciful in his treatment of contemporary French film, but...
</Question>
<Choice>Truffaut, François</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1894–1982). U.S. director King Vidor created a series of motion pictures in the 1920s and 1930s that are considered among the most creative Hollywood productions of the late silent and early sound eras. Vidor's films of the period typically deal in relatively uncompromising terms with such themes as idealism and disillusionment in contemporary...
</Question>
<Choice>Vidor, King</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The U.S. motion-picture studio Warner Brothers played a pivotal role in the development of the Hollywood film industry. In 1927 the young studio revolutionized film by introducing the first genuine talking picture, The Jazz Singer.
</Question>
<Choice>Warner Brothers</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1915–85), U.S. director, actor, writer, and producer. Orson Welles, the maverick “boy wonder” of American theater, experienced fame at a young age. At 23, he was featured on the cover of Time magazine. At 25, he made his debut film, ‘Citizen Kane' (1941), which was eventually hailed as a masterpiece and rated one of the greatest films ever made...
</Question>
<Choice>Welles, Orson</Choice>
</item>
</topics>