<topics> 
<item>
<Question>
(born 1934), U.S. baseball player. “Throwing a fastball by Henry Aaron is like trying to sneak sunrise past a rooster,” St. Louis pitcher Curt Simmons once said, expressing the frustration that pitchers around the league felt while facing one of the most prolific power hitters in major league baseball history. By the start of the 1974 season...
</Question>
<Choice>Aaron, Hank</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(born 1942). One of the greatest U.S. heavyweight boxing champions, Muhammad Ali was known as much for his flamboyant self-promotion and controversial political stances as for his boxing ability. His motto was “I am the greatest!” He became the first boxer to win the heavyweight title three times.
</Question>
<Choice>Ali, Muhammad</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The sport of archery—shooting arrows from bows at targets—has its roots in prehistoric times. Arrows were used by ancient peoples to battle their opponents and to hunt wild game. In some societies, people still use bows and arrows as weapons.
</Question>
<Choice>archery</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
For millions of people automobile racing and rallies are among the most exciting and colorful of all spectator sports. Rallies are not speed contests but tests of driving skill on the part of sports-car owners. A major automobile race probably attracts more spectators than does any other single sporting event. In the United States, for example...
</Question>
<Choice>automobile racing and rallies</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At first glance, badminton might seem like an easy game. Two or four players use small, light rackets to hit a feathered cork across a net on a court that resembles a tennis court. But the cork, called a shuttlecock, or bird, can travel as fast as 110 miles (177 kilometers) per hour. Then it quickly slows down and dips toward the ground. The...
</Question>
<Choice>badminton</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A sport usually played on a large outdoor field, baseball is a game contested between two teams of nine players. On the inner part of the field are four white bases laid out in a square. The basic equipment consists of a bat, ball, and gloves. During a game, the two teams alternate between being fielders (playing defense) and batters (playing...
</Question>
<Choice>baseball</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
It could have been called boxball. In the winter of 1891, James Naismith, an instructor at a YMCA training school in Springfield, Mass., asked the janitor to hang a couple of boxes from the gymnasium balcony for an experimental indoor ball game. The game became known as basketball because the janitor, unable to find boxes to make the elevated...
</Question>
<Choice>basketball</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the most popular family sports is boating. Although people have enjoyed pleasure boating for hundreds of years, its popularity has increased dramatically in the 20th century, particularly in North America, Western Europe, and Australasia.
</Question>
<Choice>boating</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
More people in the United States go bowling than go to baseball games. Bowling is a year-round sport in which the players roll a ball down a long, narrow lane and try to knock down a group of wooden pins. Forms of the game include tenpins, duckpins, and candlepins. In tenpins, the most popular form of bowling, ten pins stand in a triangular...
</Question>
<Choice>bowling</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The sport of boxing is the art of attack and defense with the fists. Some people feel that boxing is a violent and dangerous sport and that it should be abolished. It has, however, endured in one form or another since ancient times and continues to have an enthusiastic following.
</Question>
<Choice>boxing</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the oldest forms of water transportation, the canoe is a narrow, lightweight boat that is usually propelled and steered by paddles. Canoes have sharp ends and curved sides, and they move efficiently in both deep and shallow water. No longer an important means of practical transportation, canoes today are most often used for sport or...
</Question>
<Choice>canoeing</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1886–1961). Considered one of the greatest and fiercest players in the history of baseball, Ty Cobb was the first man elected to baseball's Hall of Fame. He was a left-handed batter, but he threw right-handed.
</Question>
<Choice>Cobb, Ty</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The sport of cricket is the national summer game of England, where it has been played for hundreds of years, possibly since the 13th century. Laws to standardize the rules of play have existed since at least the mid-18th century. During England's colonial history, cricket was exported around the world, and it is now played in more than...
</Question>
<Choice>cricket</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The competitive sport, the form of recreation, and the mode of transportation known as cycling developed as a result of improvements to the bicycle (see bicycle). The classic professional races in the sport are held mainly in Europe, though there are many races in the United States that draw some notable foreign competitors.
</Question>
<Choice>cycling</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Latin word for horse is equus. Equestrian sports are certain riding events held at horse shows and most specifically competitive horse and rider events held at the summer Olympic Games. The three events that comprise equestrian sports are dressage, show jumping, and hunter trails. The term excludes horse racing, rodeos, and polo. (See also...
</Question>
<Choice>equestrian sports</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The skill of fencing, or fighting with a sword, has been practiced in all parts of the world for many centuries. Men, and sometimes women, fought battles with many different types of swords. Some trained seriously for the deadly combat of the duel. After duels were forbidden by law, sport fencing remained popular.
</Question>
<Choice>fencing</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The word “football” can mean many things, depending on where you are in the world. In North America it means gridiron football. The gridiron game, which takes its name from the distinctive line markings on the playing field, is a full contact game played primarily in the United States and Canada. It is known for violent collisions, high emotions...
</Question>
<Choice>football</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1903–41). On June 1, 1925, a husky baseball rookie came into the New York Yankee lineup as a pinch hitter. The rookie, Lou Gehrig, hit a single. So started one of the most remarkable records in baseball. From that day he played in every Yankee game, regular and exhibition, until 1939. Then he contracted amyotrophic lateral sclerosis (often...
</Question>
<Choice>Gehrig, Lou</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The game of golf is one of the most popular and relaxing of all outdoor sports. It is played on a large grassy area (course) with a small resilient ball and a set of wood- and steel-headed clubs. The object of the game is to hit the ball, in as few strokes as possible, into sunken cups located at intervals on the course.
</Question>
<Choice>golf</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(born 1961). The left-shooting center for the Edmonton Oilers and the Los Angeles Kings hockey teams was already on his way to being the Great Gretzky when he was barely 10 and scored three goals within 45 seconds of junior league play. Gretzky was elected MVP for eight consecutive seasons (1979–87) with Edmonton and then, after he was traded to...
</Question>
<Choice>Gretzky, Wayne</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In a bright gymnasium there is only a hushed crowd and a faint smell of chalk. Suddenly piano music plays as an athlete dances and soars over a mat. A few yards away another contestant silently performs on a narrow beam of wood. Someone else hurtles around and between two wooden poles while a competitor flies to impossible heights over a vaulting...
</Question>
<Choice>gymnastics</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A fast-paced, energetic game in which competitors hit a ball with the hand against the walls of a court, handball originated in Ireland about 1,000 years ago. For hundreds of years the game's popularity was limited primarily to Ireland. Then in the 1880s the Irish brought it to the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>handball</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The fastest of all team sports, ice hockey has been described as a combination of “blood, sweat, and beauty.” With an increased focus on the bloodshed, descriptions of professional hockey games today are more likely to include words like “goon,” “mayhem,” and “degenerate.” Stiffer penalties have not discouraged the players from using their basic...
</Question>
<Choice>hockey, ice</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(born 1963). Both literally and figuratively, Michael Jordan soared higher than any National Basketball Association (NBA) guard before him. His high-leaping slam dunks inspired his nickname, “Air Jordan.” He was the NBA's top scorer for a record-breaking 10 seasons. Also outstanding at defense, Jordan was one of the greatest all-around players in...
</Question>
<Choice>Jordan, Michael</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The movie careers of Bruce Lee, Jackie Chan, and Jet Li helped to popularize kung fu and other martial arts in North America and Europe. The term martial arts popularly refers to a large variety of fighting sports, most of which originated in East Asia. The word martial is derived from Mars, the Roman god of war, and is used to describe...
</Question>
<Choice>martial arts</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Every four years the finest athletes in the world gather in one location to compete against each other and to determine who best exemplifies the Olympic motto—Citius,Altius,Fortius—meaning “faster, higher, stronger.” This gathering, known as the Olympic Games, is the most celebrated sporting festival in the world. The games attract athletes from...
</Question>
<Choice>Olympic Games</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1913–80). The Olympic Games of 1936 were held in Berlin, Germany, under the auspices of the new Nazi regime. It was Adolf Hitler's intent to use the games to demonstrate what he believed to be the superiority of the Aryan, or white, race. This aim was seriously undermined when an African American athlete named Jesse Owens won four gold medals...
</Question>
<Choice>Owens, Jesse</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The game of polo, in which players on horseback use long mallets in their attempts to drive a ball into the opponents' goal, is one of the most thrilling sports. It was once played only by the wealthy because of the expense of maintaining stables of polo ponies. Today polo is played chiefly by army, professional, and collegiate teams.
</Question>
<Choice>polo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1919–72). “A life is not important except in the impact it has on other lives,” reads the tombstone of Jackie Robinson, the first African American athlete to play in baseball's major leagues in the 20th century. By breaking the color barrier in 1947, Robinson made great strides not only for black athletes but also for all concerned with racial...
</Question>
<Choice>Robinson, Jackie</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The skills and courage that cowboys of the Old West needed for their daily work can still be seen in a rodeo (a Spanish word that originally referred to a roundup of cattle). A rodeo is now a spectator sport in which professional cowboy showmen exhibit their skills in a series of contests. The five standard events are calf roping, bull riding...
</Question>
<Choice>rodeo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
According to legend, the sport of rugby began one afternoon in 1823 at England's Rugby School, when William Webb Ellis, playing soccer with his fellow students, picked up the ball and ran toward the goal. Though there is little historical fact to verify this story, it is true that the first rules of the game were written at the Rugby School in...
</Question>
<Choice>rugby</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1895–1948). The crowd that jammed Chicago's Wrigley Field booed when the big man with the barrel-shaped body and pipestem legs came up to bat. It was the third game of the 1932 World Series between the Chicago Cubs and the New York Yankees. The score was 4–4 in the fifth inning. Cub pitcher Charlie Root threw one strike, then another. Grinning...
</Question>
<Choice>Ruth, Babe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Dutch word schaats means stilt, as well as skate, and people who wear skates are lifted above the ground just enough to roll down the sidewalk in warm weather or glide across a frozen pond in the winter. Indoor rinks make it possible for them to roller-skate or ice-skate year-round.
</Question>
<Choice>skating</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
People of all ages in nearly every country where there is mountainous terrain enjoy the unique appeal of skiing. It is one of the few sports that enable people to move at high rates of speed without any power-producing device.
</Question>
<Choice>skiing</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Wherever there are hills packed hard with snow, children love to go sledding. Sledding, or coasting, is a favorite winter sport. For thousands of years sleds have also been used to carry heavy loads of food, supplies, and people across the snow and ice. Some sleds and sleighs have runners on which they move. Others glide along on iron or wooden...
</Question>
<Choice>sledding</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The game of soccer, or association football, as it is properly called, is the world's most popular team sport. Virtually every country on Earth plays the game. It has been estimated that at the turn of the 21st century there were some 240 million soccer players around the globe and more than 1.3 billion fans. One of the reasons that soccer is so...
</Question>
<Choice>soccer</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The number one game in sports competition is marketing. There is hardly an athletic contest anywhere in the world that does not attract an audience. This means there is a demand for the particular type of entertainment offered. Where there is a demand, ways will be found by enterprising individuals and organizations to exploit it as a source of...
</Question>
<Choice>sports industry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The aspect of medical care that focuses on diet and exercise programs for athletes, monitors them as they train and compete, and helps to prevent or to treat sports-related injuries is called sports medicine. As participation in athletic sports and games increased in the 20th century, the need for special attention to sports medicine became...
</Question>
<Choice>sports medicine</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the United States—especially along the beaches of Hawaii, southern California, and the East coast—and in Australia, South Africa, and South America, surfing is a major water sport where huge breakers provide challenges for expert athletes.
</Question>
<Choice>surfing</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Unlike many animals, humans do not swim by instinct. Yet they can learn to swim better than almost any land animal. They need only master the proper strokes and ways of breathing.
</Question>
<Choice>swimming</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first book of rules for the game of tennis, entitled Sphairistikè, or Lawn Tennis, was published by Maj. Walter Clopton Wingfield in 1873. The retired British cavalryman enjoyed garden-party games as well as old-school sports, but at heart he was a salesman and a promoter. He soon patented a “new and improved portable court” for his outdoor...
</Question>
<Choice>tennis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1888–1953). Was he wronged, or was he simply wrong? The issue arose after Jim Thorpe achieved the unprecedented feat of winning gold medals in both the pentathlon and the decathlon in the 1912 Olympic Games in Stockholm, Sweden. It was discovered that he had played semiprofessional baseball in the summers of 1909 and 1910. He was stripped of...
</Question>
<Choice>Thorpe, Jim</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A multifaceted sport, track and field includes a wide variety of walking, running, jumping, and throwing events. Both men and women participate, but the events for men and women are somewhat different. Women, for example, do not take part in the two-day, ten-event sport called the decathlon. Instead, they compete in the heptathlon, a two-day...
</Question>
<Choice>track and field</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A sports activity that may have any of several objectives, weight lifting may be done competitively as a test of strength or as bodybuilding to increase muscle mass and definition. Many people also engage in weight lifting as part of an exercise regimen using it to build strength and stamina or as a part of physical therapy to speed recovery...
</Question>
<Choice>weight lifting</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(born 1975). Tiger Woods stunned the golfing world by winning three consecutive United States Amateur golf titles and two professional tournaments by the age of 20. By the age of 28 he had achieved worldwide fame by winning eight major championship titles and a total of 39 Professional Golfers' Association (PGA) tournaments—an accomplishment...
</Question>
<Choice>Woods, Tiger</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the first sports a child is likely to try is wrestling. Even very young children seem to enjoy pitting their growing strength against that of others of their own size. In addition to being an exciting sport, wrestling is excellent exercise. It brings into play all the muscles from head to toe. Because wrestling depends on physical rather...
</Question>
<Choice>wrestling</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1911–56). The outstanding American woman athlete of the 20th century was Babe Didrikson Zaharias. She performed in basketball, track and field, and golf. She turned to golf as a form of relaxation in 1932, but in a few years she became the United States' leading woman golfer.
</Question>
<Choice>Zaharias, Babe Didrikson</Choice>
</item>
</topics>