<topics> 
<Chapter>Theater</Chapter>
<item>
<Question>
Of medieval origin, the Passion play is a religious drama dealing with the suffering, death, and Resurrection of Christ. Early Passion plays were performed in Latin and consisted of readings from the Gospel with interpolated poetical sections on the events of Christ's Passion and related subjects, such as the Last Supper and the lament of the...
</Question>
<Choice>Passion play</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Italian theatrical form known as commedia dell'arte (comedy of art) flourished throughout Europe from the 16th through the 18th century. Outside Italy, the form had its greatest success in France, where it became the Comédie-Italienne. In England, elements from it were naturalized in the harlequinade in pantomime and in the Punch-and-Judy show...
</Question>
<Choice>commedia dell'arte</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the Roman Catholic church the celebration of the mass and special services for festivals have many dramatic elements. In the Middle Ages these services were made more popular and more instructive by the use of living pictures, or tableaux, such as the representation of the Christ child in the manger surrounded by the Wise Men. It was a natural...
</Question>
<Choice>miracle play</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(484?–406 BC). In 405 BC the comic dramatist Aristophanes staged his play ‘The Frogs'. It was based on the idea that Athens no longer had a great tragic poet. It was true. Euripides had died in 406. Along with Aeschylus and Sophocles, Euripides was one of the three great tragic poets of ancient Greece. Of his life very little is known. He was...
</Question>
<Choice>Euripides</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(496?–406 BC). The second of the three great Greek writers of tragic drama during the 5th century BC was Sophocles. Of the other two, Aeschylus preceded him, and Euripides was his successor. Sophocles is believed to have written 123 dramas, but only seven have survived. The best known is ‘Oedipus Rex' (or, Oedipus the King). The others are...
</Question>
<Choice>Sophocles</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(525–456 BC). The first great tragic dramatist of Greece was Aeschylus. His plays focused on the conflicting concerns of political leaders for their people and for themselves.
</Question>
<Choice>Aeschylus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A circus offers fun and excitement to every member of the family—young and old. Here, in acts old yet ever new, human skill and daring combine with performing animals and frolicking clowns to thrill and amuse the audience. Before a circus audience, elephants stand on their heads. Horses drill like soldiers. Bears ride bicycles, and lions and...
</Question>
<Choice>circus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Western theater, a melodrama is a sentimental drama with an improbable plot that concerns the difficulties suffered by the virtuous at the hands of the villainous but ends happily with virtue triumphant. Featuring stock characters such as the noble hero, the long-suffering heroine, and the cold-blooded villain, the melodrama focuses not on...
</Question>
<Choice>melodrama</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
To tell a story effectively without words is a difficult task. One performer who excels in this type of storytelling is the mime. Mime, or pantomime, is the art of narration and expression through body movement. To the Romans the word mime referred to simply performed, comic plays, while pantomime had serious themes and employed masks to identify...
</Question>
<Choice>mime and pantomime</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A live theatrical production, a musical typically offers a simple but entertaining plot with spoken dialogue interspersed with music, song, and dance. It is also called musical comedy or musical theater.
</Question>
<Choice>musical comedy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Imagine a person with all the desires and fears, thoughts and actions that make a man or a woman. Acting is becoming that imaginary person. Whether the character, or role, that the actor creates is based on someone who really lived, a playwright's concept, or a legendary being, that creation comes to life through the art of acting. Acting is an...
</Question>
<Choice>acting</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A play's opening night or a movie premiere is the culmination of work by many people, from actors and playwrights to lighting and costume designers. Directing is the management of that technical and creative joint effort.
</Question>
<Choice>directing</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Drama comes from Greek words meaning “to do” or “to act.” A drama, or play, is basically a story acted out. And every play—whether it is serious or humorous, ancient or modern—tells its story through characters in situations that imitate human life. In a theater, under the spell of a fascinating play, we may forget ourselves for awhile and enter...
</Question>
<Choice>drama</Choice>
</item>
</topics>