<topics>
<item>
<Question>
Situated on the north coast of Africa, Algeria is the second largest country of the continent. It covers more than 900,000 square miles (2,300,000 square kilometers), about four fifths of which is in the Sahara Desert. The country's Mediterranean coastline extends about 620 miles (1,000 kilometers). Algeria is bordered by Tunisia, Libya, Niger...
</Question>
<Choice>Algeria</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
After almost 500 years of Portuguese rule, Angola became an independent country in 1975. The seventh largest country in Africa, Angola has an area of 481,354 square miles (1,246,700 square kilometers). It lies on the southwestern coast of the continent, bordered to the west by the Atlantic Ocean, to the far northwest by the Republic of the Congo...
</Question>
<Choice>Angola</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The ancient and powerful western African kingdom of Dahomey became a colony of France in the 1800s. In the 1900s it made the transition into a self-governing republic, then a Marxist-Leninist state, and then a free democracy—all within less than a century. Now called the Republic of Benin, it occupies a strategic political and commercial position...
</Question>
<Choice>Benin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The landlocked Republic of Botswana is bounded on the northeast by Zimbabwe, on the south and southeast by South Africa, and on the west and north by Namibia. In the north Botswana also shares a short border with Zambia.
</Question>
<Choice>Botswana</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the poorest of the African nations, Burkina Faso is a landlocked country in the southern part of Africa's great bulge. Formerly known as Upper Volta, it was affiliated economically with France, which ruled it for more than 60 years. The country's capital and largest city is Ouagadougou (see Ouagadougou, Burkina Faso).
</Question>
<Choice>Burkina Faso</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A landlocked country of Central Africa, the Republic of Burundi has an area of 10,740 square miles (27,816 square kilometers). It is bordered by Rwanda on the north, the Democratic Republic of the Congo on the west, and Tanzania on the south and east.
</Question>
<Choice>Burundi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At the junction of West and Central Africa lies Cameroon, a country with more than 200 ethnic groups and a varied landscape of mountains, rainforests, and savanna. Its name comes from Rio dos Camarões (River of Prawns), the name given to the Wouri River in the southwest by Portuguese explorers of the 15th and 16th centuries. In the late 19th...
</Question>
<Choice>Cameroon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An archipelago, or group of islands, in the Atlantic Ocean, the republic of Cape Verde is 385 miles (620 kilometers) off the western coast of Africa. There are ten islands and five rocky islets divided into the Barlavento, or Windward, and Sotavento, or Leeward, groups. The archipelago has a total land area of 1,557 square miles (4,033 square...
</Question>
<Choice>Cape Verde</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Landlocked and remote, the Central African Republic is one of Africa's least modernized countries, though its economic potential is great. The country's development has been limited in part by the fact that for most of its history as an independent country it has been burdened by political instability. The capital of the Central African Republic...
</Question>
<Choice>Central African Republic</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Republic of Chad in west-central Africa is large but landlocked. For much of its history Chad has been plagued by droughts, food shortages, civil unrest, and invasion threats. Economic development of the country has been slow, and as a result, Chad is largely dependent on foreign aid and imports of food, fuel, and other supplies. The capital...
</Question>
<Choice>Chad</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Union of the Comoros is made up of a group of islands at the northern end of the Mozambique Channel between Madagascar and the eastern coast of the African mainland. The total land area, excluding the island of Mayotte, is about 719 square miles (1,862 square kilometers). The capital, on Grande Comore, is Moroni; its urban area has a...
</Question>
<Choice>Comoros</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Republic of the Congo (Congo-Brazzaville), usually simply called Congo, a small African nation lying west of the Democratic Republic of the Congo (Congo-Kinshasa)—the country formerly known as Zaire, east of Gabon, and south of Cameroon and the Central African Republic in equatorial Africa. The country has a short but important coastline on...
</Question>
<Choice>Congo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
With the defeat of Zairean government forces and the departure of President Mobutu Sese Seko in the spring of 1997, the victorious rebel leader Laurent Kabila renamed Zaire the Democratic Republic of the Congo. International diplomats began referring to the nation as Congo-Kinshasa, using the name of its capital to distinguish it from the...
</Question>
<Choice>Congo, Democratic Republic of the</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The name of Côte d'Ivoire (Ivory Coast) comes from the thriving trade in elephant tusks, or ivory, that attracted European adventurers to the area in the 17th century. Located on the southern shore of West Africa's bulge, the Republic of Côte d'Ivoire covers an area of 123,863 square miles (320,803 square kilometers). It is bounded on the north...
</Question>
<Choice>Côte d'Ivoire</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A small country in the Horn of Africa, Djibouti faces the Strait of Mandeb that links the Red Sea to the Gulf of Aden. Previously a French possession called Afars and Issas, the country has been the Republic of Djibouti since 1977. Djibouti covers an area of 8,950 square miles (23,200 square kilometers), and has a coastline, deeply indented by...
</Question>
<Choice>Djibouti</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Arab Republic of Egypt occupies the northeastern corner of the African continent and the Sinai Peninsula. It has an area of about 385,200 square miles (997,700 square kilometers), including the 23,400 square miles (60,700 square kilometers) of the Sinai. Ninety-nine percent of the Egyptian population lives on only 3.5 percent of the land...
</Question>
<Choice>Egypt</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A republic on the west coast of Africa, Equatorial Guinea includes an area on the mainland called Río Muni (or Mbini) and five islands: Bioko, Corisco, Great Elobey, Little Elobey, and Annobón. The total land area is 10,831 square miles (28,052 square kilometers). Río Muni is bordered on the north by Cameroon and on the east and south by Gabon...
</Question>
<Choice>Equatorial Guinea</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In 1993 the northern part of Ethiopia became the new nation of Eritrea. Its name comes from the Latin words Mare Erythraeum, meaning “Red Sea.”
</Question>
<Choice>Eritrea</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the largest and most populous countries in Africa and one of the oldest countries in the world is Ethiopia. It is located in northeastern Africa, in an area known as the Horn of Africa (see Horn of Africa). Although it has been influenced and sometimes occupied by other nations throughout its history, Ethiopia is one of the few countries...
</Question>
<Choice>Ethiopia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The nation of Gabon straddles the equator on the west coast of Africa. It covers an area of 103,347 square miles (267,668 square kilometers). It is bordered by Equatorial Guinea and Cameroon to the north, Congo to the south and east, and the Atlantic Ocean to the west. Libreville, the capital city, has a population of about 660,000 and is located...
</Question>
<Choice>Gabon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The long, narrow shape of The Gambia is the result of a long colonial rivalry between France and Great Britain. During the 19th century, both nations struggled to control a large section of territory at the western bulge of the African continent. In the late 1890s, the French incorporated the territory that would become Senegal into French West...
</Question>
<Choice>Gambia, The</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On March 6, 1957, Britain's Colony of the Gold Coast became the independent nation of Ghana. It was the first colony in sub-Saharan Africa to gain independence, and it became the model for others to follow. Ghana was named for a powerful African empire that flourished along the upper Niger River from the 4th to the 13th century.
</Question>
<Choice>Ghana</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Until it became independent in 1958, the Republic of Guinea was the overseas territory of French Guinea in the Federation of French West Africa. It lies north of the equator on the Atlantic coast of West Africa. Guinea has 200 miles (320 kilometers) of coastline between Guinea-Bissau and Sierra Leone. It is also bordered by Senegal, Mali, Côte d...
</Question>
<Choice>Guinea</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
When the former colony of Portuguese Guinea won its independence in 1974 after more than 10 years of warfare, it became the Republic of Guinea-Bissau. It is a small West African nation covering an area of 13,948 square miles (36,125 square kilometers). The Bijagós Archipelago, lying off the coast to the southwest, forms part of the country. Guinea...
</Question>
<Choice>Guinea-Bissau</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A republic of Africa, Kenya is located on the equator on the continent's east coast. Kenya covers an area of 224,961 square miles (582,646 square kilometers). It is bordered on the north by Ethiopia and The Sudan, on the west by Uganda and Lake Victoria, on the south by Tanzania, and on the east by the Indian Ocean and Somalia. The capital of...
</Question>
<Choice>Kenya</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The small southern African kingdom of Lesotho is completely surrounded by the Republic of South Africa, though separated from it by formidable mountains. For many years after gaining their independence in 1966, the people of this former British protectorate suffered from political turbulence, economic crises, and a growing incidence of HIV/AIDS...
</Question>
<Choice>Lesotho</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A small country on the west coast of Africa, Liberia has been influenced in many ways by the United States. This influence has its origins in the efforts of the American Colonization Society to settle freed American slaves in Africa beginning in 1822. The government was modeled on that of the United States, and Monrovia, the capital and principal...
</Question>
<Choice>Liberia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The petroleum-rich country of Libya lies in northern Africa along the southern coast of the Mediterranean Sea. Libya blends its role as one of the world's most important producers of petroleum with a traditional Arab society based on the Islamic religion. In Tripoli, the capital and the largest city, nomadic herders mingle with construction...
</Question>
<Choice>Libya</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The fourth largest island in the world, Madagascar is located off the southeastern coast of Africa in the Indian Ocean. The island covers an area of 226,658 square miles (587,041 square kilometers), and is separated from the African coast by the Mozambique Channel. With a coastline of about 2,480 miles (3,990 kilometers), Madagascar is 980 miles...
</Question>
<Choice>Madagascar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A landlocked country in Southern Africa, Malawi was known as Nyasaland until 1964. Long and narrow in shape, it covers an area of 45,747 square miles (118,484 square kilometers). More than 520 miles (830 kilometers) long and up to 100 miles (160 kilometers) wide, it extends along the western shore of Lake Nyasa (which is also known as Lake Malawi...
</Question>
<Choice>Malawi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A landlocked country in northwestern Africa, Mali covers an area of 482,077 square miles (1,248,574 square kilometers). It is bordered by Senegal and Mauritania on the west, Algeria on the northeast, Niger on the east, Burkina Faso on the southeast, and Côte d'Ivoire and Guinea on the south. The legendary city of Timbuktu, long regarded as...
</Question>
<Choice>Mali</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Named by the French after a province of the Roman Empire, the Islamic Republic of Mauritania is located in northwestern Africa. Covering an area of 398,000 square miles (1,030,700 square kilometers), it is bordered by the Atlantic Ocean to the west, Western Sahara to the northwest, Algeria to the northeast, Mali to the east and south, and Senegal...
</Question>
<Choice>Mauritania</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The island country of Mauritius comprises Mauritius and Rodrigues islands and two small groups of islands. Located in the Indian Ocean 500 miles (800 kilometers) east of Madagascar, it covers a total area of 788 square miles (2,040 square kilometers). Port Louis, the capital and major port, has a population of about 144,000.
</Question>
<Choice>Mauritius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Kingdom of Morocco is located at the western end of North Africa. Known to the Arabs as al-Maghreb al-Aqsa, or “the farthest west,” it was the center of Berber Islamic kingdoms that once included much of Spain and North Africa. France established a protectorate over Morocco in 1912 and granted independence in 1956. Morocco has a 1,140-mile...
</Question>
<Choice>Morocco</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Located on Africa's southeastern coast, Mozambique is a former Portuguese colony that gained independence in 1975. It is bordered by Tanzania on the north and by Malawi, Zambia, Zimbabwe, Swaziland, and South Africa on the west. Mozambique's transport system is the key to transportation independence from South Africa for Botswana, Malawi, Zambia...
</Question>
<Choice>Mozambique</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Situated on the southwestern coast of Africa, Namibia was long known as South West Africa. It was controlled by the government of South Africa from 1916 until it became a fully independent nation in 1990. Namibia occupies an area of 318,580 square miles (825,118 square kilometers). Straddling the Tropic of Capricorn, the country is bordered by...
</Question>
<Choice>Namibia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Republic of Niger is a large landlocked West African country that was part of French West Africa prior to its independence in 1960. It is bordered on the north by Algeria and Libya, on the east by Chad, on the south by Nigeria, on the southwest by Benin and Burkina Faso, and on the west by Mali. The capital of Niger is Niamey.
</Question>
<Choice>Niger</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The most populous and one of the most politically significant countries in Africa is Nigeria. It is a place rich in diversity. This is evidenced by its many ethnic cultures, its art and music, and its history, as well as by its physical features. The country lies on the southern coast of western Africa. It is bordered on the north by Niger and on...
</Question>
<Choice>Nigeria</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A landlocked, mountainous country in east-central Africa, the Republic of Rwanda lies south of the Equator. It is one of Africa's smallest countries, covering an area of only 10,169 square miles (26,338 square kilometers). Most of the country lies at an elevation of more than 5,000 feet (1,500 meters) above sea level. Rwanda is bordered by the...
</Question>
<Choice>Rwanda</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The island republic of São Tomé and Príncipe is located on the equator in the part of the Gulf of Guinea known as the Bight of Biafra. Consisting of two main islands—São Tomé and Príncipe—and several small islets, the republic covers an area of 386 square miles (1,001 square kilometers), of which São Tomé occupies 332 square miles (859 square...
</Question>
<Choice>São Tomé and Príncipe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the most economically advanced countries of French-speaking West Africa, Senegal is the westernmost republic of the great bulge of Africa. Its Cape Verde peninsula is the westernmost point of the African continent. Covering an area of 75,955 square miles (196,723 square kilometers), it is bounded by the Atlantic Ocean on the west...
</Question>
<Choice>Senegal</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Republic of Seychelles, comprising a scattered archipelago of about 110 islands, is situated north of Madagascar in the western Indian Ocean. The islands cover an area of 176 square miles (455 square kilometers). The capital and only port is Victoria, on Mahé Island. Located just south of the equator, Seychelles is composed of two main island...
</Question>
<Choice>Seychelles</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On the southwestern coast of the bulge of West Africa, Sierra Leone lies less than 10° from the Equator. Facing the Atlantic Ocean to the west, it is bounded by Guinea to the north and east and Liberia to the southeast. It extends over an area of 27,699 square miles (71,740 square kilometers) and has a coastline of nearly 210 miles (340 kilometers...
</Question>
<Choice>Sierra Leone</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Somali Democratic Republic is located in the Horn of Africa, the easternmost part of the African continent. It is one of the world's desperately poor countries and, beginning in the late 20th century, was beset by civil war and anarchy. As warring factions contended for power, most of the economy collapsed.
</Question>
<Choice>Somalia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the late 20th century South Africa began a tremendous transformation. From about 1950 until 1994 the country's large and diverse nonwhite population was legally dominated by the white minority in nearly every sphere of life. South Africa had an institutionalized policy of racial segregation and economic and political discrimination against its...
</Question>
<Choice>South Africa</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Covering 966,757 square miles (2,503,890 square kilometers), the Republic of the Sudan is the largest country in Africa. The Sudan is located in the northeastern part of the continent, where it has many neighbors. It is bordered by Egypt on the north and Libya on the northwest. Chad lies along the western border and the Central African Republic...
</Question>
<Choice>Sudan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Located in southeastern Africa, the kingdom of Swaziland is one of the smallest countries on that continent. The landlocked nation is surrounded by South Africa, except for its eastern border with Mozambique. Oval in shape, it covers an area of 6,704 square miles (17,364 square kilometers). The administrative and judicial capital is Mbabane, the...
</Question>
<Choice>Swaziland</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The United Republic of Tanzania is located on the East African coast of the Indian Ocean. It incorporates mainland Tanganyika and the islands of Zanzibar and Pemba as well as half of Lakes Victoria and Tanganyika. Formerly a German colony, then a League of Nations mandate and United Nations Trust Territory administered by the United Kingdom...
</Question>
<Choice>Tanzania</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Situated north of the Equator in Africa's great western bulge is the Republic of Togo. Before attaining independence in 1960, the land that is now Togo was known as French Togoland, a territory that was administered by France from 1922 to 1946 under a League of Nations mandate and from 1946 to 1960 under a United Nations trusteeship. Togo became...
</Question>
<Choice>Togo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The smallest North African country, Tunisia is located at the eastern end of the Maghreb (the northern tip of Africa), forming a wedge of territory between Algeria and Libya. Tunisia was the site of ancient Carthage and, as the province of Ifriqiyah, or Africa Minor, was a keystone of Arab and Turkish empires in North Africa. France established a...
</Question>
<Choice>Tunisia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A republic of East Africa and a member of the Commonwealth since independence in 1962, Uganda has been forced to cope with internal rivalries between its traditional kingdoms and tribes. It has suffered under frequent changes of leadership, a brutal dictatorship, invasion by Tanzania, and civil war—all of which have prevented economic growth. The...
</Question>
<Choice>Uganda</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Republic of Zambia is a landlocked country located in southern Africa on the high plateau. The Democratic Republic of the Congo borders it on the north; Tanzania on the northeast; Malawi on the east; Mozambique, Zimbabwe, a tip of Botswana, and Namibia on the south; and Angola on the west. From 1911 to 1964 the country was known as Northern...
</Question>
<Choice>Zambia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Republic of Zimbabwe is located on the high plateau of southern Africa. The terrain is rugged and even formidable at the country's borders. This landlocked country is bounded on the north by the Zambezi River and Zambia and on the south by the Limpopo River and South Africa. Both areas are hot and humid with scattered forests and bush, and...
</Question>
<Choice>Zimbabwe</Choice>
</item>

<item>
<Question>
There are more than 50 independent countries in Africa and on the islands off its coasts. Together, they make up more than one fourth of the membership of the United Nations. In 1991 Egyptian Deputy Prime Minister Boutros Boutros-Ghali became the first African and the first Arab to serve as secretary-general of the United Nations. In 1997 Kofi...
</Question>
<Choice>Africa</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital and largest city of Côte d'Ivoire (Ivory Coast), Abidjan has the unusual feature of being a major trading port that is located on a lagoon rather than on the sea. Separated from the Gulf of Guinea and the Atlantic Ocean by the Vridi-Plage sandbar, this deepwater port was opened to the sea in 1950 by the Vridi Canal. The city quickly...
</Question>
<Choice>Abidjan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On Dec. 12, 1991, the city of Abuja became the new capital of Nigeria. President Ibrahim Babangida officially took up residence in the new presidential palace on that day. While the new city was in process of completion, many of the government offices remained in Lagos, the former capital—and many government workers were very reluctant to leave...
</Question>
<Choice>Abuja</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Located on the Gulf of Guinea, Accra is the capital and largest city of Ghana. It is a blend of modern and traditional West African customs and architecture.
</Question>
<Choice>Accra</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The highest city in Africa, Addis Ababa is located at 8,000 feet (2,450 meters) above sea level. It is the capital and economic center of Ethiopia. The city lies on a well-watered plateau at the country's geographic center and has grown haphazardly among more than 90 square miles (230 square kilometers) of forested hills and valleys. Modern Addis...
</Question>
<Choice>Addis Ababa</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital of Algeria, Algiers is located between the Mediterranean Sea and the Sahara. It lies on the Bay of Algiers and extends along the slopes of the Sahel Hills. Algiers has a distinctly seasonal climate of cool, wet winters and hot, dry summers.
</Question>
<Choice>Algiers</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Formerly called Tananarive, the high, inland city of Antananarivo is the capital of Madagascar, the world's fourth largest island. The country is located in the Indian Ocean nearly 200 miles (325 kilometers) off the southeastern coast of Africa.
</Question>
<Choice>Antananarivo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The bustling capital of Mali, the city of Bamako is located on the Niger River in West Africa. Bamako lies along both sides of the Niger, which is navigable from mid-June to mid-December for 225 miles (360 kilometers) southwest to Kouroussa, Guinea. Cement and petroleum products are shipped downstream from Bamako, with rice and peanuts coming...
</Question>
<Choice>Bamako</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Located on the west bank of the Ubangi River, Bangui is the capital and largest urban area of the Central African Republic. Founded as a French military and defense post in 1889, it became the capital of the Ubangui-Shari territory in 1914.
</Question>
<Choice>Bangui</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The port of Banjul is the capital and largest city of The Gambia, a republic in West Africa. Banjul is connected with the interior of the country and with neighboring Senegal by a 3-mile (5-kilometer) ferry ride northward across the Gambia River and by a road that joins the Trans-Gambia Highway. There is regular steamer service from Banjul, and...
</Question>
<Choice>Banjul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The former capital of French Equatorial Africa, Brazzaville is now the capital and chief river port of the Republic of the Congo. It lies on the north bank of the Congo River below Stanley Pool, a lakelike expansion of the river. Kinshasa, Democratic Republic of the Congo (formerly Zaire), is on the opposite riverbank.
</Question>
<Choice>Brazzaville</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The largest city in Africa is Cairo, which is the capital of Egypt. It has stood for more than 1,000 years on the same site on the banks of the Nile River near the head of the many-channeled delta. The city spreads eastward from the Nile to the low Mokattam Hills, which separate it from the brown wastes of the desert.
</Question>
<Choice>Cairo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
As the home of South Africa's Parliament, Cape Town is the country's de facto legislative capital. It is one of the largest cities in South Africa, a major seaport, and the capital of Western Cape Province. Cape Town lies at the northern end of the Cape Peninsula about 30 miles (50 kilometers) north of the Cape of Good Hope. It is located at the...
</Question>
<Choice>Cape Town</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital and largest city of the nation of Guinea is Conakry. The main part of the city is located on the Atlantic island of Tombo, which is connected by a causeway to the mainland of the African continent.
</Question>
<Choice>Conakry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Senegal's capital and largest city, Dakar is a major regional center of industry and services for tropical Africa. It lies on the Cape Verde peninsula, near the continent's westernmost point. Dakar's location and fine, naturally sheltered harbor have helped it become one of the principal ports of the western African coast.
</Question>
<Choice>Dakar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The headquarters of Dar es Salaam region, the port city of Dar es Salaam is also Tanzania's largest city and industrial center. Located on the Indian Ocean, Dar es Salaam is hot and humid with an annual rainfall of 43 inches (109 centimeters).
</Question>
<Choice>Dar es Salaam</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital, chief port, and largest city of the West African country of Sierra Leone is Freetown. The city lies on the rocky Sierra Leone Peninsula at the seaward tip of a range of wooded hills. It was originally settled by freed and escaped slaves in the late 18th century. During World War II, Freetown's excellent natural Atlantic Ocean harbor...
</Question>
<Choice>Freetown</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital and largest city of Zimbabwe is Harare. It was formerly known as Salisbury. At an altitude of 4,865 feet (1,483 meters), Harare has a pleasant climate with annual average temperatures of 64°?F (18°?C) and 30 inches (76 centimeters) of rainfall. It is located in the northeastern part of the country and is a modern, well-planned city...
</Question>
<Choice>Harare</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital and largest city of Uganda in East Africa, Kampala lies on a series of hills in the Central Province. It is the hub of the nation's road network and is served by the railway that connects Kasese to the west with Mombasa, Kenya, on Africa's east coast. The international airport is at Entebbe, 21 miles (34 kilometers) southwest. Port...
</Question>
<Choice>Kampala</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital city of the Sudan, the largest African nation, is Khartoum, a name that means “elephant's trunk.” Khartoum lies just south of the junction of the Blue Nile and the White Nile rivers (see Nile River). The city has bridge connections with its sister towns, which are Khartoum North and Omdurman. As the country's seat of government and...
</Question>
<Choice>Khartoum</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital of the Democratic Republic of the Congo (formerly Zaire) is Kinshasa, one of the largest cities in Africa south of the Sahara. The city, formerly called Léopoldville, is in the western part of the country. It spreads out from the south bank of the Congo (Zaire) River at a widening of the river known as Malebo Pool. Across the river is...
</Question>
<Choice>Kinshasa</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Capital of Angola, Luanda is the country's largest city and second busiest seaport. Founded by the Portuguese in 1576, it became the administrative center of the colony of Angola in 1627 and was a major outlet for slave traffic to Brazil.
</Question>
<Choice>Luanda</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital city of Zambia, Lusaka is located on a limestone plateau 4,198 feet (1,280 meters) above sea level. It lies at the junction of the Great North Road, which runs to Tanzania, and the Great East Road, which goes to Malawi. Lusaka has rail connections to the towns of Livingstone and Ndola and also to Tanzania.
</Question>
<Choice>Lusaka</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital of Equatorial Guinea, Malabo is also the financial center of the republic. The city is located on the northern edge of Bioko Island 21 miles (34 kilometers) off the coast of Cameroon in the Gulf of Guinea. The island is volcanic in origin and is mountainous. The annual average temperature is 77°?F (25°?C), and the annual average...
</Question>
<Choice>Malabo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital and most populous city of Mozambique, Maputo also serves as a chief port of southeastern Africa. The city is located on Delagoa Bay, an inlet of the Indian Ocean, in southeastern Mozambique. Before Mozambique became independent from Portugal in 1975, the city (then named Lourenço Marques) was the capital of Portuguese East Africa.
</Question>
<Choice>Maputo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital and largest city of Somalia, Mogadishu is a major East African port. It is on the Indian Ocean just north of the equator.
</Question>
<Choice>Mogadishu</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital and largest city of Liberia, Monrovia is also the country's chief port, located at the mouth of the Mesurado River on the Atlantic coast. The port and industrial area are on Bushrod Island, which is linked by bridge to the rest of Monrovia. The free port was completed in 1948.
</Question>
<Choice>Monrovia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital of Kenya, Nairobi is on the Athi Plains of East Africa. It is the industrial center of the country, with the railway serving as the largest single industrial employer. Manufactured products include beverages, cigarettes, and processed food. The city is near the major East African farmlands, and many agricultural products are shipped...
</Question>
<Choice>Nairobi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital and cultural hub of Niger in West Africa, Niamey is located in the southwestern corner of the republic on the banks of Africa's third longest river, the Niger. The city lies mainly on the river's north bank but has expanded onto the south bank since the construction of the Kennedy Bridge in 1970.
</Question>
<Choice>Niamey</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital of Burkina Faso, Ouagadougou (also spelled Wagadugu) is the country's largest city. It has a large market, a major crafts center, and a prestigious national museum. Its major industries include textiles, carbonated beverages, matches, and footwear. It is the seat of the University of Ouagadougou, which was established in 1969. The...
</Question>
<Choice>Ouagadougou</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the largest cities of South Africa, Pretoria is also the administrative capital of the country. The city is spread along both sides of the Apies River in the foothills of the Magaliesberg Range. Church Square, in the center of the city, is surrounded by government buildings, including the Palace of Justice and the Raadzaal, or Council...
</Question>
<Choice>Pretoria</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital of Morocco, modern Rabat is a planned city of wide boulevards and handsome public buildings and gardens. The Moroccan king lives in his palace there for part of the year. Rabat is situated on the Atlantic coastal plain at the mouth of the river Bou Regreg. A highway and a railroad connect the city with Casablanca about 60 miles...
</Question>
<Choice>Rabat</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital and largest town in the two-island democratic republic of São Tomé and Príncipe is the city of São Tomé. It is located on the equator in the part of the Gulf of Guinea known as the Bight of Biafra. The town was founded by Portuguese merchants around 1493. Today, it is a distribution center for cacao, coconut and oil palms, coffee...
</Question>
<Choice>São Tomé</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital and largest city of Libya is Tripoli. The name is from the Greek and means “three cities.” In about the 7th century BC the Phoenicians founded their colony of Carthage and built three cities in this region of North Africa: Oea (now Tripoli), Leptis Magna, and Sabratah. In Roman times the area was called Tripolitania. During invasions...
</Question>
<Choice>Tripoli</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital and largest city of Tunisia, Tunis is located near the Mediterranean coast a few miles southwest of the ancient site of Carthage. There was a settlement at Tunis in the Carthaginian era, but it did not become prominent until the Muslim conquest of the 7th century AD, after which it became a provincial capital.
</Question>
<Choice>Tunis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital and commercial center of the Republic of Namibia is the centrally located city of Windhoek. Situated between the vast inland Kalahari Desert and the coastal Namib Desert, the city is some 175 miles (282 kilometers) east of the Atlantic Ocean. A ring of hills surrounds Windhoek. The city lies about 5,428 feet (1,654 meters) above sea...
</Question>
<Choice>Windhoek</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Once a small, remote village, Yamoussoukro, Côte d'Ivoire, was transformed into an extravagantly planned town in a remarkably short time. In 1983 it was chosen to be the capital of the country by Félix Houphouët-Boigny, who was president from 1960 to 1993. Yamoussoukro was his birthplace, and he was largely responsible for modernizing it with...
</Question>
<Choice>Yamoussoukro</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital of Cameroon and also the capital of Center Province, Yaoundé is an administrative, service, and commercial city as well as a communications center for road, rail, and air transport. It is situated on a hilly, forested plateau between the Nyong and Sanaga rivers, in the south-central part of the country.
</Question>
<Choice>Yaoundé</Choice>
</item>
</topics>