<topics>
<item>
<Question>
The mountainous country of Afghanistan lies in south-central Asia. It is bordered by Turkmenistan, Uzbekistan, Tajikistan, Iran, and Pakistan. A panhandle on the northeast, the Wakhan Corridor, connects it with China. Its southernmost part is separated from the nearest sea, the Arabian Sea, by 300 miles (480 kilometers) of Pakistani territory.
</Question>
<Choice>Afghanistan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the world's oldest centers of civilization and once the smallest republic of the Soviet Union, Armenia is an independent republic in the Caucasus Mountains.
</Question>
<Choice>Armenia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On the Caspian Sea at the eastern end of the Caucasus mountains is Azerbaijan, one of the 15 republics that made up the Soviet Union until that country was dissolved and the republics gained their independence in December 1991. Azerbaijan is bordered by Russia and Georgia to the north, the Caspian Sea to the east, Armenia to the west, and Iran to...
</Question>
<Choice>Azerbaijan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the world's most densely populated nations, Bangladesh is also one of the poorest. More than 140 million people live within this South Asian country's total area of 56,977 square miles (147,570 square kilometers). This amounts to an average of almost 2,650 persons per square mile (about 1,023 persons per square kilometer). Nearly half of...
</Question>
<Choice>Bangladesh</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The small country of Bhutan lies along the lofty ridges of the eastern Himalayas in south-central Asia. It is landlocked between India, on the east, south, and west, and the Tibet Autonomous Region of China, to the north—a location that gives it considerable geopolitical significance. It was long isolated from the mainstream of world affairs by...
</Question>
<Choice>Bhutan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A small Islamic sultanate, Brunei is one of the few remaining countries in the world without personal income tax. Located on the northwestern coast of the island of Borneo, it was a powerful state in the 16th century, with authority over the whole island.
</Question>
<Choice>Brunei</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the southwestern part of the Indochinese peninsula of Southeast Asia lies the country of Cambodia. Modern Cambodia is a remnant of the powerful Khmer Empire, which at its height from the 11th to the 13th century ruled much of what is now Vietnam, Laos, and Thailand. In more recent times Cambodia has endured great turmoil—French colonization...
</Question>
<Choice>Cambodia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Perceptions of China, a country in East Asia, must be adjusted to its enormous scale. Its culture and its civilization go back thousands of years. Its vast area of more than 3,690,000 square miles (9,560,000 square kilometers) is the third largest in the world, after Russia and Canada. With a population of more than 1.3 billion, it is Earth's...
</Question>
<Choice>China</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
South of the main ridge of the Caucasus, between the Caspian and Black seas, is the republic of Georgia. The country and its people have a rich heritage; during the 12th century, Georgia formed the center of an empire that stretched across the Caucasus. Between 1921 and 1991 Georgia was part of the Soviet Union, and it was the birthplace of...
</Question>
<Choice>Georgia, Republic of</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
About one sixth of all the human beings on Earth live in India, the world's most populous democracy. It is the second most populous country in the world, after China. India's borders encompass a vast variety of peoples, practicing most of the world's major religions and speaking scores of different languages. A civilized, urban society has...
</Question>
<Choice>India</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The largest country in Southeast Asia, both in area and population, is the Republic of Indonesia. It consists of some 13,670 islands that cover 730,024 square miles (1,890,754 square kilometers) of land along the Equator between the Indian and Pacific oceans. With a population of more than 220 million, it ranks as the world's fourth most populous...
</Question>
<Choice>Indonesia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The leading industrial state of eastern Asia and of the non-Western world, Japan rivals the most advanced economic powers of the West. It rose rapidly from a crushing military defeat in World War II to achieve the fastest-growing economy of any major country in the postwar period. Today only the United States outproduces it, although the...
</Question>
<Choice>Japan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The native Kazakhs are a Muslim people who once wandered over the grasslands of Central Asia with their herds. In the 19th century the Russians invaded their territory, which eventually became the second largest republic of the Soviet Union. Even after achieving independence in 1991, Kazakhstan remained an important agricultural, mining, and...
</Question>
<Choice>Kazakhstan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On a mountainous peninsula jutting southward from the eastern Asian mainland is Korea, the historic land bridge and buffer between China and Japan. Today Korea is a land divided into a communist north and a noncommunist south. It is torn by rival political and economic systems and by bitterness stemming from the Korean War. However, the people of...
</Question>
<Choice>Korea</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Situated in the heart of Central Asia is the small independent republic of Kyrgyzstan. A nation rich in history and cultural tradition, Kyrgyzstan lies amid the formidable Tien Shan, a location that endows the country with vast stretches of unspoiled natural regions. Kyrgyzstan covers approximately 76,600 square miles (198,400 square kilometers...
</Question>
<Choice>Kyrgyzstan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Lao People's Democratic Republic, or Laos, is a landlocked country of Southeast Asia. The former kingdom lies entirely within the tropics and occupies a rugged central strip of the Indochinese peninsula, surrounded by Vietnam on the east, Cambodia on the south, Thailand on the west, Myanmar on the northwest, and China on the north. Vientiane...
</Question>
<Choice>Laos</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A nation of Southeast Asia, Malaysia consists of two components: peninsular Malaysia, which is part of mainland Southeast Asia, and the states of Sabah and Sarawak on the island of Borneo. Although there are considerable areas of lowland and coastal plain, much of the country consists of mountainous terrain clothed in dense rainforest. With the...
</Question>
<Choice>Malaysia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the world's smallest countries, Maldives is a chain of some 1,300 small coral islands in the Indian Ocean southwest of India. The islands extend more than 510 miles (820 kilometers) from north to south and 80 miles (130 kilometers) from east to west, with a total land area of 115 square miles (298 square kilometers). Only some 200 islands...
</Question>
<Choice>Maldives</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the frontier zone of East Asia between northwestern China and Siberia lies Mongolia (formerly Outer Mongolia). Mongolia shares much of its modern history with Russia, its neighbor to the north, and China, which lies to the south. In the 13th century, however, the land that is now Mongolia formed the heart of the great empire of Genghis Khan...
</Question>
<Choice>Mongolia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Union of Myanmar, known as Burma until 1989, is the land of the great Irrawaddy, or Ayeyarwady, River. Most of the country's people live in the fertile lowlands drained by the river. Myanmar is bordered by China to the north and northeast, Laos to the east, Thailand to the southeast, the Andaman Sea and the Bay of Bengal to the south and...
</Question>
<Choice>Myanmar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The small independent country of Nepal is located along the southern slopes of the Himalayan mountains. It is a landlocked country between India and the Tibet Autonomous Region of China. With an area of 56,827 square miles (147,181 square kilometers), Nepal is roughly as big as the U.S. state of Florida and about half the size of Italy. Mountains...
</Question>
<Choice>Nepal</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Established under traumatic circumstances, modern Pakistan was carved from British India—first by partition in 1947 and later by war with India in 1971. The latter established the new country of Bangladesh from what had been East Pakistan.
</Question>
<Choice>Pakistan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A country of Southeast Asia, the Republic of the Philippines consists of more than 7,000 islands and islets in the western Pacific Ocean. It lies about 500 miles (800 kilometers) off the coast of Vietnam. The capital, Manila, is located on Luzon, the largest island.
</Question>
<Choice>Philippines</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Located in Southeast Asia, the Republic of Singapore is a city-state at the southern tip of the Malay Peninsula. Known as the Lion City, densely populated Singapore Island is a modern metropolis with a fast-growing economy based on thriving manufacturing and financial sectors and one of the world's busiest ports. The country is considered one of...
</Question>
<Choice>Singapore</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Located 18 miles (29 kilometers) off the southeastern tip of the Indian subcontinent, Sri Lanka is an island nation in the Indian Ocean. It lies about 400 miles (645 kilometers) north of the Equator. Colombo is the executive capital and largest city. A suburb of Colombo, Sri Jayawardenepura Kotte was designated the new capital in 1977. It is the...
</Question>
<Choice>Sri Lanka</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Since its final retreat from the mainland of China during the last months of 1949, the government of the Republic of China, also known as Nationalist China, has been in exile on the island of Taiwan. The Nationalist government fled from the mainland of China after the Chinese communists defeated the Chinese Nationalists in a long civil war and...
</Question>
<Choice>Taiwan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Until Tajikistan declared its independence in 1991, it was a republic of the Soviet Union. Located in Central Asia, Tajikistan is bounded on the south by Afghanistan, on the east by China, on the north by Kyrgyzstan, and on the west and north by Uzbekistan. The country's name is sometimes spelled Tadzhikistan. It has an area of 55,250 square...
</Question>
<Choice>Tajikistan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Unlike all the other countries of Southeast Asia, the Kingdom of Thailand was never a colony. Thailand was long known as Siam. In 1939 the country's name was changed to Muang Thai, or Land of the Thais, a name that itself means “free.”
</Question>
<Choice>Thailand</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Although it sits on the eastern shores of the Caspian Sea, the Central Asian country Turkmenistan is essentially a landlocked state. It is bordered by Uzbekistan on the north, Kazakhstan on the northwest, Iran on the south, Afghanistan to the southeast, and the Caspian on the west. Turkmenistan is the second largest of the Central Asian countries...
</Question>
<Choice>Turkmenistan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A landlocked country at the heart of Central Asia, Uzbekistan is part of a region whose history stretches back more than 2,500 years. The country is famous for its cities, which were centers of commerce on the old Silk Road trade routes that connected China with Europe. The cities were notable also for Islamic scholarship. For much of the 20th...
</Question>
<Choice>Uzbekistan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Socialist Republic of Vietnam consists of the former Democratic Republic of Vietnam (North Vietnam) and the former Republic of Vietnam (South Vietnam). The division of the country resulted from the defeat of the French by Communist-inspired nationalists in 1954. A prolonged civil war resulted in a victory for the Communist north, and...
</Question>
<Choice>Vietnam</Choice>
</item>

<item>
<Question>
A land of extremes and contrasts, Asia is the largest and the most populous continent on Earth. It has the highest mountains and most of the longest rivers, highest plateaus, and largest deserts and plains of all the continents. Asia is also home to some of the world's oldest cultures. It has some of the poorest as well as some of the richest...
</Question>
<Choice>Asia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Located in an oasis near the Karakum Desert is the city of Ashgabat, capital and largest city of the Central Asian republic of Turkmenistan. From 1924 to 1991 it was the capital of the Turkmen Soviet Socialist Republic. The city name was originally spelled Ashkhabad, but in 1992 the government of the newly independent nation adopted the Turkmen...
</Question>
<Choice>Ashgabat</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
capital of Kazakhstan. In November 1997 the Republic of Kazakhstan in central Asia transferred its capital from Alma-Ata, near the Chinese border, to the industrial city of Akmola on the Ishim River in the north-central steppe. Six months later the president of Kazakhstan announced that the name of the city was to be changed to Astana. The new...
</Question>
<Choice>Astana</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital of Azerbaijan, Baku is located on the western shore of the Caspian Sea and is Azerbaijan's largest city. The center of Baku is the old town, which is also a fortress. Most of the walls, strengthened after the Russian conquest in 1806, survive. This section is picturesque, with its maze of narrow alleys and ancient buildings. Part of a...
</Question>
<Choice>Baku</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ornate Buddhist temples, palaces and slums, busy canals, and overcrowded streets make Bangkok, the capital of Thailand, a city of vivid sights, colors, and sounds. Bangkok is Thailand's major metropolitan center and chief port. More than 10 percent of the people of Thailand live in the greater Bangkok metropolitan area. The culture, education...
</Question>
<Choice>Bangkok</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital of China, the world's most populous country, Beijing is also China's cultural and educational center and a major industrial city. It is China's second largest city in terms of population (after Shanghai) and in total administrative area (after Chongqing). Beijing is one of four Chinese cities designated as a special, or national...
</Question>
<Choice>Beijing</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital of Kyrgyzstan and one of the youngest cities in Central Asia, Bishkek has undergone numerous name changes during its brief history. For much of the 20th century, Kyrgyzstan was a Soviet republic, and Bishkek was called Frunze, after a Soviet Army general who had been born there in 1885. At the time of Frunze's birth, the city had been...
</Question>
<Choice>Bishkek</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The executive capital and largest city of Sri Lanka, Colombo is also the commercial center of the country. Located on Sri Lanka's west coast, Colombo is a principal Indian Ocean port. The nearby suburb of Sri Jayawardenepura Kotte is the legislative and judicial capital of the country. (See also Sri Jayawardenepura Kotte.)
</Question>
<Choice>Colombo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A populous metropolitan area made up of the cities of Old Delhi and New Delhi, Delhi is particularly important because the latter is the capital of India. Delhi also occupies a position as a strategic crossroads in South Asia. From Delhi various Hindu and Muslim dynasties, and finally the British, ruled the Indian subcontinent. The city served as...
</Question>
<Choice>Delhi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At the heart of Bangladesh lies Dhaka (also spelled Dacca), the country's capital, largest city, and commercial center. Dhaka is one of the world's fastest growing urban centers—in the last quarter of the 20th century the metropolitan population increased by almost 470 percent. This rapid growth has strained the city's resources; as a result...
</Question>
<Choice>Dhaka</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Its name is derived from the Tajik word dush, meaning “Monday,” which is bazaar day in the area. Dushanbe serves as the capital of the Central Asian republic of Tajikistan. It was known as Stalinabad from 1929 to 1961, when it was renamed Dushanbe. Until 1991 the city was the capital of the Tajik Soviet Socialist Republic.
</Question>
<Choice>Dushanbe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Since 1976 Hanoi has been the capital of Vietnam; prior to that it had served as the capital of North Vietnam. Located on the western bank of the Red River approximately 85 miles (137 kilometers) inland from the South China Sea, Hanoi has an almost tropical climate. The rich soils of the Red River have made the city an agricultural center.
</Question>
<Choice>Hanoi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The city of Islamabad was built in the 1960s to be the new capital of Pakistan. Its name means “City of Islam” and was chosen to reflect the country's religious ideology. Located on the Potwar Plateau, the city is 9 miles (14 kilometers) northeast of Rawalpindi, which had served as a temporary capital.
</Question>
<Choice>Islamabad</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The cultures of Java, India, China, and The Netherlands all contribute to the complex character of Jakarta, the capital city of Indonesia. Jakarta lies on the northwest coast of the island of Java, in a marshy plain at the edge of the Java Sea. Its location is tropical, about 6 degrees south of the equator, and the climate is generally hot and...
</Question>
<Choice>Jakarta</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital and largest city of Afghanistan, Kabul is the nation's leading cultural and economic center. The ancient city lies on the Kabul River in a triangular-shaped valley between the steep Asmai and Sherdawaza mountain ranges.
</Question>
<Choice>Kabul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital of Nepal and the country's most important business and commercial center is Kathmandu. Located at the point where the Baghmati and Vishnumati rivers meet, the city lies at an altitude of 4,344 feet (1,324 meters).
</Question>
<Choice>Kathmandu</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A city important in the history of Japan, Kyoto lies on a fertile plain in south-central Honshu, between Lake Biwa and the Inland Sea. Kyoto is the capital of Kyoto Urban Prefecture in Kinki District. It was the capital of Japan for more than 1,000 years and was the birthplace of the nation's culture. Its Shinto shrines, Buddhist temples, and...
</Question>
<Choice>Kyoto</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Long one of the fastest-growing cities in Southeast Asia, Kuala Lumpur is the national capital and largest city of Malaysia. Kuala Lumpur is an administrative center of Selangor, one of the country's 13 states.
</Question>
<Choice>Kuala Lumpur</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital of the Philippines, Manila ranks among the largest metropolitan areas in Asia. For centuries it has been the country's economic, political, social, and cultural center. Metropolitan Manila, or the National Capital Region, was formed in 1975 when four cities—Manila, Quezon City, Pasay, and Caloocan—and 13 municipalities merged...
</Question>
<Choice>Manila</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital and chief city of Cambodia is Phnom Penh. It is located at the confluence of the Tonle Sap and Mekong rivers in the south-central part of the country. Although it is situated 180 miles (290 kilometers) from the South China Sea, it is a major port of the Mekong Valley. The city is surrounded by, but independent of, Kandal province.
</Question>
<Choice>Phnom Penh</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital of North Korea, Pyongyang is one of the oldest cities in Korea. It spreads along the Taedong River in the northwestern part of the country, about 30 miles (48 kilometers) from the Yellow Sea. The climate is moderately continental, with an average annual temperature of 49°?F (9°?C) and an average annual rainfall of 36 inches...
</Question>
<Choice>Pyongyang</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The largest city and the heart of the Republic of Korea, Seoul is also one of the largest cities in the world. Described as “an endless construction project,” Seoul is the symbol of the dynamic nation that has achieved an economic miracle since the devastation of the Korean War from 1950 to 1953 (see Korean War). Seoul is also a reflection of the...
</Question>
<Choice>Seoul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
capital of the island city-state and largest port in Southeast Asia, located where the Indian Ocean meets the South China Sea; population a remarkable mixture of East Asian cultures; the modern city established as a port of call by British East India Company 1819; one of world's largest commercial centers, the port area covers 36 square miles...
</Question>
<Choice>Singapore</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The legislative and judicial capital of Sri Lanka is Sri Jayawardenepura Kotte, a suburb of Colombo. It is located about 5 miles (8 kilometers) southeast of Colombo, in Western Province in the southwestern part of the country. Sri Jayawardenepura Kotte was the capital of the Sinhalese kingdom of Kotte, which flourished in the 15th century. The...
</Question>
<Choice>Sri Jayawardenapura-Kotte</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital of Taiwan is Taipei. It is also the cultural and economic center of the island, which is located 100 miles (160 kilometers) from mainland China. Taipei lies on the Tan-shui River near the northern tip of the island. The largest city in Taiwan, it is one of the world's most densely populated urban areas.
</Question>
<Choice>Taipei</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the largest and oldest cities in Central Asia is Tashkent, the capital of Uzbekistan. Tashkent is located in the Chirchik River valley west of the Chatkal Mountains in the northeast corner of the country. The city has an arid climate, with extremely hot summers and mild winters. The exact founding date is unknown, though the city was...
</Question>
<Choice>Tashkent</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital of the Georgian Soviet Socialist Republic since 1921, Tbilisi became the capital of the independent republic of Georgia following the collapse of the Soviet Union in December 1991. The city stretches for about 19 miles (30 kilometers) along the Kura River, where it separates the Trialeti and Kartli mountain ranges.
</Question>
<Choice>Tbilisi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Chinese characters used to write the name of the Japanese super-metropolis Tokyo convey its exact meaning. To, meaning “eastern,” and kyo, “capital,” form a name chosen in 1868 to identify the city, which was founded 268 years earlier as Edo, meaning roughly “door to the creek.” This older title was much too modest because soon after its...
</Question>
<Choice>Tokyo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ulaanbaatar is the capital and largest city, as well as an autonomous municipality, of Mongolia. Surrounded by mountains, Ulaanbaatar stands on a windswept plateau and covers an area of 770 square miles (2,000 square kilometers). Situated in the north-central part of the country, it is located on the northern bank of a shallow and swift-flowing...
</Question>
<Choice>Ulaanbaatar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital and largest city of Laos, Vientiane is located on a plain just northeast of the Mekong River. The city is Laos's main port of entry. There is an international airport, and highways link Vientiane with other major cities. The Mekong River is navigable only by small boat at Vientiane, and passage across it is by ferry. The Nam Ngum Dam...
</Question>
<Choice>Vientiane</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The largest city, economic center, and chief port of Myanmar (Burma) is Yangon. It was also the country's capital from 1948 to 2006, when the government officially proclaimed the new city of Naypyidaw as capital. In 1989, when the country's official English name was changed to Myanmar, the government requested that the name Yangon, a...
</Question>
<Choice>Yangon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital of Armenia, Yerevan, is one of the world's oldest cities. It was founded in 783 BC, some years before the founding of ancient Rome; and settlements were known several thousand years earlier. It was part of the kingdom of Urartu, which was known as early as the 13th century BC. It became part of an Armenian kingdom by the 6th century BC...
</Question>
<Choice>Yerevan</Choice>
</item>
</topics>