<topics>
<item>
<Question>
The most populous state in Australia is New South Wales. It borders the Pacific Ocean on the east and the states of Victoria on the south, South Australia on the west, and Queensland on the north. The southeastern part of New South Wales surrounds the Australian Capital Territory (including Canberra). The state capital, Sydney, is Australia's...
</Question>
<Choice>New South Wales</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The second largest state in Australia is Queensland. It occupies the most tropical part of the continent, the northeast. It is bounded by the Pacific Ocean on the north and east, the states of New South Wales and South Australia on the south, and the Northern Territory on the west. Its land area is 668,207 square miles (1,730,648 square kilometers...
</Question>
<Choice>Queensland</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Australian state of South Australia occupies an arid part of the country. It has borders with the state of Western Australia to the west; the Northern Territory to the north; the states of Queensland, New South Wales, and Victoria to the east; and the Great Australian Bight of the Indian Ocean to the south. Its land area is 379,725 square...
</Question>
<Choice>South Australia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The heart-shaped island of Tasmania is the smallest state of Australia, but its area of 26,410 square miles (68,401 square kilometers) is almost as large as the country of Ireland's. Hobart, the state capital and largest city, is located in the southeast.
</Question>
<Choice>Tasmania</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Although Victoria is one of Australia's smaller states—with an area of 87,806 square miles (227,416 square kilometers)—it is nearly as big as the United Kingdom. Australia's second most populous state, Victoria also has the country's second largest city, Melbourne, which is the state capital. Nearly three fourths of the state's residents live in...
</Question>
<Choice>Victoria</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The largest state of Australia, Western Australia occupies about a third of the continent. It encompasses some 976,790 square miles (2,529,875 square kilometers)—an area nearly equivalent to that of Mexico and the U.S. state of Texas combined. The Indian Ocean lies to its south, west, and northwest, and the Timor Sea shapes its jagged northern...
</Question>
<Choice>Western Australia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Wedged between the Indian and Pacific oceans, Australia is the only continent occupied entirely by a single country. It is an island continent and, like the island continent of Antarctica, it is located entirely in the Southern Hemisphere. Tasmania, a much smaller island off the southeast coast of Australia, is also considered to be a part of the...
</Question>
<Choice>Australia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The southwestern Pacific island nation of Fiji was a crown colony of Great Britain for 96 years until it won independence in 1970. It is an archipelago, or group of islands, having several hundred islands. Fiji is in the tropics about 500 miles (800 kilometers) southwest of Samoa and 1,100 miles (1,800 kilometers) north of New Zealand. The total...
</Question>
<Choice>Fiji</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Republic of Kiribati consists of 33 coral atolls and islands that spread over an area of more than 2,000,000 square miles (5,000,000 square kilometers) of the Central Pacific Ocean and straddle the equator and the international date line. The republic includes the Gilbert Islands, Banaba, the Line Islands, and the Phoenix Islands. More than...
</Question>
<Choice>Kiribati</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A republic in the central Pacific Ocean, the Marshall Islands comprises two parallel chains of coral atolls 800 miles (1,300 kilometers) long. The Marshall Islands' nearest neighbors are Wake Island to the north, Kiribati and Nauru to the south, and the Federated States of Micronesia to the west. The Marshalls were administered by the United...
</Question>
<Choice>Marshall Islands</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A republic in the western Pacific Ocean, the Federated States of Micronesia comprises more than 600 islands and islets in the Caroline Islands archipelago. The Republic of Palau—which is also part of the Caroline archipelago—is the Federated States' nearest neighbor to the west, while its neighbor to the east is the Republic of the Marshall...
</Question>
<Choice>Micronesia, Federated States of</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Republic of Nauru, the smallest republic in the world, consists of an oval-shaped coral island of 8.2 square miles (21.2 square kilometers) in the southwestern Pacific Ocean. Situated 37 miles (60 kilometers) south of the equator, the island once contained one of the world's richest deposits of phosphate, a mineral used in making fertilizers...
</Question>
<Choice>Nauru</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Rising from the South Pacific Ocean about 1,000 miles (1,600 kilometers) southeast of Australia, New Zealand is an isolated country settled by both Maori and European peoples. It is composed mainly of two large landmasses called the North Island and the South Island. They are known in the Maori language as Te Ika a Maui (meaning “The Fish of Maui...
</Question>
<Choice>New Zealand</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(or Belau, formerly Palau, or Pelew Islands), part of the Caroline Islands group in the western Pacific Ocean. The Republic of Palau consists of more than 340 islands in a 400-mile- (640 kilometer- ) long chain. Its area totals 188 square miles (487 square kilometers). Palau lies about 565 miles (900 kilometers) southeast of the Philippines and...
</Question>
<Choice>Palau</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An island nation located just north of Australia in the southwest Pacific Ocean, Papua New Guinea is known for its variety. More than 700 languages are spoken. There are dense jungles, snowcapped mountains, exotic birds of paradise, and Stone Age cultures.
</Question>
<Choice>Papua New Guinea</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The island country of Samoa (formerly Western Samoa), located in the south-central Pacific Ocean, is one of the smallest countries in the world. Covering an area of 1,093 square miles (2,831 square kilometers), it consists of nine islands. Four are inhabited; these are the two large islands of Savai'i and Upolu and the relatively smaller Manono...
</Question>
<Choice>Samoa</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Consisting of eight large islands and island groups, the Solomon Islands are situated about 1,000 miles (1,600 kilometers) northeast of Australia in the southwest Pacific Ocean. The islands are arranged in two parallel chains located between Papua New Guinea on the northwest and Vanuatu on the southeast. They cover a total area of 10,954 square...
</Question>
<Choice>Solomon Islands</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A kingdom in the southwestern Pacific Ocean, Tonga consists of roughly 170 islands; however, only about 40 of these are inhabited. They are divided into three main groups: Vava'u in the north, Ha'apai in the center, and Tongatapu in the south. The total area of Tonga is about 290 square miles (750 square kilometers). Tonga's closest neighbors are...
</Question>
<Choice>Tonga</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Formerly known as the Ellice Islands, Tuvalu is a constitutional monarchy made up of nine small islands in the west central Pacific. The islands are located 2,500 miles (4,000 kilometers) northeast of Australia and have a total land area of less than 10 square miles (26 square kilometers). Funafuti Atoll is the capital and main port. The other...
</Question>
<Choice>Tuvalu</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Republic of Vanuatu consists of 12 islands and 60 islets that form a Y-shaped chain in the southwestern Pacific Ocean. Formerly known as New Hebrides, it is situated about 1,200 miles (1,900 kilometers) east of Australia. Vanuatu's total land area is 4,707 square miles (12,190 square kilometers). The capital and largest city, Vila, is on Efate...
</Question>
<Choice>Vanuatu</Choice>
</item>

<item>
<Question>
Wedged between the Indian and Pacific oceans, Australia is the only continent occupied entirely by a single country. It is an island continent and, like the island continent of Antarctica, it is located entirely in the Southern Hemisphere. Tasmania, a much smaller island off the southeast coast of Australia, is also considered to be a part of the...
</Question>
<Choice>Australia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital of the Australian state of South Australia, Adelaide is located on the eastern side of Gulf St. Vincent, an inlet of the Great Australian Bight and the Indian Ocean. Adelaide lies on the banks of the Torrens River. The central part of the city is surrounded by parklands, and the scenic Mount Lofty Ranges rise to the east. The climate...
</Question>
<Choice>Adelaide</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Located on the north coast of the island of Upolu, the city, port, and capital (since 1959) of the South Pacific state of Samoa is Apia. The city's commercial activities center on the export of copra, bananas, cocoa, and coffee. Staples, including taro and other root crops, are shipped to nearby American Samoa. Vailima, former home of Scottish...
</Question>
<Choice>Apia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The largest city and commercial center of New Zealand is Auckland. The city lies in the northwestern part of the North Island, on an isthmus between Waitemata, Kaipara, and Manukau harbors. The Auckland metropolitan area is home to more than a fourth of the country's population and a large concentration of Maori (native New Zealand Polynesians...
</Question>
<Choice>Auckland</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The state capital of Queensland, Brisbane is one of Australia's larger cities. It lies in the southeastern corner of the state, about 12 miles (19 kilometers) west of Moreton Bay, which joins the Pacific Ocean. Brisbane rests on the southern slopes of the Taylor Range, an extension of the Great Dividing Range. The city is the heart of a major...
</Question>
<Choice>Brisbane</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital of Australia is Canberra, a city located about 150 miles (240 kilometers) southwest of Sydney. It is the heart of Australia's federal district, the Australian Capital Territory (ACT), which is surrounded by the state of New South Wales. Canberra's metropolitan area includes suburbs in the ACT and the city of Queanbeyan, in New South...
</Question>
<Choice>Canberra</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
capital and port city; located at mouth of Mataniko River on n. coast of Guadalcanal Island in s.w. Pacific Ocean, scene of some of the fiercest World War II battles; town founded after the war; capital since 1952; coconuts, timber, fish, small gold deposits; communications center; government buildings; Henderson Airfield, international airport...
</Question>
<Choice>Honiara</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Australia's southernmost city, Hobart is the capital of the island-state of Tasmania. Its metropolitan area is home to some two fifths of the state's residents. The city lies on the Derwent River Estuary, about 12 miles (19 kilometers) from the southeastern coast of the island. The often snow-covered Mount Wellington rises 4,167 feet (1,270 meters...
</Question>
<Choice>Hobart</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital and commercial center of the Australian state of Victoria is Melbourne. The city lies on a wide coastal plain in the southeastern part of the country. Its metropolitan area is the second most populous in Australia, trailing not far behind Sydney, its traditional rival. The Yarra River crosses Melbourne before emptying into Port...
</Question>
<Choice>Melbourne</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital of the state of Western Australia, Perth is located near the southwestern corner of the continent. It is one of Australia's larger cities, and its metropolitan area is home to nearly 75 percent of its state's population. Situated on the Swan River estuary, Perth enjoys a mild Mediterranean-style climate and miles of sandy beaches. The...
</Question>
<Choice>Perth</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Famous for the gleaming white Sydney Opera House and its picturesque waterfront, Sydney is the largest and oldest city in Australia. The capital of the state of New South Wales, it stretches along roughly 45 miles (70 kilometers) of the southeastern coast of the country-continent. Sydney is one of the chief transportation centers of the South...
</Question>
<Choice>Sydney</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital of New Zealand, Wellington is located at the southern tip of the North Island. Much of the city is built on land reclaimed from an almost landlocked bay, Port Nicholson. This fine harbor's access to Cook Strait allows shipping in both the Tasman Sea and the Pacific Ocean.
</Question>
<Choice>Wellington</Choice>
</item>
</topics>