<topics>
<item>
<Question>
The tiny Republic of Albania is located on the Balkan Peninsula. It is bordered on the south by Greece, on the east by Macedonia, on the northeast by Serbia, and on the northwest by Montenegro. The Adriatic Sea washes its western shore. Albania became a Communist state in 1946. In succeeding decades it became the poorest country of Europe. In the...
</Question>
<Choice>Albania</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the smallest nations in the world, Andorra has been independent for more than 1,000 years and was an autonomous coprincipality for more than seven centuries. Despite the transformations that neighboring European countries have undergone over the centuries, Andorra has managed to preserve its mountain tranquillity and medieval traditions as...
</Question>
<Choice>Andorra</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A small, mountainous country in Central Europe, Austria was once at the center of a great empire and one of the great powers of Europe. Its position at the middle of Europe made it a center of trade, transportation, and culture.
</Question>
<Choice>Austria</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Eastern European nation of Belarus lies nestled between Russia to the east, Poland to the west, Ukraine to the south and Lithuania to the north. From 1939 until December 1991 Belarus was a republic within the Soviet Union, after being annexed by Soviet military forces early in World War II. Its name was the Belorussian Soviet Socialist...
</Question>
<Choice>Belarus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spreading out from the southern shore of the North Sea is the small kingdom of Belgium, a historic buffer zone between Europe's Latin and Germanic civilizations. Occupying the southern rim of the Rhine-Meuse-Schelde delta, it shares with The Netherlands a strategic location on Western European trade routes. This has helped Belgium become one of...
</Question>
<Choice>Belgium</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The country of Bosnia and Herzegovina is located on the western side of the Balkan Peninsula, an area of land that extends southward from Central Europe toward the Mediterranean Sea. Bosnia and Herzegovina is bounded on the north, west, and south by Croatia, on the southwest by the Adriatic Sea, on the northeast by Serbia, and on the southeast by...
</Question>
<Choice>Bosnia and Herzegovina</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Republic of Bulgaria occupies the eastern portion of the Balkan Peninsula. In 1946, some 1,200 years after it was founded as a kingdom, it came under Communist control, which lasted until the great political upheaval in Eastern Europe in 1989–90 and the demand for greater freedom (see communism). Its neighbors are Serbia and Macedonia on the...
</Question>
<Choice>Bulgaria</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The crescent-shaped republic of Croatia became part of Yugoslavia when that country was created after World War I. It remained part of Yugoslavia for 74 years, until it, along with Slovenia, declared its independence on June 25, 1991. Resistance to independence on the part of the Serbian population of Yugoslavia plunged the nation into a...
</Question>
<Choice>Croatia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An island nation in the Mediterranean Sea, Cyprus is located approximately 40 miles (65 kilometers) south of Turkey and 60 miles (100 kilometers) west of Syria. It is the third largest island in the Mediterranean and has an area of 3,572 square miles (9,251 square kilometers). Since 1974 the northern third of the island has been under the control...
</Question>
<Choice>Cyprus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The nation of Czechoslovakia split peacefully into two countries on Jan. 1, 1993. The western provinces of Bohemia and Moravia became the Czech Republic, while the eastern section became Slovakia (see Slovakia). Of the two new countries, the Czech Republic was the larger, with a land area of 30,450 square miles (78,866 square kilometers...
</Question>
<Choice>Czech Republic</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the most prosperous nations of Europe, Denmark also has one of the most well-developed social-welfare systems. The country provides all its citizens with free education, health care, and other social benefits, along with one of the highest standards of living in the world. Denmark's location on the North Sea makes it easily reached by the...
</Question>
<Choice>Denmark</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The three small Baltic republics of the Soviet Union—Estonia, Latvia, and Lithuania—were the first of the republics to declare their sovereignty and regain their independence in 1991. An attempted coup in Moscow in August to stop the reform movement begun by the Baltics led instead to a popular uprising and the dissolution of the Soviet Union...
</Question>
<Choice>Estonia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the northernmost countries of Europe, Finland is located between Russia on the east, Sweden on the west, and the tip of Norway on the north. On the southwest the land juts into the Baltic Sea, which splits into the Gulf of Bothnia on the country's western side and the Gulf of Finland along its southern edge. About one third of the length...
</Question>
<Choice>Finland</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Situated in northwestern Europe, France has historically and culturally been among the most important countries in the Western world. Former French colonies in every corner of the globe attest to the country's stature in world affairs. The French language ranks second only to English in international use, and French culture has spread far and...
</Question>
<Choice>France</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the great powers of the industrial world, Germany rose from a collection of small states, principalities, and dukedoms to become a unified empire in 1871. The German empire was strategically located between France and Russia, and it clashed with both nations as it attempted to expand its borders. This rivalry resulted in World War I, in...
</Question>
<Choice>Germany</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The birthplace of Western civilization, the small country of Greece has had a long and eventful history. At one time a major center of science, philosophy, and art, it is today a country with political and economic problems. These problems exist in part because of the mountainous nature of its land, poor soil, and few natural resources—and in...
</Question>
<Choice>Greece</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the spring of 1989 the Hungarian government symbolically opened its frontier by removing stretches of the barbed wire that formed the Iron Curtain. After more than 40 years of one-party Communist rule and Soviet domination, in October 1989, during a period of broad political and economic liberalization in the Soviet Union and Eastern Europe...
</Question>
<Choice>Hungary</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The island of Iceland is one of the stepping-stones of land between the North American and European continents. It is located just south of the Arctic Circle about 180 miles (290 kilometers) southeast of Greenland, 620 miles (1,000 kilometers) west of Norway, and 500 miles (800 kilometers) northwest of Scotland. Over 80 percent of the island is...
</Question>
<Choice>Iceland</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Republic of Ireland occupies most of the island of Ireland, which lies across the Irish Sea from the island of Great Britain. The British controlled the area for about 750 years, until 1921, when they made southern Ireland a dominion. The link with the United Kingdom ended when Ireland became a republic in 1949. However, Northern Ireland...
</Question>
<Choice>Ireland</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Although Italy became a united country only in 1861, it has one of the oldest cultures in Europe. Italy's eras of greatness and artistic brilliance and the variety of its natural environments have attracted many travelers in search of beautiful art, landscapes, and places of religious importance. Rome, one of the world's oldest and most colorful...
</Question>
<Choice>Italy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Latvia was one of the three Baltic states that established democratic governments after the Russian Revolution of 1917 but lost independence in 1940 when they were incorporated in the Soviet Union. After more than 50 years under Soviet rule, Latvia again gained its independence in the dramatic year of 1991. (See also Estonia; Lithuania.)
</Question>
<Choice>Latvia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the smallest independent states of Europe is Liechtenstein, with an area of 61.8 square miles (160 square kilometers). It is situated between Switzerland and Austria. The Rhine River forms the boundary with Switzerland. From the Rhine's narrow valley the land rises eastward to rugged uplands. The highest peak is Grauspitz, with an...
</Question>
<Choice>Liechtenstein</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the three Baltic countries, Lithuania was a major power in Eastern Europe in the Middle Ages but was partitioned between Russia and Prussia in the 18th century. In 1918 it became an independent country, but, after Soviet troops occupied it in 1940, it was proclaimed the Lithuanian Soviet Socialist Republic—one of the 15 constituent...
</Question>
<Choice>Lithuania</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Grand Duchy of Luxembourg is a country of only 999 square miles (2,586 square kilometers), surrounded by Belgium, Germany, and France. Despite its size, it is a center of European diplomacy and it outranks many other countries as an iron and steel producer. The country is composed of two natural regions. The fertile south and center is known...
</Question>
<Choice>Luxembourg</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A landlocked country in the Balkan region of southeastern Europe, the Republic of Macedonia incorporates a complex blend of cultural traditions from both Europe and Asia. Macedonia was one of Yugoslavia's six constituent republics until it declared its independence in December 1991. The country of Macedonia accounts for less than half the...
</Question>
<Choice>Macedonia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An island country, Malta is located in the central Mediterranean Sea 58 miles (93 kilometers) south of Sicily. Covering an area of 122 square miles (316 square kilometers), the country consists of five islands—Malta (the largest), Gozo, and Comino, which are inhabited, and the uninhabited islands of Cominotto and Filfla. The capital and chief...
</Question>
<Choice>Malta</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Until it declared its independence from the Soviet Union on Aug. 27, 1991, Moldova was called Moldavia, or the Moldavian Soviet Socialist Republic. Also formerly known as Bessarabia, it was the second smallest of the 15 Soviet republics and now covers an area of about 13,000 square miles (33,700 square kilometers). It is bordered by Ukraine on...
</Question>
<Choice>Moldova</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Its world-class reputation as one of the most luxurious tourist resorts far exceeds its size of about 0.76 square mile (1.96 square kilometers). Monaco, the home of the famous casino at Monte-Carlo, is part of the French Riviera on the Mediterranean Sea. It is a sovereign, or independent, principality ruled by the Grimaldi family, whose reign...
</Question>
<Choice>Monaco</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Located in the Balkan region of southeastern Europe, the country called Montenegro sits along the Adriatic Sea. Montenegro was part of Yugoslavia for most of the 1900s and later, after Yugoslavia broke apart, part of the country called Serbia and Montenegro. In 2006 Montenegro peacefully gained its independence and became a separate country.
</Question>
<Choice>Montenegro</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Although it is one of the smallest countries in Europe, the kingdom of The Netherlands played an important role in the history of the continent. At one time it was a great sea power and a trade rival of England on the oceans of the world. The Dutch established colonies on several continents. Today The Netherlands is no longer a great colonial...
</Question>
<Choice>Netherlands, The</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Land and sea are very closely linked in Norway, a country that occupies the western half of the Scandinavian peninsula in northern Europe. Norway is bounded on the north by the Arctic Ocean, on the west by the North Sea, on the south by the Skagerrak Straits, and on the east by Sweden, Finland, and Russia. Norway's location on the Arctic Circle...
</Question>
<Choice>Norway</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the largest of the countries of eastern Europe, Poland was the first of these countries to liberate its government from the Communist domination endured for 45 years. It was the relegalization of the trade union Solidarity and the agreement to hold partially free parliamentary elections that appeared to have opened the floodgates of...
</Question>
<Choice>Poland</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the smallest nations in western Europe, Portugal played a far greater role in history than it does in modern world affairs. The socioeconomic gap between Portugal and its partners in the European Union was considerable by the early 21st century despite extensive economic reform. The capital of Portugal is Lisbon.
</Question>
<Choice>Portugal</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Once part of the Roman Empire, as its name and language indicate, Romania has had a long and varied history. At various times its territory has been occupied by Hungarians, Turks, and Russians, but after World War I Romania emerged as a united country. A member of the Soviet bloc for more than 40 years, Romania was the last unreconstructed...
</Question>
<Choice>Romania</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Formerly the preeminent republic of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics, Russia has been an independent nation since the dissolution of the Soviet Union in 1991. As part of the Soviet Union, it was called the Russian Soviet Federated Socialist Republic, or the Russian Federation.
</Question>
<Choice>Russia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the smallest independent states in Europe (only Vatican City and Monaco are smaller), San Marino is also the world's second smallest republic after Nauru. A landlocked country, San Marino is located on the eastern slope of the Apennine mountain system in central Italy. Roughly rectangular in shape, it has an area of 24 square miles...
</Question>
<Choice>San Marino</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
For most of the 20th century, the Balkan country of Serbia was a republic, or state, of the country of Yugoslavia. After World War I, Yugoslavia was created as a homeland for several different ethnic groups. It was formed largely from remnants of the collapsed Ottoman Empire and Austria-Hungary. Demands for self-determination by Slovenes, Croats...
</Question>
<Choice>Serbia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The independent country of Slovakia came into existence on Jan. 1, 1993, when the nation of Czechoslovakia voluntarily separated into two countries. From 1918 until the end of 1992 Slovakia had been one of the three provinces of Czechoslovakia, along with Bohemia and Moravia. The other two provinces became the Czech Republic. (See also...
</Question>
<Choice>Slovakia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
From 1946 until 1991 Slovenia was one of the republics of Yugoslavia. After Yugoslavia turned away from Communism in 1990, Slovenia held free elections, and in December it voted for independence. On June 25, 1991, Slovenia and neighboring Croatia both declared their independence. Two days later the Serbian-dominated Yugoslav army attacked the...
</Question>
<Choice>Slovenia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The country of Spain has had a greater influence on the rest of the world than have most countries. The lion's share of the Western Hemisphere is known as Latin America. Most of its people speak Spanish or Portuguese as a mother tongue and follow the precepts of the Roman Catholic church. This is not surprising when it is recalled that Spain and...
</Question>
<Choice>Spain</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The largest of the Scandinavian countries, Sweden has played a major historical role in northern Europe. It has a well-developed economy and a high standard of living. Its social-welfare system protects citizens against financial problems and has been a model for those of other European countries. The capital of Sweden is Stockholm.
</Question>
<Choice>Sweden</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A key landlocked nation in central Europe, Switzerland is bordered on the north by Germany, on the east by Austria and the tiny principality of Liechtenstein, on the south by Italy, and on the west by France. Its north-south maximum extent is about 140 miles (220 kilometers), while its east-west stretch is roughly 225 miles (360 kilometers), for...
</Question>
<Choice>Switzerland</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On Dec. 1, 1991, citizens of Ukraine voted overwhelmingly for independence from the rapidly disintegrating Soviet Union. Thus what had been since Dec. 30, 1922, the Ukrainian Soviet Socialist Republic became simply Ukraine. For the first time in centuries the Ukrainian people were out from under Russian or Soviet control and free to plan and...
</Question>
<Choice>Ukraine</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The United Kingdom is an island country of western Europe. It consists of four parts: England, Scotland, and Wales, which occupy the island of Great Britain, and Northern Ireland, on the island of Ireland. The country's full name is the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland. Sometimes the name Great Britain, or simply Britain, is...
</Question>
<Choice>United Kingdom</Choice>
</item>

<item>
<Question>
With about 7 percent of the world's land area, Europe is the second smallest continent on Earth, after Australia. It occupies part of the Eurasian landmass, from the Atlantic Ocean in the west to the Ural Mountains in the east. Europe also includes many islands and archipelagoes, among them Novaya Zemlya, Iceland, the British Isles, Corsica...
</Question>
<Choice>Europe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Bustling Amsterdam, capital of The Netherlands, is famous for its scenic canals, countless bridges, and stately old houses. The city was designed in such a way that some 63 miles (101 kilometers) of canals lace the inner city, so that one is never more than a few blocks from the nearest waterway. Ships sailing out of Amsterdam's harbor in order...
</Question>
<Choice>Amsterdam</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
capital and commercial center, also capital of the province of Andorra, located near the confluence of the Riu Valira and the Riu Valira del Norte in the Gran Valira Valley on the southern slopes of the Pyrenees; marketing center for goods imported from Europe and Asia; winter resort, noted for the spa of Les Escaldes; pop. 15,639
</Question>
<Choice>Andorra la Vella</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The city of Athens was the birthplace of Western civilization and is still one of Europe's great cities. In ancient times it was the most important Greek city-state. Today it is the capital and chief center of commerce and industry of Greece. The city attracts a large number of tourists each year to visit its historic sites that date to ancient...
</Question>
<Choice>Athens</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital and largest city of Northern Ireland and the busiest port in all Ireland is Belfast. It is located on Belfast Lough, an inlet of the Irish Sea.
</Question>
<Choice>Belfast</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital and largest city of Serbia, Belgrade is situated at the confluence of the Danube and Sava rivers. Belgrade is an ancient city but has been battered and rebuilt so many times that it presents a relatively modern appearance and has become a major industrial center.
</Question>
<Choice>Belgrade</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
From 1961 until 1989 a concrete wall prohibited the residents of Berlin, Germany's largest city and historic capital, from passing unrestricted between the city's eastern and western sections. For more than four decades Berlin, though well within East Germany (the German Democratic Republic), belonged to two different countries. West Berlin...
</Question>
<Choice>Berlin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Although somewhat overshadowed by Zürich and Geneva, Bern is the capital of the Swiss Confederation. The city is also the capital of Bern canton (state) and the headquarters of the Universal Postal Union. Most of Bern's people speak German. In Switzerland's second language of French, and sometimes also in English, the name of the city is spelled...
</Question>
<Choice>Bern</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the world's greatest metal-manufacturing cities and the metropolis of England's industrial Midlands area is Birmingham, to the northwest of London. It lies near the geographic center of England, at the crossing points of the national railway, highway, and canal systems. The town existed before the Norman Conquest. Its manufacturing fame...
</Question>
<Choice>Birmingham</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the aftermath of World War II Germany became a divided country, and its historic capital city of Berlin was also divided. In 1949 Bonn was chosen as the capital of the new Federal Republic of Germany (West Germany). In 1991 Berlin was designated the capital of the reunified country, though Bonn served as the center of the German federal...
</Question>
<Choice>Bonn</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The eastern part of Czechoslovakia became Slovakia on Jan. 1, 1993, and Bratislava was named capital of the new country. Bratislava is also capital of the Bratislava Region. The city is located in the southwest corner of Slovakia, about 35 miles (60 kilometers) down the Danube River from Vienna, Austria. Just to the north are the Little...
</Question>
<Choice>Bratislava</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The city of Brussels is the capital of the kingdom of Belgium. As the headquarters city for both the European Union and the North Atlantic Treaty Organization, Brussels is a world capital as well. Most of its people speak French and call their city by the name of Bruxelles. Speakers of Flemish, Belgium's other major language, use the name Brussel.
</Question>
<Choice>Brussels</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital of Romania, Bucharest once considered itself the Paris of the East, because of its Western-style architecture and stimulating social life. The luxurious style of life enjoyed by the upper class vanished after 1947 when the Communists came to power, but the city remained a major center of culture, industry, and trade.
</Question>
<Choice>Bucharest</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Situated on the east and west banks of the Danube River, Budapest is one of the largest and most beautiful cities of Eastern Europe. At one time the cocapital (with Vienna) of Austria-Hungary, it rivaled Vienna in the magnificence of its architecture and in its gracious way of life. The city is now the capital of Hungary.
</Question>
<Choice>Budapest</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital of Wales since 1955, Cardiff had barely 1,000 inhabitants at the beginning of the 19th century. However, it became for several decades the world's leading coal-exporting port at the beginning of the 20th century.
</Question>
<Choice>Cardiff</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The city of Chi?inau became the capital of the Moldavian Soviet Socialist Republic in 1940. In late 1991, when the Soviet Union broke up, the city became capital of the newly independent republic of Moldova. Located on the Byk River, Chi?inau is the largest industrial city of Moldova. Among its products are machine tools, refrigerators, tractors...
</Question>
<Choice>Chisinau</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital and largest city of Denmark, Copenhagen is also the seat of its own amtskommune (county commune). Most of the city is located on two islands—Zealand and Amager—in the straits between the North and Baltic seas. Warm sea currents give the city a milder climate than many places that are not nearly so far to the north.
</Question>
<Choice>Copenhagen</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital and largest city of Ireland, Dublin is only 46 square miles (118 square kilometers) in area but is rich in cultural achievements. It serves as the political, economic, and cultural center and chief port of Ireland.
</Question>
<Choice>Dublin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the loveliest cities of Europe, historic Edinburgh is the capital of Scotland. It is built on a series of ridges, separated by ravines, and its buildings harmonize with its unusual setting. Edinburgh was affectionately nicknamed “Auld Reekie” because of the smoke (reek) from its thousands of chimneys.
</Question>
<Choice>Edinburgh</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Florence was one of the greatest cities in Renaissance Italy. Its beautiful churches, galleries, palaces, and museums stand as noble monuments to its exciting history and to its past achievements in art. These buildings are filled with some of the richest historical and art treasures in the world. Florence, however, is not a city that lives only...
</Question>
<Choice>Florence</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The largest city in Scotland, and one of the largest in the United Kingdom, is Glasgow. The city lies on both banks of the River Clyde about 20 miles (32 kilometers) from the river's mouth on Scotland's western, or Atlantic, coast. It is about 45 miles (72 kilometers) east of Edinburgh, the capital of Scotland.
</Question>
<Choice>Glasgow</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The seat of government of The Netherlands and its third largest city, The Hague lies in the province of South Holland about 2 miles (3.2 kilometers) from the North Sea. The legislature convenes at The Hague, but Amsterdam is considered the capital because the constitution requires the sovereign to be crowned there. The original Dutch name of the...
</Question>
<Choice>Hague, The</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Located at the southern tip of the Finnish peninsula, Helsinki is the capital of Finland. It is also the leading seaport and industrial city of Finland.
</Question>
<Choice>Helsinki</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ancient Kiev, known as the Mother of Russian Towns, is now the capital of Ukraine. Situated on the banks of the Dnieper River just below its confluence with the Desna River, Kiev is a major port and one of the largest and most important cities of Eastern Europe. Kiev is not only the national capital but the capital of Kiev oblast (province) as...
</Question>
<Choice>Kiev</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
As ancient explorers sailed up the Tagus River from the Atlantic Ocean, they reached a point about 8 miles (13 kilometers) above the mouth where the river suddenly broadened into a lake. The northwest bank of this sheltered estuary became the site of Lisbon, which is Portugal's capital as well as its largest city and port.
</Question>
<Choice>Lisbon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The “city of ships,” Liverpool, is one of England's largest ports, located in Merseyside metropolitan county on the Mersey River, three miles (five kilometers) inland from the Irish Sea. It is the natural outlet for the Lancashire industrial region's textiles and machinery. The chief imports are cereals, ores, scrap metal, sugar, wood, and pulp...
</Question>
<Choice>Liverpool</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital and largest city of Slovenia, Ljubljana lies not far from the center of the country, in a basin surrounded by peaks of the Dinaric Alps. The Ljubljanica River, a short tributary of the Sava, flows through the city center. The climate is temperate, with cold winters and warm summers.
</Question>
<Choice>Ljubljana</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
London is the capital and largest city of the United Kingdom, as well as its economic and cultural center. Sprawling along the banks of the Thames River in southeastern England, London is a cosmopolitan and globally connected city, with a far greater mixture of peoples and cultures than the country as a whole. London is also the seat of one of...
</Question>
<Choice>London</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital of Spain and of Madrid autonomous community is the city of Madrid. It is Spain's largest city and its center of government, finance, and the arts. It lies nearly at the center of the Iberian Peninsula on a large, high plateau called the Meseta. At an elevation of about 2,120 feet (646 meters) above sea level, Madrid is one of Europe's...
</Question>
<Choice>Madrid</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Since 1991 the city of Minsk has been the capital of Belarus. It is also the administrative center of Minsk oblast (province) and of the Commonwealth of Independent States. Minsk is situated in the central part of the nation. It lies on gently hilly terrain on both banks of the Svisloch River, which flows southeast through the region. The climate...
</Question>
<Choice>Minsk</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital of Russia for most of the 20th century, Moscow was also for 74 years the capital of the Soviet Union and its major industrial, scientific, and cultural center. Prior to the Russian Revolution of 1917, the capital city of Russia under the czars had been St. Petersburg. With the dissolution of the Soviet Union in December 1991, Russia...
</Question>
<Choice>Moscow</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
capital of the Republic of Cyprus and Nicosia District, and also capital of the Turkish Republic of Northern Cyprus and Lefkosa District. Greeks call the city Levkosía, and Turks call it Lefkosa. The city lies in the north-central part of Cyprus on the Pedieos River. It is the chief trading center for the surrounding agriculturally rich region.
</Question>
<Choice>Nicosia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Norway's largest city is Oslo. It is the national capital and the capital of its own fylke (county). Oslo is also Norway's main commercial center and seaport. The city lies in southeastern Norway where the Aker River meets the Oslofjord. The fjord is an inlet of the Skagerrak, an arm of the North Sea. Even though the city is at a latitude of...
</Question>
<Choice>Oslo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
For generations of sophisticated urbanites, Paris has been the city against which all others are measured. The capital of France, Paris is sometimes characterized as the “City of Light.” It is acknowledged the world over as the perfect example of cosmopolitanism—raising city life almost to an art form. In Paris a pervasive elegance threads...
</Question>
<Choice>Paris</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital of the Czech Republic and one of the most beautiful cities of Europe, Prague is a traditional center of European culture. It has an ancient university and was at one time the home of such famous composers as Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart, Carl Maria von Weber, and Antonín Dvorák and such writers as Franz Kafka and Karel Capek. In modern...
</Question>
<Choice>Prague</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital of Latvia, Riga stands at the southern end of the Gulf of Riga, an arm of the Baltic Sea. The city grew up on both sides of the mouth of the Western Dvina (Daugava) River. It is a port city and an administrative, cultural, and industrial center. As a city of the north, Riga has cold winters, but the climate is moderated by the sea.
</Question>
<Choice>Riga</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Visitors from all over the world regularly stream into Rome, the capital of Italy. Pilgrims, scholars, art lovers, and tourists are fascinated with the Eternal City. More than 3,000 years old, Rome has survived countless devastating invasions. Magnificent remains of the powerful Roman Empire lie in the heart of a modern metropolis. Pagan temples...
</Question>
<Choice>Rome</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The second largest city and largest seaport of Russia, St. Petersburg lies on the Gulf of Finland. Capital of czarist Russia for more than 200 years, St. Petersburg, renamed Leningrad in 1924, resumed its original name in September 1991. A showcase of 18th-century palaces and churches, it remains a center of modern culture, learning, and industry.
</Question>
<Choice>Saint Petersburg</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In June 1914 the assassination that began World War I took place in the city of Sarajevo, capital of Bosnia and Herzegovina. The city again became known for violence during the bloody and destructive civil war that followed Bosnia and Herzegovina's declaration of independence from Yugoslavia in 1992. In the more peaceful year of 1984, Sarajevo...
</Question>
<Choice>Sarajevo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital of the former Yugoslav republic of Macedonia, Skopje is located on the banks of the Vardar River in the northern part of the country. It is the principal city of the Skopje Administrative District.
</Question>
<Choice>Skopje</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital and largest city of Bulgaria, Sofia (also spelled Sofiya) is situated in the heart of the Balkans. It occupies the Sofia Basin, a lowland region in the western part of the country, and is the capital of the Sofiya-Grad District. The Vitosha Mountains, which are accessible by cable lifts, are nearby. Sofia has a continental climate...
</Question>
<Choice>Sofia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital of Sweden, Stockholm is the cultural, educational, and industrial center of Sweden. It is also the administrative center of its own län (county). The heart of the city is built on a number of small islands that are situated where the low-lying Lake Mälaren finds an outlet to the Baltic Sea. Channels twist around the islands and...
</Question>
<Choice>Stockholm</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital of Estonia, Tallinn is located on Tallinn Bay in the Gulf of Finland, an arm of the Baltic Sea. A northern city, Tallinn has cold winters but the sea has a moderating effect on the climate. Tallinn is also the capital of Harju County. Except for the period between 1918 and 1940, the city was subject to outside control between 1219 and...
</Question>
<Choice>Tallinn</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Albania's capital and largest city, Tiranë is situated near the center of the country. Lying west of the city, separating it from the Adriatic Sea, is a fertile plain about 17 miles (27 kilometers) wide. The short Ishm River passes just north of the city as it flows down from the mountains that lie to the east. The climate is continental, with...
</Question>
<Choice>Tiranë</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Once a city-state that as a great maritime power served as a bridge between East and West, Venice, Italy, is now one of the great cultural centers of Europe. It attracts thousands of tourists each year. It serves as the capital of the province of Venice (Venezia) and the Veneto region.
</Question>
<Choice>Venice</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital and largest city of Austria, Vienna was once one of the most important political and cultural centers of the world. For more than 2,000 years a gateway between East and West, Vienna was the seat of the Holy Roman Empire from 1558 to 1806 and the capital of Austria-Hungary until 1918 (see Austria-Hungary).
</Question>
<Choice>Vienna</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
When Lithuania gained its independence from the Soviet Union on Sept. 6, 1991, Vilnius became a national capital once again. It is also the capital of Vilnius County. Vilnius is in the southeast part of the country, near the Belarus border, at the confluence of the Neris and Vilnia rivers. The climate is temperate, with cold winters and warm...
</Question>
<Choice>Vilnius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Few cities in Europe have had a more sorrowful history than Warsaw, Poland's capital. In World War II, German occupation forces demolished much of the city and killed at least 600,000 of its residents. But Warsaw, whose motto is contemnit procellas, “It defies the storms,” survived and was rebuilt.
</Question>
<Choice>Warsaw</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital and largest city of Croatia, the city of Zagreb stands on the slopes of the Medvednica Mountains and the Sava River floodplain. To the north of the mountain is the Zagorje region of woodlands, vineyards, villages, and ancient castles. The city has cool winters and hot summers.
</Question>
<Choice>Zagreb</Choice>
</item>
</topics>