<topics>
<item>
<Question>
One of the greatest engineering projects ever executed is the Aswan High Dam, across the Nile River in southern Egypt. The reservoir that it created, Lake Nasser, is one of the world's largest—1,930 square miles (5,000 square kilometers) in area, with a capacity of 137 million acre-feet (169 billion cubic meters).
</Question>
<Choice>Aswan High Dam</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In ancient Greece, the people turned to their gods for answers to questions and problems that worried them. Both the god's answer and the shrine where worshipers sought such advice were called an oracle. The most celebrated oracle was at the town of Delphi on the south slope of lofty Mount Parnassus. There a sacred stone marked what in ancient...
</Question>
<Choice>Delphi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
There is no more famous landmark in the world than the Eiffel Tower. It announces to all who see it: This is Paris. Not only does it dominate the skyline of Paris, but it is also a landmark of building construction history. (See also Paris; France.)
</Question>
<Choice>Eiffel Tower</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The state of Maharashtra in western India has many great temples cut out of rock. The most remarkable of these are the 8th- and 9th-century cave temples at Elephanta Island. The island is located in Mumbai Harbour about 6 miles (10 kilometers) east of Mumbai (Bombay) in the Arabian Sea. The island's area of 4–6 square miles (10–16 square...
</Question>
<Choice>Elephanta</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Located close to the village of Ellora in the state of Maharashtra in western India is a series of 34 magnificent rock-cut temples. The temples were cut from basaltic cliffs and are spread over a distance of more than 1 mile (2 kilometers).
</Question>
<Choice>Ellora Caves</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On Tiananmen Square in the heart of China's capital, Beijing, stands the Forbidden City. Once forbidden to the common people, it is now open as the Palace Museum. The place where 24 of the Ming and Qing emperors lived, it includes a maze of structures with golden-tiled roofs and dark red walls—the colors of the imperial court. In an area of...
</Question>
<Choice>Forbidden City</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the largest engineering and building projects ever carried out is the Great Wall of China. Originally a defensive system, it is today a major tourist attraction and a national symbol of China. The Great Wall is actually not one wall but many different walls built over time in northern China and southern Mongolia. Some of the walls run...
</Question>
<Choice>Great Wall of China</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A kremlin was a medieval Russian fortress, usually built at a strategic point along a river and separated from the surrounding parts of its adjoining city by a wooden—later stone or brick—wall with a moat, ramparts, towers, and battlements. A number of capitals of principalities—such as Moscow, Pskov, Novgorod, Smolensk, Rostov, Suzdal, Yaroslavl...
</Question>
<Choice>Kremlin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The giant statue titled Liberty Enlightening the World has become a symbol of the United States and of freedom to oppressed people everywhere. It stands on Liberty Island in New York Harbor. The statue was a gift from the people of France to the people of the United States commemorating the alliance of the two nations during the American...
</Question>
<Choice>Liberty, Statue of</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Every nation has areas of natural beauty. These areas almost always contain valuable and interesting plants and animals that often cannot be found anywhere else on Earth. Therefore, these areas must be protected if they are to continue to add to society's enjoyment and scientific knowledge.
</Question>
<Choice>national parks</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Italian countryside around the Bay of Naples, called Campania, has always been noted for its beauty. In the days of the Roman Empire, its blue skies and magnificent scenery led many wealthy Romans to build villas there. The old and prosperous cities of Pompeii and Herculaneum and the quiet little town of Stabiae were among the many local...
</Question>
<Choice>Pompeii and Herculaneum</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The prehistoric monument known as Stonehenge includes a circular arrangement of massive, upright stones surrounded by a large circular earthen embankment. It was built between about 3100 and 1500 BC and is located about 8 miles (13 kilometers) northwest of Salisbury, in southern England. There are hundreds of similar structures throughout Britain...
</Question>
<Choice>Stonehenge</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Before it became the name of one of the world's most beautiful buildings, Taj Mahal was the name of a woman. She was Arjumand Banu Begum (begum is a title for a Muslim woman of high social rank), the favorite wife of Shah Jahan, who was the Muslim ruler of India's Mughal Empire from 1628 to 1658. He affectionately called her Mumtaz Mahal...
</Question>
<Choice>Taj Mahal</Choice>
</item>
</topics>