<topics>
<item>
<Question>
The capital of the Republic of Guatemala, Guatemala City is also the largest city in Central America. An ancient city rebuilt from the ruins of earthquakes, it lies in a valley of the central highlands 4,897 feet (1,493 meters) above sea level and has a temperate mountain climate.
</Question>
<Choice>Guatemala City</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital and largest city in Nicaragua, Managua is also the country's political, commercial, cultural, and industrial center. Situated on the densely populated Pacific coastal plain just south of Lake Managua, the city has a hot and humid climate. Managua lies within the tropics at less than 163 feet (50 meters) above sea level and is one of...
</Question>
<Choice>Managua</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital of Mexico and the center of its industry, culture, and education is Mexico City. It is the oldest city in North America, a continuation of the Aztec capital of Tenochtitlán, founded in about 1325. Like Washington, D.C., it constitutes a federal district (Distrito Federal), and it is officially called Mexico, D.F. Its metropolitan area...
</Question>
<Choice>Mexico City</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital and largest city of the Republic of Panama, Panama City is located near the Pacific Ocean entrance of the Panama Canal on the Gulf of Panama. It developed into a modern city after the canal was opened to world commerce in 1914 and is the cultural heart of the country. The city's restored historic district was designated a UNESCO World...
</Question>
<Choice>Panama City</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Central American city of San José is remembered by visitors for its subtle charms. It is Costa Rica's largest city and the capital of both the country and San José province. It lies on the temperate Meseta (plateau) Central in a fertile region where coffee is grown and cattle are grazed. On the horizon to the northeast looms volcanic Mount...
</Question>
<Choice>San Jose</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital and largest city of the Republic of El Salvador, San Salvador is one of the major cities of Central America. Located in a coffee-growing region, it is about 25 miles (40 kilometers) from its chief Pacific Ocean port, La Libertad, in the western part of the country.
</Question>
<Choice>San Salvador</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital of Honduras since 1880, Tegucigalpa is situated on hilly land surrounded by mountains. The city's name comes from the Nahuatl language, and means “silver mountain,” an indication of the rich resources awaiting colonial settlers who founded the city as a mining center for silver and gold in 1578.
</Question>
<Choice>Tegucigalpa</Choice>
</item>
</topics>