<topics>
<item>
<Question>
A small Arab monarchy in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain consists of two separate groups of islands between the Qatar peninsula and the northeastern coast of Saudi Arabia. Named for the main island in the archipelago, Bahrain covers an area of about 270 square miles (692 square kilometers).
</Question>
<Choice>Bahrain</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Middle Eastern nation of Iran was once the heartland of the ancient Persian Empire. About 2,500 years ago the empire extended from the Indus Valley, in what is now Pakistan, to the Nile River and parts of present-day Libya in northern Africa. The state was popularly known as Persia, a name first used by the ancient Greeks, after the ancient...
</Question>
<Choice>Iran</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In ancient times Iraq was called Mesopotamia, a Greek word meaning “land between the rivers.” This Middle Eastern country, located at the headwaters of the Persian Gulf, lies partly between the Tigris and Euphrates rivers, a fertile area often regarded as the cradle of civilization. Its history dates back some 5,000 years. In the second half of...
</Question>
<Choice>Iraq</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The State of Israel lies at the eastern edge of the Mediterranean Sea, within the region known as the Middle East. The state was established in 1948 as a homeland for the Jewish people. Israel has had to forge a nation from the diverse Jewish people who immigrated from all parts of the world, while trying to integrate a large Arab minority. While...
</Question>
<Choice>Israel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Hashemite Kingdom of Jordan is a small country with limited natural resources, but for years it has played a critical role in the struggle for power in the Middle East. Jordan's significance results partly from its strategic location at the crossroads of what most Christians, Jews, and Muslims call the Holy Land. The country is bounded by...
</Question>
<Choice>Jordan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The tiny desert nation of Kuwait was a quiet Middle Eastern country until August 1990, when it was invaded and annexed by its much larger northern neighbor, Iraq. This act of aggression was met with military force by a United Nations coalition. The Persian Gulf War, which took place during the first two months of 1991, freed Kuwait from the...
</Question>
<Choice>Kuwait</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the world's smallest sovereign states, the Middle Eastern republic of Lebanon is situated on a long, narrow strip of land on the eastern shore of the Mediterranean Sea in western Asia. Lebanon covers an area of 4,016 square miles (10,400 square kilometers); it extends roughly 135 miles (217 kilometers) in length and measures approximately...
</Question>
<Choice>Lebanon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An independent Arab sultanate, Oman is located on the southeastern coast of the Arabian Peninsula. Covering an area of 119,500 square miles (309,500 square kilometers), Oman is bordered by the Strait of Hormuz and the Gulf of Oman on the north, the Arabian Sea on the east, Yemen on the southwest, and Saudi Arabia and the United Arab Emirates on...
</Question>
<Choice>Oman</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The State of Qatar occupies a small peninsula jutting northward from the larger Arabian Peninsula into the Persian Gulf. Qatar is about 100 miles (160 kilometers) long and 50 miles (80 kilometers) wide. The total land area is about 4,184 square miles (10,836 square kilometers). The country shares a border with Saudi Arabia and lies very near to...
</Question>
<Choice>Qatar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Kingdom of Saudi Arabia occupies four fifths of the Arabian Peninsula. Its area is approximately 830,000 square miles (2,149,690 square kilometers). Saudi Arabia is separated from Egypt, The Sudan, and Eritrea by the Red Sea to the west; from Iran by the Persian Gulf to the east; and from Bahrain by the Gulf of Bahrain, also to the east. It...
</Question>
<Choice>Saudi Arabia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Syrian Arab Republic, located in the Middle East at the eastern end of the Mediterranean Sea, lies at the heart of a region that has experienced intense political conflict since World War II. Syria is bordered on the north by Turkey, on the east and southeast by Iraq, on the south and southwest by Jordan, on the southwest by Israel, and on...
</Question>
<Choice>Syria</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The country of Turkey occupies a position between Europe and Asia. This geographical location has had a major influence on the history of Turkey and on the politics and culture of its people. At one time Turkey was the heart of the large Ottoman Empire that contained much of the Middle East, North Africa, and southeastern Europe.
</Question>
<Choice>Turkey</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A union of seven Arab kingdoms on the eastern coast of the Arabian Peninsula, the United Arab Emirates consists of Abu Dhabi, Dubai, Sharjah, Ajman, Umm al Qaiwain, Ras al Khaimah, and Fujairah emirates. The capital and the largest town of the federation is Abu Dhabi. Bordered by Qatar and the Persian Gulf on the north, Saudi Arabia on the west...
</Question>
<Choice>United Arab Emirates</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
From 1962 until unification in 1990, Yemen was divided into two warring states: the People's Democratic Republic of Yemen, a single-party Communist republic known as South Yemen or Aden, and the Yemen Arab Republic, a single-party Islamic republic known as North Yemen or Yemen (San?a). In 1990 San?a was made the capital of the new Republic of...
</Question>
<Choice>Yemen</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital and largest city of the Hashemite Kingdom of Jordan, Amman is also Jordan's only modern urban area. It is built on rolling hills in the northwestern part of the country, about 50 miles (80 kilometers) east of the Jordan River.
</Question>
<Choice>Amman</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital of Turkey and of Ankara il (province), Ankara lies at the northern edge of the central Anatolian Plateau, about 125 miles (200 kilometers) south of the Black Sea coast. It is an ancient city that, according to archaeologists, has been inhabited at least since the Stone Age.
</Question>
<Choice>Ankara</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In ancient times, Baghdad was a tiny village in a region dominated by Babylon and other powerful city-states. Today this city, once famous for its Arabian Nights tales, is the capital and largest population center of Iraq. Located along the banks of the Tigris River, Baghdad has Iraq's main concentration of industry, finance, communications, and...
</Question>
<Choice>Baghdad</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital and largest city of Lebanon, Beirut was devastated during the country's civil war from 1975 to 1991. Once one of the most attractive cities in the Middle East, Beirut was reduced to rubble. A massive reconstruction effort began soon after the war ended. Beirut lies on the Mediterranean Sea west of the Lebanon Mountains. For years the...
</Question>
<Choice>Beirut</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Located in the Judaean Hills 5 miles (8 kilometers) south of Jerusalem, the town of Bethlehem is situated in the West Bank. In Judaism it was the birthplace of David, who became king of Israel in about 1000 BC. It is also one of the most sacred places for Christians. According to the Gospels, Bethlehem was the place where Jesus was born.
</Question>
<Choice>Bethlehem</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital of Syria is Damascus, one of the oldest cities in the world. Its location at a natural oasis at the end of the easiest route through the Anti-Lebanon Mountains made it an important trade center for centuries. The modern city is a major metropolis fringed by lush gardens and orchards; it is also a center of government, culture...
</Question>
<Choice>Damascus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Israel's major port and third largest city, Haifa has been compared to San Francisco for its mountainous seaside beauty. Located in the northern part of the country on the shore of the Mediterranean Sea, Haifa has majestic views from Mount Carmel, looking northward over Haifa Bay.
</Question>
<Choice>Haifa</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
For centuries the ancient city of Istanbul was known as Constantinople, the name it was given when it became the capital of the Eastern Roman Empire. While it is no longer a capital city, Istanbul is still the cultural center of modern Turkey. It straddles the Bosporus, a narrow strait that divides the continents of Europe and Asia—a strategic...
</Question>
<Choice>Istanbul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
town 7 mi (11 km) n. of Dead Sea in West Bank territory occupied by Israel after the 1967 war. Considered the world's oldest city by some, Jericho was settled in about 9000 BC. The city was captured and destroyed by Joshua (see in the Bible, Joshua vi, 20–24). Later Jericho was repeatedly rebuilt and destroyed. The present city was built in the...
</Question>
<Choice>Jericho</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Three of the world's major religions regard Jerusalem as a holy city. The city has served as the center of Jewish life for 3,000 years. To Christians it is sacred because of its associations with Jesus. In the religion of Islam, Jerusalem ranks in importance as a holy city only after Mecca and Medina in Saudi Arabia.
</Question>
<Choice>Jerusalem</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
capital and largest city, on the s. shore of Kuwait Bay on the Persian Gulf; founded by Arab traders early 18th century on site of a 16th-century Portuguese fort; modern growth began with petroleum industry after World War II; flourishing administrative, commercial, and financial center; Kuwait University, historical museum; several residential...
</Question>
<Choice>Kuwait city</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Manama is the capital and largest city of Bahrain, an emirate in the Persian Gulf. Located at the northeastern tip of Bahrain Island, Manama is frequently a touchdown point for international visitors to the Arabian Peninsula. The city, whose name means “sleeping place,” is a modern commercial and banking center and one of the Persian Gulf's...
</Question>
<Choice>Manama</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The most holy city of Islam, Mecca is the birthplace of the prophet Muhammad (see Muhammad). Devout Muslims throughout the world turn toward Mecca in prayer five times each day. Every Muslim hopes to make a hajj, or pilgrimage, to its shrine at least once. Non-Muslims are not permitted to enter its gates. It is the capital of Makkah...
</Question>
<Choice>Mecca</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital and largest city of Saudi Arabia, Riyadh is the capital of Riyadh province. It is located in the Najd region in the east-central part of the Arabian Peninsula. Situated on a high plateau, the city spreads in the midst of oases.
</Question>
<Choice>Riyadh</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Situated at the western foot of Mount Nuqum, San?a served as the capital of the Yemen Arab Republic from 1962 to 1990. In May 1990, when the Arab republic was reunified with the People's Democratic Republic of Yemen, San?a was designated as the political capital of the new Republic of Yemen.
</Question>
<Choice>San'a</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In less than 200 years, Tehran has evolved from a tiny village into one of the most sophisticated cities of the Middle East. The capital city of Iran, Tehran is located 62 miles (100 kilometers) south of the Caspian Sea, in the north-central part of the country. The city lies nestled at the foot of the Elburz Mountains at an altitude of about...
</Question>
<Choice>Tehran</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Located on the Mediterranean coast of Israel, Tel Aviv-Yafo is the nation's largest urban center. It was formed in 1950 by the unification of the ancient port of Jaffa, or Yafo, with its former suburb of Tel Aviv. The port of Jaffa had been Israel's second largest before it was shut down in 1965, when the modern port of Ashdod, to the south, was...
</Question>
<Choice>Tel Aviv-Yafo</Choice>
</item>
</topics>