<topics>
<item>
<Question>
The Adirondack wilderness in northeastern New York State is one of the great playgrounds of the United States. It is a region of wild beauty, covering about 5,000 square miles (13,000 square kilometers). Rugged mountain scenery, good hunting and fishing, and a large variety of winter sports bring hundreds of thousands of visitors each year to the...
</Question>
<Choice>Adirondack Mountains</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The AlleghenyMountains (or Alleghenies), comprise the mountainous eastern part of the Allegheny Plateau in the Appalachian Mountains, U.S.; range extends south-southwestward for more than 500 mi (800 km) from north-central Pennsylvania to southwestern Virginia; rises to 3,213 ft (979 m) at Mount Davis, the highest point in Pennsylvania, and...
</Question>
<Choice>Allegheny Mountains</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
From the French-Italian border region near the Mediterranean Sea, the Alps curve north and northeast as far as Vienna, Austria, forming a giant mountain spine that divides the central part of Western Europe into northern and southern portions. This division has done much to shape the nations, languages, and ways of life of Europe. Occupying...
</Question>
<Choice>Alps</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A complex mountain system of Central Asia, the Altai Mountains extend approximately 1,200 miles (2,000 kilometers) in a southeast–northwest direction from the Gobi to the West Siberian Plain, through Chinese, Mongolian, Russian, and Kazakh territory. The jagged mountain ridges, whose collective name derives from the Turkic-Mongolian altan...
</Question>
<Choice>Altai, or Altay, Mountains</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ages ago geologic forces pushed the bed of the Pacific Ocean against landmasses in both North and South America. The rocks between the rising Pacific bed and the old lands were squeezed and forced into a towering mountain system called the Cordilleras, from a Spanish term meaning “little ropes.” The South American Cordilleras are called the...
</Question>
<Choice>Andes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sweeping from Newfoundland to Alabama, the Appalachian Highlands dominate the landscape of the Eastern seaboard. Their peaks, ridges, hills, and valleys form a belt almost 2,000 miles (3,200 kilometers) long and up to 360 miles (580 kilometers) wide. These highlands have played an important role in the history and economic development of the...
</Question>
<Choice>Appalachian Highlands</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The “Island of the Arabs,” Jazirat al-Arab, is located in southwestern Asia. Arabia, or the Arabian Peninsula, is the original homeland of the Arab population in the Middle East, of Arabic language and culture, and of the major world religion of Islam.
</Question>
<Choice>Arabian Peninsula</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A vital zone between North America's and Russia's northernmost frontiers consists of the Arctic regions. Once only explorers, traders, and Inuit, or Eskimo, hunters were interested in the vast, icy area at the “top” of the world. Today, because of its strategic location and its value to scientists, the Arctic is the scene of much activity. Year...
</Question>
<Choice>Arctic regions</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The vast highlands of North Africa, the Atlas Mountains span three countries and separate the southern rim of the Mediterranean basin from the Sahara Desert. They extend for more than 1,200 miles (1,900 kilometers) across Morocco, Algeria, and Tunisia.
</Question>
<Choice>Atlas Mountains</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
From a distance, the rounded hilltops and heavily forested slopes of the Black Hills, in the west-central United States, present the dark appearance that suggested their name. This isolated and eroded mountain region lies mostly within the Black Hills National Forest, which covers nearly 1.25 million acres (0.5 million hectares) in western South...
</Question>
<Choice>Black Hills</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The eastern and southeastern part of the Appalachian Mountains system in the United States is called the Blue Ridge, or Blue Ridge Mountains. It extends southwestward 615 miles (990 kilometers), from Carlisle, Pa., through parts of Maryland, Virginia, North Carolina, South Carolina, and Tennessee, to Mount Oglethorpe in Georgia. A relatively...
</Question>
<Choice>Blue Ridge</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A deep, steep-walled, V-shaped valley cut by a river through resistant rock is often called a canyon, from the Spanish word cañón, meaning “tube.” Such valleys often occur in the upper courses of rivers, where the stream has a strong, swift current that digs its valley relatively rapidly. Smaller valleys of similar appearance are called gorges.
</Question>
<Choice>canyon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Next to the Alps, the Carpathian Range is the major mountain barrier of Europe. Extending about 900 miles (1,450 kilometers) across south-central Europe in a large crescent, it holds the broad and fertile Hungarian lowlands within its curve. The top of the crescent points southwestward across the narrow Danube Valley toward Vienna and the Alps...
</Question>
<Choice>Carpathian Mountains</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Three rivers cut through the Cascade Range on their way to the sea—the Klamath River to the south, the Columbia River near the middle of the range, and the Fraser River far to the north. The many cascades, or small waterfalls, of the deep-gorged Columbia River gave the mountain range its name.
</Question>
<Choice>Cascade Range</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A ribbon of water, only 38 miles (61 kilometers) long and from 34 to 4 miles (1.2 to 6.4 kilometers) wide, separates the continent of Europe from the westernmost tip of Asia Minor. This strategically important strait is the Dardanelles, in northwestern Turkey. It leads from the Aegean Sea to the Sea of Marmara and then through the Bosporus strait...
</Question>
<Choice>Dardanelles</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The lowest point in the Western Hemisphere, Death Valley is also famous as a scene of suffering in the gold rush of 1849. There many gold seekers nearly lost their lives in searing heat. They gave the valley its grim name.
</Question>
<Choice>Death Valley</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A major mountain range in northern Iran, the Elburz Mountains extend from west to east parallel with the south shore of the Caspian Sea in a crescent-shaped arc for 560 miles (900 kilometers). Its steep, rocky slopes divide the coastal plains of the Caspian Sea from the desertlike central Iranian plateau. Many of its peaks rise more than...
</Question>
<Choice>Elburz Mountains</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The highest active volcano in Europe is Mount Etna. It rises on the east coast of the island of Sicily. The name comes from the Greek word Aitne, which is from aitho, meaning “I burn.” Its topmost elevation is about 11,000 feet (3,350 meters), depending on the effects of its most recent eruption. More than 135 eruptions have been recorded since...
</Question>
<Choice>Etna, Mount</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Known in Tibet as Chomolungma, or “goddess mother of the world,” Mount Everest is the highest point on Earth but was not recognized as such until 1852, when the governmental Survey of India established the fact. On the crest of the Himalayan range on the border of Nepal and the Chinese autonomous region of Tibet, Everest reaches a height of...
</Question>
<Choice>Everest, Mount</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The highest mountain in Japan, Mount Fuji rises to a height of 12,389 feet (3,776 meters) near the Pacific coast of central Honshu, the largest of the Japanese islands. Mount Fuji (in Japan called Fujiyama, Fuji-no-Yama, or Fujisan) is the major feature of Fuji-Hakone-Izu National Park.
</Question>
<Choice>Fuji, Mount</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nature's greatest example of sculpture, the Grand Canyon in northern Arizona is the most spectacular canyon in the world. It is a 277-mile (446-kilometer) gorge cut through high plateaus by the Colorado River. It is noted for its fantastic shapes and colors. Within the walls of the canyon stand imposing peaks, canyons, and ravines. In general...
</Question>
<Choice>Grand Canyon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Cherokee Indians called the mountains of their ancestral home Great Smoky because of the blue-gray haze that veils the rounded summits. The mountains are in the U.S. states of Tennessee and North Carolina. The Great Smoky Mountains National Park, created in 1934, straddles the crest of the Smokies from north to south along the boundary...
</Question>
<Choice>Great Smoky Mountains</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The highest mountain range on Earth, the Himalayas form the northern border of the Indian subcontinent in Asia. The mountains extend in a massive arc for about 1,550 miles (2,500 kilometers) from west to east with more than 30 peaks rising to heights greater than 24,000 feet (7,300 meters) above sea level. These include Mount Everest, the world's...
</Question>
<Choice>Himalayas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Earth's second highest mountain, after Mount Everest, is K2, also known as Mount Godwin Austen and as Dapsang. The peak, 28,238 feet (8,607 meters) high, is in the Karakoram Range of northern Jammu and Kashmir, near the border of Pakistan and China. It was given the name K2 because it was the second peak measured in this range. It was also...
</Question>
<Choice>K2, or Mount Godwin Austen</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the highest mountain systems in the world, the Karakoram Range of Central Asia extends southeastward some 300 miles (480 kilometers) from the easternmost part of Afghanistan. The borders of Tajikistan, China, Pakistan, Afghanistan, and India all converge within the system.
</Question>
<Choice>Karakoram Range</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A spectacular and imposing mountain in Tanzania, near the Kenya border, Mount Kilimanjaro extends for 50 miles (80 kilometers) and comprises three major extinct volcanoes. Its central cone, the snow-clad Kibo, is the youngest of the volcanoes. It rises to 19,340 feet (5,895 meters), the highest point in Africa. The other peaks are Mawensi...
</Question>
<Choice>Mount Kilimanjaro</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A major mountain system of southern Central Asia, the Kunlun Mountains consist of dozens of ranges in western China. From the Pamir Mountains at the border with Tajikistan, they extend eastward for about 1,250 miles (2,000 kilometers), running along the border between the Xinjiang and Tibet autonomous regions and into central Qinghai Province...
</Question>
<Choice>Kunlun Mountains</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The highest mountain in North America, Mount McKinley is located in south-central Alaska near the center of the Alaska Range. It rises 20,320 feet (6,194 meters) above sea level and 17,000 feet (5,200 meters) above the timberline. Two peaks crown Mount McKinley with the south peak the higher. The upper two thirds of the summits are covered with...
</Question>
<Choice>Mount McKinley</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Greek mythology Mount Olympus was the home of the gods and the site of the throne of Zeus, the chief deity. The highest mountain peak in Greece, it reaches 9,570 feet (2,917 meters) above sea level. It is part of the broader Olympus mountain mass near the Thermaic Gulf on the Aegean Sea. On the border of Macedonia and Thessaly, Olympus...
</Question>
<Choice>Olympus, Mount</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The upland region of the Ozark Mountains rises like an island in the midst of the Middle Western plains. Also called the Ozark Plateau, the Ozarks are the only extensive elevated area between the Appalachian and Rocky mountain ranges. The word Ozark is a corruption of the French name for the region, Aux Arcs, which means “at the bows.” The Ozark...
</Question>
<Choice>Ozark Mountains</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The mountain ranges known as the Pacific Coast Ranges constitute a major physical feature of western North America. They run parallel to the Pacific coasts of California, Washington, and Oregon for 4,500 miles (7,240 kilometers) in the United States and extend north into Canada for about 1,000 miles (1,600 kilometers) and south into Mexico for...
</Question>
<Choice>Pacific Coast Ranges</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Located in Tajikistan, the Pamir Mountains are a combination of east–west and north–south ranges. They are situated in the highland region of Central Asia.
</Question>
<Choice>Pamir Mountains</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Rugged and massive, the Rocky Mountains form a nearly continuous mountain chain in the western part of the North American continent. The Rockies sweep down from Alaska through Canada and the western third of the United States. More than 3,000 miles (4,800 kilometers) long, they vary in width from 70 to 300 miles (110 to 480 kilometers) and cover...
</Question>
<Choice>Rocky Mountains</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The loftiest mountain range in the United States, not including the mountains in Alaska, the Sierra Nevada range rises mainly in eastern California and partly in western Nevada. It is about 400 miles (645 kilometers) long and between 50 and 80 miles (80 and 130 kilometers) wide. The range is composed mostly of granite. The eastern side rises...
</Question>
<Choice>Sierra Nevada</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The highest mountain in Australia, Mount Kosciuszko, is one of the Snowy Mountains. This range is part of the Australian Alps in eastern Victoria and southeastern New South Wales. The Snowy Mountains contain several peaks that are more than 7,000 feet (2,100 meters) high. Mount Kosciuszko rises 7,310 feet (2,228 meters) above sea level. The Snowy...
</Question>
<Choice>Snowy Mountains</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Rising almost precisely on the meridian of 60° E. longitude, the Ural Mountains in Russia extend for about 1,250 miles (2,000 kilometers) from the Kara Sea in the north to the Ural River in the south. The mountains have served to mark the traditional boundary between Europe and Asia.
</Question>
<Choice>Ural Mountains</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An active volcano in southern Italy, rising 4,190 feet (1,277 meters) above the Bay of Naples, Mount Vesuvius is situated on the plain of Campania, about 7 miles (11 kilometers) from the city of Naples. Its fiery eruptions have claimed a high toll in lives and property through the centuries, but the mountainside and surrounding area remain the...
</Question>
<Choice>Vesuvius, Mount</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A volcano is a vent, or opening, in the surface of the Earth through which magma and associated gases and ash erupt. The word also refers to the form or structure, usually conical, produced by accumulations of erupted material. Volcanoes occur mainly near plate tectonic boundaries and are especially common around the Pacific basin, called the...
</Question>
<Choice>volcano</Choice>
</item>
</topics>