<topics>
<item>
<Question>
Italy is separated from Eastern Europe by a baylike arm of the Mediterranean Sea—the Adriatic Sea. It was named for Adria, which was a flourishing port during Roman times. About 500 miles (800 kilometers) long, the Adriatic Sea has an average width of about 100 miles (160 kilometers). Its maximum depth is 4,100 feet (1,250 meters).
</Question>
<Choice>Adriatic Sea</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The sparkling blue Aegean Sea lies between the peninsula of Greece on the west and Turkey on the east. Named after Aegeus, a legendary Athenian king, the Aegean Sea was the cradle of two of the great early civilizations, Crete and Greece.
</Question>
<Choice>Aegean Sea</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Allegheny River rises in the hilly plateau region of Potter county, Pa., U.S., and flows generally northward for about 80 mi (130 km); enters New York State where the Allegheny Reservoir is confined at Allegheny State Park; turning southwest, it continues for 120 mi (190 km), eventually joining the Monongahela River at Pittsburgh to form the...
</Question>
<Choice>Allegheny River</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The greatest river of South America, the Amazon is also the world's largest river in water volume and the area of its drainage basin. Together with its tributaries the river drains an area of 2,722,000 square miles (7,050,000 square kilometers)—roughly one third of the continent. It empties into the Atlantic Ocean at a rate of about 58 billion...
</Question>
<Choice>Amazon River</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The highest waterfall in the world, Angel Falls barely makes contact with the cliff over which it flows. About 20 times higher than Niagara Falls, it plunges 3,212 feet (979 meters) and is about 500 feet (150 meters) wide at its base.
</Question>
<Choice>Angel Falls</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Located between the Indian and Arabian peninsulas in the northwestern section of the Indian Ocean, the Arabian Sea forms part of the major trade route between India and the countries of Europe. It is also bounded on the north by Pakistan and Iran, and on the west by the Horn of Africa. The principal waterway draining into the Arabian Sea is the...
</Question>
<Choice>Arabian Sea</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Once the fourth largest body of inland water in the world, the Aral Sea is a saltwater lake located in the heart of Central Asia, roughly 200 miles (320 kilometers) east of the Caspian Sea. The Aral is bordered by Kazakhstan on the north and the Karakalpakstan Autonomous Republic in Uzbekistan on the south. To the southeast spreads the great...
</Question>
<Choice>Aral Sea</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
By far the smallest of the world's oceans, with an area of 5,440,000 square miles (14,090,000 square kilometers), the Arctic Ocean covers the northern polar region of the Earth. The North Pole is located approximately at its center.
</Question>
<Choice>Arctic Ocean</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The vast body of water that separates Europe and Africa from North and South America is the Atlantic Ocean. Its name, which comes from the Greek, may refer to Atlantis, the legendary island continent said to have been the site of a great civilization before the island sank.
</Question>
<Choice>Atlantic Ocean</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Baltic Sea is an arm of the North Sea, and it is Russia's chief outlet to the Atlantic Ocean and the only outlet for Finland, Estonia, Latvia, Lithuania, and Poland. Sweden, Denmark, and Germany also use this waterway as a transportation route.
</Question>
<Choice>Baltic Sea</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The northernmost part of the Pacific Ocean is the Bering Sea, the body of water that separates Siberia in Asia from Alaska in North America. The narrowest part, only 53 miles (85 kilometers) wide, is the Bering Strait. In this channel are Little Diomede Island, which belongs to the United States, and Big Diomede Island, which belongs to Russia...
</Question>
<Choice>Bering Sea</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Two arms of land enclose the Black Sea—the Balkan Peninsula, which thrusts southward from Europe, and the peninsula of Asia Minor, projecting westward from Asia. The sea connects with the Mediterranean through the Bosporus strait, the Sea of Marmara, and the Dardanelles strait. The area of the Black Sea (including a baylike arm, the Sea of Azov...
</Question>
<Choice>Black Sea</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A great arm of the Atlantic Ocean located between the long, sweeping crescent of the West Indies and the coasts of Central and South America, the Caribbean Sea is one of the world's great crossroads for ocean shipping. The islands that dot the sea and the land areas that border it include some of the most popular vacation destinations in the world...
</Question>
<Choice>Caribbean Sea</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The largest inland sea in the world, the Caspian Sea lies east of the Caucasus Mountains at Europe's southeasternmost extremity. It dominates the huge, flat expanses of west central Asia. The sea is bordered by Kazakhstan, Turkmenistan, Russia, Azerbaijan, and Iran. The area of the Caspian Sea is approximately 149,200 square miles (386,400 square...
</Question>
<Choice>Caspian Sea</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Between Israel and Jordan lies the Dead Sea, a salt lake located on the lowest point of Earth's surface. Its basin lies some 1,300 feet (400 meters) below sea level, making it the lowest body of water in the world. The lake is about 50 miles (80 kilometers) long and 11 miles (18 kilometers) wide. Its surface area is about 394 square miles...
</Question>
<Choice>Dead Sea</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
So many ships have been wrecked on Lake Erie that it has been called the “marine graveyard of the inland seas.” The shallowest and stormiest of the Great Lakes of North America, it has a maximum depth of only 210 feet (64 meters). It is fourth in size among the five Great Lakes with a length of 241 miles (388 kilometers) and an area of...
</Question>
<Choice>Erie, Lake</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The longest river of western Asia is the 1,700-mile (2,700-kilometer) Euphrates. It begins in the high mountains of eastern Turkey, crosses eastern Syria, and then flows southeastward through the length of Iraq. Because of Iraq's hot, dry climate much of the river's water is lost through evaporation and use for irrigation. The river receives...
</Question>
<Choice>Euphrates River</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Ganges, or Ganga, is one of the world's great rivers. Its wide valley stretches across northern India and Bangladesh from the Himalayas to the Bay of Bengal. It is one of the most fertile of all agricultural regions. Its rice and other crops feed hundreds of millions of people in India and in Bangladesh, where the river is also known as the...
</Question>
<Choice>Ganges River</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the Coral Sea, off the coast of Queensland, Australia, lies the Great Barrier Reef, one of the natural wonders of the world. A barrier reef is a long, narrow, mostly submerged coral formation that lies parallel to the shoreline of a landmass. The Great Barrier Reef is the largest complex of coral reefs, shoals, and islets in the world. Despite...
</Question>
<Choice>Great Barrier Reef</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Five huge lakes in the heart of eastern North America form the greatest connected area of fresh water on Earth. One of them—Lake Superior—is bigger than any other freshwater lake and any saltwater lake except the Caspian Sea. Put together, the five Great Lakes would more than cover the states of New York and Pennsylvania.
</Question>
<Choice>Great Lakes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The main river of northern China, the Huang He (or Hwang Ho) is the second longest river in the country, after the Yangtze. It rises on the Plateau of Tibet and flows generally eastward, emptying into the Yellow Sea. Chinese historians routinely refer to the Huang He as the cradle of Chinese civilization. The river, its tributaries, and its...
</Question>
<Choice>Huang He, or Hwang Ho (Yellow River)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The second largest of the Great Lakes, Lake Huron has an area of 23,000 square miles (59,570 square kilometers), including Georgian Bay. It is bounded on the south and west by Michigan and on the north and east by Ontario. The United States–Canada border passes through the lake. The lake is irregularly shaped, with Saginaw Bay indenting the...
</Question>
<Choice>Huron, Lake</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Among the most spectacular sights in South America are the Iguazú Falls. They are located on a stretch of the Iguazú River that forms the boundary between Brazil and Argentina. In Brazil the name is Iguaçu, or Iguassú.
</Question>
<Choice>Iguazú Falls</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Two thousand years ago mariners would venture on only the most cautious coastal voyages along the Atlantic coast. The Indian Ocean, however, had well-established trade routes. Sailors struck boldly across the Arabian Sea from Arabia to India. Arabian merchants traded with the east coast of Africa. Indian traders, colonists, and priests carried...
</Question>
<Choice>Indian Ocean</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The fertile basin of the Indus River was an important center of ancient civilization. Buried cities found here—such as Mohenjo-daro near Karachi—are at least as old as the first pyramids of Egypt. They had broad streets, fine brick buildings, bathrooms, and drainage systems. Through the centuries the river valley was a trade route and the path...
</Question>
<Choice>Indus River</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Located at the western edge of the Pacific Ocean, the Sea of Japan is bounded by Japan and the Russian island of Sakhalin to the east and by Russia and North and South Korea on the Asian mainland to the west. Its area is 389,100 square miles (1,007,800 square kilometers). The sea's average depth is 4,429 feet (1,350 meters), with a maximum...
</Question>
<Choice>Japan, Sea of</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Flowing southward from Syria across Israel and into Jordan, the Jordan River is the lowest river in the world. From the Hula Panhandle, a marshy region at the northern tip of Israel, the river drops sharply to the Sea of Galilee, 686 feet (209 meters) below sea level. It is more than 223 miles (358 kilometers) long. Over most of its course the...
</Question>
<Choice>Jordan River</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Technically, a lake is an inland body of water surrounded by land. It is larger than a pool or pond. The name, however, is sometimes given to the widened parts of rivers and to bodies of water that are in direct connection with the sea. Coastal lakes, for example, are often formed where waves and shore currents build sandbars across bays or wide...
</Question>
<Choice>lake</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The longest river in France, the Loire runs a course of 634 miles (1,020 kilometers). The Loire rises in southeastern France, only 85 miles (137 kilometers) north of the Mediterranean Sea, and flows northward for about half its course. Then it sweeps with a great curve to the southwest and flows into the Atlantic Ocean near Nantes.
</Question>
<Choice>Loire River</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The largest natural lake in South America, Lake Maracaibo is a huge inlet of the Caribbean Sea in northwestern Venezuela. Covering an area of approximately 5,150 square miles (13,350 square kilometers), it is about 130 miles (210 kilometers) long by 75 miles (120 kilometers) at its widest. Situated in a basin between the Sierra de Perijá range in...
</Question>
<Choice>Maracaibo, Lake</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The area surrounding the Mediterranean Sea has been called the “cradle of civilization.” The sea lies between Europe to the north and west, Africa to the south, and Asia to the east. Including the Sea of Marmara, the area of the Mediterranean is 970,000 square miles (2,512,000 square kilometers). The sea evokes images of Homer's early stories...
</Question>
<Choice>Mediterranean Sea</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The brown-watered Mekong is one of the great rivers, and one of the longest, of Southeast Asia. From its glacial sources in the lofty Tibetan Highlands, the Mekong flows for 2,600 miles (4,200 kilometers) through China, Laos, Thailand, Cambodia, and Vietnam, finally emptying into the South China Sea south of Ho Chi Minh City.
</Question>
<Choice>Mekong River</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A great indentation of the Atlantic Ocean, the Gulf of Mexico is almost completely surrounded by the United States and Mexico. In the 450-mile (720-kilometer) stretch between Yucatán and Florida are the Yucatán Channel, the northwestern coast of Cuba, and the Straits of Florida. From east to west the gulf measures about 1,100 miles...
</Question>
<Choice>Mexico, Gulf of</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Third in size of the five Great Lakes, Lake Michigan is the only one that lies entirely within the United States. It is 307 miles (494 kilometers) long and 118 miles (190 kilometers) across at its greatest width. Its area is 22,300 square miles (57,800 square kilometers), and its greatest depth is 923 feet (281 meters). It is bounded on the...
</Question>
<Choice>Michigan, Lake</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The “father of waters,” the Mississippi River is one of the longest in the world. According to the United States Army Corps of Engineers, if it is measured from the Upper Red Rock Reservoir—which leads to its longest branch, the Missouri—the Mississippi flows 3,658 miles (5,887 kilometers) to the Head of Passes in the delta. From Lake Itasca in...
</Question>
<Choice>Mississippi River</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Situated between the state of New York and the province of Ontario, Niagara Falls is one of the most spectacular natural wonders on the North American continent. The falls are on the Niagara River, which flows between the United States and Canada from Lake Erie to Lake Ontario. The falls are about 17 miles (27 kilometers) northwest of Buffalo, N...
</Question>
<Choice>Niagara Falls</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The longest river in Africa, the Nile at 4,132 miles (6,650 kilometers) is the longest river in the world. Known in Arabic as Al-Bahr or Bahr en Nil, it rises just south of the equator in eastern Africa and flows in a generally northward direction to drain into the Mediterranean Sea.
</Question>
<Choice>Nile River</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The third largest and most southern of the East African Rift Valley lakes, Lake Nyasa is also called Lake Malawi because it forms much of Malawi's northern and eastern boundaries with Tanzania and Mozambique. Nyasa, which means “lake,” is 363 miles (584 kilometers) long, north to south, with varying widths of 10 to 50 miles (16 to 80 kilometers...
</Question>
<Choice>Nyasa, Lake</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Two great tributaries flow into the Mississippi River. One is the Missouri, and the other is the Ohio. The Ohio is formed by the confluence of the Allegheny and Monongahela rivers at Pittsburgh, Pa. The river travels 981 miles (1,579 kilometers). It flows northwestward from Pittsburgh and then mostly southwestward to join the Mississippi at...
</Question>
<Choice>Ohio River</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The smallest of the Great Lakes of North America, Lake Ontario forms part of the boundary between the eastern United States and Canada. It is bordered on the north by Ontario and on the south by New York. It lies east of the four other Great Lakes, just slightly northeast of Lake Erie.
</Question>
<Choice>Ontario, Lake</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The major feature of the Pacific Ocean is its enormous size: not only is it the largest ocean in the world, it is also the world's largest single physical feature. With an area of about 64 million square miles (166 million square kilometers), it is twice the size of the Atlantic Ocean and occupies nearly a third of the surface of the Earth—more...
</Question>
<Choice>Pacific Ocean</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The longest river in Italy is the Po. Its headwaters are on the slopes of Mount Viso in the Cottian Alps, near the French border. Here Italy's principal river begins its long course across the northern portion of the country. The river flows 405 miles (652 kilometers) to empty into the Adriatic Sea on the east coast of Italy. The Po forms a...
</Question>
<Choice>Po River</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An inland sea connected with the Gulf of Aden and the Indian Ocean, the Red Sea separates the Arabian Peninsula from northeastern Africa. Bordered by Egypt, Sudan, and Ethiopia on the west and Saudi Arabia and Yemen on the east, the Red Sea occupies an area of approximately 174,000 square miles (451,000 square kilometers). From a maximum width...
</Question>
<Choice>Red Sea</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Physically and culturally, the Rhine River has played a major role in shaping European history. It is also the busiest waterway in Europe. From its source high in the Swiss Alps, the Rhine flows 820 miles (1,320 kilometers) through widely varying terrain from east-central Switzerland northward and westward to its North Sea outlet in The...
</Question>
<Choice>Rhine River</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of Europe's most picturesque and significant streams, the Rhône River flows from the Swiss Alps westward and southward to the Mediterranean Sea, draining the eastern quarter of France.
</Question>
<Choice>Rhône River</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A river whose waters are vital to its dry basin, the Rio Grande rises in the San Juan Mountains of southwestern Colorado and flows for 1,885 miles (3,035 kilometers) to the Gulf of Mexico. From its source, the Rio Grande travels southward through central New Mexico before angling southeastward for some 1,250 miles (2,010 kilometers) to form the...
</Question>
<Choice>Rio Grande</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Earth's rivers carry the water that people, plants, and animals must have to live. They also provide transportation and waterpower. Nations have learned to harness the power of rivers by building hydroelectric dams such as those constructed on the Volga River. Rivers are also a principal natural force in shaping land surfaces. They drain...
</Question>
<Choice>river</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the world's major canal systems, the Sault Ste. Marie is actually made up of two canals, one operated by the United States and the other by Canada. The waterway allows shipping between Lake Superior and Lake Huron and thus provides access from Lake Superior to the Atlantic seaboard.
</Question>
<Choice>Sault Sainte Marie canals</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the world's great rivers is the St. Lawrence. It is part of a giant seaway from the Atlantic Ocean to the Great Lakes. It ranks in importance with the Suez and Panama canals.
</Question>
<Choice>Saint Lawrence River</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The dream of a canal across the Isthmus of Suez had existed since the time 4,000 years ago when the pharaohs built Egypt's first canal. (It linked the Nile River with the Great Bitter Lake, which then opened onto the Gulf of Suez.) This canal, however, was filled in, and for centuries trade with the Far East was carried overland across Asia...
</Question>
<Choice>Suez Canal</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The largest of the five Great Lakes, Lake Superior is one of the world's largest bodies of fresh water. Its name comes from the French Lac Supérieur, meaning “upper lake.” The lake's area is 31,700 square miles (82,100 square kilometers). It is 350 miles (565 kilometers) long from east to west and its greatest north-south width is 160 miles...
</Question>
<Choice>Superior, Lake</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A major waterway of the southeastern United States, the Tennessee River is also a central part of one of the largest irrigation and hydroelectric power systems in the world (see Tennessee Valley Authority). The river begins with the joining of the Holston and French Broad rivers east of Knoxville, Tenn. From there it follows a U-shaped course of...
</Question>
<Choice>Tennessee River</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Not for its length but for its location is the Thames one of the best-known rivers in the world. Although it is only 210 miles (338 kilometers) long, it is England's chief waterway. The Thames begins at Seven Springs in the Cotswold Hills. From there it pursues a very winding course through the Chiltern Hills. At Oxford, the famous university...
</Question>
<Choice>Thames River</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The streams that join to form the Tigris River begin in high mountains that rim Lake Van in eastern Turkey. Leaving Turkey, the Tigris touches the northeastern border of Syria and then flows southeastward across Iraq. In Iraq it is joined by tributaries from the east—principally the Great Zab, Little Zab, and Diyala. The Euphrates, west of the...
</Question>
<Choice>Tigris River</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
At 12,500 feet (3,810 meters) above sea level, Lake Titicaca is the world's highest lake navigable to large vessels. It is also the second largest lake in South America, after Lake Maracaibo. Located in the Andes Mountains, Titicaca spans the border between Bolivia and Peru in an area known as the Altiplano—a series of valleys, hills, and vast...
</Question>
<Choice>Titicaca, Lake</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the world's mightiest waterfalls is in east-central Africa, on the border between Zambia and Zimbabwe (formerly Rhodesia). Here the Zambezi River spreads out into an island-studded channel that extends to more than 5,500 feet (1,680 meters) wide and drops abruptly some 355 feet (108 meters) into a deep cleft set squarely across the current...
</Question>
<Choice>Victoria Falls</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Africa's largest lake is on the equator. It is bordered by Kenya, mainland Tanzania, and Uganda. At its longest, it stretches 210 miles (338 kilometers) across the East African plateau. Its greatest width is 150 miles (241 kilometers). Its area is about 26,828 square miles (69,484 square kilometers). Its shores, except on the west, are deeply...
</Question>
<Choice>Victoria, Lake, or Victoria Nyanza</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Europe's longest river and the principal waterway of Russia, the Volga arises in the Valdai Hills northwest of Moscow and flows southeastward for 2,325 miles (3,740 kilometers) to empty into the Caspian Sea. Known as Mother Volga, it is a symbol of Russia and a central theme in songs and stories.
</Question>
<Choice>Volga River</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The longest river in Asia and the third longest in the world is the Yangtze River, which is known in China mainly as the Chang Jiang. It flows for 3,915 miles (6,300 kilometers), from the Plateau of Tibet in western China to the East China Sea at Shanghai. The river flows generally eastward, crossing or serving as the border between 10 of China's...
</Question>
<Choice>Yangtze River</Choice>
</item>
</topics>