<topics>
<item>
<Question>
One of the great crossroads of ancient civilization is a broad peninsula that lies between the Black and Mediterranean seas. Called Asia Minor (Lesser Asia) by the Romans, the land is the Asian part of modern Turkey. It lies across the Aegean Sea to the east of Greece and is usually known by its Greek name Anatolia.
</Question>
<Choice>Asia Minor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Balkan Peninsula forms a large, roughly wedge-shaped area of land that extends southward from Central Europe toward the Mediterranean Sea. It is about 800 miles (1,300 kilometers) wide in the north and stretches about 650 miles (1,050 kilometers) to its southern point, Cape Taínaron, in Greece. The Balkans cover an area of about...
</Question>
<Choice>Balkans</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Central America extends for a distance of 1,200 miles (1,900 kilometers) southeastward from Mexico to South America. Long but narrow, it covers an area of about 202,000 square miles (523,000 square kilometers). The region faces the Pacific Ocean to the west and the Caribbean Sea to the east. Its wider northern half, which extends up to 125 miles...
</Question>
<Choice>Central America</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the extreme southern part of Ukraine the Crimean peninsula juts into the Black Sea. It is almost surrounded by water because the Perekop Isthmus that joins it to the mainland is only 5 miles (8 kilometers) wide. From the main peninsula the narrow Kerch' peninsula stretches eastward. It almost encloses the shallow Sea of Azov.
</Question>
<Choice>Crimea</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The largest and most populated part of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland is England. By world standards, it is neither large nor particularly rich in natural resources, yet in the past, as the heart of the vast British Empire, its political and economic power was virtually unrivaled. Today England's influence on the...
</Question>
<Choice>England</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The notorious Devil's Island—where France once confined political prisoners and wartime spies—is off the Atlantic coast of French Guiana. The French overseas département (administrative district) lies between Brazil and Suriname on the northeastern coast of South America. It has an area of 33,399 square miles (86,504 square kilometers). Its...
</Question>
<Choice>French Guiana</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Near the southern tip of Spain a peninsula forms a finger of land that points to the coast of Africa, 14 miles (23 kilometers) away. That peninsula is the British overseas territory known as Gibraltar. It includes the famous Rock of Gibraltar, which stands at the western gateway to the Mediterranean. Since 1704 when the British captured it...
</Question>
<Choice>Gibraltar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Great Britain is one of the two main islands that make up the British Isles. By this definition it includes England, Scotland, and Wales. However, the name Great Britain is commonly used to refer to the United Kingdom as a whole, which also includes Northern Ireland and some offshore islands.
</Question>
<Choice>Great Britain</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the Lesser Antilles island chain of the West Indies is Guadeloupe, which is officially an overseas department of France. The total land area is 658 square miles (1,705 square kilometers), consisting of the twin islands of Basse-Terre and Grande-Terre as well as several smaller islands. Basse-Terre is mountainous, while Grande-Terre is flatter.
</Question>
<Choice>Guadeloupe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A special administrative region of China, Hong Kong is located on the southern coast of China at the mouth of the Pearl (Zhu) River delta. Some of its land is on the Chinese mainland, and some is on islands just offshore in the South China Sea. Its area—about 426 square miles (1,104 square kilometers)—has expanded as it has reclaimed land from...
</Question>
<Choice>Hong Kong</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The northeastern part of the island of Ireland is occupied by Northern Ireland, a part of the United Kingdom. It covers only one sixth of the total area of the island but has about one third of the population. The rest of the island is occupied by the Republic of Ireland. The capital and largest city of Northern Ireland is Belfast.
</Question>
<Choice>Northern Ireland</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Formerly a province of Serbia, Kosovo is a self-declared independent country in the Balkans region of southeastern Europe. The vast majority of Kosovo's people are ethnic Albanians, who are predominantly Muslim. Kosovo is historically important to the Serbs, however, who ruled it during the later Middle Ages and still consider it to be the heart...
</Question>
<Choice>Kosovo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The region called Lapland (Finnish, Lapi or Lappi; Swedish, Lappland) stretches across Arctic Norway, Sweden, and Finland and includes the Kola Peninsula of Russia. It is bounded by the Norwegian Sea on the west and the Arctic Ocean on the north and east. The western part of Lapland contains high mountains that are deeply eroded into fjords and...
</Question>
<Choice>Lapland</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The region of Latin America covers all the Americas south of the U.S. border—that is, Mexico, Central America, South America, and the West Indies—about 15 percent of the Earth. With well over half a billion people, Latin America is 50 percent more populous than Anglo America.
</Question>
<Choice>Latin America</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Chinese special administrative region of Macau (or Macao) is located on the southern coast of China. It consists of a small peninsula of mainland China and the islands of Taipa and Coloane, which lie just offshore in the South China Sea. These three parts of Macau are linked by bridges. All together, Macau covers an area of 11.3 square miles...
</Question>
<Choice>Macau</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The oval-shaped island of Martinique is a French overseas department in the eastern Caribbean Sea. Located 4,400 miles (7,000 kilometers) from France, it is the smallest of all French overseas departments. Martinique is the largest of the Windward Islands in the West Indies, covering 436 square miles (1,128 square kilometers). The islands of...
</Question>
<Choice>Martinique</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The area between the Tigris and Euphrates rivers in what is now Iraq is the site of ancient Mesopotamia, birthplace of the world's first civilizations. The name is Greek for “land between the rivers.” As the muddy streams flooded and receded, their silt built the rich alluvial plain. Tradition locates the Biblical Garden of Eden in Mesopotamia.
</Question>
<Choice>Mesopotamia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Located at the junction of three continents—Europe, Asia, and Africa—the region known as the Middle East has historically been a crossroads for conquerors, peoples, trade, and ideas as well as a transition zone for political and cultural interaction. Today the Middle East's strategic location as a tricontinental hub and its vast petroleum reserves...
</Question>
<Choice>Middle East</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The geographic region Oceania includes roughly 10,000 islands in the Pacific Ocean, mainly in the western and central portions. Oceania covers about 20 million square miles (50 million square kilometers), or roughly one third of the enormous Pacific Ocean. Yet the total land area of the islands is very small—only some 324,000 square miles...
</Question>
<Choice>Oceania</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Since ancient times, the region between the Jordan River and the Mediterranean Sea has commanded a significance far greater than its size. Strategically located at the joining of Africa and Southwest Asia, it was fought over and ruled in succession by nearly all the great powers of the Middle East. It was part of the kingdom of Israel in biblical...
</Question>
<Choice>Palestine</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
An island in the western Indian Ocean, Réunion is located about 450 miles (720 kilometers) east of Madagascar. Roughly oval in shape, it covers an area of 970 square miles (2,512 square kilometers). It was a French colony until 1946, when it became a French overseas department. Volcanic in origin, its landform is dominated by volcanic cones...
</Question>
<Choice>Réunion</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The region of Northern Europe made up of Sweden,Norway, and Denmark is called Scandinavia. Its people are known for their rugged pioneer spirit as well as their quest for international peace. The term Scandinavia sometimes includes Finland; Iceland; and the Faeroe Islands, which are part of Denmark, though a self-governing region.
</Question>
<Choice>Scandinavia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A part of the United Kingdom, Scotland occupies the northern part of the island of Great Britain. Rugged uplands separate it from England to the south. Within this border territory north of England the Scots fought many wars to keep their independence. In 1707, however, Scotland was joined to England, and the entire island became a single kingdom...
</Question>
<Choice>Scotland</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The enormous Russian region known as Siberia occupies Eurasia's northeastern quadrant. It covers an area of 5,207,900 square miles (13,488,400 square kilometers) and makes up more than three quarters of Russia. It is a fourth bigger than Canada, the world's second largest country. It extends from the Ural Mountains on the west to the Pacific...
</Question>
<Choice>Siberia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Long known as the Roof of the World, Tibet was isolated for most of its more than 1,000-year history. It is composed of high plateaus and some of the tallest mountains in the world. Tibet is an autonomous region of China that is located along China's southwestern frontier with India, Nepal, Bhutan, and Myanmar (Burma). The Tibet Autonomous Region...
</Question>
<Choice>Tibet</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Though a part of the United Kingdom, Wales has retained a character of its own—the result of its Celtic culture and its rugged landscape. In the Welsh language, Wales is called Cymru. Much of Wales is still a land of picturesque mountains and valleys. However, the existence of large coalfields in the south brought industry and urbanization. The...
</Question>
<Choice>Wales</Choice>
</item>
</topics>