<topics>
<item>
<Question>
Within Latin America the nation of Argentina is second in area only to Brazil and fourth in population only to Brazil, Mexico, and Colombia. This large land covers more than 1 million square miles (2.7 million square kilometers), in the southern part of South America east of the Andes Mountains. It extends from the Tropic of Capricorn south to...
</Question>
<Choice>Argentina</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The South American republic of Bolivia has great natural wealth, though its location, nestled within two ranges of the Andes, prevents easy access to its riches. Mountains and tropical forests make transportation difficult, and because it is landlocked—meaning that it does not border an ocean—Bolivia has no seacoast for ships. The mountains hold...
</Question>
<Choice>Bolivia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Occupying half of South America and much of the Amazon River basin, Brazil is bordered by every country on the continent except for Ecuador and Chile. Framed by the Atlantic Ocean on the northeast and southeast, Brazil forms a rough triangle about 2,500 miles (4,000 kilometers) from east to west and 2,700 miles (4,350 kilometers) from north to...
</Question>
<Choice>Brazil</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
When seen on a map, the republic of Chile looks like a long piece of narrow ribbon on the southwestern coast of South America. Chile is a land of physical extremes, from its desert north—one of the driest places on earth—to its windswept and rainy south, which is roughly comparable to the Pacific coast of Canada. It is bordered by Peru in the...
</Question>
<Choice>Chile</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The third most populous country in Latin America is the Republic of Colombia, which is located in the northwest corner of South America. It was named in honor of the explorer Christopher Columbus. With an area of about 440,000 square miles (1,140,000 square kilometers), the country is roughly twice the size of France and three times the size of...
</Question>
<Choice>Colombia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The republic of Ecuador became an independent nation in 1830. Its small area of about 108,000 square miles (280,000 square kilometers) gives it a limited range of natural resources.
</Question>
<Choice>Ecuador</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Although located in northern South America, Guyana is culturally and historically tied closely to the former British colonies of the Caribbean. Guyana was known as the colony of British Guiana until 1966, when it received full political independence.
</Question>
<Choice>Guyana</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Located in the interior of southern South America, Paraguay is one of the smaller countries of the continent, with an area of 157,048 square miles (406,752 square kilometers). Its population is about 3.9 million. Argentina on the south and west, Brazil on the east, and Bolivia on the west and north surround the country. The Argentina boundary is...
</Question>
<Choice>Paraguay</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
This South American land of arid coasts, high Andes Mountains, and Amazon rainforest is more than three times the size of the U.S. state of California and, covering 496,218 square miles (1,285,198 square kilometers), is equal to Spain, France, and the United Kingdom combined. Peru is the third largest country in South America after Brazil and...
</Question>
<Choice>Peru</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
With an area of 63,251 square miles (163,820 square kilometers), Suriname is one of the smallest countries in South America. It is located on the continent's north-central coast and is bounded by the Atlantic Ocean on the north, French Guiana on the east, Brazil on the south, and Guyana on the west. The boundaries with French Guiana and Guyana...
</Question>
<Choice>Suriname</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the smallest countries in South America, Uruguay, lies between Latin America's two largest republics. Covering an area of about 68,037 square miles (176,215 square kilometers), the nation is dwarfed by its giant neighbors—Brazil, to the north and northeast, and Argentina, to the west and south. The Atlantic Ocean on the east and the...
</Question>
<Choice>Uruguay</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the world's chief oil exporters, the Bolivarian Republic of Venezuela is as famous for its petroleum as it is for its natural wonders. The country boasts majestic Angel Falls, which is the world's highest waterfall. Other marvels include the forest-covered Guiana Highlands; the northern arm of the Andes Mountains; coastal Lake Maracaibo...
</Question>
<Choice>Venezuela</Choice>
</item>

<item>
<Question>
A triangular-shaped continent, South America is bordered on the east by the Atlantic Ocean, on the west by the Pacific Ocean, and on the north by the Caribbean Sea. It is connected to North America by the Isthmus of Panama. The fourth largest of the continents, South America has an area of about 6,882,000 square miles (about 17,825,000 square...
</Question>
<Choice>South America</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital of Paraguay and the nation's largest city is Asunción. It is situated on the east bank of the Paraguay River where it widens to form a broad bay. The Pilcomayo River joins the Paraguay on the opposite shore. The Atlantic Ocean is more than 1,000 miles (1,600 kilometers) distant via the Paraguay, the Paraná, and the Río de la Plata. A...
</Question>
<Choice>Asunción</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital of Colombia, Bogotá lies in a fertile upland basin of the Northern Andes Mountains. The city is laid out in a grid pattern and has a number of plazas surrounded by public buildings and churches. Modern apartment towers stand alongside buildings dating from the colonial period.
</Question>
<Choice>Bogotá</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On April 21, 1960, the capital of Brazil was moved from Rio de Janeiro, on the South Atlantic coast, to Brasília, a completely new and preplanned city 600 miles (960 kilometers) to the northwest. Brasília is located within the 2,248-square-mile (5,822-square-kilometer) Federal District on Brazil's Central Plateau. The headwaters of the Tocantins...
</Question>
<Choice>Brasília</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital of the country, Buenos Aires is also Argentina's leading city in population, commerce, and industry. It is located near the Atlantic Ocean coast, on the broad Río de la Plata, an estuary at the mouth of the Paraná and Paraguay rivers. The early Spanish colonists named the city for the “good winds” that brought them to the port. Today...
</Question>
<Choice>Buenos Aires</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital of Venezuela is Caracas, a city that sprawls across an elevated valley just 7 miles (11 kilometers) from the Caribbean Sea. Caracas has long been called one of the more modern and cosmopolitan of Latin American cities, but, as is common in the region, many residents are mired in poverty, and slums cling to many of the hillsides.
</Question>
<Choice>Caracas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital city of Guyana, Georgetown is also the nation's chief port. Located on the Atlantic Ocean, on the northern coast of South America at the mouth of the Demerara River, Georgetown is the main commercial and manufacturing center of Guyana. It exports sugar, rice, and tropical fruits as well as timber, balata (a product made by drying tree...
</Question>
<Choice>Georgetown</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The highest government seat in the world is La Paz, Bolivia. It lies between 10,650 and 13,250 feet (3,250 and 4,040 meters) above sea level in a deep gorge cut in the Altiplano (high plain) by the Río de La Paz (also known as the Choqueyapu River), roughly 42 miles (68 kilometers) southeast of Lake Titicaca. La Paz (“peace” in Spanish) is Bolivia...
</Question>
<Choice>La Paz</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Lima is the largest city and capital of Peru. It lies on the south bank of the Rímac River, about 8 miles (13 kilometers) inland from the Pacific Ocean port of Callao, and has an area of 27 square miles (70 square kilometers). Lima lies at an altitude of 500 feet (152 meters) above sea level, near the center of the arid Peruvian coastal plain...
</Question>
<Choice>Lima</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital and largest city of Uruguay, Montevideo lies at the mouth of the Río de la Plata on the northern shore. The small peninsula that the city occupies encloses a natural harbor on the Atlantic Ocean.
</Question>
<Choice>Montevideo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The oldest of all South American capitals, Quito is the capital and second largest city of Ecuador. It is also the capital of the northern Pichincha province. Situated at an elevation of 9,350 feet (2,850 meters), the city occupies a thin valley in the Andes Mountains. The city lies on the slopes of the Pichincha volcano, which began erupting in...
</Question>
<Choice>Quito</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Widely considered one of the world's most beautiful and fascinating cities, Rio de Janeiro is Brazil's second largest city and the capital of Rio de Janeiro estado, or state. Often simply called Rio, it lies at the entrance to Guanabara Bay along a strip of Brazil's Atlantic coast that runs east to west. Fronted by miles of beaches, the city is...
</Question>
<Choice>Rio de Janeiro</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital and largest city of Chile, Santiago is also the capital of the Metropolitan Region of Santiago. Covering an area of more than 100 square miles (259 square kilometers), Greater Santiago contains nearly a third of the country's total population.
</Question>
<Choice>Santiago</Choice>
</item>
</topics>