<topics>
<item>
<Question>
Although Alabama has no official nickname the state has been associated with the slogan the Heart of Dixie. This slogan symbolized Alabama's central location in the Deep South and its status as the birthplace of the Confederacy, which tried to preserve the Old South's plantation economy. Before the American Civil War, the warmer climate “away...
</Question>
<Choice>Alabama</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The last American frontier, Alaska is the largest of the states in size and the third smallest in population. Nearly everything about this 49th state is big. Its Mount McKinley is higher than any other peak in North America. Its Yukon River is one of the longest navigable waterways in the world. Huge animals still thrive in its open spaces—Kodiak...
</Question>
<Choice>Alaska</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The Grand Canyon State is a combination of the changeless past and the volatile present. On lonely mesa tops high above the plains are Native American villages where ancient rituals are still observed, their origins lost in the mists of time. The modern-day counterparts of tribal medicine men, Lowell Observatory scientists, use the most advanced...
</Question>
<Choice>Arizona</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In pioneer days Arkansas was known as the Bear State. Then the Native Americans who first farmed and hunted the land were driven westward, and the sloths (packs) of brown bears began to disappear too—along with the once-abundant bison, panthers, and wolves. Now numerous bears again roam the forested hills of Arkansas and leave their tracks in the...
</Question>
<Choice>Arkansas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Virtually every kind of climate, landform, vegetation, and animal life that can be found anywhere else in the United States can be found in California, the Golden State. The third largest state stretches for more than 800 miles (1,290 kilometers) along the Pacific coast. It meets the sea with sandy beaches and rugged cliffs. Inland, past wooded...
</Question>
<Choice>California</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The majestic peaks of Colorado reach out so high that the average elevation of the state is more than a mile above sea level, making it the highest of all the states. More than 800 of these peaks rise above 10,000 feet (3,000 meters), and more than 50 of them are at least 14,000 feet (4,267 meters) high. Part of the Continental Divide, Colorado's...
</Question>
<Choice>Colorado</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American history is deeply rooted in Connecticut, one of the 13 original states. It is known as the Constitution State because the set of laws by which the first settlers agreed to govern themselves—the Fundamental Orders of Connecticut (1639)—embodied the first laws that recognized the people as the real basis of civil authority. This principle...
</Question>
<Choice>Connecticut</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On Dec. 7, 1787, Delaware became the first of the 13 original colonies to ratify the federal Constitution. Since that historic event, Delaware has been known as “The First State” of the Union. The state is named after Baron De La Warr, or Warre, a colonial governor in the early 1600s. Delaware is bounded by Pennsylvania and Maryland. To the east...
</Question>
<Choice>Delaware</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Florida is a playground for millions of sunseekers—snowbirds, beachcombers, college students on spring break, sports fans who watch and play outdoor games. Its low-lying peninsula probes deep into warm southern seas. Along its coasts, seemingly endless white-sand beaches meet the incoming surf. Inland, thousands of freshwater lakes nestle in...
</Question>
<Choice>Florida</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Few states of the Deep South have met the challenges of change with the resourcefulness and success of Georgia. For decades the state remained heavily dependent upon a single crop—cotton. Before the American Civil War, the landscape had been dominated by the lavish plantations of slaveholders. Gradually they were either abandoned or broken up...
</Question>
<Choice>Georgia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Millions of years ago fiery basalt rock erupted through a crack in the floor of the Pacific Ocean. Gradually the lava cooled and formed great undersea mountains whose summits protruded from the ocean. Over the centuries the action of wind, water, fire, and ice on the chain of volcanic peaks created the islands that became the state of Hawaii—a...
</Question>
<Choice>Hawaii</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The people of Idaho call their state the Gem of the Mountains, and there is a wild, spectacular beauty in the swift rivers, evergreen forests, and steep waterfalls and canyons that break its lofty mountain ranges. Most of Idaho lies in the rugged highlands of the Rocky Mountains. Within the forested region are two of the longest rivers in the...
</Question>
<Choice>Idaho</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
As the early pioneers moved westward, the barren Illinois landscape—periodically burned off by Native Americans to drive out game—was their first encounter with long stretches of treeless plains. The flat grassland that the 19th-century settlers called the Prairie State has been transformed into one of the most vital sections of the North...
</Question>
<Choice>Illinois</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
From the wooded green hill country along the Ohio River to the stretches of sandy dunes on Lake Michigan's south shore, Indiana is a state of striking contrasts. In this state, which calls itself the Crossroads of America, a 19th-century covered bridge on a lonely road in Parke County is minutes away from the junction of four superhighways at...
</Question>
<Choice>Indiana</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
According to a Native American legend, Iowa was named by a party of Sauk and Fox who had ventured across the Mississippi in search of fresh hunting grounds. Spellbound by the splendor of the new land, their chief claimed it with his spear and proclaimed something that sounded like Iowa. The actual source of the name, however, is still debated...
</Question>
<Choice>Iowa</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
When the Kansas-Nebraska Act (1854) created two new federal territories, the doctrine of popular (or squatter) sovereignty became the law of their land. Suddenly slavery was no longer prohibited north of the border set by the Missouri Compromise, and the early settlers, rather than the United States Congress, had the right to determine their...
</Question>
<Choice>Kansas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
When Daniel Boonefirst hunted in the Kentucky wilderness in 1767, herds of bison roamed the grassy areas and its forests offered a seemingly unlimited supply of bear, deer, and wild turkey. Two years later he returned with some companions to hunt and trap in this lush, wild country, which he called a “second paradise.” Many others had explored...
</Question>
<Choice>Kentucky</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the most favorably located states in the nation, Louisiana stands astride the mouth of the mighty Mississippi River on the Gulf of Mexico. To the north lies the vast basin of the Mississippi, one of the richest river valleys in the world. To the south, across the Gulf, are the growing markets of Central and South America. This location has...
</Question>
<Choice>Louisiana</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The great natural assets of Maine, the most northeastern state in the United States, are its woods and its waters. More than four fifths of Maine is covered with forests. The land surface is dotted with lakes and rivers, while the Atlantic Ocean washes the state's rocky shoreline, with its hundreds of islands, inlets, and harbors. Although a...
</Question>
<Choice>Maine</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
When the first United States census was taken in 1790, the center of population was found to be in Maryland. The state is often called “America in miniature.” Its geography and history have given it the ways of the North, the South, the East, and the West. Within its borders are the shorelines and river valleys, the rolling upland hills and...
</Question>
<Choice>Maryland</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Much of the heritage of the United States is embodied in Massachusetts. The windswept seacoast of this small northeastern state may have been the first part of what is now the United States seen by Europeans. Norse explorers probably landed on Cape Cod more than 1,000 years ago. The Mayflower colonists who reached Plymouth in December...
</Question>
<Choice>Massachusetts</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
When the Algonquian Indian tribes greeted the first Europeans in the land of the Great Lakes, Michigan's two peninsulas were deeply forested. Underground lay rich stores of iron and copper. Trappers and traders, lumbermen and miners, in turn exploited the land's resources. The magnificent forest became acres of stump and stubble. Beaver, foxes...
</Question>
<Choice>Michigan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The natural landscape of Minnesota is etched in valleys, prairies, wilderness areas, high bluffs, rocky shores, and thousands and thousands of lakes. For most of its people, the Land of the Sky-Blue Waters is a huge playground—dotted with romantic place-names like Ah-Gwah-Ching (Chippewa for “out-of-doors”) and Blooming Prairie and Minnetonka...
</Question>
<Choice>Minnesota</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In the last few decades of the 20th century Mississippi was uplifted by greater change than any other state. The significant efforts of government and the business community to alter the socioeconomic patterns of the past created a brighter image for the Magnolia State. A succession of progressive governors led Mississippi—once identified as a...
</Question>
<Choice>Mississippi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The middle-of-the-road state of Missouri stands nearly midcenter in the coterminous United States. It shares its borders with eight states of the Midwest, South, and Southwest—Kansas, Nebraska, Iowa, Illinois, Kentucky, Tennessee, Arkansas, and Oklahoma.
</Question>
<Choice>Missouri</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Even in the 1860s Native Americans still considered Montana their promised land. This vast region, which they called the Land of the Shining Mountains, was the hunting ground for great herds of buffalo—their mainstay for meat, hides, and the bones used to fashion tools and utensils. Before the wide-spread slaughter of the animals for sport, the...
</Question>
<Choice>Montana</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Transportation routes and rich soil have been keys to both the history and the prosperity of the Cornhusker State. First rivers, then overland trails, and finally railroads and highways opened new parts of Nebraska for settlement. Today the rolling plains of eastern Nebraska support both farms and cities, great fields of wheat and corn cover the...
</Question>
<Choice>Nebraska</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the largest but least populated states in the United States, Nevada ranks seventh in size but 35th in population. It is among the most mountainous of the 50 states. It also has vast desert areas. Part of Nevada's interior is so desolate that it is used as a testing range for nuclear devices. Other areas attract so many visitors that...
</Question>
<Choice>Nevada</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A small, mountainous, heavily forested state of the northeastern United States, New Hampshire is rich in the history and traditions that formed the nation. So firmly is independence rooted here that the state constitution asserts the right of revolution.
</Question>
<Choice>New Hampshire</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
One of the smallest states in size, New Jersey is one of the largest in population. Although it ranks only 46th in area, its more than 8 million people make it the ninth largest state in population. Some nine tenths of this total live in cities and towns, one of the highest percentages of any state. For every square mile New Jersey has an average...
</Question>
<Choice>New Jersey</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In present-day New Mexico the past and the future meet. Here stand the ruins of ancient cliff dwellings, not far from space-research installations that are triumphs of up-to-the-minute technology. Near Alamogordo, where the world's first atom bomb was exploded, Native American drums and the bells of old Spanish missions can still be heard.
</Question>
<Choice>New Mexico</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
New York holds a preeminent position among the 50 states of the nation. Its great metropolis and seaport, New York City, is the largest city in the United States. Long regarded as the cultural and financial capital of the country, the city was the first political capital of the newborn nation. Tradition holds that in 1784—five years before George...
</Question>
<Choice>New York</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The richly varied economy of North Carolina is based on the state's fertile farms, its mixture of traditional manufacturing and high-technology industries, and tourism. The state has a wide variety of soils, and the land supports small truck farms as well as broad grazing areas for beef and dairy cattle. Since more than half of the state is...
</Question>
<Choice>North Carolina</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Midway along the border between the United States and Canada lies the plains state of North Dakota. There the level prairies stretch out to the horizon. Only widely scattered farms and towns rise up to break the severe beauty of the far-reaching plains that had been the buffalo-hunting grounds of many tribes of Native Americans.
</Question>
<Choice>North Dakota</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In many ways Ohio is typical of the United States as a whole. Its earliest settlers came from both the North and the South, and the great diversity of European immigrants attracted to Ohio has helped create an ethnically mixed culture. A state in which agriculture was typically paramount 150 years ago, it now represents the urbanized...
</Question>
<Choice>Ohio</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Many fossilized remnants of prehistoric America are preserved in a creek bed in Oklahoma's western Panhandle, where huge footprints mark the presence of the dinosaurs that trampled through ancient tropical forests 200 million years ago. The early Indian cultures that developed in the region at least 10,000 years ago also left behind some traces...
</Question>
<Choice>Oklahoma</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
“Fifty-four Forty or Fight!” was the Democratic slogan in the 1844 presidential campaign. The figure referred to 54 degrees 40 minutes north latitude (54°?40'?N.)—the proposed northern boundary of the lush Pacific Northwest, which had been coveted by Spain, Russia, Britain, and the United States.
</Question>
<Choice>Oregon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Few states can equal Pennsylvania's wealth of natural resources, its diversity of landscape, or its contributions to United States history. Pennsylvania's traditions of civil and religious freedom have attracted people of many lands. Their labors have turned the state's resources into vast industries.
</Question>
<Choice>Pennsylvania</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The smallest state in the Union, Rhode Island has nevertheless made history through the courage and convictions of its citizens. It was one of the 13 original colonies, settled by religious refugees under the leadership of Roger Williams, who had been banished from the neighboring Massachusetts Bay Colony. More liberal in its views than most of...
</Question>
<Choice>Rhode Island</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The leading state of the Old South, and once predominantly agricultural, South Carolina today has become an industrial leader of the New South. A state with a turbulent history, it was a major battleground of the American Revolution and suffered severely during the American Civil War—a conflict into which it led the other Southern states in its...
</Question>
<Choice>South Carolina</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Where the Missouri River courses through central South Dakota, the prairies of the Midwest meet the grasslands of the Western plains. East of the Missouri—or “east river,” as South Dakotans say—lie flat, fertile farmlands of oats, hay, flaxseed, and corn. In “west river,” rolling pasturelands are dominated by cattle ranches. In the far west rise...
</Question>
<Choice>South Dakota</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Bordered by eight other states, Tennessee cuts a long, narrow path across much of the mid-South. Tennessee has often been thought of as three states in one because of its three so-called grand divisions—each represented by a star in the state flag. Although the citizens of the state share a common heritage and character, these geographical...
</Question>
<Choice>Tennessee</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A giant among states, vast Texas was once a sovereign nation. During 300 years of rule by Spain, it had sprawled like a sleeping giant, its riches undeveloped and its colonization limited to a few missions, supported by presidios (military posts). When Mexico became an independent country in 1821, Texas became a Mexican state and new settlers...
</Question>
<Choice>Texas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
To most of the 19th-century American pioneers who pushed westward in search of pastureland and timberland, the canyon country of Utah offered little promise. The settlement of the bleak region began instead with wagon trains of persecuted exiles who sought a place no one else wanted where they could worship in a nontraditional way. On July...
</Question>
<Choice>Utah</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Vermont has been called a piece of America's past. In no other state has natural beauty been so untouched by modern development. In no other state has the small-town atmosphere of more than a century ago been so well preserved. Often chosen as a comfortable second home by city dwellers, Vermont seemingly has escaped the urban sprawl that has...
</Question>
<Choice>Vermont</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Virginia's place in American history was assured nearly 400 years ago when the first permanent English settlement in North America was established on its shores in 1607 at Jamestown. Just 12 years later, in 1619, the state of the colony was solidified when Jamestown became the meeting place of the first representative assembly in the New World...
</Question>
<Choice>Virginia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Although its borders enclose an area greater than that of all New England, Washington is the smallest of the Pacific seaboard states. With the exception of California and Hawaii, it is more densely populated than any other Western state. Each year its permanent residents are outnumbered two to one by out-of-state visitors—and many of these...
</Question>
<Choice>Washington</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Until the American Civil War, there was no such place as West Virginia. The area was known only as the western part of Virginia. From the time that Virginia became the 10th state in the Union, in 1788, up to the beginning of the war, in 1861, the ideological division between the two regions became as well defined and as impenetrable as the...
</Question>
<Choice>West Virginia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
“America's Dairyland” is the slogan on Wisconsin's license plates. Among the state's credentials for the title is a history of being one of the country's leaders in dairy production, surpassed only by California, and in most milk products since shortly after the first cheese factory was opened in the state in 1864. Although the farm economy in...
</Question>
<Choice>Wisconsin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The first area in the country to be set aside from commercial exploitation was Yellowstone National Park, most of which lies within the Wyoming rectangle. The park was created in 1872, when Wyoming was still a territory. The natural grandeur of the 44th state in the Union was further recognized in 1906 with the designation of the first national...
</Question>
<Choice>Wyoming</Choice>
</item>


<Chapter>Wetlands</Chapter>
<item>
<Question>
The Greek equivalent to the English letter D is the letter ?, called delta. The ancient Greek historian Herodotus used the letter's name to describe the similarly shaped low-lying plains at the mouth of the Nile River, in Egypt. The term is now applied to any plain composed of sediment deposited at the mouth of a river. Many such deltas are...
</Question>
<Choice>delta</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
A vast area of land and water in southern Florida, the Everglades cover about 4,000 square miles (10,000 square kilometers). Through this marshy region water moves slowly from the lip of Lake Okeechobee to mangrove swamps bordering the Gulf of Mexico and Florida Bay. On the east the marsh reaches near the Greater Miami metropolitan area.
</Question>
<Choice>Everglades</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Wetlands are usually classified as swamps, marshes, or bogs, according to the type of soil and plant life they contain. Swamps and marshes both occur in low-lying areas near rivers or on flat areas along coasts between the high and low watermarks. Both swamps and marshes have mineral soils because they have access to mineral-rich groundwater. The...
</Question>
<Choice>swamp, marsh and bog</Choice>
</item>
</topics>