<topics>
<item>
<Question>
The capital and only port of entry of the island-state of Barbados, Bridgetown is located on the southwestern end of the island, on the wide curve of Carlisle Bay. A built-up coastal strip, including a deepwater harbor for commercial shipping, stretches for several miles on each side of the town. Sugar refining and rum distilling, together with...
</Question>
<Choice>Bridgetown</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
capital city and main port of the island of Saint Lucia in the eastern Caribbean Sea, lying 40 mi (65 km) south of Fort-de-France, Martinique; landlocked, deep-water harbor is on the northwestern coast of Saint Lucia; ships mainly bananas but also exports sugarcane, rum, molasses, cacao, coconuts, copra, limes and lime juice, essential oils, bay...
</Question>
<Choice>Castries</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Cuba's capital and largest city, Havana, is a commercial and industrial center and the focus of Cuba's economic, cultural, social, and political life. It lies on the northwestern coast of Cuba in the Gulf of Mexico. Its landlocked harbor is less than 100 miles (160 kilometers) south of Key West, Fla. Its location in the tropical zone gives it a...
</Question>
<Choice>Havana</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital and chief port of Jamaica, Kingston sprawls along the island's southeastern coast. The city is backed by the Blue Mountains and is famous for its fine natural harbor. The harbor is protected by a narrow peninsula that has been widely developed as a resort.
</Question>
<Choice>Kingston</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital, chief port, and commercial center of the West Indian republic of Haiti, Port-au-Prince is also the capital of Haiti's Ouest département. On a magnificent bay of the Gulf of Gonâve, the city is surrounded with natural beauty.
</Question>
<Choice>Port-au-Prince</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
capital and chief town, on the s.w. coast of the island, at the mouth of the Roseau River; rebuilt after almost total destruction by Hurricane David in 1979; chief port; secondary airport; limes, essential oils, tropical vegetables, spices; Roman Catholic Cathedral, St. George's Church (Anglican), Government House, Victoria Memorial Museum; pop...
</Question>
<Choice>Roseau</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
capital, on the s.w. coast of the island; founded by French in 1650; capital of all British Windward Islands 1885–1958; site of fighting during U.S. invasion Oct. 1983; main port; yachting and charter-boat center of the Caribbean; cacao, nutmeg, bananas, sugar processing, rum distilling; Fort George, Government House; pop. 7,500 ,
</Question>
<Choice>Saint George's</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital and largest city of the island commonwealth of Puerto Rico, San Juan is a major Caribbean port and tourist resort. It is located on a well-protected harbor on the island's northern coast. The oldest city under the United States flag, it occupies part of a small island separated from the remainder of Puerto Rico by San Juan Bay and...
</Question>
<Choice>San Juan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The capital and largest city of the Dominican Republic, Santo Domingo is the oldest permanent city established by Europeans in the Western Hemisphere. The city is situated on the Ozama River on the southeastern coast of Hispaniola.
</Question>
<Choice>Santo Domingo</Choice>
</item>
</topics>