<topics>
<item>
<Question>
Berber caliph of the Almohad dynasty (reigned 1130–63), who conquered the North African Maghrib from the Almoravids andbrought all the Berbers under one rule.
</Question>
<Choice>Abd al-Mu'min</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Marinid sultan of Morocco (reigned 1331–51) who increased the territories of his dynasty and, for a brief time, created a united North African empire.In 1331 Abu al-?asan succeeded his father, Abu Sa?id, to the throne. With the goals of expelling the Christians from Spain and uniting all the Islamic lands of North Africa, Abu al-?asan attacked and captured Algeciras and Gibraltar in Spain (1333). He next attacked the Algerian territories of the ?Abd al-Wadid dynasty and after a three-year siege took the strategic town of Tlemcen (1337). Taking advantage of the internal weakness of Spain, he wo...
</Question>
<Choice>Abu al-Hasan 'Ali</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German king from May 5, 1292, to June 23, 1298, when he was deposed in favour of his Habsburg opponent, Albert I.Adolf, who was count of Nassau from 1277 and a mercenary soldier of repute, was chosen king at Frankfurt by the German electors, who preferred him to Albert as successor to Albert's father, Rudolf I, the first Habsburg king. After his coronation at Aachen on June 24, 1292, Adolf had to face exorbitant demands by his electors and the hostility of Albert, who as duke of Austria commanded great financial and territorial resources.Adolf seized Meissen as a vacant fief and purchased the...
</Question>
<Choice>Adolf</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the first king of Portugal (1139–85), who conquered Santarém and Lisbon from the Muslims (1147) and secured Portuguese independence from Leon (1139).Alfonso VI, emperor of Leon, had granted the county of Portugal to Afonso's father, Henry of Burgundy, who successfully defended it against the Muslims (1095–1112). Henry married Alfonso VI's illegitimate daughter, Teresa, who governed Portugal from the time of her husband's death (1112) until her son Afonso came of age. She refused to cede her power to Afonso, but his party prevailed in the Battle of São Mamede, near Guimarães (1128). Though at f...
</Question>
<Choice>Afonso I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
fifth king of Portugal (1248–79), who supplanted his brother, King Sancho II, and completed the reconquest of the Algarve from the Muslims.The younger son of Afonso II and Urraeca, daughter of Alfonso VIII of Castile, Afonso emigrated and became, by marriage, count of Boulogne. His elder brother, Sancho II, was deposed by order of the pope, who granted Afonso the crown. He returned to Portugal and was welcomed by the towns and the church. He reconquered the district of Faro in 1249 and shared the former Muslim region of Algarve with Castile.His reign saw the first meeting of the Portuguese Cor...
</Question>
<Choice>Afonso III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
seventh king of Portugal (1325–57).Afonso IV was the son of King Dinis and of Isabella, daughter of Peter II of Aragon. Afonso resented his father's generosity toward two illegitimate sons and in 1320 demanded to be given power, remaining in open revolt until May 1322. His mother reconciled them, but the conflict broke out again. When Dinis died, Afonso succeeded to the throne, but the quarrel was transferred to Castile, which sheltered his half brother. However, when the Marinid sultan of Morocco invaded Spain in 1340, Afonso IV led a force that joined Alfonso XI of Castile in the victory of...
</Question>
<Choice>Afonso IV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
10th king of Portugal (1438–81), known as the African from his campaigns in Morocco.The son of King Edward (Duarte) and Queen Leonor, daughter of King Ferdinand I of Aragon, Afonso succeeded to the throne at the age of six. In 1440 his mother was deprived of the regency by his uncle Pedro, Duke de Coimbra, whose daughter Isabella Afonso married. The regent was in turn challenged by a half brother, the Duke de Bragança, and was forced to fight, dying at Alfarrobeira (May 1449). Afonso remained considerably under the influence of others, and he distributed his favours rashly. In North Africa he...
</Question>
<Choice>Afonso V</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
second wife of the Holy Roman emperor Henry III. She was regent (1056–62) during the minority of her son, the future Henry IV.Agnes was a daughter of William V the Great, duke of Aquitaine, and was a descendant of the kings of Burgundy and Italy. She married Henry III on Nov. 1, 1043, forming an alliance designed to cement the empire's relations with its neighbouring states to the west. On Henry's death she assumed the regency for her son until it was wrested from her by Archbishop Anno of Cologne in 1062. Agnes then retired to a convent, but she remained an important figure in the movement fo...
</Question>
<Choice>Agnes Of Poitou</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
duke of Austria and German king from 1298 to 1308 who repressed private war, befriended the serfs, and protected the persecuted Jews.The eldest son of King Rudolf I of the House of Habsburg, Albert was invested with the duchies of Austria and Styria in 1282. After Rudolf's death (1291), the electors, determined to prevent the German crown from becoming a hereditary possession of the Habsburgs, checked Albert's aspirations by choosing Adolf of Nassau as German king. Albert, however, drew the electors into an alliance and engineered the deposition (June 23, 1298) of Adolf, who was defeated in ba...
</Question>
<Choice>Albert I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German king from 1438, king (Albert) of Hungary, king (Albrecht) of Bohemia, and duke (Albrecht) of Luxembourg. As a member of the Habsburg dynasty he was archduke (Albert V) of Austria from infancy (1404).On the death of his father-in-law, the Holy Roman emperor Sigismund, Albert was crowned king of Hungary (Jan. 1, 1438), elected king of Germany (March 18), and, despite opposition, actually crowned king of Bohemia (June 29). Calling a diet at Nürnberg (1438), he ended all feuds based on the right of private warfare and appointed arbiters to settle disputes. He further divided Germany into ad...
</Question>
<Choice>Albert II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Scotland from 1107 to 1124.The son of King Malcolm III Canmore (reigned 1058–93), Alexander succeeded to the throne upon the death of his brother King Edgar (ruled 1097–1107). In accordance with Edgar's instructions, Alexander allowed his younger brother and heir, David, to rule southern Scotland.Alexander probably acknowledged King Henry I of England as his overlord. He married Henry's illegitimate daughter, Sibylla, and in 1114 he led a Scottish contingent in Henry's Welsh campaigns. Nevertheless, Alexander strove to preserve the independence of the Scottish Church from the English C...
</Question>
<Choice>Alexander I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Scotland from 1214 to 1249; he maintained peace with England and greatly strengthened the Scottish monarchy.Alexander came to the throne on the death of his father, William I (the Lion; reigned 1165–1214). When the English barons rebelled against King John (reigned 1199–1216) in 1215, Alexander sided with the insurgents in the hope of regaining territory he claimed in northern England. After the rebellion collapsed in 1217, he did homage to King Henry III (reigned 1216–72), and in 1221 he married Henry's sister, Joan (d. 1238). In 1237 Henry and Alexander concluded the Peace of York, a...
</Question>
<Choice>Alexander II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Scotland from 1249 to 1286, the last major ruler of the dynasty of kings descended from Malcolm III Canmore (reigned 1058–93), who consolidated royal power in Scotland. Alexander left his kingdom independent, united, and prosperous, and his reign was viewed as a golden age by Scots caught up in the long, bloody conflict with England after his death.The only son of King Alexander II (reigned 1214–49), Alexander III was seven years old when he came to the throne. In 1251 he was married to Margaret (d. 1275), the 11-year-old daughter of England's King Henry III. Henry immediately began pl...
</Question>
<Choice>Alexander III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prince of Novgorod (1236–52) and of Kiev (1246–52) and grand prince of Vladimir (1252–63), who halted the eastward drive of the Germans and Swedes but collaborated with the Mongols in imposing their rule on Russia. By defeating a Swedish invasion force at the confluence of the Rivers Izhora and Neva (1240), he won the name Nevsky, “of the Neva.”Alexander was the son of Yaroslav II Vsevolodovich, grand prince of Vladimir, the foremost among the Russian rulers. In 1236 Alexander was elected prince—a figure who functioned as little more than military commander—of the city of Novgorod. In 1239 he...
</Question>
<Choice>Alexander Nevsky, Saint</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor (1081–1118) at the time of the First Crusade who founded the Comnenian dynasty and partially restored the strength of the empire after its defeats by the Normans and Turks in the 11th century.The third son of John Comnenus and a nephew of Isaac I (emperor 1057–59), Alexius came from a distinguished Byzantine landed family and was one of the military magnates who had long urged more effective defense measures, particularly against the Turks' encroaching on Byzantine provinces in eastern and central Anatolia. From 1068 to 1081 he gave able military service during the short reig...
</Question>
<Choice>Alexius I Comnenus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor from 1180 to 1183. Alexius was the son of Manuel I Comnenus and Maria, daughter of Raymond, prince of Antioch. When his father died on September 24, 1180, Alexius became emperor at the age of 11, with his mother as regent. She, in turn, entrusted the government to her favourite, Manuel's unpopular and incapable nephew Alexius. Because Maria was Latin, she was widely opposed, but plotters, who included Alexius II's sister Maria and her husband, Renier of Montferrat, failed to overthrow the regency. Andronicus I Comnenus, Manuel's cousin, eventually succeeded in deposing the re...
</Question>
<Choice>Alexius II Comnenus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor from 1195 to 1203. He was the second son of Andronicus Angelus, grandson of Alexius I. In 1195 he was proclaimed emperor by the troops; he captured his brother, the emperor Isaac II, at Stagira in Macedonia and had him blinded and imprisoned. Crowned in April 1195, Alexius III was a weak and greedy emperor, and his coup d'état had disastrous results. Byzantine prestige declined in the Balkans, where his failure to aid his son-in-law Stephen Prvovencani (Stephen the First-Crowned) caused the latter to turn to the Bulgars for help. Campaigns against the Bulgars ended in defeat...
</Question>
<Choice>Alexius III Angelus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor from 1203 to 1204. Alexius was the son of Emperor Isaac II. He regained control of his rights to the Byzantine throne with the help of the Fourth Crusade but was deposed soon after by a palace coup.Imprisoned in 1195 with his father (who had been blinded) by Alexius III, he escaped in 1201 and joined his sister and her husband, Philip of Swabia, in Germany. Promising funds, supplies, and troops to conquer Egypt, the maintenance of 500 knights in the Holy Land, and submission of the Byzantine church to Rome, he convinced Philip of Swabia, Crusade leader Boniface of Montferrat,...
</Question>
<Choice>Alexius IV Angelus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor in 1204, son-in-law of Alexius III Angelus. He led a revolt against the coemperors Isaac II and Alexius IV, who were supported by the Fourth Crusade. He then became the last emperor of Byzantium before its overthrow and partition by the Crusaders. In January 1204 Alexius began his four-month reign by imprisoning the deposed Alexius IV, whom he later had strangled. The leader of the anti-Latin party in Constantinople, he disavowed Alexius IV's debt to the Crusaders and demanded their withdrawal from Constantinople. They instead besieged the city, and three days later (April 12...
</Question>
<Choice>Alexius V Ducas Mourtzouphlus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Aragon and of Navarre from 1104 to 1134.Alfonso was the son of Sancho V Ramírez. He was persuaded by Alfonso VI of Leon and Castile to marry the latter's heiress, Urraca, widow of Raymond of Burgundy. In consequence, when Alfonso VI died (1109) the four Christian kingdoms were nominally united and Alfonso I took his father-in-law's imperial title. The union failed, however, because Leon and Castile felt hostility toward an Aragonese emperor; because Urraca disliked her second husband; and because Bernard, the French Cluniac archbishop of Toledo, wanted to see his protégé, Alfonso Ramír...
</Question>
<Choice>Alfonso I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Aragon (1416–58) and king of Naples (as Alfonso I, 1442–58), whose military campaigns in Italy and elsewhere in the central Mediterranean made him one of the most famous men of his day. After conquering Naples, he transferred his court there.
</Question>
<Choice>Alfonso V</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Leon (1065–70) and king of reunited Castile and Leon (1072–1109), who by 1077 had proclaimed himself “emperor of all Spain” (imperator totius Hispaniae). His oppression of his Muslim vassals led to the invasion of Spain by an Almoravid army from North Africa (1086). His name is also associated with the national hero of Spain, Rodrigo Díaz de Vivar (El Cid), who was alternatively his enemy and indifferent supporter.Alfonso was the second son of King Ferdinand I and his wife Sancha; he was educated by Raimundo, later the bishop of Palencia, and by Pedro Ansúrez, the count of Carrión. On...
</Question>
<Choice>Alfonso VI</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Leon and Castile from 1126 to 1157, son of Raymond of Burgundy and the grandson of Alfonso VI, whose imperial title he assumed. Though his reign saw the apogee of the imperial idea in medieval Spain and though he won notable victories against the Moors, he remains a somewhat hazy figure.His childhood was complicated by the struggle between his mother Urraca and her second husband, Alfonso I of Aragon, for control of Castile and Leon. Only on Urraca's death (1126) did his stepfather finally relinquish his claims. Alfonso was then formally accepted as emperor by the kings of Aragon and P...
</Question>
<Choice>Alfonso VII</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Castile from 1158, son of Sancho III, whom he succeeded when three years old.Before Alfonso came of age his reign was troubled by internal strife and the intervention of the kingdom of Navarre in Castilian affairs. Throughout his reign he maintained a close alliance with the kingdom of Aragon, and in 1179 he concluded the Pact of Cazorla, which settled the future line of demarcation between Castile and Aragon when the reconquest of Moorish Spain was completed. From 1172 to 1212 he was engaged in resistance to the Muslim Almohad invaders, who defeated him in 1195. In the same year the k...
</Question>
<Choice>Alfonso VIII</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Leon from 1188 to 1230, son of Ferdinand II of Leon, and cousin of Alfonso VIII of Castile (next to whom he is numbered as a junior member of the family). A forceful personality, Alfonso IX was determined to recover Leonese territory lost to Castile; and, despite the fact that he had done homage to Alfonso VIII, he did not hesitate to ally himself with the Muslim Almohads to further this end. As a result, his kingdom was placed under papal interdiction, and he was finally compelled to marry the Castilian king's eldest daughter. He refused, however, to join his father-in-law in the Crus...
</Question>
<Choice>Alfonso IX</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Castile and Leon from 1252 to 1284.Alfonso's father, Ferdinand III, conquered Andalusia and imposed tribute on the remaining Muslim states in Spain—Murcia and Granada. His mother, Beatrice, was granddaughter of the Holy Roman emperor Frederick I. Alfonso, already known as a scholar, became king in 1252. He had many scholars in his traveling court, and he was an active participant in their writing and editing. Some were experts on Roman law, which Alfonso hoped to make the basis of a uniform code for his lands. The court, gifts to friends, and foreign intrigue proved expensive, and Alfo...
</Question>
<Choice>Alfonso X</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Castile and Leon from 1312, who succeeded his father, Ferdinand IV, when he was only a year old.His minority was marked by violent strife between factions of nobles, but when he came of age, in 1325, he restored order with unprecedented vigour. He gave new powers to the municipalities and to the Cortes, in exchange for their support against the nobles, and furthered the power of the crown by choosing officials without aristocratic affiliations. He then turned his attention to the Marinid kings of Morocco, who had seized Gibraltar and routed the Castilian fleet at Algeciras in 1340. Wit...
</Question>
<Choice>Alfonso XI</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
second sultan of the Seljuq Turks (1063–72), who inherited the Seljuq territories of Khorasan and western Iran and went on to conquer Georgia, Armenia, and much of Asia Minor (won from the Byzantines).Alp-Arslan was the son of Chaghri Beg, the ruler of Khorasan in Iran, and the nephew of Toghrïl, the governor of western Iran, the base of Seljuq expansion. In 1061 his father died. When, in 1063, his uncle died without issue, Alp-Arslan became sole heir to all the possessions of the dynasty except Kerman, in southern Iran, which was held by one of his brothers, whom he promptly reduced to vassal...
</Question>
<Choice>Alp-Arslan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Cyprus (1194–1205) and of Jerusalem (1197–1205) who ably ruled the two separated kingdoms.Amalric had been constable of Palestine before he was summoned by the Franks in Cyprus to become king there after the death of his brother Guy of Lusignan. Amalric planned a close alliance with Henry of Champagne, the uncrowned ruler of Palestine, betrothing his three sons to Henry's three daughters. He also became the vassal of the Holy Roman emperor Henry VI. On Henry of Champagne's accidental death (1197), Amalric, a widower, was induced to marry Henry's widow, Queen Isabella I, because the emp...
</Question>
<Choice>Amalric II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the first king of all of Myanmar, or Burma (reigned 1044–77), who introduced his people to Theravada Buddhism. His capital at Pagan on the Irrawaddy River became a prominent city of pagodas and temples.During his reign Anawrahta united the northern homeland of the Burmese people with the Mon kingdoms of the south. He extended his dominion as far north as the kingdom of Nanchao, west to Arakan, south to the Gulf of Martaban (near what is now Yangon [Rangoon]), and as far east as what is now northern Thailand.In 1057 Anawrahta captured the Mon city of Thaton, a centre of Indian civilization. Its...
</Question>
<Choice>Anawrahta</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prince of Rostov-Suzdal (1157) and grand prince of Vladimir (1169), who increased the importance of the northeastern Russian lands and contributed to the development of government in that forest region.Having accompanied his father, Yury Dolgoruky, on his conquest of Kiev, Andrew refused to remain in the ancient capital of Rus and returned to Vladimir, a town in his father's principality of Rostov-Suzdal in northeastern Russia. When his father died (1157), the cities of Rostov and Suzdal elected Andrew their prince, and he transferred the capital of the entire principality to Vladimir. Subsequ...
</Question>
<Choice>Andrew I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Hungary (1205–35) whose reign was marked by controversy with barons and the great feudatories and by the issuance of the Golden Bull of 1222 (q.v.), which has been called the Hungarian Magna Carta. The son of Béla III, Andrew succeeded László III, his elder brother's son, on the throne in 1205. Powerful landed interests forced Andrew to spend royal funds so recklessly that the crown was soon impoverished and dependent on the feudatories, who soon reduced Hungary to a state of near anarchy. Objecting to the prodigality of the German followers of Andrew's first wife, Gertrude of Meran, r...
</Question>
<Choice>Andrew II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor from 1183 to 1185, the last of the Comnenus dynasty, who attempted to reform the government but whose bitter opposition to Western Christianity precipitated a Norman invasion.A cousin of the emperor Manuel I Comnenus (reigned 1143–80), Andronicus opposed the unpopular regency of the dowager empress Maria of Antioch after Manuel's death. In the spring of 1182 he raised an army and entered Constantinople posing as the protector of the young emperor Alexius II; one of the results of his seizure of power was a massacre of the Westerners living in the city, mostly Pisans and Genoe...
</Question>
<Choice>Andronicus I Comnenus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor who was the son of Michael VIII Palaeologus. During Andronicus's reign (1282–1328) the Byzantine Empire declined to the status of a minor state, confined by the Ottoman Turks in Anatolia and the Serbs in the Balkans.An intellectual and theologian rather than a statesman or soldier, Andronicus weakened Byzantium by reducing its land forces to a few thousand cavalry and infantry and eliminating the navy altogether, relying solely on a Genoese mercenary fleet. His lack of military initiative enabled the Ottoman Turks to gain control of nearly all of Anatolia by 1300, and his emp...
</Question>
<Choice>Andronicus II Palaeologus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor who sought to strengthen the empire during its final period of decline.Andronicus was the grandson of the emperor Andronicus II Palaeologus, but his youthful excesses cost him the favour of his grandfather, and, after he accidentally caused the death of his brother in 1320, the emperor excluded him from the succession. A civil war ensued, with the younger Andronicus enlisting the support of the powerful Byzantine nobility, particularly the wealthy John VI Cantacuzenus; in 1325 Andronicus compelled the old emperor to recognize him as coemperor, with control over the provinces...
</Question>
<Choice>Andronicus III Palaeologus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor from 1376 to 1379. Conspiring against his father, John V Palaeologus, he was imprisoned and deprived of his rights to the succession. John's rivals, the Genoese, however, helped Andronicus to escape, and he entered Constantinople on August 12, 1376, took his father prisoner, and was crowned the following year (October 18, 1377). In 1379, however, it was his father's turn to escape—with Venetian and Turkish aid—and be restored to the throne, on the condition that he recognize Andronicus as his rightful heir and swear allegiance as the vassal of the sultan. After another rebell...
</Question>
<Choice>Andronicus IV Palaeologus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
eldest daughter of Louis XI of France and Charlotte of Savoy, who exercised, with her husband, Pierre de Bourbon, seigneur de Beaujeu, a virtual regency in France from 1483 to 1491, during the early years of the reign of King Charles VIII.Anne's energy, strength of will, cunning, and political sense enabled her to overcome the difficulties threatening the kingdom, the most important of which was unrest among the magnates, who had suffered under Louis XI's callous oppressions. Concessions were made: many of Louis's favourites were sacrificed; lands were restored to hostile nobles, among whom wa...
</Question>
<Choice>Anne Of France</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
81st emperor of Japan; his death in the famous naval Battle of Dannoura (1185) on the Inland Sea in western Japan resulted in the loss of the great sword that was one of the Three Imperial Regalia, the symbols of Imperial authority, supposedly brought to earth when the first Japanese emperor descended from heaven.He was placed on the throne in 1180, at the age of two, by the Taira clan, and assumed the reign name Antoku. Because of his youth, real power resided in the hands of the former emperor Shirakawa and Antoku's grandfather, the renowned warrior Taira Kiyomori. In 1181 the Taira clan was...
</Question>
<Choice>Antoku</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
fourth Mongol Il-Khan (subordinate khan) of Iran (reigned 1284–91). He was the father of the great Ma?mud Ghazan (q.v.).Upon the death of his father, Il-Khan Abagha (reigned 1265–82), Prince Arghun was a candidate for the throne but was forced to yield to a stronger rival, his uncle Tegüder. Arghun thereafter accused Tegüder's followers of having poisoned his father, protested Tegüder's conversion to Islam, and, by the beginning of 1284, was at the head of a rebellion. After some reverses, he succeeded in overthrowing Tegüder and having him executed (Aug. 10, 1284); Arghun was formally enthron...
</Question>
<Choice>Arghun</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English statesman and archbishop of Canterbury who aided the opponents of King Richard II; during the reign of King Henry IV, Arundel vigorously suppressed the Lollards. His father was Richard Fitzalan, 3rd earl of Arundel, and his mother was a member of the powerful House of Lancaster. He became bishop of Ely in 1374, and during the early years of the reign of Richard II he sided with the nobles opposed to the King. This party forced Richard to make Arundel chancellor of England (1386) and archbishop of York (1388) until, in 1389, he was able to throw off control by the nobles and remove Arun...
</Question>
<Choice>Arundel, Thomas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
warrior and statesman who founded the Ashikaga shogunate (hereditary military dictatorship) that dominated Japan from 1338 to 1573.The Ashikaga family became one of the most powerful in Japan during the Kamakura period (1199–1333). They provided leading retainers of the Hojo regents who, with their capital at Kamakura, dominated the country during that time, relegating the emperors to a puppet role in the government. Finally, in 1331, the emperor Go-Daigo (reigned 1318–39) attempted to restore the status of the imperial court by raising a revolt. The uprising was easily quashed, and the empero...
</Question>
<Choice>Ashikaga Takauji</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
shogun (hereditary military dictator) who helped promote one of Japan's greatest cultural eras. His attempts to select an heir, however, brought on a dispute that caused the great Onin War (1467–77). This conflict not only laid waste the area around the capital at Kyoto and destroyed many of its great architectural treasures but also eliminated the fiction of central control over the outlying regions of the country, thus touching off a century of civil warfare.Yoshimasa was proclaimed shogun in 1449 at the age of 13, at a time when central control over the countryside had begun to deteriorate,...
</Question>
<Choice>Ashikaga Yoshimasa</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
shogun (hereditary military dictator) of Japan, who achieved political stability for the Ashikaga shogunate, which had been established in 1338 by his grandfather, Ashikaga Takauji. The period of this shogunate's rule (until 1573) subsequently became known as the Muromachi period after the district of Kyoto in which Yoshimitsu lived.Proclaimed shogun in 1368, Yoshimitsu, in contrast to his father and grandfather, assumed an active role in the imperial bureaucracy. In 1381 he became inner minister, later advancing to the position of minister of the left and, in 1394, minister of state. By the e...
</Question>
<Choice>Ashikaga Yoshimitsu</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
count of Flanders (as Baldwin IX) and of Hainaut (as Baldwin VI), a leader of the Fourth Crusade, who became the first Latin emperor of Constantinople (now Istanbul).The son of Baldwin V, count of Hainaut, and Margaret of Alsace, countess of Flanders, Baldwin I was an ally of the English royal house of the Plantagenets, fighting at the side of Richard I against Philip II Augustus of France. During the Fourth Crusade, which was conceived by Pope Innocent III in 1198, he took part in the installation of the pro-Latin Alexius IV Angelus as emperor in Constantinople in 1203. After Alexius and his...
</Question>
<Choice>Baldwin I (Byzantine emperor)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the Crusader state of Jerusalem (1100–18) who expanded the kingdom and secured its territory, formulating an administrative apparatus that was to serve for 200 years as the basis for Frankish rule in Syria and Palestine.Son of Eustace II, count of Boulogne, and Ida d'Ardenne, Baldwin was the younger brother of Godfrey of Bouillon, whom he accompanied on the First Crusade (1096–99). While Baldwin was campaigning against the Seljuq Turks in Anatolia, Toros, the Christian prince of Edessa (now Urfa, Turkey), promised to make him his heir in return for military aid. Baldwin forced Toros to...
</Question>
<Choice>Baldwin I (king of Jerusalem)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
count of Edessa (1100–18), king of Jerusalem (1118–31), and Crusade leader whose support of the religious-military orders founded during his reign enabled him to expand his kingdom and to withstand Muslim attacks.A son of Hugh, count of Réthel, in the Ardennes region of France, he held the castle of Bourcq as a feudal domain and was at first referred to as Baldwin of Bourcq. He accompanied his cousins Godfrey of Bouillon and Baldwin of Boulogne (later King Baldwin I of Jerusalem) to Palestine with the First Crusade (1096). In 1100 he was named count of Edessa (now Urfa, Turkey) by Baldwin I wh...
</Question>
<Choice>Baldwin II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the last Latin emperor of Constantinople, who lost his throne in 1261 when Michael VIII Palaeologus restored Greek rule to the capital.The son of Yolande, sister of Baldwin I, the first Latin emperor of Constantinople, and Peter of Courtenay, the third Latin emperor, he came to the throne after the death of his brother Robert, the fourth emperor, in 1228. In his minority the regency was entrusted to John of Brienne. During this time, invasions by the Greeks under the emperor John III Ducas Vatatzes at Nicaea and by the Bulgars under Tsar John Asen II substantially reduced the territory of the...
</Question>
<Choice>Baldwin II Porphyrogenitus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Jerusalem (1174–85), called the “leper king” for the disease that afflicted him for most of his short life. His reign saw the growth of factionalism among the Latin nobility that weakened the kingdom during the years when its greatest adversary, the Muslim leader Saladin, extended his influence from Egypt to Syria.Educated by William, archdeacon of Tyre, Baldwin was crowned four days after his father died. Too young at age 13 to rule the kingdom, he was assisted by his kinsman Raymond III, count of Tripoli, who acted as his regent until 1176. Baldwin's health steadily deteriorated, req...
</Question>
<Choice>Baldwin IV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor (976–1025), who extended imperial rule in the Balkans (notably Bulgaria), Mesopotamia, Georgia, and Armenia and increased his domestic authority by attacking the powerful landed interests of the military aristocracy and of the church.The reign of Basil II, widely acknowledged to be one of the outstanding Byzantine emperors, admirably illustrates both the strength and the weakness of the Byzantine system of government. His indomitable and forceful personality and his shrewd statesmanship were offset by the inherent weakness of an imperial autocracy that depended so much on the...
</Question>
<Choice>Basil II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
grandson of Genghis Khan and founder of the Khanate of Kipchak, or the Golden Horde.In 1235 Batu was elected commander in chief of the western part of the Mongol empire and was given responsibility for the invasion of Europe. By 1240 he had conquered all of Russia. In the campaign in central Europe, one Mongol army defeated Henry II, Duke of Silesia (now in Poland), on April 9, 1241; another army led by Batu himself defeated the Hungarians two days later.With Poland, Bohemia, Hungary, and the Danube valley under his control, Batu was poised for the invasion of western Europe when he received n...
</Question>
<Choice>Batu</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
most eminent of the Mamluk sultans of Egypt and Syria, which he ruled from 1260 to 1277. He is noted both for his military campaigns against Mongols and crusaders and for his internal administrative reforms. The Sirat Baybars, a folk account purporting to be his life story, is still popular in the Arabic-speaking world.Baybars was born in the country of the Kipchak Turks on the northern shores of the Black Sea. After the Mongol invasion of their country in about 1242, Baybars was one of a number of Kipchak Turks sold as slaves. Turkish-speaking slaves, who had become the military backbone of m...
</Question>
<Choice>Baybars I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ottoman sultan in 1389–1402 who founded the first centralized Ottoman state based on traditional Turkish and Muslim institutions and who stressed the need to extend Ottoman dominion in Anatolia.In the early years of Bayezid's reign, Ottoman forces conducted campaigns that succeeded in controlling vast Balkan territories. Later, Venetian advances in Greece, Albania, and Byzantium and the extension of Hungarian influence in Walachia and Danubian Bulgaria compelled Bayezid to blockade Constantinople (1391–98), to occupy Tirnova, in what is now Bulgaria (July 1393), and to conquer Salonika (April...
</Question>
<Choice>Bayezid I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
chancellor of England (1155–62) and archbishop of Canterbury (1162–70) during the reign of King Henry II. His career was marked by a long quarrel with Henry that ended with Becket's murder in Canterbury cathedral.
</Question>
<Choice>Becket, Saint Thomas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Hungary (1173–96) under whom Hungary became the leading power of south-central Europe.Béla was educated at the Byzantine court and placed on the throne by force of arms by the Byzantine emperor Manuel I Comnenus in 1173. He made the Hungarian monarchy hereditary by naming his infant son, Imre, his successor. He also made his court among the most brilliant in Europe. Béla adopted Roman Catholicism, sought the assistance of Rome, and established close ties with France. Upon the death of his first wife, Anne of Châtillon, he married Margaret, sister of Philip II Augustus of France. Many l...
</Question>
<Choice>Béla III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Hungary (1235–70) during whose reign the Mongol invasions left three-quarters of Hungary in ruins. He was the son of Andrew II.Routed on the banks of the Sajó River in 1241 by Mongols under Batu Khan, Béla fled to Dalmatia, and for a year the kingdom of Hungary did not exist. So nearly complete was the country's destruction that Hungarians, when referring to total calamity, use the word tatárjárás, meaning Tatar invasion.When the Mongols withdrew because of dynastic troubles, Béla began to reconstruct his realm, a task that occupied the rest of his reign. Particularly difficult was the...
</Question>
<Choice>Béla IV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mongol ruler of the Golden Horde (1257–67), great-grandson of Genghis Khan.The first Mongol ruler to embrace Islam, Berke succeeded to the khanate soon after the death of his brother Batu. His conversion, as well as the rising power of his cousin Hülegü in Persia, led him to seek alliance with the Mamluks of Egypt and resulted in war with Hülegü, conqueror of the Caliphate. He also became involved in the dispute over the great khanate between Kublai and Arigböge. Nominally a suzerain of the great khan, Berke became increasingly autonomous and died virtually independent.
</Question>
<Choice>Berke</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
archbishop-elector of Mainz, imperial chancellor and reformer, who worked unsuccessfully for an increase in the powers of the clerical and lay nobility at the expense of the Holy Roman emperor.Berthold was elected archbishop of Mainz in 1484 and played a leading role in securing the election of Maximilian I, a Habsburg, as king of the Romans (prospective successor to the Holy Roman emperor) in 1486. With his appointment as imperial chancellor in 1493, he pursued a policy of internal reform for the next decade. The reform program presented to Maximilian by the nobility at the Diet of Worms (149...
</Question>
<Choice>Berthold Von Henneberg</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the virtual ruler of Sweden from 1248 until his death.Before 1238 Birger married Ingeborg (d. 1254), the sister of King Erik Eriksson (1222–50), and was created jarl (earl) of Sweden in 1248. When Erik died, leaving no son, Birger obtained the election as king of his own son Valdemar, a minor for whom he acted as regent. He enlisted the support of the church against the magnates and the provincial assemblies and issued the first Swedish national laws developing the concept of the king's peace. He established closer links with Norway and Denmark, confirmed by marriage alliances: his daughter, R...
</Question>
<Choice>Birger Jarl</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
wife of Louis VIII of France, mother of Louis IX (St. Louis), and twice regent of France (1226–34, 1248–52), who by wars and marital alliances did much to secure and unify French territories.Blanche was the daughter of Alfonso VIII of Castile and Eleanor, who was the daughter of Henry II of England. Her grandmother Eleanor of Aquitaine, queen of England, traveled to Spain to take the 11-year-old Blanche to France, where a marriage treaty was concluded with Louis, the young son of King Philip II Augustus. This politically motivated marriage had been arranged by Blanche's uncle, King John of Eng...
</Question>
<Choice>Blanche Of Castile</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prince of Otranto (1089–1111) and prince of Antioch (1098–1101, 1103–04), one of the leaders of the First Crusade, who conquered Antioch (June 3, 1098).The son of Robert Guiscard (the Astute) and his first wife, Alberada, Bohemond was christened Marc but nicknamed after a legendary giant named Bohemond. The nickname proved well taken because physically Bohemond was the ideally tall and strong knight—in the words of a contemporary, “a wonderful spectacle.” His boyhood home was in southern Italy, where his Norman father, Robert, had gone as a mercenary and had risen to the rank of duke of Apulia...
</Question>
<Choice>Bohemond I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
count of Tripoli (1187–1233) and prince of Antioch (1201–16, 1219–33).The younger son of Bohemond III and Orguilleuse, he became count of Tripoli in 1187 and succeeded his father in the principality of Antioch to the exclusion of his nephew Raymond Ruben in 1201. In 1216 Raymond seized control while Bohemond was off in Tripoli, but he was deposed in 1219 and died the following year. Bohemond reigned in Antioch and Tripoli until his own death.
</Question>
<Choice>Bohemond IV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
duke (from 992) and then (from 1024) first king of Poland, who expanded his country's territory to include Pomerania, Lusatia, and, for a time, the Bohemian princely lands. He made Poland a major European state and also created a Polish church independent of German control.The son of Mieszko I, the first of the Piast dukes, and the Bohemian princess Dobrawa (Dubravka), Boleslaw I inherited the principality of Great Poland (Wielkopolska, between the Oder and the Warta rivers) upon his father's death in 992. He soon began, by energetic political and military action, to develop and expand the Pol...
</Question>
<Choice>Boleslaw I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
duke (1058–76) and later king (1076–79) of Poland.Boleslaw assumed the rule of Poland on the death of his father, Casimir I the Restorer, in 1058. During the struggle between the German kings and the papacy, Boleslaw was able to restore the international position of Poland. He helped Béla I to obtain the Hungarian crown (1060) against the Germans' protégé and refused to pay the tribute for Silesia that his father had paid to the Czechs. In 1069 he intervened on behalf of a relative by marriage, Izyaslav, to give him the throne of the principality of Kiev. Boleslaw and Pope Gregory VII had comm...
</Question>
<Choice>Boleslaw II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prince of Poland who introduced into his country the senioriate system, by which the eldest son received the major part of the royal inheritance. He converted the people of Pomerania to Christianity.Son of Wladyslaw I Herman, ruler of Poland, and Judith of Bohemia, Boleslaw III and his illegitimate elder half brother, Zbigniew, each ruled a Polish province during their father's lifetime. Boleslaw III succeeded to his father's princely title (no Polish ruler assumed the title of king from 1082 to 1296) in 1102 and spent the next several years fighting Zbigniew for control of the country. Not lo...
</Question>
<Choice>Boleslaw III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Danish king of England (1016–35), of Denmark (as Canute II; 1019–35), and of Norway (1028–35), who was a power in the politics of Europe in the 11th century, respected by both emperor and pope. Neither the place nor the date of his birth is known.Canute was the grandson of the Polish ruler Mieszko I on his mother's side. As a youth he accompanied his father, Sweyn I Forkbeard, king of Denmark, on his invasion of England in 1013. Canute was left in charge of the fleet at Gainsborough, Lincolnshire, and it was probably then that he met Aelfgifu, daughter of an ealdorman (chief officer) of Northu...
</Question>
<Choice>Canute</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
martyr, patron saint, and king of Denmark from 1080 to 1086.The son of King Sweyn II Estrithson of Denmark, Canute succeeded his brother Harold Hen as king of Denmark. Canute opposed the aristocracy and kept a close association with the church in an attempt to create a powerful and centralized monarchy. In ecclesiastical matters, Canute generously patronized several churches, including the Cathedral of Lund, Denmark's archbishopric; established a Benedictine abbey at Odense; and supported apostolic preaching throughout Denmark. In temporal matters, he attempted an administrative reform, partic...
</Question>
<Choice>Canute IV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Denmark (coregent, 1170–82; king, 1182–1202), during whose reign Denmark withdrew from the Holy Roman Empire and extended its dominion along the southern Baltic coast to Pomerania, Mecklenburg, and Holstein. Canute's role in the Danish expansion was overshadowed by that of his more active brother Valdemar, duke of Schleswig (later king as Valdemar II), and of the Danish archbishop Absalon.The son of the Danish king Valdemar I, Canute was anointed as coregent with his father in 1170, beginning the hereditary reign of the Valdemar dynasty. He succeeded to the throne in 1182 and, at the i...
</Question>
<Choice>Canute VI</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Poland from 1333 to 1370, called “the Great” because he was deemed a peaceful ruler, a “peasant king,” and a skillful diplomat. Through astute diplomacy he annexed lands from western Russia and eastern Germany. Within his realm he unified the government, codified its unwritten law, endowed new towns with the self-government of the Magdeburg Law, and founded Poland's first university, at Kraków, in 1364.Casimir was the second king of the reunited and resuscitated Poland that for nearly two centuries had been split into numerous small principalities. His father, Wladyslaw I, who had succ...
</Question>
<Choice>Casimir III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
grand duke of Lithuania (1440–92) and king of Poland (1447–92), who, by patient but tenacious policy, sought to preserve the political union between Poland and Lithuania and to recover the lost lands of old Poland. The great triumph of his reign was the final subjugation of the Teutonic Knights (1466).Casimir was the second son of Wladyslaw II Jagiello and his fourth wife, Zofja Holszanska. His father was already over 75 at Casimir's birth, and his brother Wladyslaw III, three years his senior, was expected to become king before his majority. Casimir was thus the second in succession to the th...
</Question>
<Choice>Casimir IV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the second son of Genghis Khan who, at his father's death, received Kashgaria (now the southern part of Uygur Autonomous Region of Xinjiang, China) and most of Transoxania between the Amu Darya and the Syr Darya (ancient Oxus and Jaxartes rivers, respectively) as his vassal kingdom. His capital was at Almarikh near present-day Kuldja (Yining), in western Xinjiang. Chagatai appears to have been a just and energetic ruler for about 14 years. Although it is recorded that he left numerous children, he was succeeded by a grandson, Kara Hülegü.
</Question>
<Choice>Chagatai</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
courtly, pious king of Hungary who restored his kingdom to the status of a great power and enriched and civilized it.Charles was the son of Charles Martel of Anjou-Naples and Clemencia of Habsburg, daughter of the Holy Roman emperor Rudolf I. As great-grandson of Stephen V and with papal approval, Charles claimed the Hungarian throne after the death of Andrew III, the last of the Árpád line, and was crowned in 1301. When his claim was disputed, however, he was forced to surrender the crown to Wenceslas of Bohemia, who in 1305 transferred his right to Otto, duke of Lower Bavaria. After Otto was...
</Question>
<Choice>Charles I (king of Hungary)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Naples and Sicily (1266–85), the first of the Angevin dynasty, and creator of a great but short-lived Mediterranean empire.The younger brother of Louis IX of France, Charles acquired the county of Provence in 1246 and accompanied Louis on his Egyptian Crusade (1248–50). Allied with the papacy, he conquered Naples and Sicily in the 1260s, defeating Manfred and Conradin, the last representatives of the Hohenstaufen dynasty, at Benevento (1266) and Tagliacozzo (1268). He thereafter expanded his power into the Balkans and in 1277 became heir to the Kingdom of Jerusalem. Charles's transfer...
</Question>
<Choice>Charles I (king of Naples and Sicily)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Navarre from 1349, who made various short-lived attempts to expand Navarrese power in both France and Spain.He was the son and successor of Joan of France, queen of Navarre, and Philip, count of Évreux. Married in 1352 to Joan, daughter of John II of France, he demanded Champagne, Brie, and Angoulême as fiefs once held by his mother. Because John had granted these to the constable of France, Charles of La Cerda, Charles II's supporters assassinated the constable (1354); but, since Charles II was meanwhile negotiating with the English, John had to make terms with him, ceding extensive l...
</Question>
<Choice>Charles II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of France and of Navarre (as Charles I) from 1322, the last of the direct line of the Capetian dynasty; his inglorious reign was marked by his invasion of Aquitaine and by political intrigues with his sister Isabella, wife of King Edward II of England.After the death of his brother Philip V in 1322, Charles ignored Philip's daughter and successfully claimed the throne for himself. Among his first political intrigues as king were to bid for the German throne and to intervene in Flanders, hoping to bring that territory under the French crown; both ventures failed.Charles also renewed war wi...
</Question>
<Choice>Charles IV (king of France)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German king and king of Bohemia (as Charles) from 1346 to 1378 and Holy Roman emperor from 1355 to 1378, one of the most learned and diplomatically skillful sovereigns of his time. He gained more through diplomacy than others did by war, and through purchases, marriages, and inheritance he enlarged his dynastic power. Under Charles's rule Prague became the political, economic, and cultural centre—and eventually the capital—of the Holy Roman Empire. Indeed, from his reign until the 18th century it was understood that the German imperial crown was based on the crown of the king of Bohemia.
</Question>
<Choice>Charles IV (Holy Roman emperor)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of France from 1364 who led the country in a miraculous recovery from the devastation of the first phase of the Hundred Years' War (1337–1453), reversing the disastrous Anglo-French settlement of 1360.Having purchased the Dauphiné (on France's southeastern frontier) in 1349, Charles bore the title of dauphin until his coronation. After his father, King John II the Good, was captured by the English at Poitiers in 1356, Charles, in order to raise his father's ransom money, had to convene a hostile States General, which, led by Étienne Marcel, provost of the Paris merchants, forced him to is...
</Question>
<Choice>Charles V</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of France who throughout his long reign (1380–1422) remained largely a figurehead, first because he was still a boy when he took the throne and later because of his periodic fits of madness.Crowned on October 25, 1380, at Reims at the age of 11, Charles remained under the tutelage of his uncles until his declaration to rule alone in 1388. During those early years France was ruled by his uncles and their creation, the administrative Council of 12. Philip the Bold of Burgundy conducted the council from 1382. The marriage of Isabella of Bavaria to Charles (July 17, 1385) was arranged by Phil...
</Question>
<Choice>Charles VI</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of France from 1422 to 1461, who succeeded—partly with the aid of Joan of Arc—in driving the English from French soil and in solidifying the administration of the monarchy. Before ascending the throne he was known as the Dauphin and was regent for his father, Charles VI, from 1418.
</Question>
<Choice>Charles VII</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of France from 1483, known for beginning the French expeditions into Italy that lasted until the middle of the next century.The only son of Louis XI and Charlotte of Savoy, Charles showed no aptitude for government at the time of his accession: he was in poor health and of poor intelligence. Though he was legally of age, the government in the first years of his reign was in the hands of a regency comprising his sister Anne and her husband Pierre de Bourbon, seigneur de Beaujeu. After his marriage to Anne of Brittany in 1491, however, Charles was persuaded by his favourite, Étienne de Vesc...
</Question>
<Choice>Charles VIII</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
reign name (nianhao) of the sixth and eighth emperor (reigned 1435–49 and 1457–64) of the Ming dynasty (1368–1644), whose court was dominated by eunuchs who weakened the dynasty by a disastrous war with Mongol tribes. In 1435 Zhu Qizhen ascended the throne and became known as the Zhengtong emperor, with his mother, the empress, as regent. He soon placed his confidence in the eunuch Wang Zhen (died 1449), who came to dominate the government. By the time the emperor came of age, Mongol power had revived under the leadership of Esen Taiji, a chief of the Oyrat branch. In 1449 Wang mismanaged a ca...
</Question>
<Choice>Cheng-t'ung</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
reign name (nianhao) of the second emperor of the Ming dynasty (1368–1644), under whose brief reign (1398–1402) a civil war nearly destroyed the newly founded dynasty.Succeeding to the throne in 1398, Jianwen continued the efforts of his predecessor to erase the Mongol legacies of the previous Yuan dynasty (1206–1368) and to encourage the cultural, intellectual, and technological advances for which the Ming dynasty was to become noted. He met his downfall when he tried to reassert central control over several princedoms within the empire that were ruled by his uncles. This effort provoked a re...
</Question>
<Choice>Chien-wen</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
reign name (nianhao) of the seventh emperor (reigned 1449–57) of the Ming dynasty. He ascended to the throne after his brother, the Zhengtong emperor, was captured while leading the imperial forces against the Oryat (western Mongol) leader Esen Taiji in 1449. When Esen tried to take advantage of his victory and attack the capital at Beijing, Jingtai's defense minister, Yu Qian, drove Esen's forces back into Mongolia. In 1450 Esen released the abducted former emperor.Although his brother returned to China, Jingtai continued to reign. He caused much resentment by setting up his own son, rather t...
</Question>
<Choice>Ching-t'ai</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
temple name (miaohao) of the last emperor (reigned 1125/26–1127) of the Bei (Northern) Song dynasty (960–1127).Zhao Huan became emperor when his father, the Huizong emperor (reigned 1100–1125/26), abdicated in the face of an invasion by the Juchen tribes. The invasion was halted when the Chinese agreed to a large cession of territory and a huge indemnity, but the Juchen renewed their attack two years later, capturing the capital and taking the Qinzong emperor and his father prisoner. Qinzong's brother, Zhao Gou, escaped to South China and founded the Nan (Southern) Song dynasty (1127–1279), ru...
</Question>
<Choice>Ch'in-tsung</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Denmark (1448–81), Norway (1450–81), and Sweden (1457–64, 1465–67), and founder of the Oldenburg dynasty, which ruled Denmark until 1863. He tried to gain control over Sweden and maintain a union of the Scandinavian nations but was defeated by rebellious Swedish nobles (1471).The son of Count Dietrich the Happy of Oldenburg and Hedvig of Holstein, Christian was elected to succeed Christopher III, king of Denmark and Norway, by the Danish Rigsråd (state council) in 1448. The following year he married his predecessor's widow, Queen Dorothea of Hohenzollern. The decision of a meeting of t...
</Question>
<Choice>Christian I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the Danes (1439–48), Swedes (1441–48), and Norwegians (1442–48) whose reign saw a sharp decline in royal power as a result of commercial domination by the north German trading centres of the Hanseatic League and increasing political authority of the Danish and Swedish state councils.The son of John, count of the Upper Palatinate (Germany), Christopher succeeded his maternal uncle Erik of Pomerania as ruler of Denmark, Norway, and Sweden. Erik had been deposed in all three countries when dissident Swedish nobles opposed to his absolutist rule were supported by the Danish state council,...
</Question>
<Choice>Christopher III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1st duke of),second son of King John I of Portugal, younger brother of King Edward, and uncle of Edward's son Afonso V, during whose minority he was regent.The second of the “illustrious generation,” comprising the sons of John I and Philippa of Lancaster, Pedro was present at the conquest of Ceuta from the Muslims in 1415 and later traveled abroad in Europe, encouraging his younger brother Henry the Navigator in his discoveries. King Edward died young, leaving his foreign wife as regent for their young son Afonso V. Pedro successfully challenged her, took over the regency, married his daught...
</Question>
<Choice>Coimbra, Pedro, 1o duque de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Hungary from 1095 who pursued expansionist policies and stabilized and improved the internal order of Hungary.Coloman was the natural son of King Géza I by a Greek concubine. King Ladislas (László), his uncle, would have made him a monk, but Coloman refused and eventually escaped to Poland. On Ladislas' death (1095), Coloman returned to Hungary and seized the crown. His legitimately born half brother, Álmos, continued to plot against the usurpation until 1113, when Coloman imprisoned him and his infant son, Béla, and had them blinded.Though his accession to the throne was irregular, Co...
</Question>
<Choice>Coloman</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German king (1024–39) and Holy Roman emperor (1027–39), founder of the Salian dynasty. During his reign, he proved that the German monarchy had become a viable institution. Since the survival of the monarchy was no longer primarily dependent on a compact between sovereign and territorial nobles, it was henceforth invulnerable to prolonged rebellion on their part.Conrad was the son of Count Henry of Speyer, who had been passed over in his inheritances in favour of a younger brother. Henry was descended, through the marriage of his great-grandfather Conrad the Red to a daughter of Emperor Otto,...
</Question>
<Choice>Conrad II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German king from 1138 to 1152, the first king of the Hohenstaufen family.The son of Frederick I, duke of Swabia, and grandson of Emperor Henry IV, Conrad was appointed duke of Franconia by his uncle, Emperor Henry V, in 1115. In 1116, with his elder brother Frederick II, duke of Swabia, he was left by Henry as regent of Germany. When the Emperor died in 1125 the electors, rejecting the hereditary principle, chose Lothar, duke of Saxony, to succeed him. By the end of the year Frederick and Conrad were in revolt; on Dec. 18, 1127, Conrad was elected antiking at Nürnberg and in June 1128 was crow...
</Question>
<Choice>Conrad III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German king from 1237 and king of Sicily from 1251.The son of Emperor Frederick II and his second wife, Isabella (Yolande) de Brienne, Conrad was heir to the Kingdom of Jerusalem through his mother; he was also invested by his father as duke of Swabia in 1235. At Vienna in February 1237 he was elected king of the Romans in place of his half-brother, Henry VII, who had rebelled against the Emperor in 1235. After Pope Gregory IX excommunicated Frederick II in 1239, Conrad was opposed by a growing papal party in Germany, led by the Archbishops Siegfried of Mainz and Conrad of Cologne. In 1245 Pop...
</Question>
<Choice>Conrad IV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
queen of Sicily (1194–98) and Holy Roman empress-consort (1191–97), whose marriage to a Hohenstaufen gave that German dynasty a claim to the throne of Sicily and whose political skill preserved the throne for her son.The daughter of King Roger II of Sicily, Constance married the future emperor Henry VI in 1186 and was crowned with him in Rome in 1191. On the death of her nephew William II (1189), she claimed the Sicilian throne. The Sicilians, however, supported Tancred of Lecce, her natural nephew, who waged war against her and actually held her prisoner. The death of Tancred (1194) allowed H...
</Question>
<Choice>Constance</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor, coemperor with his brother Basil II from c. 962 to 1025 and sole ruler from 1025 to 1028. He was a pleasure-loving man who allowed the administration to fall into the hands of others. He had no male heir, and on his deathbed he arranged that his second daughter, Zoe, should succeed him and marry the eparch of Constantinople, Romanus III Argyrus.
</Question>
<Choice>Constantine VIII</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor from 1042 to 1055.Constantine owed his elevation to Zoe, the empress of the Macedonian dynasty, who took him as her third husband. Constantine belonged to the civil party, the opponents of the military magnates, and he neglected the defenses of the empire and reduced the army. He spent extravagant sums on luxuries and magnificent buildings and seriously debased the coinage. Rebellions broke out at home and abroad; the Normans were overrunning the Byzantine possessions in south Italy; the Pechenegs (Patzinaks) crossed the Danube River and attacked Thrace and Macedonia; and the...
</Question>
<Choice>Constantine IX Monomachus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor from 1059 to 1067, successor to Isaac I Comnenus.Constantine's accession was a triumph for the civil aristocracy and was unfortunate in that he proved an incapable emperor. He reduced the army and neglected the frontier defenses at a time when the Seljuq Turks were pressing into the eastern provinces; consequently, the sultan Alp Arslan overran Armenia (1064–65) and attacked Caesarea (1067). In 1064 the Hungarians occupied Belgrade, and the Pechenegs (Patzinaks) and Uzes (Kumans) crossed the Danube River and ravaged the Balkan provinces, penetrating into Greece. In Italy the...
</Question>
<Choice>Constantine X Ducas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the last Byzantine emperor (1449–53), killed in the final defense of Constantinople against the Ottoman Turks. He is sometimes referred to as Constantine XII, based on the erroneous idea that Constantine Lascaris was crowned in 1204.Constantine was the fourth son of the emperor Manuel II and his Serbian wife, Helen, of the dynasty of Dragas in Macedonia. He spent his early career with his brothers Theodore and Thomas governing the Byzantine despotate of the Morea (Peloponnese) and completing its recovery from the Franks.When his brother John VIII Palaeologus died childless in 1448, he was proc...
</Question>
<Choice>Constantine XI Palaeologus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
emperor of Japan (1318–39), whose efforts to overthrow the shogunate and restore the monarchy led to civil war and divided the imperial family into two rival factions.
</Question>
<Choice>Daigo, Go-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
ruler of the principalities of Galicia and Volhynia (now in Poland and Ukraine, respectively), who became one of the most powerful princes in east-central Europe.Son of Prince Roman Mstislavich, Daniel was only four years old when his father, who had united Galicia and Volhynia, died in a battle against the Poles (1205). Not until 1221 did Daniel begin to overthrow other pretenders to Roman's succession and assert his authority over Volhynia; and only in 1238 did he finally gain control of Galicia. He then directed his efforts toward enriching his domain, encouraging migrants to settle there,...
</Question>
<Choice>Daniel Romanovich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the last native prince of Gwynedd in northern Wales; he initiated a major rebellion against the English in Wales, and upon his death Wales fell completely under English rule.David's grandfather, Llywelyn ap Iorwerth, had made Gwynedd the centre of Welsh power. After failing to prevent his brother, Llywelyn ap Gruffudd, from becoming sole prince of Gwynedd in 1255, David continued to oppose him during his brother's wars against the English kings Henry III (ruled 1216–72) and Edward I (ruled 1272–1307). In 1277 Edward I rewarded David with lands in northeast Wales. Nevertheless, David was so ang...
</Question>
<Choice>David ap Gruffudd</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
one of the most powerful Scottish kings (reigned from 1124). He admitted into Scotland an Anglo-French (Norman) aristocracy that played a major part in the later history of the kingdom. He also reorganized Scottish Christianity to conform with continental European and English usages and founded many religious communities, mostly for Cistercian monks and Augustinian canons.The youngest of the six sons of the Scottish king Malcolm III Canmore and Queen Margaret (afterward St. Margaret), David spent much of his early life at the court of his brother-in-law King Henry I of England. Through David's...
</Question>
<Choice>David I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Scots from 1329, although he spent 18 years in exile or in prison. His reign was marked by costly intermittent warfare with England, a decline in the prestige of the monarchy, and an increase in the power of the barons.On July 17, 1328, in accordance with the Anglo-Scottish peace treaty of Northampton, the four-year-old David was married to Joanna, sister of King Edward III of England. The boy succeeded his father, Robert I the Bruce, as king of Scots on June 7, 1329. A rival claimant to the Scottish throne, Edward de Balliol, a vassal of Edward III, became de facto king after Edward's...
</Question>
<Choice>David II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
sixth king of Portugal (1279–1325), who strengthened the kingdom by improving the economy and reducing the power of the nobility and the church.The son of Afonso III, Dinis was educated at a court subject to both French and Castilian cultural influences and became a competent poet. He founded the first university in Portugal—in Lisbon—in 1290. A skilled negotiator, Dinis was able to establish with Castile a definitive frontier for Portugal. At home, he made the authority of the crown supreme, intervening in local government, reducing the power of the nobility, and combating the supremacy of th...
</Question>
<Choice>Dinis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prince of Moscow, or Muscovy (1359–89), and grand prince of Vladimir (1362–89), who won a victory over the Golden Horde (Mongols who had controlled Russian lands since 1240) at the Battle of Kulikovo (Sept. 8, 1380).Son of Ivan II the Meek of Moscow (reigned 1353–59), Dmitry became ruler of Muscovy when he was only nine years old; three years later he convinced his suzerain, the great khan of the Golden Horde, to transfer the title grand prince of Vladimir (which had been held by Muscovite princes from 1328 to 1359) from Dmitry of Suzdal to him.In addition to gaining the title grand prince of...
</Question>
<Choice>Dmitry Donskoy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the Scots from 1034 to 1040.Duncan was the grandson of King Malcolm II (ruled 1005–34), who irregularly made him ruler of Strathclyde when that region was absorbed into the Scottish kingdom (probably shortly before 1034). Malcolm violated the established system of succession whereby the kingship alternated between two branches of the royal family. Upon Malcolm's death, Duncan succeeded peacefully, but he soon faced the rivalry of Macbeth, Mormaor (subking) of Moray, who probably had a better claim to the throne. Duncan besieged Durham unsuccessfully in 1039 and in the following year wa...
</Question>
<Choice>Duncan I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Scotland (1093–94), son of Malcolm III and grandson of Duncan I.For many years (1072?–87) Duncan lived as a hostage of the Norman English, allegedly as a confirmation of his father's homage to William I of England. He became king of the Scots while driving out his uncle, Donald Bane, in 1094, an enterprise in which he was helped by some English and Normans. He was killed at the instigation of Donald Bane, possibly at Monthechin, making way for the restoration of Donald Bane.
</Question>
<Choice>Duncan II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Scots from 1097, eldest surviving son of Malcolm III Canmore and Queen Margaret (granddaughter of King Edmund II of England) and thus the first king of the Scots to unite Celtic and Anglo-Saxon blood.As vassal to King William II Rufus of England, he was placed on the Scottish throne to succeed the Celtic, anti-English Donald Bane, his uncle, who was deposed. In 1098 Edgar ceded the Hebrides to Magnus III, king of Norway, who had been raiding the islands. Edgar was a generous benefactor of the church; a contemporary historian (St. Aelred of Rievaulx) called him the equal of Edward the C...
</Question>
<Choice>Edgar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the English from April 23 to Nov. 30, 1016, surnamed “Ironside” for his staunch resistance to a massive invasion led by the Danish king Canute.The son of King Ethelred II the Unready (reigned 978–1016), Edmund defied his father's orders by marrying (1015) the widow of one of the Danish lords then occupying English territory, probably in order to enhance his chances at succession. Nevertheless, when Canute invaded England later in 1015, Edmund raised an army in northern England and ravaged regions that would not rally to his cause.Upon Ethelred's death (April 1016), a small number of co...
</Question>
<Choice>Edmund II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of England from 1042 to 1066. Although he is often portrayed as a listless, ineffectual monarch overshadowed by powerful nobles, Edward preserved much of the dignity of the crown and managed to keep the kingdom united during his reign of 24 years. His close ties to Normandy prepared the way for the conquest of England by the Normans under William, duke of Normandy (later King William I), in 1066.Edward was the son of King Ethelred II (reigned 978–1016) and Emma, daughter of Richard II, duke of Normandy. When the Danes invaded England in 1013, the family escaped to Normandy; the following...
</Question>
<Choice>Edward (king of England [1006-1066])</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Portugal whose brief reign (1433–38) witnessed a strengthening of the monarchy through reform of royal land-grant laws, a continuation of voyages of discovery, and a military disaster in Tangier.A scholarly, sensitive man of high moral character, Edward was known as the philosopher-king and the author of O Leal Conselheiro (“The Loyal Counselor”). He ascended the throne on the death of his father, John I, well schooled in legal principles. Shortly thereafter, Edward promulgated the lei mental (April 8, 1434), which facilitated the recovery of certain previous royal land grants and made...
</Question>
<Choice>Edward (king of Portugal)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
son of King John de Balliol of Scotland and claimant to the title of King of Scots, who was crowned in September 1332. Expelled in December 1332, he was restored in 1333–56, having acknowledged Edward III of England as his lord.Edward inherited only the family lands in France and his father's claim to Scotland. He was kept in England from 1296 (the year of his father's death) to 1315, after which he lived mainly in France. In 1332 Balliol led an invasion of Scotland from France by a group of English nobles whose lands in Scotland had been seized by the Scottish king Robert I the Bruce, father...
</Question>
<Choice>Edward (king of Scotland)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
son of Henry III and king of England in 1272–1307, during a period of rising national consciousness. He strengthened the crown and Parliament against the old feudal nobility. He subdued Wales, destroying its autonomy; and he sought (unsuccessfully) the conquest of Scotland. His reign is particularly noted for administrative efficiency and legal reform. He introduced a series of statutes that did much to strengthen the crown in the feudal hierarchy. His definition and emendation of English common law has earned him the name of the “English Justinian.”
</Question>
<Choice>Edward I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of England from 1307 to 1327. Although he was a man of limited capability, he waged a long, hopeless campaign to assert his authority over powerful barons.The fourth son of King Edward I, he ascended the throne upon his father's death (July 7, 1307) and immediately gave the highest offices to Edward I's most prominent opponents. He earned the hatred of the barons by granting the earldom of Cornwall to his frivolous favourite (and possible lover), Piers Gaveston. In 1311 a 21-member baronial committee drafted a document—known as the Ordinances—demanding the banishment of Gaveston and the r...
</Question>
<Choice>Edward II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of England from 1327 to 1377, who led England into the Hundred Years' War with France. The descendants of his seven sons and five daughters contested the throne for generations, climaxing in the Wars of the Roses (1455–85).
</Question>
<Choice>Edward III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of England from 1461 until October 1470 and again from April 1471 until his death in 1483. He was a leading participant in the Yorkist-Lancastrian conflict known as the Wars of the Roses.Edward was the eldest surviving son of Richard, duke of York, by Cicely, daughter of Ralph Neville, earl of Westmorland. His father was descended from two sons of the 14th-century king Edward III and, in the 1450s, led a revolt against Henry VI; in 1460, Richard's supporters declared him Henry's successor. When his father was killed in December of that year, Edward gathered an army in Wales and defeated H...
</Question>
<Choice>Edward IV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of England from April to June 1483, who was deposed and possibly murdered by King Richard III.The eldest surviving son of King Edward IV and Queen Elizabeth (Woodville), Edward was born at Westminster Abbey while his father, momentarily deposed, was in exile in Holland. In June 1471, after Edward IV had crushed his foes and reclaimed his crown, young Edward was made prince of Wales. The boy was sent with his mother to Ludlow, Shropshire, in 1473 to be titular ruler of Wales and the Welsh Marches (border region between England and Wales), and he seems to have stayed at Ludlow, except for b...
</Question>
<Choice>Edward V</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the united realms of Denmark, Norway (as Erik III), and Sweden (as Erik XIII) from 1397 to 1439; his autocratic rule and foreign wars eventually lost him the throne in all three of his dominions.The son of Duke Vratislav VII of Pomerania and the great-nephew of Margaret, queen of the three united Scandinavian realms, Erik was adopted by Margaret in 1387. Her skillful diplomacy won him the throne of the three realms (the Kalmar Union) in 1397, but she continued as effective ruler until her death in 1412.Erik soon set out to establish a powerful Scandinavian Baltic empire, based in Denma...
</Question>
<Choice>Erik VII</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mongol chief who succeeded in temporarily reviving Mongol power in Central Asia by descending on China and capturing the Ming emperor Yingzong (reigning as Zhengtong, 1435–49).In 1439 Esen became the chief of the Oyrat Mongols, living in the remote mountainous region in western Mongolia near Lake Baikal, from which had come some of Genghis Khan's most ferocious warriors. Esen began to follow in Genghis' footsteps, subjugating other Mongol tribes and extending his authority eastward until he came to rule the territory between the Great Wall of China and the Korean border.In 1449 Esen stopped pa...
</Question>
<Choice>Esen Taiji</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the English from 978 to 1013 and from 1014 to 1016. He was an ineffectual ruler who failed to prevent the Danes from overrunning England. The epithet “unready” is derived from unraed, meaning “bad counsel” or “no counsel,” and puns on his name, which means “noble counsel.”The son of King Edgar (ruled 959–975), Ethelred ascended the throne upon the assassination of his half brother King Edward the Martyr in March 978. Widespread suspicion that Ethelred may have had a part in the murder created much of the distrust and disloyalty that undermined his authority. Hence, there was no unified...
</Question>
<Choice>Ethelred II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Norway (1103–22) whose reign with his brother Sigurd I Jerusalemfarer was the longest joint rule in the history of Norway. An illegitimate son of Magnus III Barefoot, Eystein succeeded to the throne in 1103 with his younger brothers Sigurd I and Olaf (IV); the latter, a child, died in 1115, but Sigurd outlived Eystein. While Sigurd was off on crusades in Moorish Spain and the Holy Land in 1107–11, Eystein served Norway with great ability, gaining territory from Sweden, building churches, and fostering internal progress.
</Question>
<Choice>Eystein I Magnusson</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
founder and first king of the Lao kingdom of Lan Xang who created the first unified state of the Lao people.Fa Ngum was the grandson of Souvanna Khamphong, the last in a long line of local rulers of the principality of Muang Swa, later called Luang Prabang, on the upper Mekong River. According to local legend, Souvanna Khamphong banished Fa Ngum's father for having seduced one of his concubines. The family is said to have fled to the Cambodian capital at Angkor, where Fa Ngum was reared and married a Khmer princess.About 1350 Fa Ngum and his father raised an army in Cambodia and fought their w...
</Question>
<Choice>Fa Ngum</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Naples from 1458.He was the illegitimate son of Alfonso V of Aragon, who, after establishing himself as king of Naples in 1442, had Ferdinand legitimized and recognized as his heir. Succeeding Alfonso in 1458, Ferdinand was soon faced with a baronial revolt in favour of René of Anjou, the pretender to the throne. He overcame the rebellion in 1464, but his rule was threatened by Ottoman expansionism, by the territorial ambitions of other Italian states, and by the rebelliousness of his own barons. Ferdinand, therefore, pursued an opportunist policy. In August 1480 the Turks seized the s...
</Question>
<Choice>Ferdinand I (king of Naples)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
ninth king of Portugal (1367–83), whose reign was marked by three wars with Castile and by the growth of the Portuguese economy.The son of Peter I of Portugal, Ferdinand became a contender for the Castilian throne after the assassination (1369) of Peter the Cruel of Castile, thus initiating the first (1369–71) of the unsuccessful wars with Castile. After Ferdinand allied himself in 1372 with John of Gaunt, Duke of Lancaster, there ensued a second war with Castile (1372–73), in which Castilian troops invaded Portugal, surrounded Lisbon (1373), and obliged Ferdinand to repudiate the English alli...
</Question>
<Choice>Ferdinand I (king of Portugal)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Aragon from 1412 to 1416, second son of John I of Castile and Eleanor, daughter of Peter IV of Aragon.Because his elder brother, Henry III, was an invalid, Ferdinand took the battlefield against the Muslims of Granada. When Henry III died in 1406, his son John II was an infant and the regency was divided between Henry's widow, Queen Catherine of Lancaster, and Ferdinand, who claimed positions on the royal council for his sons. In 1410 Ferdinand captured the Granadine fortress of Antequera, a feat that ensured his election to the throne of Aragon, vacant with the death of King Martin in...
</Question>
<Choice>Ferdinand I (king of Aragon)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the first ruler of Castile to take the title of king. He also was crowned emperor of Leon.Ferdinand's father, Sancho III of Navarre, had acquired Castile and established hegemony over the Christian states. On his death in 1035 he left Navarre to his eldest son (García III) and Castile to his second son, Ferdinand, who had married Sancha, sister and heiress of Bermudo III of Leon. Ferdinand's Castilians defeated and killed Bermudo at Tamarón in 1037, and he had himself crowned emperor in the city of León in 1039. In 1054 his Castilian troops defeated and killed his elder brother, García III, at...
</Question>
<Choice>Ferdinand I (king of Castile and Leon)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Aragon and king of Castile (as Ferdinand V) from 1479, joint sovereign with Queen Isabella I. (As Spanish ruler of southern Italy, he was also known as Ferdinand III of Naples and Ferdinand II of Sicily.) He united the Spanish kingdoms into the nation of Spain and began Spain's entry into the modern period of imperial expansion.Ferdinand was the son of John II of Aragon and Juana Enríquez, both of Castilian origin. In 1461, in the midst of a bitterly contested succession, John II named him heir apparent and governor of all his kingdoms and lands. Ferdinand's future was assured when he...
</Question>
<Choice>Ferdinand II (king of Spain)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Leon from 1157 to 1188, second son of Alfonso VII.Despite several internal revolts against his rule, Ferdinand's reign was notable for the repopulation of Leonese Extremadura and for the victories he secured farther south against the Almohads in the last 20 years of his reign. These included the capture of Alcántara (1166) and Badajoz (1169). He also gave important support to the new military order of Santiago, founded with his approval in 1170. Ferdinand, who called himself rex hispanorum (“king of the Spaniards”), established a temporary tutelage over Castile during the minority of h...
</Question>
<Choice>Ferdinand II (king of Leon)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Castile from 1217 to 1252 and of Leon from 1230 to 1252 and conqueror of the Muslim cities of Córdoba (1236), Jaén (1246), and Sevilla (1248). During his campaigns, Murcia submitted to his son Alfonso (later Alfonso X), and the Muslim kingdom of Granada became his vassal.Ferdinand was the son of Alfonso IX of Leon and Berenguela, daughter of Alfonso VIII of Castile. At birth, he was the heir to Leon, but his uncle, Henry I of Castile, died young, and his mother inherited the crown of Castile, which she conferred on him. His father, like many Leonese, opposed the union, and Ferdinand fo...
</Question>
<Choice>Ferdinand III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German king from 1314 to 1326, also duke of Austria (as Frederick III) from 1308, the second son of the German king Albert I.After his father's murder (1308) Frederick became the head of the House of Habsburg and duke of Austria but did not succeed him as king, the count of Luxembourg being elected instead, as Henry VII. Frederick and his brothers made a treaty with Henry at Speyer in 1309, whereby they renounced the Habsburg claim to Bohemia in return for a sum of 50,000 Marks. Frederick's quarrel with his cousin Louis IV of Upper Bavaria concerning the wardship of Henry III of Lower Bavaria...
</Question>
<Choice>Frederick</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
duke of Swabia (as Frederick III, 1147–90) and German king and Holy Roman emperor (1152–90), who challenged papal authority and sought to establish German predominance in western Europe. He engaged in a long struggle with the cities of northern Italy (1154–83), sending six major expeditions southward. He died while on the Third Crusade to the Holy Land.
</Question>
<Choice>Frederick I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Sicily (1197–1250), duke of Swabia (as Frederick VI, 1228–35), German king (1212–50), and Holy Roman emperor (1220–50). A Hohenstaufen and grandson of Frederick I Barbarossa, he pursued his dynasty's imperial policies against the papacy and the Italian city states; and he also joined in the Sixth Crusade (1228–29), conquering several areas of the Holy Land and crowning himself king of Jerusalem (reigning 1229–43).
</Question>
<Choice>Frederick II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Holy Roman emperor from 1452 and German king from 1440 who laid the foundations for the greatness of the House of Habsburg in European affairs.Frederick, the son of Duke Ernest of Austria, inherited the Habsburg possessions of Inner Austria (Styria, Carinthia, Carniola, and Gorizia) on his father's death in 1424. By 1439 he had become the senior member of the dynasty and the following year was elected German king; yet he was to be plagued by conflicts with his relatives and a powerful, rebellious nobility throughout his reign. As guardian of Ladislas Posthumus, son of his cousin the German kin...
</Question>
<Choice>Frederick III (Holy Roman emperor)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Sicily from 1296, who strengthened the Aragonese interest there against the Angevins of Naples.Appointed regent of Sicily by his brother, James II of Aragon, in 1291, Frederick was elected king by the Sicilian parliament (Dec. 11, 1295), to prevent the island's return to the rule of the Angevin Charles II of Naples; he was crowned on March 25, 1296. To revive the Ghibelline tradition of the Holy Roman emperors Frederick I and II, he called himself Frederick III, though he was in fact only the second Frederick to reign in Sicily. A war with Naples and the papacy followed. By the Peace o...
</Question>
<Choice>Frederick III (king of Sicily [1272-1337])</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the most powerful of the Fujiwara regents, during whose reign the Imperial capital in Kyoto achieved its greatest splendour, and the Fujiwara family, which dominated the Japanese court between 857 and 1160, reached the apogee of its rule.Michinaga was the son of Kaneie, the previous head of the Fujiwara family, and he succeeded to the leadership of the clan after the death of his elder brother in 995. Michinaga never took the title kampaku (chancellor) but advanced through the regular Imperial offices until he was named great minister of state (dajo daijin) in 1017.Michinaga was given the hono...
</Question>
<Choice>Fujiwara Michinaga</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prime minister of the Majapahit Empire and a national hero in Indonesia. He is believed to have unified the entire archipelago. The principal poet of the era, Prapanca, eulogized Gajah Mada in an epic, and the first Indonesian university in Jogjakarta was named after him (1946).No information is available on his early life, except that he was born a commoner. He rose to power on his intelligence, courage, and loyalty to King Jayanagara (1309–28) during a rebellion led by Kuti in 1319. He served as the head of the royal bodyguard that escorted King Jayanagara to Badander, when Kuti captured the...
</Question>
<Choice>Gajah Mada</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Pamplona (Navarre) from 1035 to 1054. Following an old custom, Sancho III the Great divided his Spanish lands among his four sons: Ferdinand I received Castile; Gonzalo received Sobrarbe and Ribagorza (modern Huesca); Ramiro I received Aragon; and García III received the ancient patrimony of Pamplona enlarged by portions of Castile. He then expanded the kingdom into the Rioja. Although García helped his brother Ferdinand I of Castile against the Leonese, Ferdinand made war on him to recover the territories of Castile, and García was killed in the Battle of Atapuerca. He was succeeded b...
</Question>
<Choice>García III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mongolian warrior-ruler, one of the most famous conquerors of history, who consolidated tribes into a unified Mongolia and then extended his empire across Asia to the Adriatic Sea.Genghis Khan was a warrior and ruler of genius who, starting from obscure and insignificant beginnings, brought all the nomadic tribes of Mongolia under the rule of himself and his family in a rigidly disciplined military state. He then turned his attention toward the settled peoples beyond the borders of his nomadic realm and began the series of campaigns of plunder and conquest that eventually carried the Mongol ar...
</Question>
<Choice>Genghis Khan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Bohemia from 1458. As head of the conservative Utraquist faction of Hussite Protestants, he established himself as a power when Bohemia was still under Habsburg rule, and he was thereafter unanimously elected king by the estates. A nationalist and Hussite king of a prosperous state, he incurred the enmity of the papacy and Bohemia's Roman Catholic neighbours, which finally destroyed his power.George became the leader of the Utraquists in 1444. Opposing the Roman Catholic pro-Habsburg party, whose prospective Bohemian king Ladislav was still a minor, he captured Prague in 1448, thereaft...
</Question>
<Choice>George</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
most prominent of the Il-Khans (subordinate khans) to rule the Mongol dynasty in Iran. Reigning from 1295 to 1304, he is best known for the conversion of his state to Islam and his wars against Egypt.
</Question>
<Choice>Ghazan, Mahmud</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Jerusalem who lost that Crusader kingdom in a struggle with rival Conrad of Montferrat.In 1180 he married Sibyl, sister of the leprous Baldwin IV, king of Jerusalem. When Baldwin died in 1185, Sibyl's son by a previous marriage, the six-year-old Baldwin V, inherited the crown but died in 1186. Sibyl then became queen and, announcing her intention to choose the most worthy noble to be her husband and king, divorced Guy, only to choose him again as king and husband.War broke out with Saladin (1137–93), sultan of Egypt and Syria, and, when the city of Tiberiade fell in 1187, Guy resolved...
</Question>
<Choice>Guy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
also spelled Kuyuk grandson of Genghis Khan and eldest son and successor of Ögödei, the first khagan, or great khan, of the Mongols.Güyük was elected to the throne in 1246, partly through the maneuvering of his mother. He was strongly influenced by Nestorianism, a form of Christianity considered a heresy by Western Christians, and he favoured Christian advisers. His election to the throne embittered the conqueror of Russia, Batu (d. c. 1255), also a grandson of Genghis. Güyük's early death, however, prevented the dispute from tearing the Mongol Empire completely asunder.
</Question>
<Choice>Güyük</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Norway (1217–63) who consolidated the power of the monarchy, patronized the arts, and established Norwegian sovereignty over Greenland and Iceland. His reign is considered the beginning of the “golden age” (1217–1319) in medieval Norwegian history.Acknowledged as the illegitimate posthumous son of Haakon III and the grandson of Sverrir of Norway, Haakon was reared at the court of Inge II and, on Inge's death in 1217, was proclaimed king by the Birchlegs, the adherents of Sverrir. Doubts of his paternity, especially by the ecclesiastical leaders, were allayed after his mother passed thr...
</Question>
<Choice>Haakon IV Haakonsson</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Norway (1299–1319) whose anti-English foreign policy paved the way for the commercial domination of Norway by north German traders of the Hanseatic League. His reign marked the end of the “golden age” in medieval Norwegian history.The younger son of Magnus VI Lawmender, Haakon succeeded his older brother, Erik II Magnusson, in 1299. Determined to reduce the power of the higher nobles and clerics, which had increased during Erik's reign, Haakon abolished the title of baron in 1308, removed members of the aristocracy from the royal council, and regained the right to appoint selected prie...
</Question>
<Choice>Haakon V Magnusson</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Norway (1355–80) whose marriage to Margaret, daughter of the Danish king Valdemar IV, in 1363 paved the way for the eventual union (1397) of the three major Scandinavian nations—Denmark, Norway, and Sweden—the Kalmar Union. Haakon was deeply embroiled throughout his reign in political conflicts with Sweden, Denmark, and the cities of the north German trading confederation, the Hanseatic League.The younger son of Magnus VII Eriksson, king of Norway and Sweden, Haakon was named his father's successor in Norway in 1343 and became king there in 1355, five years after the nation had been de...
</Question>
<Choice>Haakon VI Magnusson</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
sixth ruler of the Egyptian Shi?ite Fa?imid dynasty, noted for his eccentricities and cruelty, especially his persecutions of Christians and Jews. He is held by adherents of the Druze religion to be a divine incarnation.Al-?akim was named caliph in 996 and depended at first on the Berber regiments in his army for his power. When he took control of government, his policies proved to be arbitrary and harsh. He ordered, for example, the sacking of the city al-Fus?a? (near present-day Cairo), the killing of all dogs (whose barking annoyed him), and bans on various kinds of vegetables and shellfish...
</Question>
<Choice>Hakim, al-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Norway (1045–66). His harsh suppression of lesser Norwegian chieftains cost him their military support in his unsuccessful struggle to conquer Denmark (1045–62).The son of Sigurd Sow (Syr), a chieftain in eastern Norway, and of Estrid, mother of the Norwegian king Olaf II Haraldsson (St. Olaf), Harald fought at the age of 15 against the Danes with Olaf II in the celebrated Battle of Stiklestad (1030) in which Olaf was killed. He then fled to Russia, where he served under the grand prince of Kiev, Yaroslav I the Wise, whose daughter Elizabeth he later married. After enlisting in the mil...
</Question>
<Choice>Harald III Sigurdsson</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Denmark from 1028 to 1042 and of England from 1040 to 1042.Son of King Canute and Emma, daughter of Richard I, duke of Normandy, Hardecanute was made co-king of Denmark by Canute about 1030. On Canute's death in 1035, a party led by Emma and Godwine, earl of Wessex, wished to elect Hardecanute king of England. Leofric, earl of Mercia, with the support of the Londoners and the northern thanes, however, obtained the appointment of Harold, Canute's son by Aelfgifu, as regent of England. Emma and her son's retainers stayed at Winchester, where they protected Hardecanute's interests and spr...
</Question>
<Choice>Hardecanute</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of England from 1035 to 1040, and the son of Aelgifu and Canute, the Danish king of England from 1016 to 1035.Harold was made regent of England after Canute's death. Hardecanute, Canute's son by Emma and claimant to the English throne, was not chosen because he was occupied with affairs in Denmark, where he became king. In 1036 Harold was responsible for the brutal murder of another royal claimant, Alfred the Aetheling, son of King Ethelred the Unready (Ethelred II; reigned 978–1016). Harold then proclaimed himself king and banished Hardecanute's mother. He protected his realm from Welsh...
</Question>
<Choice>Harold I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
last Anglo-Saxon king of England. A strong ruler and a skilled general, he held the crown for nine months in 1066 before he was killed at the Battle of Hastings by Norman invaders under William the Conqueror.Harold's mother, Gytha, belonged to a powerful Danish noble family with close connections to Canute, the Danish king of England. Harold's father, Godwine, earl of Wessex and Kent, was an important supporter of the king. Although an ally of the Anglo-Danish line, Godwine accepted the accession as king of a member of the former English royal family, Edward the Confessor (1042–66), following...
</Question>
<Choice>Harold II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
ruler of the Javan Hindu state of Majapahit at the time of its greatest power.Hayam Wuruk inherited the throne in 1350 at the age of 16, when the great patih (“prime minister”) Gajah Mada was at the height of his career. Under the two leaders, Majapahit extended its power throughout the Indonesian archipelago. Its core area was directly administered by Hayam Wuruk, and the vast outlying territory acknowledged his supremacy, but he exerted little direct control over it. Javanese sea power was supreme, and Hayam Wuruk enjoyed an effective monopoly of trade in the region.Hayam Wuruk had no heir b...
</Question>
<Choice>Hayam Wuruk</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
youngest and ablest of William I the Conqueror's sons, who as king of England (1100–35) strengthened the crown's executive powers and, like his father, also ruled Normandy (from 1106).
</Question>
<Choice>Henry I (king of England)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of France from 1026 to 1060 whose reign was marked by struggles against rebellious vassals.The son of Robert II the Pious and grandson of Hugh Capet, founder of the Capetian dynasty, Henry was anointed king at Reims (1026) in his father's lifetime, following the death of his elder brother Hugh. His mother, Constance, however, favoured his younger brother Robert for the throne, and civil war broke out on King Robert II's death (1031). The younger Robert was given Burgundy in 1032, after Henry had sought refuge with Robert, Duke of Normandy. From 1033 to 1043 Henry struggled with his feudat...
</Question>
<Choice>Henry I (king of France)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
duke of Normandy (from 1150), count of Anjou (from 1151), duke of Aquitaine (from 1152), and king of England (from 1154), who greatly expanded his Anglo-French domains and strengthened the royal administration in England. His quarrels with Thomas Becket, archbishop of Canterbury, and with members of his family (his wife, Eleanor of Aquitaine, and such sons as Richard the Lion-Heart and John Lackland) ultimately brought about his defeat.
</Question>
<Choice>Henry II (king of England)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
duke of Bavaria (as Henry IV, 995–1005), German king (from 1002), and Holy Roman emperor (1014–24), last of the Saxon dynasty of emperors. He was canonized by Pope Eugenius III, more than 100 years after his death, in response to church-inspired legends. He was, in fact, far from saintly, but there is some truth in the legends concerning his religious character. Together with Henry III, he was the great architect of cooperation between church and state, following a policy inaugurated by Charlemagne and promoted by Otto I the Great (Holy Roman emperor, 962–973). His canonization is sometimes ju...
</Question>
<Choice>Henry II (Holy Roman emperor)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Castile from 1369, founder of the house of Trastámara, which lasted until 1504.The illegitimate son of Alfonso XI of Castile, Henry rebelled against his younger half brother, Peter I (Peter the Cruel), invaded Castile with French aid in 1366, and was crowned king at Burgos. Peter sought English aid, and Henry was routed by Edward the Black Prince at Najera (April 3, 1367). He obtained more French aid and captured Peter, whom he murdered on March 23, 1369.The legitimist claim was upheld in Galicia, in Portugal, which he invaded; and he also had to defend himself against England's John o...
</Question>
<Choice>Henry II (king of Castile)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of England from 1216 to 1272. In the 24 years (1234–58) during which he had effective control of the government, he displayed such indifference to tradition that the barons finally forced him to agree to a series of major reforms, the Provisions of Oxford (1258).The elder son and heir of King John (ruled 1199–1216), Henry was nine years old when his father died. At that time London and much of eastern England were in the hands of rebel barons led by Prince Louis (later King Louis VIII of France), son of the French king Philip II Augustus. A council of regency presided over by the venerabl...
</Question>
<Choice>Henry III (king of England [1207-72])</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
duke of Bavaria (as Henry VI, 1027–41), duke of Swabia (as Henry I, 1038–45), German king (from 1039), and Holy Roman emperor (1046–56), a member of the Salian dynasty. The last emperor able to dominate the papacy, he was a powerful advocate of the Cluniac reform movement that sought to purify the Western church.
</Question>
<Choice>Henry III (Holy Roman emperor)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Castile from 1390 to 1406. Though unable to take the field because of illness, he jealously preserved royal power through the royal council, the Audiencia (supreme court), and the corregidores (magistrates). During his minority, the anti-Jewish riots of Sevilla (Seville) and other places produced the large class of conversos (converts).The son of John I, Henry bore the title of prince of Asturias, which from then on designated the heir apparent. His marriage to Catherine of Lancaster, granddaughter of Peter I, ended the dynastic rift and consolidated the house of Trastámara.Henry succe...
</Question>
<Choice>Henry III (king of Castile)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of England from 1399 to 1413, the first of three 15th-century monarchs from the house of Lancaster. He gained the crown by usurpation and successfully consolidated his power in the face of repeated uprisings of powerful nobles. However, he was unable to overcome the fiscal and administrative weaknesses that contributed to the eventual downfall of the Lancastrian dynasty.Henry was the eldest surviving son of John of Gaunt, duke of Lancaster, by his first wife, Blanche. Before becoming king, he was known as Henry Bolingbroke, and he received from his cousin Richard II the titles earl of Der...
</Question>
<Choice>Henry IV (king of England)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
duke of Bavaria (as Henry VIII, 1055–61), German king (from 1054), and Holy Roman emperor (1084–1105/06), who engaged in a long struggle with Hildebrand (Pope Gregory VII) on the question of lay investiture (seeInvestiture Controversy), eventually drawing excommunication on himself and doing penance at Canossa (1077). His last years were spent countering the rebellion of his sons Conrad and Henry (the future Henry V).
</Question>
<Choice>Henry IV (Holy Roman emperor)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Castile from 1454 to 1474, whose reign, though at first promising, became chaotic.Henry's weak father, John II, was entirely under the control of his constable, Álvaro de Luna, who gave the young Henry a separate court at Segovia, hoping to control him. Instead, Henry became the tool of other cliques, who eventually overthrew and executed Luna. In 1464 Henry reconquered Gibraltar from the Muslims, but his nobles fell into warring factions.Henry IV's first marriage was childless and ended in divorce. He then married a Portuguese princess Joana, who bore a daughter, Juana (La Beltraneja)...
</Question>
<Choice>Henry IV (king of Castile)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
second and most able of the Latin emperors of Constantinople, who reigned from 1206 to 1216 and consolidated the power of the new empire.Son of Baldwin V, count of Hainaut, and younger brother of Baldwin I, the first Latin emperor, Henry began the conquest of Asia Minor in 1204 and was on the point of crushing the Byzantine loyalist leader Theodore I Lascaris when a Bulgarian invasion of Thrace necessitated his return to Europe. After the death of Baldwin at the hands of Kalojan, the Bulgarian tsar, in 1205, he served as regent and was made emperor of the Latin empire in August 1206. Henry def...
</Question>
<Choice>Henry of Hainault</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of England (1413–22) of the House of Lancaster, son of Henry IV. As victor of the Battle of Agincourt (1415, in the Hundred Years' War with France), he made England one of the strongest kingdoms in Europe.
</Question>
<Choice>Henry V (king of England)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German king (from 1099) and Holy Roman emperor (1111–25), last of the Salian dynasty. He restored virtual peace in the empire and was generally successful in wars with Flanders, Bohemia, Hungary, and Poland. As son of Henry IV, he continued his father's Investiture Controversy with the papacy.Henry was the second son of Henry IV and his first wife, Bertha of Turin. After his father became emperor, Henry's elder brother, Conrad, was elected German king; Henry succeeded him after Conrad had rebelled unsuccessfully against his father, being crowned on Jan. 6, 1099. In 1104, in the conflict betwee...
</Question>
<Choice>Henry V (Holy Roman emperor)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of England from 1422 to 1461 and from 1470 to 1471, a pious and studious recluse whose incapacity for government was one of the causes of the Wars of the Roses.Henry succeeded his father, Henry V, on Sept. 1, 1422, and on the death (Oct. 21, 1422) of his maternal grandfather, the French king Charles VI, Henry was proclaimed king of France in accordance with the terms of the Treaty of Troyes (1420) made after Henry V's French victories.Henry's minority was never officially ended, but from 1437 he was considered old enough to rule for himself, and his personality became a vital factor. Ther...
</Question>
<Choice>Henry VI (king of England)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German king and Holy Roman emperor of the Hohenstaufen dynasty who increased his power and that of his dynasty by his acquisition of the kingdom of Sicily through his marriage to Constance I, posthumous daughter of the Sicilian king Roger II. Although Henry failed in his objective of making the German crown hereditary, like the Sicilian crown, his son Frederick II, who became king of Sicily immediately after Henry VI's death, was subsequently elected Holy Roman emperor.A son of the emperor Frederick I Barbarossa, Henry was chosen German king at Bamberg in June 1169 and crowned at Aachen in Aug...
</Question>
<Choice>Henry VI (Holy Roman emperor)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
count of Luxembourg (as Henry IV), German king (from 1308), and Holy Roman emperor (from 1312) who strengthened the position of his family by obtaining the throne of Bohemia for his son. He failed, however, in his attempt to bind Italy firmly to the empire.Henry succeeded his father, Henry III, as count of Luxembourg in 1288. He was chosen German king in November 1308 at Frankfurt and was crowned at Aachen the following January, becoming the first German king of the House of Luxembourg.Bohemia was acquired through the Bohemian princess Elizabeth, who, in exchange for imperial assistance in her...
</Question>
<Choice>Henry VII</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(Ojibwa: “He Makes Rivers”), a legendary chief (c. 1450) of the Onondaga tribe of North American Indians, to whom Indian tradition attributes the formation of what became known as the Iroquois Confederacy. In his miraculous character, Hiawatha was the incarnation of human progress and civilization. He taught agriculture, navigation, medicine, and the arts, conquering by his magic all the powers of nature that war against man. The story of Hiawatha is told in Henry Wadsworth Longfellow's Song of Hiawatha (1855), a long poem, written in the metre of the Finnish Kalevala, that enjoyed wide popula...
</Question>
<Choice>Hiawatha</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese warrior who aided Minamoto Yoritomo in establishing the Kamakura shogunate, the military government by which Yoritomo ruled the country from his base at Kamakura in central Japan, while the emperor continued to rule only symbolically from his residence at Kyoto, to the southwest. After Yoritomo's death, Tokimasa transferred the power of government from Yoritomo's descendants to his own family.Tokimasa's original family name was Taira, but early in his life he changed it to Hojo, the name of his domain in eastern Japan. In 1160, when the great warrior Taira Kiyomori (1118–81) killed Mi...
</Question>
<Choice>Hojo Tokimasa</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
warrior responsible for the consolidation of the power of the Kamakura shogunate, the military dictatorship that ruled Japan from the city of Kamakura in central Japan (1192–1333).Yoshitoki succeeded his father, Hojo Tokimasa (q.v.), as regent, making this office the hereditary post of the Hojo family. Thereafter, although the emperor at Kyoto was the official governmental authority, he ruled through his shogun in Kamakura, whose real power was vested in his regent. In 1219 the Shogun was assassinated, and Yoshitoki replaced him with an infant son of the Fujiwara lineage (a family with high st...
</Question>
<Choice>Hojo Yoshitoki</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
archbishop of Canterbury, papal legate, justiciar of King Richard I of England, and chancellor of King John of England. Hubert was an administrator whose position in church and state was unmatched until the time of Cardinal Wolsey in the 16th century.Employed in the household of King Henry II of England by 1182, he became bishop of Salisbury in October 1189. The following year he traveled with Richard and Archbishop Baldwin of Canterbury on the Third Crusade, in which his distinguished services included negotiating on Richard's behalf with the Muslim leader Saladin and directing the return of...
</Question>
<Choice>Hubert Walter</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
temple name (miaohao) of the eighth and penultimate emperor (reigned 1100–1125/26) of the Bei (Northern) Song dynasty (960–1127). He is best remembered both as a patron of the arts and as a painter and calligrapher.The Huizong emperor sought escape from affairs of state through the pleasures of arts and letters. He urged painters in his academy of painting to depict objects that were “true to colour and form,” inviting an extreme literalness of representation; his own paintings of birds and flowers were detailed, accurately coloured, and perfectly composed. He is also known as a calligrapher w...
</Question>
<Choice>Huizong</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mongol ruler in Iran who founded the Il-Khanid dynasty and, as part of a Mongol program of subduing the Islamic world, seized and sacked Baghdad, the religious and cultural capital of Islam. Some historians consider that he did more than anyone else to destroy medieval Iranian culture.Hülegü, a grandson of Genghis Khan, was appointed by his brother Mangu Khan, the fourth great khan of the Mongols, to extend Mongol power in Islamic areas. Hülegü destroyed the fortress of the Assassins (a militant Islamic sect) in 1256 at Alamut in north central Iran. He then defeated the caliph's army and captu...
</Question>
<Choice>Hülegü</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
reign name (nianhao) of the Chinese emperor (reigned 1368–98) who founded the Ming dynasty that ruled China for nearly 300 years. During his reign, the Hongwu emperor instituted military, administrative, and educational reforms that centred power in the emperor.
</Question>
<Choice>Hung-wu</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English John Hunyadi, or Huniades Hungarian general and governor of the Kingdom of Hungary from 1446 to 1452, who was a leading commander against the Turks in the 15th century.
</Question>
<Choice>Hunyadi, János</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
third and greatest Delhi sultan of the so-called Slave dynasty. Iltutmish was sold into slavery but married the daughter of his master, Qu?b al-Din Aibak, whom he succeeded in 1211. He strengthened and expanded the Muslim empire in northern India and moved the capital to Delhi, where he built the great victory tower, the Qu?b Minar.A wise and patient statesman who had been trained as a trusted administrator under his predecessors Mu?izz al-Din Mu?ammad ibn Sam and Qu?b al-Din, Iltutmish was faced upon his accession not only with the deterioration of Muslim rule but also with the claim of Taj a...
</Question>
<Choice>Iltutmish</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine ruler and saint of the Greek Orthodox Church who was instrumental in restoring the use of icons in the Eastern Roman Empire.The wife of the Byzantine emperor Leo IV, Irene became, on her husband's death in September 780, guardian of their 10-year-old son, Constantine VI, and co-emperor with him. Later in that year she crushed what seems to have been a plot by the Iconoclasts (opposers of the use of icons) to put Leo's half brother, Nicephorus, on the throne.Irene favoured the restoration of the use of icons, which had been prohibited in 730. She had Tarasius, one of her supporters, e...
</Question>
<Choice>Irene</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor who restored economic stability at home and built up the neglected military defenses of the empire.Isaac was a son of Manuel Comnenus, an officer of the Byzantine emperor Basil II. On his deathbed, Manuel commended Isaac and his other son, John, to the emperor's care. After having them educated, Basil advanced them to high positions. Isaac, by his prudent conduct in protecting the peoples of the empire, won the confidence of the army during the reigns of Basil's successors.In 1057 Isaac entered into a military plot to depose the emperor Michael VI, and in June of that year Is...
</Question>
<Choice>Isaac I Comnenus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor, who, although incapable of stemming administrative abuses, partly succeeded, by his defeat of the Serbians in 1190, in retrieving imperial fortunes in the Balkans.In September 1185 Isaac was unexpectedly proclaimed emperor by the Constantinople mob that had murdered his cousin, the emperor Andronicus I Comnenus. Isaac's reign was inaugurated by the decisive victory of his general Alexius Branas over the Normans who, after invading the empire and sacking Thessalonica (1185), were then driven off Greek soil (except for the islands of Cephalonia and Zacynthus [modern Zante]). I...
</Question>
<Choice>Isaac II Angelus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
queen of Jerusalem (1192–1205).Daughter of Almaric I of Jerusalem and Maria Comnena, she succeeded to the throne of Jerusalem after the death of her sister, Sibyl (Sibylle), in 1190 and the deposition of Sibyl's husband and consort in 1192.First married to Humphrey IV, lord of Toron, she was forcibly divorced from her beloved husband in order to be married to Conrad of Montferrat, lord of Tyre, and, after his assassination (1192), to Henry of Troyes (died 1197). Her fourth husband was Almaric II, king of Cyprus.Isabella's daughter Mary (Marie) of Montferrat, succeeded her as queen and was marr...
</Question>
<Choice>Isabella I (queen of Jerusalem)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
queen of Castile (1474–1504) and of Aragon (1479–1504), ruling the two kingdoms jointly from 1479 with her husband, Ferdinand II of Aragon (Ferdinand V of Castile). Their rule effected the permanent union of Spain and the beginning of an overseas empire in the New World, led by Christopher Columbus under Isabella's sponsorship.
</Question>
<Choice>Isabella I (queen of Spain)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
queen consort of Charles VI of France, who frequently was regent because of her husband's periodic insanity. Her gravest political act was the signing of the Treaty of Troyes (May 21, 1420), which recognized King Henry V of England as heir to the French crown in place of her son Charles (afterward Charles VII), who was to be exiled from France.The daughter of Stephen III, duke of Bavaria-Ingolstadt, she was married to Charles VI on July 17, 1385. Her husband's first severe attack of insanity (Aug. 5, 1392) caused her great distress; for years she sought remedies, both medical and supernatural....
</Question>
<Choice>Isabella Of Bavaria</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
tsar of the Second Bulgarian empire from 1218 to 1241, son of Ivan Asen I.Ivan Asen overthrew his cousin Tsar Boril (reigned 1207–18) and blinded him, proclaiming himself tsar. A good soldier and administrator, he restored law and order, controlled the boyars, and, after defeating Theodore Ducas, despot of Epirus, in 1230, acquired large parts of Albania, Serbia, Macedonia, and Epirus. The record of his achievements, dated 1230, can still be seen in the old Church of the Forty Martyrs at Turnovo.One of Ivan's daughters was married to the Serbian prince Vladislav, whom Ivan was able to establis...
</Question>
<Choice>Ivan Asen II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
grand prince of Moscow (1328–40) and grand prince of Vladimir (1331–40) whose policies increased Moscow's power and made it the richest principality in northeastern Russia.The son of Prince Daniel of Moscow, Ivan succeeded his brother Yury as prince (1325) and then as grand prince (1328) of Moscow. Determined to persuade the Khan of the Golden Horde, the overlord of all the Russian princes, to make him grand prince of Vladimir, he cooperated with the Khan in an expedition against his chief rival, Grand Prince Alexander of Tver, whose subjects had revolted against the Khanate (1327). Despite hi...
</Question>
<Choice>Ivan I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
grand prince of Moscow and Vladimir.The son of Ivan I, he succeeded his brother Semen on the throne of Moscow in 1353 and was granted the patent to that principality by the Khan of the Golden Horde in spite of the vigorous claim laid by Konstantin Vasilyevich of Suzdal. At first the principalities of Suzdal, Ryazan, and the republic of Novgorod refused to recognize Ivan as grand duke, and they waged war against him until 1354. Ivan was dominated by his aristocratic advisors (boyars), prominent among whom was the military commander in Moscow, Aleksey Khvost, and the metropolitan Aleksei. As gra...
</Question>
<Choice>Ivan II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
grand prince of Moscow (1462–1505), who subdued most of the Great Russian lands by conquest or by the voluntary allegiance of princes, rewon parts of Ukraine from Poland–Lithuania, and repudiated the old subservience to the Mongol-derived Tatars. He also laid the administrative foundations of a centralized Russian state.
</Question>
<Choice>Ivan III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
queen of Poland (1384–99) whose marriage to Jogaila, grand duke of Lithuania (Wladyslaw II Jagiello of Poland), founded the centuries-long union of Lithuania and Poland.Jadwiga was the daughter of Louis I, king of both Hungary and Poland, and Elizabeth of Poland. After Louis died on September 11, 1382, his elder daughter, Maria, was elected queen of Hungary, but the Poles opted to end the personal union between the two countries by choosing Jadwiga as their queen, though she was then but a child of nine years. On October 15, 1384, she was crowned rex (“king”) of Poland. The Polish magnates fur...
</Question>
<Choice>Jadwiga</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Scots from 1406 to 1437. During the 13 years (1424–37) in which he had control of the government, he established the first strong monarchy the Scots had known in nearly a century.James was the son and heir of King Robert III (reigned 1390–1406). In 1406 Robert decided to send him to France, presumably to keep him out of the reach of the powerful and treacherous Robert Stewart, Duke of Albany. On the way, James was captured by English sailors and taken as a prisoner to the royal court in London. Robert died shortly thereafter, and Albany, who became regent, had no desire to ransom young...
</Question>
<Choice>James I (king of Scotland)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the most renowned of the medieval kings of Aragon (1213–76), who added the Balearic Islands and Valencia to his realm and thus initiated the Catalan-Aragonese expansion in the Mediterranean that was to reach its zenith in the last decades of the 14th century.James was the son of Peter II of Aragon and Mary of Montpellier. When Peter, allied with the Albigensian heretics, died fighting against the crusaders sent against them at the Battle of Muret, James was only five years old and was at Carcassonne, Fr., in the hands of the crusaders' leader, Simon de Montfort. James was released in April 121...
</Question>
<Choice>James I (king of Aragon)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Scots from 1437 to 1460. He survived the civil strife of the first half of his reign and eventually emerged as a masterful ruler who consolidated his power throughout the kingdom.The only surviving son of King James I, he succeeded to the throne at the age of six upon his father's assassination (February 1437). Because he was too young to take control of the government, the strong central authority that his father had established quickly collapsed. In the ensuing turmoil three rival families—the Crichtons, the Livingstons, and the Douglases—fought to gain control of the young king. Jam...
</Question>
<Choice>James II (king of Scotland)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Aragon from 1295 to 1327 and king of Sicily (as James I) from 1285 to 1295.At the death of his father, Peter III, on Nov. 11, 1285, James inherited Sicily, and his elder brother became Alfonso III of Aragon, Catalonia, and Valencia. When his brother died (1291) he inherited Aragon and resigned Sicily (1295), marrying Blanche, daughter of Charles II of Naples, in an endeavour to make peace with the Angevins. Sardinia and Corsica were both assigned to him in compensation for Sicily, but he was able to occupy Sardinia only (1324). He was succeeded by his son Alfonso IV.
</Question>
<Choice>James II (king of Aragon and Sicily)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Scots from 1460 to 1488. A weak monarch, he was confronted with two major rebellions because he failed to win the respect of the nobility.James received the crown at the age of eight upon the death of his father, King James II. Scotland was governed first by James's mother, Mary of Gueldres (d. 1463), and James Kennedy, bishop of St. Andrews (d. 1465), and then by a group of nobles headed by the Boyds of Kilmarnock, who seized the king in 1466. In 1469 James overthrew the Boyds and began to govern for himself. Unlike his father, he was, however, unable to restore strong central governm...
</Question>
<Choice>James III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
one of the most forceful and productive kings of the Khmer (Cambodian) empire of Angkor (reigning 1181–c. 1220). He expanded the empire to its greatest territorial extent and engaged in a building program that yielded numerous temples (including Angkor Thom), highways, rest houses, and hospitals.
</Question>
<Choice>Jayavarman VII</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
countess of Provence and queen of Naples (1343–82) who defended her claim as well as that of the house of Anjou to the throne of Naples, only to lose it to Charles of Durazzo (Charles III of Naples). Beautiful and intelligent, she was also a patron of the poets and scholars of her time.Joan I succeeded her grandfather, King Robert, in 1343, after her marriage to her cousin Andrew, brother of Louis I of Hungary (1342–82); her accession was intended to reconcile the Hungarian and Angevin claims on Naples. The swarm of Hungarians who followed Andrew to Naples, however, antagonized many of the Ang...
</Question>
<Choice>Joan I (queen of Naples)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
queen consort of Philip IV (the Fair) of France (from 1285) and queen of Navarre (as Joan I, from 1274), mother of three French kings—Louis X, Philip V, and Charles IV.Joan was the sole daughter and heir of Henry I, king of Navarre, her brother Theobald (Thibaut) having died at an early age. She married (Aug. 16, 1284) the future Philip IV, thus bringing to the French crown her rights to Navarre and the countships of Champagne and Brie. On her death in childbirth in 1305 these rights were transmitted to her son, the future Louis X. Joan was a woman of great intelligence and vivacity, a lover o...
</Question>
<Choice>Joan I (queen of France)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
queen of Naples whose long reign (1414–35) was marked by a succession of love affairs, by continual intrigues, and by power struggles over her domain between the French house of Anjou and that of Aragon, in Spain.After her first husband, William of Austria, died in 1406, Joan is reported to have led a promiscuous life. When her brother Ladislas died in 1414, she became queen and appointed her lover Pandolfello Alopo grand chamberlain. Alopo temporarily removed from power the condottiere Muzio Attendolo Sforza, an important figure in the previous regime. On July 14, 1415, Joan married Jacques d...
</Question>
<Choice>Joan II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
margrave of Moravia and Brandenburg and for 15 weeks German king (1410–11), who, by his political and military machinations in east-central Europe, played a powerful role in the political life of Germany.A member of the Luxembourg dynasty, Jobst was a nephew of the Holy Roman emperor Charles IV and cousin to the Bohemian and German king Wenceslas and his half brother, the future emperor Sigismund. Ruling Moravia from 1376, Jobst also became general vicar of Italy (1383 and 1389) without ever setting foot there. In 1388 he added Luxembourg and Brandenburg to his dominions. In his many disputes,...
</Question>
<Choice>Jobst</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Bohemia from 1310 until his death, and one of the more popular heroic figures of his day, who campaigned across Europe from Toulouse to Prussia.He was born the son of the future Holy Roman emperor Henry VII of the house of Luxembourg and was made count of Luxembourg in 1310. At about the same time, he also was named king of Bohemia, and on Feb. 7, 1311, he was solemnly crowned at Prague. When his father died in 1313, John was too young to succeed him as emperor and supported instead the election of Louis the Bavarian as Emperor Louis IV (1314). John subsequently sided with Louis in his...
</Question>
<Choice>John (king of Bohemia)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
count of Brienne who became titular king of Jerusalem (1210–25) and Latin emperor of Constantinople (1231–37).A penniless younger son of the French count Erard II of Brienne and Agnes of Montbéliard, John passed most of his life as a minor noble until befriended by King Philip II Augustus of France, who arranged for him to marry Mary (Marie) of Montferrat, queen of the Crusader state of Jerusalem, in 1210. John reached the Palestinian town of Acre on September 13, 1210, married Mary the following day, and was crowned at Tyre on October 3. Mary died in 1212, and John was named regent for their...
</Question>
<Choice>John (Byzantine emperor)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Denmark (1481–1513) and Norway (1483–1513) and king (as John II) of Sweden (1497–1501) who failed in his efforts to incorporate Sweden into a Danish-dominated Scandinavian union. He was more successful in fostering the commercial development of Danish burghers to challenge the power of the nobility.John succeeded his father, Christian I, king of Denmark and Norway, in 1481, but only by agreeing to a stringent charter imposed by the Danish nobles to limit royal power. Although he was also recognized as sovereign by the Swedish state council (1483), the Swedish regent, Sten Sture the Eld...
</Question>
<Choice>John (king of Denmark, Norway, and Sweden)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of England from 1199 to 1216. In a war with the French king Philip II, he lost Normandy and almost all his other possessions in France. In England, after a revolt of the barons, he was forced to seal the Magna Carta (1215).
</Question>
<Choice>John (king of England)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Scotland from 1292 to 1296, the youngest son of John de Balliol and his wife Dervorguilla, daughter and heiress of the lord of Galloway. His brothers dying childless, he inherited the Balliol lands in England and France in 1278 and succeeded to Galloway in 1290. In that year, when the heiress to the kingdom of Scotland, Margaret, the Maid of Norway, died, Balliol became one of 13 competitors for the crown. He at once designated himself “heir of the kingdom of Scotland,” clearly anticipating the vindication of his claim, which was derived from his mother, daughter of Margaret, eldest da...
</Question>
<Choice>John (king of Scotland [1250-1313])</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of France, the posthumous son of Louis X of France by his second consort, Clémence of Hungary. He died just a few days after his birth but is nevertheless reckoned among the kings of France. His uncle, who succeeded him as Philip V, has been accused of having caused his death, or of having substituted a dead child in his place; but nothing has ever been proved. In 1358 a man called Giannino, in Florence, persuaded Clémence's nephew, Louis I of Hungary, that he was John I; but otherwise he met with little success and died in jail in Naples (1363).
</Question>
<Choice>John I (king of France)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Portugal from 1385 to 1433, who preserved his country's independence from Castile and initiated Portugal's overseas expansion. He was the founder of the Aviz, or Joanina (Johannine), dynasty.
</Question>
<Choice>John I (king of Portugal)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Aragon (1387–1395), son of Peter IV. Influenced by his wife, Violante, he pursued a pro-French policy but refused to become involved in the Hundred Years' War. He died by a fall from his horse, like his namesake, cousin, and contemporary of Castile, John I. He was a man of insignificant character, with a taste for artificial verse.
</Question>
<Choice>John I (king of Aragon)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Castile from 1379 to 1390, son of Henry II, founder of the dynasty of Trastámara.In the beginning of his reign John had to contend with the hostility of John of Gaunt, who claimed the crown by right of his wife Constance, daughter of Peter I the Cruel. The king of Castile finally bought off the claim of his English competitor by arranging a marriage between his son Henry and Catherine, daughter of John of Gaunt, in 1387. Before this date he had been engaged in hostilities with Portugal, which was in alliance with John of Gaunt. His first quarrel with Portugal was settled by his marriag...
</Question>
<Choice>John I (king of Castile)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of France from 1350 to 1364. Captured by the English at the Battle of Poitiers on Sept. 19, 1356, he was forced to sign the disastrous treaties of 1360 during the first phase of the Hundred Years' War (1337–1453) between France and England.After becoming king on Aug. 22, 1350, John continued a truce with the English until later that year, when he had an English hostage, Raoul de Brienne, comte d'Eu, former constable of France, executed. By March 1351 King Edward III of England realized the impossibility of remaining at peace; but John committed the first act of hostility by attacking and...
</Question>
<Choice>John II (king of France)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Portugal from 1481 to 1495, regarded as one of the greatest Portuguese rulers, chiefly because of his ruthless assertion of royal authority over the great nobles and his resumption of the exploration of Africa and the quest for India.
</Question>
<Choice>John II (king of Portugal)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Aragon (1458–79) and also king of Navarre (1425–79); he was the instigator of the union of Castile and Aragon through the historic marriage of his son Ferdinand with Isabella of Castile.John was a younger son of Ferdinand of Antequera, elected king of Aragon (as Ferdinand I) in 1412. John and his brothers retained their positions and revenues in Castile, and he married Blanche, the heiress to Navarre, of which he claimed the kingship (1425–79). On his wife's death, he married Juana Enriques, daughter of the admiral of castile (1447), whose ambitions led to a conflict between John and h...
</Question>
<Choice>John II (king of Aragon and Navarre)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Castile from 1406 to 1454; his political weakness led him to rely on his favourite, Álvaro de Luna, whom he made constable. He was nevertheless considered a man of cultivated taste and a patron of poets.John succeeded his father, Henry III, as an infant of less than two years of age, under the joint regency of his mother, Catherine of Lancaster, and his uncle, the infante Ferdinand, who became king of Aragon (as Ferdinand I) in 1412. John took the reins in 1419 but soon placed himself in the hands of his companion Luna, who contested the influence of Ferdinand's sons in Castile. This l...
</Question>
<Choice>John II (king of Castile)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor (1118–43) whose reign was characterized by unremitting attempts to reconquer all important Byzantine territory lost to the Arabs, Turks, and Christian Crusaders.A son of Emperor Alexius I Comnenus and Irene Ducas, John kept an austere court and spent most of his reign with his troops. He canceled Venetian trading privileges granted by his father but was forced to restore them after the Venetians launched a fleet against him. He thwarted Pecheneg, Hungarian, and Serbian threats during the 1120s, and in 1130 he allied himself with the German emperor Lothar II (III) against the...
</Question>
<Choice>John II Comnenus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
emperor of Nicaea (1222–54) who, by acquiring territory, encouraging economic growth, and supporting a cultural revival from his capital at Nicaea (modern Iznik, Turkey), paved the way for the recovery of Constantinople from the Latin emperors and the reestablishment of the Byzantine Empire.Born to an aristocratic Byzantine family, he married Irene, daughter of Theodore I Lascaris, emperor of Nicaea, becoming emperor on Theodore's death. Civil war broke out when Theodore's brothers, Alexius and Isaac, protested the succession, but John defeated them in battle and imprisoned and blinded them (1...
</Question>
<Choice>John III Ducas Vatatzes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
emperor of Nicaea whose brief reign as a minor was filled with intrigue and conspiracies that culminated in the seizure of power by Michael Palaeologus, the future Byzantine emperor Michael VIII.John IV's parents were the Nicaean emperor Theodore II Lascaris (reigned 1254–58) and Helen, a daughter of the Bulgarian tsar John Asen II. Eight years old when his father died, John was advised by his regent George Muzalon, a trusted friend of the former emperor. But Muzalon was assassinated nine days after Theodore's death by associates of Michael Palaeologus, who then became regent. Michael proclaim...
</Question>
<Choice>John IV Lascaris</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor (1341–91) whose rule was marked by civil war and increased domination by the Ottoman Turks, despite his efforts to salvage the empire.Nine years old when his father, Andronicus III, died, John was too young to rule, and a dispute over the regency broke out between his mother, Anna of Savoy, and John Cantacuzenus, chief minister under Andronicus III. Cantacuzenus won the ensuing civil war and was crowned coemperor with John V at Constantinople in 1347. Despite John V's subsequent marriage to Helen, Cantacuzenus's daughter, he formed an alliance with the Venetians against Canta...
</Question>
<Choice>John V Palaeologus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman, Byzantine emperor, and historian whose dispute with John V Palaeologus over the imperial throne induced him to appeal for help to the Turks, aiding them in their conquest of the Byzantine Empire.John was chief adviser to Andronicus III Palaeologus, having helped him gain the throne from his grandfather Andronicus II. From 1328 to 1341 Cantacuzenus directed both domestic and foreign policy for the Emperor. He encouraged a reform of the law courts and promoted commercial independence from the Genoese and Venetians by initiating a large shipbuilding project. He distinguished himself in...
</Question>
<Choice>John VI Cantacuzenus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor who spent his reign appealing to the West for help against the final assaults by the Ottoman Turks on the Byzantine Empire.Son of Manuel II Palaeologus, John was crowned coemperor with his father in 1408 and took effective rule in 1421. He was sole emperor after his father's death in 1425. He ruled the area immediately surrounding Constantinople, while his brothers governed remnants of the fragmented empire in the Greek Peloponnese and in the districts on the Black Sea.When the Turks took Thessalonica (modern Thessaloníki, Greece) in March 1430, John turned to the West for he...
</Question>
<Choice>John VIII Palaeologus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
sultan (from 1218) of the Ayyubid line, who ruled Egypt, Palestine, and Syria during the Fifth and Sixth crusades.On his accession to the sultanate, al-Kamil engaged the armies of the Fifth Crusade and eventually negotiated their withdrawal from Egypt in 1221. During this conflict he had an interview with St. Francis of Assisi, who wished to convert him to Christianity. In 1229 al-Kamil ceded Jerusalem and other Palestinian towns to Emperor Frederick II, leader of the Sixth Crusade.
</Question>
<Choice>Kamil, al-Malik al-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
temple name (miaohao) of the first emperor of the Nan (Southern) Song dynasty (1127–1279). He fled to South China when the nomadic Juchen tribesmen overran North China and captured Gaozong's father, the abdicated Bei (Northern) Song emperor Huizong (reigned 1100–1125/26), and Gaozong's brother, the emperor Qinzong (1125/26–27). Gaozong reestablished the dynasty in the South with greatly reduced territory in 1127. The Juchen had pursued him, but the great general Yue Fei held off the invaders, who in any case were having difficulty using their cavalry in the rivers and hills of southern and cen...
</Question>
<Choice>Kao-tsung</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the Scots (from 997), son of Dub and grandson of Malcolm I. He succeeded to the throne perhaps after killing his cousin Constantine III (reigned 995–997); he was himself killed at Monzievaird by Malcolm (son of Kenneth II), who became Malcolm II. Gruoch, wife of the future King Macbeth, was apparently a granddaughter of Kenneth III.
</Question>
<Choice>Kenneth III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
last king (1268–92) of Tumapel (or Singhasari) in Java, still venerated among the Javanese as one of their greatest rulers. He united Java, extended his influence over Sumatra, and resisted Mongol attempts to exact tribute from his kingdom.
</Question>
<Choice>Kertanagara</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mongolian general and statesman, grandson of Genghis Khan. He conquered China and became the first emperor of its Yüan, or Mongol, dynasty. He was thus at one and the same time the overlord of all the Mongol dominions—which included areas as diverse as that of the Golden Horde in southern Russia, the Il-Khanate of Persia, and the steppe heartlands where Mongol princes were still living the traditional nomadic life—and the ruler of his own realm of China. To govern China, with its long and individual political and cultural history, demanded statecraft of a special order.
</Question>
<Choice>Kublai Khan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Naples (from 1386), claimant to the throne of Hungary (from 1390), and prince of Taranto (from 1406). He became a skilled political and military leader, taking advantage of power struggles on the Italian peninsula to greatly expand his kingdom and his power.Succeeding his father, Charles III, in 1386, Ladislas was king at age nine under the regency of his mother, Margaret of Durazzo. Expelled from Naples in 1387 by the rival claimant Louis II of Anjou, he first subdued the recalcitrant Neapolitan barons and finally, in 1399, drove out Louis, who no longer was supported by France. In pu...
</Question>
<Choice>Ladislas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Hungary who greatly expanded the boundaries of the kingdom and consolidated it internally; no other Hungarian king was so generally beloved by the people.The son of Béla I of Hungary and the Polish princess Rycheza (Ryksa), Ladislas was born in exile. Returning to Hungary, he and his brother Géza refused to contest the throne against their cousin Salomon; however, they quarreled with him and drove him from the country (1073). Géza took the throne, and, on his death, in 1077, Ladislas succeeded him as king of Hungary.Ladislas extended Hungary's frontier in Transylvania and occupied Croa...
</Question>
<Choice>Ladislas I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
boy king of Hungary and of Bohemia (from 1453), who was caught up in the feud between his guardian Ulrich, count of Cilli, and the Hunyadi family of Hungary.Ladislas was the posthumous only son of the Habsburg German king Albert II, who had also been king of Hungary and Bohemia. The estates of Hungary had already selected Wladyslaw III of Poland to be their king as Ulászló I, but Ladislas' mother Elizabeth compelled the primate to crown Ladislas king at Székesfehérvár on May 15, 1440. She then placed him under the guardianship of his cousin, who was later to become Holy Roman emperor Frederick...
</Question>
<Choice>Ladislas V</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the greatest ruler of the Later Le dynasty (q.v.; 1428–1788) in Vietnam. Though the early years of Le Thanh Tong's reign were marked by a struggle for power, he eventually developed a governmental power base. He established a Chinese-style centralized administration and expanded dynastic control southward, at the expense of the once great kingdom of Champa, located on the southern coast of modern Vietnam.Ascending the throne in 1460, Le Thanh Tong divided the empire into 13 circuits (similar to Chinese provinces), each of which was subdivided into prefectures (phu), districts (huyen), and depa...
</Question>
<Choice>Le Thanh Tong</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prince of Gwynedd in northern Wales who struggled unsuccessfully to drive the English from Welsh territory. He was the only Welsh ruler to be officially recognized by the English as prince of Wales, but within a year after his death Wales fell completely under English rule.Although Llywelyn ap Gruffudd's grandfather, Llywelyn ap Iorwerth (d. 1240), had made Gwynedd the centre of Welsh power, the state nearly collapsed during the brief reign of his son David ap Llywelyn (1240–46). When David died in 1246, Llywelyn and his brother Owain divided the remaining territory. In 1255 Llywelyn seized Ow...
</Question>
<Choice>Llywelyn Ap Gruffudd</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
ecclesiastical statesman who governed England in 1190–91, while King Richard I (reigned 1189–99) was away from the kingdom during the Third Crusade.Of Norman origin, Longchamp was made chancellor of England and bishop of Ely when Richard ascended the throne. After Richard's departure on crusade, he became joint justiciar with Hugh de Puiset, bishop of Durham (March 1190). Longchamp soon drove Hugh from office, and in June 1190 he was appointed papal legate by Pope Clement III. Although he was able and completely loyal to Richard, Longchamp's overbearing manner and anti-English prejudices earne...
</Question>
<Choice>Longchamp, William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German king (1125–37) and Holy Roman emperor (1133–37). He is reckoned as Lothar III by those who count not only Lothar I but also his son Lothar in their numeration of German kings. Lothar II's election as king in 1125 represented a triumph for the principle of elective monarchy over that of hereditary succession, on which the claims of his Hohenstaufen opponents and their Salian predecessors were based.Lothar, the son of Gebhard, count of Supplinburg, was born a few days before his father was killed in battle on June 9, 1075. He succeeded to extensive lands around Helmstedt, in Saxony, and i...
</Question>
<Choice>Lothar II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
duke of Anjou, count of Maine, count of Provence, and claimant to the crown of Sicily and Jerusalem, who augmented his own and France's power by attempting to establish a French claim to the Sicilian throne and by vigorously fighting the English in France.A son of John II of France, Louis in 1356 fought ably at Poitiers against the English. He was sent to England as one of the hostages under the Treaty of Brétigny (1360) but soon escaped. In 1360 his father created the hereditary duchy of Anjou for him, having already given him the county of Maine (1356).Having been made lieutenant general of...
</Question>
<Choice>Louis I (duke of Anjou)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Hungary from 1342 and of Poland (as Louis) from 1370, who, during much of his long reign, was involved in wars with Venice and Naples.Louis was crowned king of Hungary in succession to his father, Charles I, on July 21, 1342. In 1346 he was defeated by the Venetians at Zara (now Zadar, Croatia), an Adriatic port city that had been under Hungarian protection. In 1347 he led an expedition against the kingdom of Naples to avenge the murder (1345) of his younger brother, Andrew, consort of Joan I of Naples, whose new husband, Louis of Taranto, was a suspected accomplice in the murder. Loui...
</Question>
<Choice>Louis I (king of Hungary)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
duke of upper Bavaria (from 1294) and of united Bavaria (1340–47), German king (from 1314), and Holy Roman emperor (1328–47), first of the Wittelsbach line of German emperors. His reign was marked by incessant diplomatic and military struggles to defend the right of the empire to elect an emperor independently of the papacy, to consolidate his own position, and to improve the status of his family.
</Question>
<Choice>Louis IV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of France from 1108 to 1137; he brought power and dignity to the French crown by his recovery of royal authority over the independent nobles in his domains of the Île-de-France and the Orléanais.Louis was designated by his father, Philip I, as his successor in 1098 and was already effectively the ruler well before Philip's death in 1108. He quickly recognized that his priority must be to bring the unruly barons of the royal lands under firm control, and he spent much of his reign in conflict with such men as Hugh de Puiset. His success won him the respect of his greater vassals and was cr...
</Question>
<Choice>Louis VI</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Capetian king of France who pursued a long rivalry, marked by recurrent warfare and continuous intrigue, with Henry II of England.In 1131 Louis was anointed as successor to his father, Louis VI, and in 1137 he became the sole ruler at his father's death. Louis married Eleanor, daughter of William X, duke of Aquitaine, in 1137, a few days before his effective rule began, and he thus temporarily extended the Capetian lands to the Pyrenees. Louis continued his father's pacification program by building the prestige of the kingship through an administrative government based on trustworthy men of hu...
</Question>
<Choice>Louis VII</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Capetian king of France from 1223 who spent most of his short reign establishing royal power in Poitou and Languedoc.On May 23, 1200, Louis married Blanche of Castile, daughter of Alfonso VIII of Castile, who effectively acted as regent after Louis's death. In 1212 Louis seized Saint-Omer and Aire to prevent a powerful Flanders from being on the flank of his county of Artois. In 1216, after the barons rebelling against King John of England had offered the English throne to Louis in return for his aid, Louis went to England to aid the rebels. Initially he was successful, but eventually he was d...
</Question>
<Choice>Louis VIII</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of France from 1226 to 1270, the most popular of the Capetian monarchs. He led the Seventh Crusade to the Holy Land in 1248–50 and died on another crusade to Tunisia.
</Question>
<Choice>Louis IX</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Capetian king of France from 1314 and king of Navarre from 1305 to 1314, who endured baronial unrest that was already serious in the time of his father, Philip IV the Fair.The eldest son of Philip and Joan of Navarre, he took the title of king of Navarre on his mother's death (April 4, 1305). But when he succeeded his father as king of France (Nov. 30, 1314), he resigned Navarre to his next brother, the future Philip V of France. In 1305 Louis married Margaret, daughter of Robert II, duke of Burgundy; in the last months of Philip IV's reign, she was convicted of adultery and was later strangle...
</Question>
<Choice>Louis X</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of France (1461–83) of the House of Valois who continued the work of his father, Charles VII, in strengthening and unifying France after the Hundred Years' War. He reimposed suzerainty over Boulonnais, Picardy, and Burgundy, took possession of France-Comté and Artois (1482), annexed Anjou (1471), and inherited Maine and Provence (1481).
</Question>
<Choice>Louis XI</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Scots from 1040, the legend of whose life was the basis of Shakespeare's Macbeth. He was probably a grandson of King Kenneth II (reigned 971–995), and he married Gruoch, a descendant of King Kenneth III (reigned 997–1005). About 1031 Macbeth succeeded his father, Findlaech (Sinel in Shakespeare), as mormaer, or chief, in the province of Moray, in northern Scotland. Macbeth established himself on the throne after killing his cousin King Duncan I in battle near Elgin—not, as in Shakespeare, by murdering Duncan in bed—on August 14, 1040. Both Duncan and Macbeth derived their rights to the...
</Question>
<Choice>Macbeth</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Norwegian ruler, king of Norway (1035–47) and Denmark (1042–47), who wrested hegemony in the two Scandinavian nations from descendants of Canute the Great (d. 1035), king of Denmark and England.An illegitimate son of the Norwegian king Olaf II Haraldsson (St. Olaf), Magnus was named after the Holy Roman emperor Charlemagne (Old Norse: Karlamagnús) and was taken to Russia at the age of four with his father, who had been exiled by Canute. In 1035 the chiefs of Norway rebelled against the rule of Canute's son Sweyn (Svein) and elected Magnus king. As a very young king, Magnus took his revenge on...
</Question>
<Choice>Magnus I Olafsson</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Sweden (1319–63) and of Norway (1319–55, as Magnus VII) who devoted himself to defending his Swedish sovereignty against rebellious nobles aided by various foreign leaders, most notably Valdemar IV Atterdag, king of Denmark.The son of Ingeborg, daughter of the Norwegian king Haakon V, and of Duke Erik, brother of the Swedish king Birger Magnusson, Magnus was accepted as ruler of both Norway and Sweden on Haakon V's death (1319). A regency controlled his two dominions until he came of age in 1332. Since Magnus spent nearly all his time in Sweden, the leading Norwegian nobles arranged in...
</Question>
<Choice>Magnus II Eriksson</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Norway (1093–1103), warrior who consolidated Norwegian rule in the Orkney and Hebrides islands and on the Isle of Man (all now part of the United Kingdom). He was called Barefoot (i.e., bareleg) because he often wore Scottish kilts.After succeeding his father, Olaf III Haraldsson, Magnus initially ruled jointly with his cousin Haakon and became sole ruler on Haakon's death the following year. In 1098 he launched expeditions to the Hebrides and the Isle of Man and responded to Welsh pleas for help against the Normans by attacking Anglesey, where he defeated the Norman earls Hugh of Ches...
</Question>
<Choice>Magnus III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Norway (1162–84) who used church support to gain the throne (1162) and become the nation's first crowned monarch (1163). After 1177 his rule was challenged by his rival Sverrir, whose forces killed Magnus in battle.The son of Erling the Crooked, Magnus became king in 1162 when his supporters, led by his father, defeated the forces of the incumbent king, Haakon II Sigurdsson. Magnus' father served as regent until 1164 and remained the real power behind the throne until his death in 1179.In 1163 Erling arranged with the Norwegian archbishop Eystein Erlandsson to have Magnus crowned in ex...
</Question>
<Choice>Magnus V Erlingsson</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Norway (1263–80) who transformed the nation's legal system by introducing new national, municipal, and ecclesiastical codes, which also served as a model for many of the Norwegian colonies. His national code was used for more than 400 years.Magnus succeeded his father, Haakon IV Haakonsson, in 1263 and quickly made peace with the Scottish king Alexander III, ceding to Scotland the Hebrides Islands and the Isle of Man in exchange for an initial payment and an annual rent. In 1274 Magnus introduced a new national legal code based on the existing system but replacing the provincial laws w...
</Question>
<Choice>Magnus VI</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
sultan of the kingdom of Ghazna (998–1030), originally comprising modern Afghanistan and northeastern modern Iran but, through his conquests, eventually including northwestern India and most of Iran. He transformed his capital, Ghazna, into a cultural centre rivalling Baghdad.
</Question>
<Choice>Mahmud</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Scotland from 1005 to 1034, the first to reign over an extent of land roughly corresponding to much of modern Scotland.Malcolm succeeded to the throne after killing his predecessor, Kenneth III, and allegedly secured his territory by defeating a Northumbrian army at the battle of Carham (c. 1016); he not only confirmed the Scottish hold over the land between the rivers Forth and Tweed but also secured Strathclyde about the same time. Eager to secure the royal succession for his daughter's son Duncan, he tried to eliminate possible rival claimants; but Macbeth, with royal connections to...
</Question>
<Choice>Malcolm II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Scotland from 1058 to 1093, founder of the dynasty that consolidated royal power in the Scottish kingdom.The son of King Duncan I (reigned 1034–40), Malcolm lived in exile in England during part of the reign of his father's murderer, Macbeth (reigned 1040–57). Malcolm killed Macbeth in battle in 1057 and then ascended the throne. After the conquest of England by William the Conqueror, in 1066, Malcolm gave refuge to the Anglo-Saxon prince Edgar the Aetheling and his sisters, one of whom, Margaret (later St. Margaret), became his second wife.Malcolm acknowledged the overlordship of Will...
</Question>
<Choice>Malcolm III Canmore</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Scotland (1153–65). Malcolm ascended the throne at the age of 11. He was the eldest son of Henry, Earl of Huntingdon and of Northumberland (d. 1152), and succeeded his grandfather King David I. Under Malcolm's predecessors, the kingdom of Scotland had been extended to embrace the modern English counties of Northumberland and Cumbria. In 1157, by a treaty signed at Chester, England's King Henry II forced the boy king Malcolm to surrender these counties in return for confirming Malcolm's rights to the earldom of Huntingdon.Malcolm died young, unmarried (thus his nickname, the Maiden) and...
</Question>
<Choice>Malcolm IV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
third and most famous of the Seljuq sultans.Malik-Shah succeeded his father, Alp-Arslan, in 1072 under the tutelage of the great vizier Ni?am al-Mulk, who was the real manager of the empire until his death. Malik-Shah had first to overcome a revolt of his uncle Qawurd (Kavurd) and an attack of the Qarakhanids of Bukhara on Khorasan; thereafter he consolidated and extended his empire more through diplomacy and the quarrels of his enemies than by actual warfare. He suppressed the former vassal principalities of upper Mesopotamia and Azerbaijan, acquired Syria and Palestine, and established a str...
</Question>
<Choice>Malik-Shah</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
effective king of Sicily from 1258, during a period of civil wars and succession disputes between imperial claimants and the House of Anjou.The son of the Holy Roman emperor Frederick II, Manfred became vicar of Italy and Sicily for his half brother Conrad IV but soon began seeking the Sicilian crown for himself. On Conrad's death in 1254 a diet at San Germano ignored the imperial representative and elected Manfred. Pope Alexander IV, however, after having excommunicated Manfred twice, invested Edmund, son of Henry III of England, with the Sicilian kingdom in April 1255. A papal army entered t...
</Question>
<Choice>Manfred</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
third ruler of the Mu?minid dynasty of Spain and North Africa, who during his reign (1184–99) brought the power of his dynasty to its zenith.When his father, Abu Ya?qub Yusuf, died on July 29, 1184, Abu Yusuf Ya?qub succeeded to the throne with minor difficulties. In November factious tribes in Algeria captured Algiers and other towns, but by 1188 he had pacified his African territories and returned to his Spanish possessions to check the encroachments of the Portuguese and Castilians. His efforts took seven years—until the Battle of Alarcos (July 18, 1195), when he decisively defeated the Cas...
</Question>
<Choice>Mansur, Abu Yusuf Ya'qub al-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
military leader, statesman, and Byzantine emperor (1143–80) whose policies failed to fulfill his dream of a restored Roman Empire, straining the resources of Byzantium at a time when the Seljuq Turks menaced the empire's survival.The son of John II Comnenus (reigned 1118–43) and the Hungarian princess Irene, Manuel transformed the austere, conservative court of his father into a gay setting for tournaments and festivities imported from medieval western Europe. Manuel devoted himself to affairs in the West at the beginning of his reign, practically ignoring the growing Turkish threat on the pla...
</Question>
<Choice>Manuel I Comnenus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
soldier, statesman, and Byzantine emperor (1391–1425) whose diplomacy enabled him to establish peaceful relations with the Ottoman Turks throughout his reign, delaying for some 50 years their ultimate conquest of the Byzantine Empire.Manuel was a son of John V Palaeologus (reigned 1341–91 with interruptions) and Helena Kantakouzene and was named heir to the throne in 1373 after his older brother, Andronicus IV, led an unsuccessful revolt against their father. Manuel was crowned coemperor in September 1373 and, in 1379, helped his father regain Constantinople and the throne, which Andronicus ha...
</Question>
<Choice>Manuel II Palaeologus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
regent of Denmark (from 1375), of Norway (from 1380), and of Sweden (from 1389), who, by diplomacy and war, pursued dynastic policies that led to the Kalmar Union (1397), which united Denmark, Norway, and Sweden until 1523 and Denmark and Norway until 1814.
</Question>
<Choice>Margaret I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prince of Serbia from 1371 to 1395 and a hero in the literature and traditions of the South Slavic peoples.Marko Kraljevic (“Mark, the King's Son”) was a member of the powerful Macedonian family allied to that of Balšic, which ruled in northern Albania and along the Adriatic. When his father, King Vukašin, was slain in battle with the Turks in 1371, Marko succeeded him as a vassal to the sultan. He is known to have completed a monastery at Sušica, near Skopje, and to have died fighting at the Battle of Rovine (1395) during a war between the Turks and the Walachian prince Mircea the Old, but ot...
</Question>
<Choice>Marko Kraljevic</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
queen consort of William I the Conqueror, whom she married c. 1053. During William's absences in England, the duchy of Normandy was under her regency, with the aid of their son, Robert Curthose (see Robert II [Normandy]), except when he was in rebellion against his father. The embroidery of the Bayeux tapestry was once wrongly attributed to her.
</Question>
<Choice>Matilda Of Flanders</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Hungary (1458–90), who attempted to reconstruct the Hungarian state after decades of feudal anarchy, chiefly by means of financial, military, judiciary, and administrative reforms. His nickname, Corvinus, derived from the raven (Latin corvus) on his escutcheon.
</Question>
<Choice>Matthias I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Muslim jurist who played an important role in formulating orthodox political theory as to the nature of the authority of the caliph.As a young man al-Mawardi entered the service of the caliph and soon came to be entrusted with the conduct of important negotiations with neighbouring princes. When the Buyid emirs, who since 946 had subjected the caliphs of Baghdad to their temporal authority, were weakened by internal dissensions and military revolts, the moment seemed ripe for an attempt to reassert caliphal authority, and al-Mawardi was commissioned to write an exposition of the prerogatives o...
</Question>
<Choice>Mawardi, al-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ottoman sultan who reunified the dismembered Ottoman territories following the defeat of Ankara (1402). He ruled in Anatolia and, after 1413, in the Balkans as well.Timur (Tamerlane), victorious over the Ottoman sultan Bayezid I at the Battle of Ankara, restored to the Turkmen their principalities that had been annexed by the Ottomans and divided the remaining Ottoman territory among three of Bayezid's sons. Thus, Mehmed ruled in Amasya, Isa in Bursa, and Süleyman in Rumelia (Balkan lands under Ottoman control). Mehmed defeated Isa and seized Bursa (1404–05) and then sent another brother, Mûsa...
</Question>
<Choice>Mehmed I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ottoman sultan from 1444 to 1446 and from 1451 to 1481. A great military leader, he captured Constantinople and conquered the territories in Anatolia and the Balkans that comprised the Ottoman Empire's heartland for the next four centuries.
</Question>
<Choice>Mehmed II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine prime minister, negotiator for Emperor Andronicus II Palaeologus, and one of the principal literary and philosophical scholars of the 14th century.The son of George Metochites, a prominent Eastern Orthodox cleric under Emperor Michael VIII Palaeologus and a leading advocate of union with the Latin church, Theodore became a favourite of Emperor Andronicus II and undertook various diplomatic missions to enlist help against the encroaching Ottoman Turks. In a vain attempt to reverse Byzantium's military and political decline through an alliance with Serbia, Metochites, in 1298, led an e...
</Question>
<Choice>Metochites, Theodore</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor during whose seven-year reign an important treaty was signed with the Fa?imid Caliphate of Egypt, temporary gains were made in Sicily, and a revolt in Bulgaria was suppressed.A man of humble origin, Michael owed his elevation to his brother John the Orphanotrophus, an influential and capable eunuch, who brought him to court where the old Macedonian empress Zoe fell in love with him and married him on the death of her husband, Romanus III, in April 1034.A 30 years' peace was signed with the Fa?imid Caliphate (c. 1037), thus ending a period of hostilities. Byzantium and Egypt e...
</Question>
<Choice>Michael IV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
GreekCaulkerByzantine emperor (1041–42). The nephew of Michael IV, Michael Calaphates was adopted by his uncle's elderly wife, Empress Zoe. Several months after his accession to the throne (Dec. 10, 1041), he exiled Zoe to a convent. An uprising erupted, however, and to stem it Michael hurriedly recalled her. Nevertheless, his political opponents had him deposed, blinded, and sent to a monastery.
</Question>
<Choice>Michael V Calaphates</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor who in his one-year reign (1056–57) failed to control the military aristocracy, which deposed him.The empress Theodora, the last ruler of the Macedonian dynasty, had chosen Michael, an elderly official, as her successor. On her death (August 21, 1056), Michael became emperor. His policies, however, antagonized the military leaders in Asia Minor, who proclaimed Isaac Comnenus emperor on June 8, 1057. Comnenus marched on Constantinople and defeated Michael's supporters on August 20. Michael abdicated 11 days later.
</Question>
<Choice>Michael VI Stratioticus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor (1071–78) whose policies hastened the conquest of Asia Minor by the Turks.The eldest son of Constantine X Ducas, Michael was a minor on his father's death (May 21, 1067), and his mother assumed the regency. Because of the dangerous military and political situation, she soon married the military commander Romanus Diogenes, who was crowned coemperor as Romanus IV in January 1068. On the defeat of Romanus by the Seljuq Turks at Manzikert in 1071, Michael was proclaimed sole emperor (October 24).When a Norman mercenary, Roussel de Bailleul, rebelled and attempted to set up a sepa...
</Question>
<Choice>Michael VII Ducas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nicaean emperor (1259–61) and then Byzantine emperor (1261–82), who in 1261 restored the Byzantine Empire to the Greeks after 57 years of Latin occupation and who founded the Palaeologan dynasty, the last and longest-lived of the empire's ruling houses.
</Question>
<Choice>Michael VIII Palaeologus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Poland from 1025 to 1034, grandson of Mieszko I. He was dominated by his wife, the German Ryxa (or Richeza), the niece of the emperor Otto III. Complications ensued from his political alliances with the German emperors and Saxon aristocracy, and he let the achievements of his father, Boleslaw I, crumble. Much territory was lost to Bohemia and to the Holy Roman Empire. At his death, Poland fell into anarchy.
</Question>
<Choice>Mieszko II Lambert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
founder of the bakufu, or shogunate, a system whereby feudal lords ruled Japan for 700 years.Defying the emperor, Yoritomo established shugo (constables) and jito (district stewards) throughout the Japanese provinces, thus undermining the central government's local administrative power, and in 1192 he acquired the title of supreme commander (shogun) over the shugo and jito.
</Question>
<Choice>Minamoto Yoritomo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
grandson of Genghis Khan and heir to the great Mongol empire.Elected great khan in 1251, he was the last man who held this title to base his capital at Karakorum, in central Mongolia. Under his rule the city achieved an unprecedented splendour, and the Mongol Empire continued to expand at a rapid rate. Its territory became so large and diverse that Möngke was the last great khan capable of exerting real authority over all the Mongol conquests.In the West, Möngke's armies, led by his brother Hülegü (c. 1217–65), launched an attack on Iran, crushing the last resistance there by the end of 1256....
</Question>
<Choice>Möngke</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
leader of the baronial revolt against King Henry III and ruler of England for less than a year.Simon de Montfort, wholly French by birth and education, was the son of Simon de Montfort l'Amaury, leader of the crusade against the heretical Albigenses. On coming of age, he renounced to his eldest brother, Amaury, his claims on the family lands in return for the sole right to revive the Montfort claim to the English earldom of Leicester. This claim derived from his father's mother, Amicia, sister of Robert IV (died 1204), the last Beaumont earl of Leicester, whose lands had been divided between A...
</Question>
<Choice>Montfort, Simon de, Earl Of Leicester</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
second sultan of the Tughluq dynasty (reigned 1325–51), who briefly extended the rule of the Delhi sultanate of northern India over most of the subcontinent. As a result of misguided administrative actions and unexampled severity toward his opponents, he eventually lost his authority in the south; at the end of his reign, the sultanate had begun to decline in power.
</Question>
<Choice>Muhammad ibn Tughluq</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
last Na?rid sultan of Granada, Spain. His reign (1482–92) was marked by incessant civil strife and the fall of Granada to Ferdinand and Isabella, the Roman Catholic rulers of Aragon and Castile.Instigated by his mother, a jealous wife, Boabdil rebelled against his father, the sultan Abu al-?asan ?Ali (called in Spanish sources Muley Hacén, or Alboacen); and with the aid of the Abencerrajes family seized the Alhambra in 1482 and was recognized as sultan. Abu al-?asan succeeded in recapturing the capital but was deposed by his brother az-Zaghall (Abu ?Abd Allah Mu?ammad az-Zaghall). On Boabdil's...
</Question>
<Choice>Muhammad XI</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ottoman sultan who ruled from 1360 to 1389. Murad's reign witnessed rapid Ottoman expansion in Anatolia and the Balkans and the emergence of new forms of government and administration to consolidate Ottoman rule in these areas.Murad ascended the throne in succession to his father, Orhan. Shortly after Murad's accession, his forces penetrated western Thrace and took Adrianople and Philippopolis and forced the Byzantine emperor John V Palaeologus to become a vassal. Adrianople was renamed Edirne, and it became Murad's capital. In 1366 a crusade commanded by Amadeus VI of Savoy rescued the Byzant...
</Question>
<Choice>Murad I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ottoman sultan (1421–44 and 1446–51) who expanded and consolidated Ottoman rule in the Balkans, pursued a policy of restraint in Anatolia, and helped lead the empire to recovery after its near demise at the hands of Timur following the Battle of Ankara (1402).Early in his reign, Murad had to overcome several claimants to the Ottoman throne who were supported by the Byzantine emperor Manuel II Palaeologus and by many of the Turkmen principalities in Anatolia. By 1425 Murad had eliminated his rivals, had reestablished Ottoman rule over the Turkmen principalities of western Anatolia, and had once...
</Question>
<Choice>Murad II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
mansa (emperor) of the West African empire of Mali from 1307 (or 1312). Mansa Musa left a realm notable for its extent and riches (he built the Great Mosque at Timbuktu), but he is best remembered in the Middle East and Europe for the splendour of his pilgrimage to Mecca (1324).
</Question>
<Choice>Musa</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the last ?Abbasid caliph in Baghdad (reigned 1242–58).Ineffectual himself and surrounded by advisers with conflicting opinions, al-Musta??im presented no strong defense against the Mongol conqueror Hülegü, grandson of Genghis Khan. Al-Musta??im ignored several demands of Hülegü and answered others with blustering and empty threats. Finally Hülegü laid siege to Baghdad in 1258 and entered the city in February of that year. The caliph and 300 officials hurried to present their surrender and, 10 days later, were all put to death. This left Islam without a caliph for the first time in its history....
</Question>
<Choice>Musta'sim, al-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
third and last member of the ?Abbadid dynasty of Sevilla (Seville) and the epitome of the cultivated Muslim Spaniard of the Middle Ages—liberal, tolerant, and a patron of the arts.At age 13 al-Mu?tamid commanded a military expedition that had been sent against the city of Silves. The venture was successful, and he was appointed governor of this and another district. In 1069 his father died, and al-Mu?tamid acceded to the throne of Sevilla. He was destined to rule in difficult times: neighbouring princes were resuming the inexorable advance that in time would bring all of Spain once again under...
</Question>
<Choice>Mu'tamid, al-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor (1078–81) whose use of Turkish support in acquiring and holding the throne tightened the grip of the Seljuq Turks on Anatolia.Nicephorus, who belonged to the military aristocracy of Asia Minor and who was related to the powerful Phocas family, became commander of the Anatolian theme (administrative district). When discontent against the government of Michael VII Ducas led to rioting in Constantinople, Nicephorus was proclaimed emperor (January 7, 1078) by his supporters there. With some support from Suleiman, the Seljuq ruler in Anatolia, Nicephorus was acclaimed emperor by h...
</Question>
<Choice>Nicephorus III Botaneiates</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
temple name (miaohao) of the 13th emperor of the Song dynasty (960–1279), whose reign (1195–1224) is noted as a period of intellectual and cultural achievement; Zhu Xi, the great Neo-Confucian philosopher, wrote some of his most famous works during this time. The government, however, was plagued by rising inflation, and the emperor came under the domination of the minister Han Tuozhou, who attempted to recover the Song territory in North China that had been lost to the Juchen several generations earlier. The war was disastrous, and more territory was lost to the Juchen, who demanded a huge ann...
</Question>
<Choice>Ning Tsung</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Arabic“Order of the Kingdom”Persian vizier of the Turkish Seljuq sultans (1063–92), best remembered for his large treatise on kingship, Seyasat-nameh (The Book of Government; or, Rules for Kings).
</Question>
<Choice>Nizam al-Mulk</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
son and successor of the Mongol ruler Genghis Khan (d. 1227), who greatly expanded the Mongol Empire.The third son of Genghis, Ögödei succeeded his father in 1229. He was the first ruler of the Mongols to call himself khagan (“great khan”); his father used only the title khan. He made his headquarters on the Orhon River in central Mongolia, where he built the capital city of Karakorum on the site laid out by his father. Like his father, he carried out several simultaneous campaigns, using generals in the field who acted independently but who were subject to his orders. The orders were transmit...
</Question>
<Choice>Ögödei</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the first effective king of all Norway and the country's patron saint, who achieved a 12-year respite from Danish domination and extensively increased the acceptance of Christianity. His religious code of 1024 is considered to represent Norway's first national legislation.The son of the lord Harald Grenske and a descendant of the Norwegian ruler Harald I Fairhair, Olaf was reared as a pagan and became a Viking warrior in the Baltic region. He fought against the English in 1009–11 but assisted the English ruler Ethelred (Aethelred) II the Unready against the Danes in 1013. When the Danish king...
</Question>
<Choice>Olaf II Haraldsson</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Norway (1066–93) who guided the nation through one of its most prosperous periods, maintaining an extended peace rare in medieval Norwegian history. He also strengthened the organization of the Norwegian church.A son of King Harald III Hardraade, Olaf fought in the unsuccessful Norwegian invasion of England (1066) in which his father was killed. He subsequently sued for peace with the English king Harold II and returned to Norway to rule jointly with his brother, Magnus II; he became sole monarch on Magnus' death in 1069. In 1068 he concluded a peace treaty with the Danish king Sweyn (...
</Question>
<Choice>Olaf III Haraldsson</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Denmark (as Olaf III, 1376–87) and of Norway (1380–87). He was the son of Haakon VI and of Margaret (Margrete), daughter of Valdemar IV, king of Denmark.After Valdemar's death in 1375, Olaf was elected (1376) king of Denmark and succeeded his father as king of Norway in 1380. The government of Norway was conducted by a state council, but power was largely in the hands of Olaf's mother, who planned to unite Norway, Sweden, and Denmark. Olaf attained his majority in 1385 but died two years later.
</Question>
<Choice>Olaf IV Haakonsson</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polish statesman and cardinal who was chief councillor to King Wladyslaw II and regent of Poland (1434–47).A member of the Polish noble house of Debno of Olesnica, he became the leading member of the royal Privy Council after he saved the King's life at the Battle of Grunwald in 1410. Olésnicki was ordained a priest in 1412 and was made bishop of Kraków in 1423. Representing the interests of the church and the nobility, he secured a limitation of royal power (March 1430) in exchange for the nobles' recognition of the King's young son Wladyslaw as the heir to the throne, thereby beginning the P...
</Question>
<Choice>Olesnicki, Zbigniew</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
eighth Il-Khan ruler of Iran, during whose reign the Shi?ite branch of Islam was first proclaimed the state religion of Iran.A great-grandson of Hülegü, founder of the Il-Khan dynasty, Öljeitü was baptized a Christian and given the name Nicholas by his mother. As a youth he converted to Buddhism and later to the Sunnite branch of Islam, taking the name Mo?ammad Khudabanda. After the death (1304) of his brother Ma?mud Ghazan, the seventh Il-Khan, he disposed of his rivals easily and acceded to a relatively peaceful reign. In 1307 the Caspian province of Jilan was conquered, strengthening Il-Kha...
</Question>
<Choice>Öljeitü</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the second ruler of the Ottoman dynasty, which had been founded by his father, Osman I. Orhan's reign (1324–60) marked the beginning of Ottoman expansion into the Balkans.Under Orhan's leadership, the small Ottoman principality in northwestern Anatolia continued to attract Ghazis (warriors for the Islamic faith) from surrounding Turkish emirates fighting against Byzantium. In 1324 the Byzantine town of Brusa (later Bursa) fell to the Ottomans, followed by Nicaea (modern Iznik) in 1331 and Nicomedia (modern Izmit) in 1337.Turning to the neighbouring Turkmen states, Orhan annexed the principalit...
</Question>
<Choice>Orhan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
ruler of a Turkmen principality in northwestern Anatolia who is regarded as the founder of the Ottoman Turkish state. Both the name of the dynasty and the empire that the dynasty established are derived from the Arabic form (?Uthman) of his name.Osman was descended from the Kayi branch of the Oguz Turkmen. His father, Ertugrul, had established a principality centred at Sögüt. With Sögüt as their base, Osman and the Muslim frontier warriors (Ghazis) under his command waged a slow and stubborn conflict against the Byzantines, who sought to defend their territories in the hinterland of the Asiati...
</Question>
<Choice>Osman I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Bohemia (1198–1230), who won both Bohemia's autonomy from the German king and the hereditary rights to the Bohemian crown for his house of Premysl.Initially confirmed as duke of Bohemia in 1192 by the Holy Roman emperor Henry VI, Otakar was deposed the following year but subsequently regained possession of the fief of Bohemia in 1197. He obtained the title of king in 1198 and almost total autonomy for Bohemia from the emperor Philip of Swabia. His title was subsequently confirmed by the emperor Frederick II (1212), who thereby all but extinguished the control of the empire in Bohemian...
</Question>
<Choice>Otakar I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Bohemia (1253–78), who briefly established his crownland as the most powerful state of the Holy Roman Empire.The son of King Wenceslas I of Bohemia, Otakar was elected duke of Austria in November 1251 and succeeded his father as king of Bohemia and Moravia in September 1253. In 1254 he conducted a crusade against the pagans of East Prussia, where later the Teutonic Knights named their citadel of Königsberg (modern Kaliningrad, Russia) after him. He also conducted another crusade against the Lithuanians (1266–67). He seized Styria (1260) from the Hungarians and in 1269 took possession o...
</Question>
<Choice>Otakar II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German king and Holy Roman emperor, candidate of the German anti-Hohenstaufen faction, who, after struggling against two Hohenstaufen kings, was finally deposed.A member of the Welf dynasty, Otto was a son of Henry the Lion of Brunswick and Matilda, daughter of Henry II of England. Brought up at the court of his uncle Richard I of England, Otto was made earl of York in 1190 and count of Poitou and duke of Aquitaine in 1196. Under both kings Richard and John, English diplomatic and financial help were to be of great assistance to Otto in his struggles with the Hohenstaufens.When the Hohenstaufe...
</Question>
<Choice>Otto IV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
last great king of North Wales (Gwynedd) who helped advance Welsh independence against Norman and English dominance.Together with his brother Cadwaladr, Owain led three expeditions (1136–37) against the English stronghold of Ceredigion to the south. The brothers ravaged the region and established themselves there. Upon his father's death in 1137, Owain took the throne of North Wales. During the reign of the English king Stephen, Owain extended the boundaries of northern Wales almost to the city of Chester. Henry II, who succeeded to the English throne in 1154, challenged Owain in 1157. Both si...
</Question>
<Choice>Owain Gwynedd</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mongol leader and khan of the Golden Horde, or Kipchak empire, of southern Russia, under whom it attained its greatest power; he reigned from 1312 to 1341. Öz Beg was a convert to Islam, but he also welcomed Christian missionaries from western Europe into his realm. Öz Beg encouraged the predominance of the princes of Moscow among his Christian vassals; his name survives today in that of the Uzbek people and of Uzbekistan.
</Question>
<Choice>Öz Beg</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Inca emperor (1438–71), an empire builder who, because he initiated the swift, far-ranging expansion of the Inca state, has been likened to Philip II of Macedonia. (Similarly, his son Topa Inca Yupanqui is regarded as a counterpart of Philip's son Alexander III the Great.)Pachacuti first conquered various peoples in what is now southern Peru and then extended his power northwesterly to Quito, Ecuador. He is said to have devised the city plan adopted for his capital, Cuzco (in present southern Peru). He also maintained royal estates for mummified past rulers.
</Question>
<Choice>Pachacuti Inca Yupanqui</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
celebrated king of Castile and Leon from 1350 to 1369, charged by his contemporary enemies with monstrous cruelty but viewed by later writers as a strong executor of justice.He succeeded his father, Alfonso XI, at the age of 15, and John II of France saw the chance to force Castile into a military alliance against England. The alliance was concluded (1352), and Peter was forced to marry (1353) Blanche, daughter of Pierre, duc de Bourbon, though he was already passionately in love with the beautiful María de Padilla—who was to remain his mistress, and perhaps his legal wife, until her death (13...
</Question>
<Choice>Peter</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Portugal from 1357 to 1367.The son of Afonso IV and his consort Beatriz of Castile, Peter was married in 1336 to Constanza of Castile; but she died in 1345, and Peter is chiefly remembered for his tragic amour with Inês de Castro (q.v.), whose death he savagely avenged after his accession to the throne. Even so, some of his acts, designed to curb abuses and to enhance the royal power, were of great importance: he reformed the administration of justice (1361) and did much to make the Portuguese church a national one by insisting on the beneplácito régio, that is, the royal approbation o...
</Question>
<Choice>Peter I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Aragon from 1196 to 1213, the eldest son and successor of Alfonso II.Peter married (1204) Mary, lady of Montpellier, and thus greatly extended Aragonese power in southern France. Despite the violent objections of his subjects, he had himself crowned by Pope Innocent III in Rome and declared his kingdom a feudatory of the Holy See (1204). Peter, with other Spanish kings, took a prominent part in the victory over the Moors at Las Navas de Tolosa (July 16, 1212); but he then went to support his brother-in-law Raymond VI of Toulouse against the crusader Simon de Montfort in Languedoc. Ther...
</Question>
<Choice>Peter II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Aragon from July 1276, on the death of his father, James I, and king of Sicily (as Peter I) from 1282.In 1262 he had married Constance, heiress of Manfred, the Hohenstaufen king of Sicily; and after the revolt of the Sicilians in 1282 he invaded the island and was proclaimed king at Palermo, despite strong Guelph and papal opposition (seeSicilian Vespers). His Sicilian enterprise was unpopular in Aragon, where an association of nobles and some municipalities, the Unión Aragonesa, forced him to grant a privilege not only confirming the Aragonese fueros (legal rights) but diminishing som...
</Question>
<Choice>Peter III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German Hohenstaufen king whose rivalry for the crown involved him in a decade of warfare with the Welf Otto IV.The youngest son of the Holy Roman emperor Frederick I Barbarossa, Philip was destined for the church. After being provost of the cathedral at Aachen, he was, in 1190 or 1191, elected bishop of Würzburg. Shortly after the death of his brother Frederick (1191), however, he abandoned his ecclesiastical career. Another brother, the Holy Roman emperor Henry VI, made him duke of Tuscany in 1195 and duke of Swabia in 1196. In May 1197 he married Irene, daughter of the Byzantine emperor Isaa...
</Question>
<Choice>Philip</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of France (1059–1108) who came to the throne at a time when the Capetian monarchy was extremely weak but who succeeded in enlarging the royal estates and treasury by a policy of devious alliances, the sale of his neutrality in the quarrels of powerful vassals, and the practice of simony on a huge scale.Philip was the elder son of Henry I of France by his second wife, Anne of Kiev. Crowned at Reims in May 1059, he became sole king on his father's death in 1060; Baldwin V, count of Flanders, exercised the regency. Two years after he came of age in 1066, he obtained the county of Gâtinais as...
</Question>
<Choice>Philip I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the first of the great Capetian kings of medieval France (reigned 1179–1223), who gradually reconquered the French territories held by the kings of England and also furthered the royal domains northward into Flanders and southward into Languedoc. He was a major figure in the Third Crusade to the Holy Land in 1191.
</Question>
<Choice>Philip II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of France (1270–85), in whose reign the power of the monarchy was enlarged and the royal domain extended, though his foreign policy and military ventures were largely unsuccessful.Philip, the second son of Louis IX of France (Saint Louis), became heir to the throne on the death of his elder brother Louis (1260). Accompanying his father's crusade against Tunis in 1270, he was in Africa when Louis IX died. He was anointed king at Reims in 1271.Philip continued his father's highly successful administration by keeping in office his able and experienced household clerks. Mathieu de Vendôme, ab...
</Question>
<Choice>Philip III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of France from 1285 to 1314 (and of Navarre, as Philip I, from 1284 to 1305, ruling jointly with his wife, Joan I of Navarre). His long struggle with the Roman papacy ended with the transfer of the Curia to Avignon, Fr. (beginning the so-called Babylonian Captivity, 1309–78). He also secured French royal power by wars on barons and neighbours and by restriction of feudal usages. His three sons were successively kings of France: Louis X, Philip V, and Charles IV.
</Question>
<Choice>Philip IV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of France (from 1316) and king of Navarre (as Philip II, from 1314), who largely succeeded in restoring the royal power to what it had been under his father, Philip IV.Philip was the second son of Philip IV, who made him count of Poitiers in 1311. When his elder brother, King Louis X, died in 1316, leaving an infant daughter Joan by his adulterous first wife, and a pregnant widow, Philip won recognition as regent for the unborn child and then, upon its death in November 1316, five days after birth, declared himself king. Anointed at Reims in January 1317, Philip quickly moved to consolida...
</Question>
<Choice>Philip V</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first French king of the Valois dynasty. Reigning at the outbreak of the Hundred Years' War (1337–1453), he had no means of imposing on his country the measures necessary for the maintenance of his monarchical power, though he continued the efforts of the 13th-century Capetians toward the centralization of the administration in Paris. To raise taxes for war, he was obliged to make concessions to the nobility, the clergy, and the bourgeoisie; hence his reign witnessed the important development of the political power of the estates. The bourgeoisie, profiting from the king's power, proved gratef...
</Question>
<Choice>Philip VI</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine philosopher, theologian, and statesman whose advocacy of Platonic philosophy as ideally integrable with Christian doctrine initiated a renewal of Byzantine classical learning that later influenced the Italian Renaissance.Psellus served in the Byzantine state secretariat under the emperors Michael V (1041–42) and Constantine IX (1042–54). The latter in 1045 chose him to head the philosophy faculty in the newly founded imperial university.In 1054, after the ecclesiastical upheaval following the definitive separation of the Greek and Roman churches, Psellus withdrew from academic work i...
</Question>
<Choice>Psellus, Michael</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
a founder of Muslim rule in India and an able general of Mu?izz al-Din Mu?ammad ibn Sam of Ghur.In childhood Qu?b was sold as a slave and raised at Nishapur. He came into the possession of Mu?izz al-Din, who put him in charge of the royal stables. Eventually he was appointed to military command, and in 1193, after conquering Delhi, Mu?izz al-Din returned to Khorasan and left the consolidation of the Ghurid conquests in northwest India to Qu?b. With his headquarters at Delhi, Qu?b subjugated areas between the Ganges (Ganga) and Yamuna (Jumna) rivers. He then turned his attention to the Rajputs...
</Question>
<Choice>Qutb-ud-Din Aybak</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German statesman, chancellor of the Holy Roman Empire, and archbishop of Cologne, the chief executor of the policies of the emperor Frederick I Barbarossa in Italy.After studying at Hildesheim and Paris and serving as a church provost, Rainald became (1153) a member of Emperor Frederick I's embassy to Pope Eugene III in Rome. In May 1156 he was appointed imperial chancellor. Between 1158 and 1164 Rainald led troops to Italy several times and negotiated with towns on Frederick's behalf. In 1159 he was elected archbishop of Cologne. After Pope Adrian IV's death the same year, Rainald championed...
</Question>
<Choice>Rainald Of Dassel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Aragon from 1134 to 1137. He was the third son of Sancho V Ramirez. His elder brother, Alfonso I the Battler, left no issue and bequeathed his kingdom to the military orders. Ramiro, who had entered a monastery and was bishop-elect of Barbastro, renounced his vows, married, and received the crown. His daughter Petronila was betrothed to the son of Count Ramón Berenguer IV of Barcelona. Ramiro abdicated in 1137 in favour of his daughter and son-in-law. In 1164 the crown of Aragon was united with the county of Barcelona under their son, Alfonso II.
</Question>
<Choice>Ramiro II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
third king of Sukhothai in what is now north-central Thailand, who made his young and struggling kingdom into the first major Tai state in 13th-century Southeast Asia.On the death of his brother, King Ban Muang, about 1279, Ramkhamhaeng inherited his tiny kingdom of only a few hundred square miles. Over the next two decades—by careful diplomacy, shrewd alliances, and military campaigns—he extended his power and influence as far as Vientiane and Luang Prabang in what is now Laos, west to the Indian Ocean coast of Myanmar (Burma), and south on the Malay Peninsula to Nakhon Si Thammarat. It is li...
</Question>
<Choice>Ramkhamhaeng</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
count of Barcelona from 1131 to 1162, regent of Provence from 1144 to 1157, and ruling prince of Aragon from 1137 to 1162.The elder son of Ramon Berenguer III, he continued his father's crusading wars against the Almoravid Muslims. The kingdom of Aragon soon sought Ramon Berenguer IV's aid against Castile. In the course of their negotiations, he was promised the hand of the Aragonese king Ramiro II's daughter and heir, Petronila (Peronella); they were married on Aug. 11, 1137, and a few months later (November 13), Ramiro II abdicated in favour of his daughter and son-in-law. Ramon Berenguer IV...
</Question>
<Choice>Ramon Berenguer IV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Persian statesman and historian who was the author of a universal history, Jami? at-tawarikh.He belonged to a Jewish family of Hamadan but was converted to Islam and as a physician joined the court of the Mongol ruler of Persia, Abagha (1265–82). He became vizier to Ghazan in 1298 and served under his successor Öljeitü. Accused by his rivals of having poisoned his sovereign, he was put to death by Öljeitü's son Abu Sa?id.Rashid ad-Din's history covers a vast field even outside the Muslim world. His sources of information for Mongolia and China were high officials of the Mongol empire and the M...
</Question>
<Choice>Rashid ad-Din</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prince of Antioch (1136–49) who successfully resisted the attempts of the Byzantine emperor John II to establish control over the principality.Raymond was the younger son of William VII, count of Poitiers, in west-central France. In 1135 King Fulk of the Latin kingdom of Jerusalem, regent for the heiress Constance of Antioch, sent envoys to offer her in marriage to Raymond, who was then at the court of Henry I of England. Raymond arrived in Antioch in April 1136 and married the nine-year-old Constance, thereby becoming ruler of Antioch.The Byzantine Empire had claimed Antioch ever since the Fi...
</Question>
<Choice>Raymond</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
count of the crusaders' state of Tripoli (1152–87) and twice regent of the Latin Kingdom of Jerusalem (1174–77, 1184–85).Raymond succeeded to the countship after the assassination of his father, Raymond II, in 1152. In his campaigns against the Muslims he was taken prisoner by their leader Nureddin in 1164 but was released in 1172. When the new king of Jerusalem, Baldwin IV, took the throne in 1174, Raymond successfully claimed the regency as the first cousin once removed of Baldwin, a minor and a leper. The regency ended when Baldwin came of age (1177), but Raymond continued to take an active...
</Question>
<Choice>Raymond III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prince of Antioch (1153–60), one of the leading military figures of the Crusades between 1147 and 1187, whose reckless policy in raiding Muslim caravans during periods of truce led to the virtual destruction of the Latin kingdom of Jerusalem and the loss of most of its territory.Reginald left for the Holy Land in 1147 and put himself at the service first of King Baldwin III of Jerusalem and then of Constance of Antioch. Constance, whose first husband had died in 1149, fell in love with Reginald and married him in 1153.As prince of Antioch, Reginald was cruel and violent. He treated the patriar...
</Question>
<Choice>Reginald of Châtillon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the Romans from 1256 to 1271, aspirant to the crown of the Holy Roman Empire.He was the second son of King John of England and was created Earl of Cornwall (May 30, 1227). Between 1227 and 1238 he frequently opposed his brother, King Henry III by joining the barons in several crises but never proceeding to rebellion and always making Henry pay heavily for reconciliation. He took the cross (1236) and led a small English force to the Holy Land (June 1240–January 1242), refortifying Ascalon and negotiating an advantageous treaty. During Henry III's disastrous Poitevin campaign in France (...
</Question>
<Choice>Richard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
duke of Aquitaine (from 1168) and of Poitiers (from 1172) and king of England, duke of Normandy, and count of Anjou (1189–99). His knightly manner and his prowess in the Third Crusade (1189–92) made him a popular king in his own time as well as the hero of countless romantic legends. He has been viewed less kindly by more recent historians and scholars.
</Question>
<Choice>Richard I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of England from 1377 to 1399. An ambitious ruler, with a lofty conception of the royal office, he was deposed by his cousin, Henry Bolingbroke (Henry IV), because of his arbitrary and factional rule.
</Question>
<Choice>Richard II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the last Plantagenet and Yorkist king of England. He usurped the throne of his nephew Edward V in 1483 and perished in defeat to Henry Tudor (thereafter Henry VII) at the Battle of Bosworth Field. For almost 500 years after his death he was generally depicted as the worst and most wicked of kings. Although some of these charges are now regarded as excessive and the work of his enemies and his supporters have attempted to rehabilitate him, modern scholars take a more balanced approach that avoids the extremes of either side.
</Question>
<Choice>Richard III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Angevin prince and Guelf (papal party) leader who ruled Naples as king for 34 years (1309–43).Robert's early years were clouded by the War of the Sicilian Vespers (1282–88), in which his father, Charles II of Anjou, was taken prisoner by the Aragonese. By the terms of the treaty Charles was freed, and Robert took his place as hostage at the Aragonese court. Taking the title of duke of Calabria (1296), he led an expedition attempting to recover Sicily from the Aragonese prince who ruled it as Frederick III. Robert's military success produced the Peace of Caltabellotta (1302), by which the Arago...
</Question>
<Choice>Robert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Scotland (1306–29), who freed Scotland from English rule, winning the decisive Battle of Bannockburn (1314) and ultimately confirming Scottish independence in the Treaty of Northampton (1328).
</Question>
<Choice>Robert I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of France who took Burgundy into the French realm.The son of Hugh Capet, founder of the Capetian dynasty, and Adelaide of Aquitaine, Robert was educated at the episcopal school of Reims under Gerbert of Aurillac, later Pope Sylvester II. Soon after his own coronation (July 987), Hugh prudently arranged the election and coronation (December 987) of Robert, thus facilitating his son's eventual succession (October 996) as sole ruler. His excommunication as a result of his marriage within the prohibited degrees of relationship was eventually lifted after the repudiation of the childless Berth...
</Question>
<Choice>Robert II (king of France)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Scots from 1371, first of the Stewart (Stuart) sovereigns in Scotland. Heir presumptive for more than 50 years, he had little effect on Scottish political and military affairs when he finally acceded to the throne.On the death (1326) of his father, Walter the Steward, in 1326, Robert became seventh hereditary steward of Scotland at age 10. From 1318 he was heir presumptive to his maternal grandfather, King Robert I the Bruce (died 1329). He lost this position in 1324 when the Bruce's son, afterward King David II, was born; but two years later the Scottish Parliament confirmed Robert th...
</Question>
<Choice>Robert II (king of Scotland)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Scots from 1390, after having ruled Scotland in the name of his father, Robert II, from 1384 to 1388. Physically disabled by a kick from a horse, he was never the real ruler of Scotland during the years of his kingship.The eldest son of Robert the Steward (the future Robert II) and Elizabeth Mure, he was legitimated by their marriage several years after his birth. In 1362–63 he joined his father in a futile revolt against King David II, who both imprisoned him and created him earl of Carrick in 1368. (He had been created earl of Atholl in 1367.) Robert II became king in 1371; in 1384,...
</Question>
<Choice>Robert III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Connaught and the last high king of Ireland; he failed to turn back the Anglo-Norman invasion that led to the conquest of Ireland by England.Roderic succeeded his father, Turloch O'Connor, as king of Connaught in 1156. Since Turloch's title of high king was claimed by Muirchertach O'Lochlainn of Ulster, Roderic did not become high king until O'Lochlainn was killed in 1166. He then attacked Dermot MacMurrough, king of Leinster, and seized his territories. Dermot appealed to the English for aid, and in 1170 the Anglo-Norman Richard de Clare, 2nd earl of Pembroke—subsequently known as “St...
</Question>
<Choice>Roderic O'connor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
grand count of Sicily (1105–30) and king of the Norman Kingdom of Sicily (1130–54). He also incorporated the mainland territories of Calabria in 1122 and Apulia in 1127.
</Question>
<Choice>Roger II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor (January 1, 1068–1071), a member of the Cappadocian military aristocracy.In 1068 Romanus married Eudocia Macrembolitissa, widow of the emperor Constantine X Ducas. He led military expeditions against the Seljuq Turks but was defeated and captured by them at the Battle of Manzikert (1071). On his release Romanus found that Constantine X's son had been crowned sole ruler as Michael VII Ducas. Romanus was blinded and exiled to the island of Prote in the Sea of Marmara, where he died.
</Question>
<Choice>Romanus IV Diogenes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first German king of the Habsburg dynasty.A son of Albert IV, Count of Habsburg, Rudolf on the occasion of his father's death (c. 1239) inherited lands in upper Alsace, the Aargau, and Breisgau. A partisan of the Hohenstaufen Holy Roman emperor Frederick II and his son Conrad IV, he increased his territories largely at the expense of his uncle, Count Hartmann of Kyburg, and his cousin, Count Hartmann the Younger, who supported the papal cause against the Hohenstaufens. Rudolf's first marriage (c. 1245), to Gertrude of Zollern-Hohenberg-Haigerloch, also added considerable property to his domain...
</Question>
<Choice>Rudolf I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German king from 1400 and, as Rupert III, elector Palatine of the Rhine from 1398. A member of the Wittelsbach dynasty, he was chosen king by the German ecclesiastical electors on Aug. 22, 1400, to succeed Wenceslas, who had been deposed the day before by the German princes. After being crowned at Cologne on Jan. 6, 1401, Rupert went to Italy, hoping to be crowned again by Pope Boniface IX. In alliance with the city of Florence he attacked Gian Galeazzo Visconti, duke of Milan (who had given financial support to Wenceslas in the 1390s), but was defeated outside Brescia on Oct. 14, 1401, and re...
</Question>
<Choice>Rupert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Muslim sultan of Egypt, Syria, Yemen, and Palestine, founder of the Ayyubid dynasty, and the most famous of Muslim heroes. In wars against the Christian Crusaders, he achieved great success with the capture of Jerusalem (Oct. 2, 1187), ending its nearly nine decades of occupation by the Franks.Saladin was born into a prominent Kurdish family. On the night of his birth, his father, Najm al-Din Ayyub, gathered his family and moved to Aleppo, there entering the service of ?Imad al-Din Zangi ibn Aq Sonqur, the powerful Turkish governor in northern Syria. Growing up in Ba?lbek and Damascus, Saladin...
</Question>
<Choice>Saladin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
last effective ruler (reigned 1239 and 1245–49) of the Ayyubid dynasty in Egypt.A?-?ali?'s campaign against the crusader kingdom of Jerusalem in alliance with the Khwarezmians (1244) provoked the launching of the Seventh Crusade under Louis IX of France. A?-?ali? died during Louis's subsequent invasion of Egypt. The Mamluk mercenaries to whom he had given extensive power overthrew his dynasty in 1250.
</Question>
<Choice>Salih Ayyub, as-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Talmudic scholar, grammarian, philologist, poet, warrior, and statesman who for two decades was the power behind the throne of the caliphate of Granada.As a youth Samuel received a thorough education in all branches of Jewish and Islamic knowledge and mastered Arabic calligraphy, a rare achievement among Jews. When Córdoba was sacked in 1013 by the Berbers, a north African people believing in Islam, Samuel fled to Málaga, at that time part of the Muslim kingdom of Granada.Samuel's unusual linguistic and calligraphic skills caught the attention of the Granadan vizier, who employed him as his pr...
</Question>
<Choice>Samuel ha-Nagid</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Castile from 1065 to 1072, the eldest son of Ferdinand I.He was allocated the kingdom of Castile in his father's will, Leon and Galicia being given to his brothers. He refused to accept this division and dispossessed García of Galicia by force (1071). Alfonso VI of Leon, defeated at Golpejera on the Carrión River in January 1072, had to seek refuge with the Moorish king of Toledo. Sancho's triumph was short-lived, for he was killed while besieging the rebel fortress-city of Zamora, held by his sister Urraca in Alfonso's name.
</Question>
<Choice>Sancho II (king of Castile)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
fourth king of Portugal, son of Afonso II and of Urraca, who was the daughter of Alfonso VIII of Castile.Factions were so fostered during Sancho's minority that his later government was never anything more than a series of vain attempts to achieve political stability in the kingdom. Renewing the struggle against the Moors, he took Tavira and Cacela (1238–39), thereby extending Portuguese sovereignty over a large part of the Algarve. But from 1240 onward internal disorders increased, and Pope Innocent IV's recognition of the king's political incapacity to govern led to Sancho's deposition (1245...
</Question>
<Choice>Sancho II (king of Portugal)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Pamplona (Navarre) from about 1000 to 1035, the son of García II (or III).Sancho established Navarrese hegemony over all the Christian states of Spain at a time when the caliphate of Córdoba was in a state of turmoil. Sancho was uninterested in a crusade against the Moors, but he was interested in the expansion of Pamplona, which he began by the seizure of the ancient Frankish counties of Sobrarbe and Ribagorza (1016–19). A skilled politician, Sancho pursued his aims more by subversion than by force of arms. He persuaded the Count of Barcelona, Berenguer Ramón I, to accept him as overl...
</Question>
<Choice>Sancho III Garcés</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Castile and Leon from 1284 to 1295, second son of Alfonso X. Though ambitious and ruthless, he was also an able politician and a cultivated man.In 1275 his elder brother, Fernando de la Cerda, was killed, leaving a son, Alfonso de la Cerda, heir to Alfonso X. Sancho, supported by the nobles and the military orders, sought recognition as heir instead of his nephew and took up arms against the king. After some years of strife he succeeded in making good his usurpation on his father's death (April 1284). Support for Alfonso de la Cerda came from factions at home and from France and Aragon...
</Question>
<Choice>Sancho IV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Seljuq prince of Khorasan from c. 1096 to 1157, whose fame almost eclipses that of the “Great Seljuqs” because of the length of his reign, his power and victories in its first half, his disasters in the second, and the fact that he was the last real Seljuq sultan in Iran.Appointed governor of Khorasan by his half brother Berk-yaruq, who succeeded Malik-Shah as sultan, Sanjar in fact acted as an independent prince throughout his reign and after the death of his full brother Muhammad in 1118 was regarded as the head of the Seljuq house. His longevity saved Khorasan from the internecine struggles...
</Question>
<Choice>Sanjar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
71st emperor of Japan, whose abdication in favour of his son, Kidahito (the emperor Shirakawa), established a precedent for government by retired emperor, thereby contributing to the decline of the powerful Fujiwara clan.One of the few Japanese rulers of the period not born of a Fujiwara mother, Takahito became emperor in 1068, taking the reign name Go-Sanjo (Later Sanjo); he ascended the throne over the objections of the great clan, which, since 857, had dominated the government, usually by making Fujiwara daughters principal concubines or consorts to reigning emperors. A lack of daughters le...
</Question>
<Choice>Sanjo, Go-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
monarch of the Yi dynasty during whose reign (1419–50) cultural achievements in Korea reached their highest point. Sejong is best known for his development of Hangul (han'gul), a phonetic system for writing the Korean language, considered one of the most scientific alphabets in use in any country. He is also known for his action in banning all Buddhist monks from Seoul, drastically reducing the power and wealth of the Buddhist hierarchy.
</Question>
<Choice>Sejong</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian Renaissance regent (1480–94) and duke of Milan (1494–98), a ruthless prince and diplomatist and a patron of Leonardo da Vinci and other artists.
</Question>
<Choice>Sforza, Ludovico</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
temple name (miaohao) of the sixth emperor (reigned 1067–85) of the Song dynasty (960–1279) of China. During his reign some of the greatest intellectual and cultural figures of the era flourished, among them Ouyang Xiu and Su Dongpo.Under the Shenzong emperor, the radical reformer Wang Anshi carried out his economic and social program. Low-interest government loans to peasants were instituted, new land surveys were made to correct tax inequities, and government revenues were increased by a program of purchasing manufactured specialties in one region and selling them in another. To augment the...
</Question>
<Choice>Shen Tsung</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
72nd emperor of Japan who abdicated the throne and then established a cloister government (insei) through which he could maintain his power unburdened by the exacting ceremonial and family duty required of the legitimate Japanese sovereign. He thus established a precedent that allowed the Japanese emperor to abdicate and, once away from the court, to assume the real power of government.He succeeded to the throne in 1072, taking the reign name Shirakawa, after his father, the emperor Go-Sanjo, had abdicated in his favour. His ascendancy came at a time when the encroachment of private landed est...
</Question>
<Choice>Shirakawa</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
77th emperor of Japan, during whose reign political power was transferred from the imperial court to the provincial warrior class.He ascended the throne in 1155, taking the reign name Go-Shirakawa, after the death of his brother, the emperor Konoe. When his father, the former emperor Toba, died a year later, another brother, the former emperor Sutoku, attempted a coup d'état. Sutoku had succeeded Toba on the throne but had abdicated in 1141 on condition that his own son succeed Konoe. After Toba chose Go-Shirakawa instead as Konoe's successor, Sutoku began to plot his revenge. In the ensuing H...
</Question>
<Choice>Shirakawa, Go-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
queen of the crusader state of Jerusalem (1186–90).The daughter of Amalric I, Sibyl succeeded to the throne upon the death of her brother, Baldwin IV (1185). Baldwin had intended for the throne to pass directly to Sibyl's son Baldwin V, but Sibyl and her husband, Guy de Lusignan, conspired to seize the throne for themselves, embroiling the kingdom in a disastrous war with Saladin.
</Question>
<Choice>Sibyl</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Holy Roman emperor from 1433, king of Hungary from 1387, German king from 1411, king of Bohemia from 1419, and Lombard king from 1431. The last emperor of the House of Luxembourg, he participated in settling the Western Schism and the Hussite wars in Bohemia.Sigismund, a younger son of the Holy Roman emperor Charles IV, received from his father the margravate of Brandenburg. Engaged to Maria, daughter of King Louis I of Hungary and Poland, he was sent on his father's death (1378) to the Hungarian court, where he married Maria. On her father's death in 1382, Maria became queen of Hungary, and S...
</Question>
<Choice>Sigismund</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Norway (1103–30) and the first Scandinavian king to participate in the Crusades. He strengthened the Norwegian church by building cathedrals and monasteries and by imposing tithes, which provided a reliable source of income for the clergy.An illegitimate son of the Norwegian king Magnus III Barefoot, Sigurd succeeded to the throne with his elder and younger brothers, Eystein and Olaf Magnusson, in 1103. Olaf died in 1115 while still a youth and never actually ruled, leaving Sigurd and Eystein to reign jointly until Eystein's death in 1122, the longest joint rule in Norwegian history.In...
</Question>
<Choice>Sigurd I Magnusson</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
West African monarch who initiated the imperial expansion of the Western Sudanese kingdom of Songhai. His conquest of the leading Sudanese trading cities established the basis for Songhai's future prosperity and expansion.When Sonni ?Ali ascended the Songhai throne c. 1464, the kingdom comprised only a small area in the upper Niger valley around its capital, the prosperous trading city of Gao. Although the Songhai people had managed to throw off the domination of the Mali Empire, they also hoped to obtain territorial benefits, like other West African peoples, from the disintegration of Mali. S...
</Question>
<Choice>Sonni 'Ali</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Serbia (1331–46) and “Emperor of the Serbs, Greeks, and Albanians” (1346–55), the greatest ruler of medieval Serbia, who promoted his nation's influence and gave his people a new code of laws.
</Question>
<Choice>Stefan Dušan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of England from 1135 to 1154. He gained the throne by usurpation but failed to consolidate his power during the ensuing civil strife.Stephen was the third son of Stephen, Count of Blois and Chartres, and Adela, daughter of King William I the Conqueror. He was reared by his uncle, King Henry I, and received vast lands in England, Normandy, and the county of Boulogne. With a number of other magnates he was pledged to support Henry's daughter, Matilda (q.v.), as successor to the throne. Nevertheless, many English nobles were reluctant to accept a woman ruler, and Henry's Norman subjects rese...
</Question>
<Choice>Stephen (king of England)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
voivod (prince) of Moldavia (1457–1504), who won renown in Europe for his long resistance to the Ottoman Turks.With the help of the Walachian prince Vlad III the Impaler, Stephen secured the throne of Moldavia in 1457. Menaced by powerful neighbours, he successfully repulsed an invasion by Hungary in 1467, but in 1471 he invaded Walachia, which had by then succumbed to Turkish vassalage.When the Ottoman sultan Mehmed II launched an attack on Moldavia, Stephen defeated the invaders near Vaslui (now in Romania; 1475). He was in turn defeated at Valea Alba (1476), and he barely managed to escape...
</Question>
<Choice>Stephen (prince of Moldavia)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first king of Hungary, who is considered to be the founder of the Hungarian state and one of the most renowned figures in Hungarian history.Stephen was a member of the Árpád dynasty and son of the supreme Magyar chieftain Géza. He was born a pagan but was baptized and reared as a Christian, and in 996 he married Gisela, daughter of Duke Henry II of Bavaria. After the death of his father (997), Stephen combated an insurrection led by his older cousin, Koppány, who claimed the throne in accordance with Árpád succession rules. Stephen defeated Koppány at Veszprém (998) and had him executed as a p...
</Question>
<Choice>Stephen I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Hungary (1270–72), the eldest son of Béla IV.In 1262, as crown prince, he compelled his father, whom he had assisted in the Bohemian war, to surrender 29 counties to him, virtually dividing Hungary into two kingdoms; while afterward he seized the southern banate of Macso, which led to a fresh war between father and son in which the latter triumphed. In 1268 he invaded Bulgaria and assumed the title of king of Bulgaria.During his father's lifetime Stephen had a double matrimonial alliance with the Neapolitan princes of the House of Anjou, the chief partisans of the pope. He certainly ne...
</Question>
<Choice>Stephen V</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
regent of Sweden (1470–97, 1501–03) who resisted Danish domination and built up a strong central administration.Sten, a member of a powerful noble family, led forces that ended an attempt by the Danish king Christian I to gain control over Sweden in 1471, inflicting a decisive defeat on the Danish ruler in the Battle of Brunkeberg. He helped the Swedish king Charles VIII regain the throne (1467) and was appointed regent on Charles's death (1470). He soon gained passage of measures that reduced German influence in Swedish municipal governments, and he strengthened the nation's legal institution...
</Question>
<Choice>Sture, Sten, The Elder</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French abbot and adviser to kings Louis VI and VII whose supervision of the rebuilding of the abbey church of Saint-Denis was instrumental in the development of the Gothic style of architecture.Suger was born of peasant parents. As a child he showed unusual intelligence, and in 1091 he was brought to the nearby abbey of Saint-Denis (the patron saint of France) to be educated by the monks. His closest friend and schoolmate at the abbey was Louis Capet, a boy his age. This boy became King Louis VI in 1108. Suger became secretary to the abbot Adam of Saint-Denis and a close adviser to the king.As...
</Question>
<Choice>Suger</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
great Khmer king of the Angkor period of Cambodian history. He was renowned as a conqueror and builder who greatly expanded his territorial holdings and consolidated the conquered lands into a strong, unified empire.Suryavarman defeated King Udayadityavarman by 1002 and Jayaviravarman (of Malay origin), his would-be successor, by 1010, securing the Khmer throne for himself. In contrast to his Hindu subjects, Suryavarman was a Mahayana Buddhist who, in the opinion of some scholars, considerably enhanced the prestige and influence of his religion among the Khmers and yet was tolerant of the loca...
</Question>
<Choice>Suryavarman I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Cambodian king renowned as a religious reformer and temple builder. Under his rule the temple of Angkor Wat, the world's largest religious structure, was constructed.Suryavarman defeated rival claimants to the throne and established sole rule over Cambodia by 1113, reuniting the country after more than 50 years of unrest. Warlike and ambitious, he expanded the limits of Cambodia to include much of what is now Thailand; his patronage stretched as far west as the frontiers of the Burmese state of Pagan, south to the coast of the Gulf of Thailand (including part of the eastern coast of the Malay...
</Question>
<Choice>Suryavarman II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
75th emperor of Japan; his attempt to usurp his brother's throne resulted in the bloody Hogen War, which allowed the powerful warrior Taira clan to gain control of the government.He ascended the throne in 1123, taking the reign name Sutoku, after the abdication of his father, the emperor Toba; despite his abdication Toba continued to hold power. In 1141 Sutoku also abdicated, and his younger brother came to the throne as the emperor Konoe. When Konoe died in 1155, their father's third and favourite son was selected to ascend the throne as Go-Shirakawa, much to the displeasure of Sutoku, who ha...
</Question>
<Choice>Sutoku</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Norway (1177–1202) and one of the best-known figures in medieval Norwegian history. By expanding the power of the monarchy and limiting the privileges of the church, he provoked civil uprisings that were not quelled until 1217.The son of Gunnhild, a Norwegian woman married to a Faroe Islands man, Sverrir was ordained priest at an unusually early age. After his mother told him that he was actually the son of the former Norwegian king Sigurd II, however, he left for Norway (1174) to claim the throne. By 1177 he had become leader of the Birchlegs, rivals of the incumbent ruler Magnus V. A...
</Question>
<Choice>Sverrir Sigurdsson</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Denmark (1047–74) who ended a short period of Norwegian domination (1042–47).The son of Ulf, a Danish earl, and Estrid, a sister of Canute I the Great, Sweyn fled to Sweden after his father was murdered in 1027 on orders of Canute. After the death of Canute (1035), when Hardecanute was ruling in Denmark and Magnus in Norway, the young kings agreed that whoever lived longer would rule both countries. Under this agreement Magnus became king also of Denmark in 1042 and appointed Sweyn viceroy. While Magnus was fighting the Wends (Slavs) in 1043, Sweyn, who was favoured by the Danish noble...
</Question>
<Choice>Sweyn II Estridsen</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Sicily whose brief reign marked the end of the Norman rule there.An illegitimate son of Duke Roger of Apulia and grandson of Roger II, king of Sicily, Tancred joined an insurrection in 1155 against his uncle William I of Sicily and was imprisoned for five years. Released, he participated in another abortive coup in 1161 and went into exile.Thirteen years later, forgiven his disloyalty to William I, Tancred led William II's expedition against Alexandria and later commanded a Sicilian fleet. William II's death in 1189 without direct heirs found Tancred a serious contender for the throne....
</Question>
<Choice>Tancred</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
regent of Antioch, one of the leaders of the First Crusade.Tancred was a Norman lord of south Italy. He went on the Crusade with his uncle, Bohemond (the future Bohemond I of Antioch), and first distinguished himself in Cilicia, where he captured Tarsus from the Turks and came into conflict with his fellow Crusader, Baldwin of Boulogne. He played a prominent part in most of the major battles of the Crusade, and after the capture of Jerusalem (1099) he received the title Prince of Galilee. He served as regent of the principality of Antioch for Bohemond while the latter was a prisoner of the Tur...
</Question>
<Choice>Tancred of Hauteville</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
count of Troyes and of Champagne (from 1201), as Theobald IV, and king of Navarre (from 1234), the most famous of the aristocratic trouvères.He was the son of Theobald III of Champagne, who died before his son was born, and Blanche of Navarre. He lived for four years at the court of King Philip II of France, to whom he did feudal homage in 1214. After Philip's death (1223), he supported Philip's son Louis VIII but deserted him in 1226 at the siege of Avignon, conducted by the king as part of his campaign against the Albigenses, a religious sect deemed heretical. On the death of Louis a few mon...
</Question>
<Choice>Theobald I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine empress who reigned jointly with her sister Zoe in 1042 and on her own in 1055–56.The third daughter of the emperor Constantine VIII, Theodora possessed a strong and austere character and refused the hand of the heir presumptive, Romanus, who was married instead to her sister Zoe (1028). Though living in retirement, she excited Zoe's jealousy and, accused of complicity in a conspiracy, was confined in a monastery. In 1042 the popular movement that caused the dethronement of Michael V also led to Theodora's installment as joint empress with her sister. After two months of active parti...
</Question>
<Choice>Theodora</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first emperor of Nicaea, which was recognized as the Byzantine government-in-exile and as the legitimate successor of the Byzantine Empire during the Crusaders' occupation of Constantinople.He was a son-in-law and heir of the Byzantine emperor Alexius III Angelus. After the Byzantine capital fell to the Fourth Crusade in 1204, Theodore gathered a band of refugees, first at Brusa and then at Nicaea, across the Bosporus in Asia Minor, and formed a new Byzantine state. In 1208 he assumed the title of emperor and defended his infant empire not only against the Crusaders but also against David Comn...
</Question>
<Choice>Theodore I Lascaris</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Turkic conqueror, chiefly remembered for the barbarity of his conquests from India and Russia to the Mediterranean Sea and for the cultural achievements of his dynasty.
</Question>
<Choice>Timur</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
82nd emperor of Japan, whose attempt to restore power to the imperial house resulted in total subjugation of the Japanese court.He was placed on the throne in 1183, taking the reign name Go-Toba (“Later Toba”), by the Minamoto clan after it had established military hegemony over most of Japan.After reigning for 15 years, Go-Toba in 1198 abdicated in favour of his son in order to form a cloister government (insei) through which he dominated the imperial court. The following year Minamoto Yoritomo, head of the Minamoto clan, whom the emperor had appointed to the office of shogun (military dictat...
</Question>
<Choice>Toba, Go-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
founder of the Seljuq dynasty, which ruled in Iran, Iraq, Syria, and Anatolia during the 11th– 14th centuries. Under his rule the Seljuqs assumed the leadership of the Islamic world by establishing political mastery over the ?Abbasid caliphate in Baghdad.The grandson of Seljuq, chief of the Oguz tribes in the Jand region, Toghrïl, with his brother Chaghrï, entered Muslim Transoxania shortly before 1016, and in 1025 they and their uncle Arslan entered the service of the Turkish Qarakhanid prince of Bukhara. Defeated by Ma?mud of Ghazna in the same year, Toghrïl and Chaghrï took refuge in Khware...
</Question>
<Choice>Toghrïl Beg</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
last emperor (reigned 1333–68) of the Yuan (Mongol) dynasty (1206–1368) in China, under whom the population was provoked into rebellion.Togon-temür became emperor at the age of 13 but proved to be a weak ruler who preferred to spend his time exploring the religious cult of Lamaism and dallying with his harem rather than governing the country. In the early years of his reign, power was held by the anti-Chinese minister Bayan, who suspended the civil-service examinations, prohibited Chinese from wearing certain colours or using certain ideographs, and even proposed mass execution of Chinese on t...
</Question>
<Choice>Togon-temür</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(b.1431, Ayutthaya, Siam [now Phra Nakhon Si Ayutthaya, Thailand]—d. 1488, Phitsanulok), eighth king of Siam (Thailand; 1448–88), who established a centralized political and administrative system, the outlines of which lasted until the late 19th century.Trailok's father, King Borommaracha II (1424–48), named him heir apparent in 1438, and even as a small boy he was named the king's deputy in the important northern city of Phitsanulok. Though only an adolescent when he came to the throne, he proved to be an energetic leader and administrator. Under the pressure of constant warfare against the T...
</Question>
<Choice>Trailok</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
probably the greatest ruler of Bosnia, ruling as Bosnian ban (provincial lord, subservient to the king of Hungary) from 1353 and king of the Serbs and Bosnia from 1377. In 1363 Tvrtko commenced war with King Louis I of Hungary, but afterward Louis helped him regain power following a revolution in Bosnia. At Bileca in 1388 Tvrtko's forces halted an Ottoman Turkish invasion. In 1390 he extended his power into Croatia and to the Dalmatian islands in the Adriatic Sea.
</Question>
<Choice>Tvrtko I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
queen of Leon and Castile from 1109 to 1126, daughter of Alfonso VI.Urraca became her father's heiress when her brother, Sancho, was killed at Uclés (1108). She was the widow of Count Raymond of Burgundy, by whom she had had one son, Alfonso Ramírez (born 1104), the future Alfonso VII. To counterbalance—it was hoped—the dangers of a female succession during the Almoravid crisis, Urraca's marriage to her second cousin, Alfonso I of Aragon, was arranged (1109). This marriage, instead of producing political stability in Urraca's kingdom, led to years of anarchy. Urraca and her husband, according...
</Question>
<Choice>Urraca</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Denmark (1157–82) who ended the Wend (Slav) threat to Danish shipping, won independence from the Holy Roman emperor, and gained church approval for hereditary rule by his dynasty, the Valdemars.The son of Knud Lavard, duke of South Jutland, and a great-grandson of the Danish king Sweyn II, Valdemar gained sole possession of the monarchy, concluding more than 25 years of civil wars waged by competing contenders for the throne. He soon began a series of expeditions against the Wends, aided by his foster brother Absalon, whom he made bishop of Roskilde. By 1169 his forces had captured the...
</Question>
<Choice>Valdemar I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Denmark (1202–41) who, between 1200 and 1219, extended the Danish Baltic empire from Schleswig in the west to include lands as far east as Estonia. In his later years he worked to unify Denmark's legal and administrative systems.The son and brother, respectively, of the Danish kings Valdemar I and Canute IV, Valdemar acted as the duke of Schleswig from 1188 and conquered Holstein (North Albingia) and Hamburg (1200–01). Succeeding to the throne in 1202, he initially supported the Welf candidate for the office of Holy Roman emperor, Otto IV, who in turn recognized Valdemar's sovereignty...
</Question>
<Choice>Valdemar II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Denmark (1340–75) who united his country under his own rule after a brief period of alien domination. His aggressive foreign policy led to conflict with Sweden, North German principalities, and the North German trading centres of the Hanseatic League.A son of King Christopher II, Valdemar lived after 1328 at the court of Louis IV the Bavarian, Holy Roman emperor. In 1338 he left the imperial court, and, with the aid of the Emperor and of Louis, margrave of Brandenburg, he began a diplomatic offensive to wrest sovereignty in Denmark from Gerhard and John the Mild, counts of Holstein. Af...
</Question>
<Choice>Valdemar IV Atterdag</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
grand prince of Moscow from 1389 to 1425.While still a youth, Vasily, who was the eldest son of Grand Prince Dmitry Donskoy (ruled Moscow 1359–89), travelled to the Tatar khan Tokhtamysh (1383) to obtain the Khan's patent for his father to rule the Russian lands as the grand prince of Vladimir. Diplomatically overcoming the challenge of the prince of Tver, who also sought the patent, Vasily succeeded in his mission. But he was subsequently kept at Tokhtamysh's court as a hostage until 1386 when, taking advantage of Tokhtamysh's conflict with his suzerain Timur Lenk (Tamerlane), he escaped and...
</Question>
<Choice>Vasily I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
grand prince of Moscow from 1425 to 1462.Although the 10-year-old Vasily II was named by his father Vasily I (ruled Moscow 1389–1425) to succeed him as the grand prince of Moscow and of Vladimir, Vasily's rule was challenged by his uncle Yury and his cousins Vasily the Squint-Eyed and Dmitry Shemyaka. After a long, chaotic, and bitter struggle, during which Vasily not only temporarily lost his throne both to Yury (1434) and to Dmitry Shemyaka (1446–47) but was also blinded by Dmitry (1446), Vasily recovered his position (1447) and ruled Muscovy for another 15 years.Despite the prolonged intern...
</Question>
<Choice>Vasily II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
grand prince of Kiev from 1113 to 1125.Vladimir was the son of Grand Prince Vsevolod I Yaroslavich (ruled Kiev 1078–93) and Irina, the daughter of the Byzantine emperor Constantine IX Monomachus. He became active in the politics of Kievan Rus, helping his father and uncle Izyaslav I (ruled at Kiev intermittently 1054–78) defeat his cousins Oleg Svyatoslavich and Boris Vyacheslavich at Chernigov (1078; modern Chernihiv, Ukraine) and succeeding his father as prince of Chernigov when Vsevolod became grand prince of Kiev. Vladimir ruled Chernigov from 1078 to 1094, restoring order among his cousin...
</Question>
<Choice>Vladimir II Monomakh</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German king and, as Wenceslas IV, king of Bohemia, whose weak and tempestuous, though eventful, reign was continually plagued by wars and princely rivalries that he was unable to control, plunging his territories into a state of virtual anarchy until he was stripped of his powers altogether by a rebellious nobility.Son of the Holy Roman emperor Charles IV, Wenceslas was crowned king of Bohemia in 1363 and king of the Romans in 1376, proving a largely incompetent ruler after his father's death in 1378. He was a peace-loving man and held frequent diets in Germany from 1378 to 1389, but he could...
</Question>
<Choice>Wenceslas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Bohemia from 1278 and of Poland from 1300 who ably ruled his Bohemian kingdom and spread his influence not only into Poland but also into Hungary.Succeeding to the throne at the age of seven on the death of his father, Premysl Otakar II, in 1278, Wenceslas lived at the court of his cousin Otto IV of Brandenburg who served as regent for Wenceslas until 1283. When Wenceslas then returned to Prague, he found that his country was dominated by the ambitious Zaviš of Falkenstein, his mother's lover and later her husband. Wenceslas arrested Zaviš in 1289, destroyed the dissident faction, and...
</Question>
<Choice>Wenceslas II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
last king of the Premyslid dynasty of Bohemia, king of Hungary from 1301 to 1304, and claimant to the Polish throne; his brief reign in Bohemia was cut short by his assassination, which also prevented him from asserting his right to Poland.Wenceslas renounced his hereditary rights to Austria and his Hungarian crown before succeeding his father, King Wenceslas II, on the Bohemian throne in 1305. An intelligent and well-educated yet dissolute person, he determined to enforce his claim to Poland and was raising an army when he died at the hand of an unknown assassin. The male line of the Premysli...
</Question>
<Choice>Wenceslas III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
duke of Normandy (as William II) from 1035 and king of England from 1066, one of the greatest soldiers and rulers of the Middle Ages. He made himself the mightiest noble in France and then changed the course of England's history by his conquest of that country.
</Question>
<Choice>William I (king of England)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Scotland from 1165 to 1214; although he submitted to English overlordship for 15 years (1174–89) of his reign, he ultimately obtained independence for his kingdom.William was the second son of the Scottish Henry, Earl of Northumberland, whose title he inherited in 1152. He was forced, however, to relinquish this earldom to King Henry II of England (reigned 1154–89) in 1157. Succeeding to the throne of his elder brother, King Malcolm IV, in 1165, William joined a revolt of Henry's sons (1173) in an attempt to regain Northumberland. He was captured near Alnwick, Northumberland, in 1174 a...
</Question>
<Choice>William I (king of Scotland)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Norman king of Sicily, an able ruler who successfully repressed the conspiracies of the barons of his realm. His epithet was bestowed on him by his hapless enemies. He patronized science and letters and showed religious tolerance; among those who frequented his court were many Muslims.The deaths of William's three elder brothers made him heir apparent in 1148. He was associated in kingship in 1151 with his father, Roger II, and was crowned king after Roger's death in the Cathedral of Palermo on Easter Sunday, April 4, 1154.On the advice of his minister, Maione of Bari, William energetically pu...
</Question>
<Choice>William I (king of Sicily)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
son of William I the Conqueror and king of England from 1087 to 1100; he was also de facto duke of Normandy (as William III) from 1096 to 1100. He prevented the dissolution of political ties between England and Normandy, but his strong-armed rule earned him a reputation as a brutal, corrupt tyrant. Rufus (“the Red”—so named for his ruddy complexion) was William's third (second surviving) and favourite son. In accordance with feudal custom, William I bequeathed his inheritance, the Duchy of Normandy, to his eldest son, Robert II Curthose; England, William's kingdom by conquest, was given to Ruf...
</Question>
<Choice>William II (king of England)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the last Norman king of Sicily; under a regency from 1166, he ruled in person from 1171. He became known as William the Good because of his policy of clemency and justice toward the towns and the barons, in contrast with his father, William I the Bad.After the regency of his mother, Margaret of Navarre, had ended, William II at first continued his father's policy of friendship with Pope Alexander III and with the Byzantine emperor Manuel I Comnenus. In 1172, however, the proposed marriage of William to Manuel's daughter Maria was thwarted by the emperor, and William immediately turned against...
</Question>
<Choice>William II (king of Sicily)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Poland (1320–33), a ruler who succeeded in bringing together a series of Polish principalities into a kingdom and laying the foundations for a strong Polish nation.Wladyslaw was the son of Casimir I of Kujawy, the ruler of one of the numerous small principalities formed after the Old Polish realm had been divided up two centuries earlier. Wladyslaw succeeded his father in 1275 and was elected by the nobles of Great Poland as their prince in 1296; however, they later transferred their allegiance to King Wenceslas II of Bohemia, who was then crowned king of Poland at Gniezno in 1300.Wlad...
</Question>
<Choice>Wladyslaw I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
grand duke of Lithuania (as Jogaila, 1377–1401) and king of Poland (1386–1434), who joined two states that became the leading power of eastern Europe. He was the founder of Poland's Jagiellon dynasty.
</Question>
<Choice>Wladyslaw II Jagiello</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polish king (1434–44) who was also king of Hungary (as Ulászló I; 1440–44) and who attempted unsuccessfully to push the Ottoman Turks out of the Balkans. His reign was overshadowed by the presence of his adviser, Zbigniew Olesnicki.At the age of 10 he succeeded to the throne of Poland on the death of his father, Wladyslaw II. During his 10 years as king, however, most of the major decisions were either made or manipulated by Olesnicki, who was a powerful Polish noble, bishop of Kraków, the first Polish cardinal, and also a close adviser to his father.Working successfully to bring the crown of...
</Question>
<Choice>Wladyslaw III Warnenczyk</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
grand prince of Kiev from 1019 to 1054.A son of the grand prince Vladimir, he was vice-regent of Novgorod at the time of his father's death in 1015. Then his eldest surviving brother, Svyatopolk the Accursed, killed three of his other brothers and seized power in Kiev. Yaroslav, with the active support of the Novgorodians and the help of Varangian (Viking) mercenaries, defeated Svyatopolk and became the grand prince of Kiev in 1019.Yaroslav began consolidating the Kievan state through both cultural and administrative improvements and through military campaigns. He promoted the spread of Christ...
</Question>
<Choice>Yaroslav I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
claimant to the English throne whose attempts to gain power helped precipitate the Wars of the Roses (1455–85) between the houses of Lancaster and York; he controlled the government for brief periods during the first five years of this struggle. He was the father of two English kings, Edward IV and Richard III.In 1415 Richard succeeded his uncle Edward as duke of York. As a descendant of Lionel, duke of Clarence, third son of King Edward III (ruled 1327–77), York had a hereditary claim to the throne that was stronger, by primogeniture, than that of Henry VI (who became king in 1422), who was d...
</Question>
<Choice>York, Richard, 3rd duke of</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
reign name (nianhao) of the third emperor (1402–24) of China's Ming dynasty (1368–1644), which he raised to its greatest power. He moved the capital from Nanjing to Beijing, which was rebuilt with the Forbidden City.
</Question>
<Choice>Yung-lo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Almoravid ruler who, during his reign from 1061 to 1106, expanded Almoravid land holdings from a small, insecurely held area in the Maghrib into a huge empire that included major portions of present-day Morocco and Algeria, Muslim Spain as far north as Fraga, and the islands of Majorca, Minorca, and Ibiza. A Berber by origin, Ibn Tashufin was an excellent general and a devoutly religious ascetic who inspired his followers by example.In 1061 Abu Bakr, who was then the leader of the Almoravids, went south into the desert to put down a tribal rebellion. He gave the command of his troops in the Ma...
</Question>
<Choice>Yusuf ibn Tashufin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine empress, by marriage from 1028 and in her own right from 1042.The daughter of the emperor Constantine VIII, Zoe was married to the heir presumptive, Romanus III Argyrus, in 1028 and became empress consort upon his elevation to the throne the same year. She became self-assertive and jealous, exiling her sister Theodora to a monastery; and, neglected by her husband, became enamoured of Michael, her young Paphlagonian chamberlain. In 1034 the emperor became ill, allegedly poisoned by Zoe; and, upon his death on April 11, she at once took control and married Michael, who was proclaimed E...
</Question>
<Choice>Zoe</Choice>
</item>
</topics>