<topics>
<item>
<Question>
Manchurian tribal leader who in 1636 became emperor of the Manchu, Mongols, and Chinese in Manchuria (Northeast China). In addition, for his family he adopted the name of Qing (“Pure”), which also became the name of the Chinese dynasty (1644–1911/12) ruled by the Manchu.Abahai was the eighth son of Nurhachi (1559–1626), the great Manchu leader who extended his people's rule over the tribes of the Inner Asian steppes and organized his tribesmen into a bureaucratic Chinese-style state. Soon after his father's death, Abahai eliminated his brothers as rivals and consolidated his personal rule. He...
</Question>
<Choice>Abahai</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Sweden from 1751 to 1771. He was the son of Christian Augustus (1673–1726), Duke of Schleswig-Holstein-Gottorp, and of Albertina Frederica of Baden-Durlach.While Adolf Frederick was bishop of Lübeck (1727–50), he administered Holstein-Kiel (1739–45) during the minority of Duke Charles Peter Ulrich (afterward Peter III of Russia). In 1743 he was elected heir to the throne of Sweden by the “Hat” faction. His election was secured by the Russian empress Elizabeth, who, as a result of Russia's defeat of Sweden in the 1741–43 war, was able to demand that Adolf Frederick be named heir under t...
</Question>
<Choice>Adolf Frederick</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Portugal, whose reign was marked by internal disputes between his partisans and those of his brother Pedro.Afonso succeeded his father, John IV, in 1656, but his mother acted as regent until 1662. His reign saw a series of victories against Spain, including the battles of Ameixal (1663), Castelo Rodrigo (1664), and Montes Claros (1665), which in 1668 led to Spanish recognition of Portuguese independence. When Afonso's wife left him, their marriage was annulled on grounds of his incapacity. She married his brother, the future Peter II, who was declared Defender of the Realm. After surre...
</Question>
<Choice>Afonso VI</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
third sultan of the Mataram dynasty of central Java who brought his domain to its greatest territorial and military power.In the early years of Sultan Agung's reign, he consolidated the sultanate by subduing the autonomous trade-based coastal states of Padang and Tuban in 1619; Banjermasin, Kalimantan, and Sukadana in 1622; Madura in 1624; and Surabaya in 1625. Because the country's economy was based on agriculture, Agung, who was openly contemptuous of trade, maintained no significant naval forces. Dutch troops had conquered Jacatra (now Jakarta) in 1619 and established there a base they name...
</Question>
<Choice>Agung</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ottoman sultan from 1603 to 1617, whose authority was weakened by wars, rebellions, and misrule. The rebellions he was able to suppress; he executed some of the viziers and exiled many palace dignitaries for bribery and intrigue; and he introduced a new regulation for the improvement of land administration. The peace of Zsitvatörök (1606) that he signed with Austria was a blow to Ottoman prestige, and he was compelled to extend commercial privileges to France, Venice, and the Netherlands within his domains.Ahmed was pious and made many donations, especially to the holy places of Mecca and Medi...
</Question>
<Choice>Ahmed I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
sultan of the Ottoman Empire from 1703 to 1730. The son of Mehmed IV, he succeeded to the throne in 1703 upon the deposition of his brother Mustafa II. Ahmed III cultivated good relations with England and France and afforded refuge at his court to Charles XII of Sweden after his defeat by Peter I the Great of Russia at the Battle of Poltava (1709). Ahmed declared war on Russia in 1710 and came nearer than any other Turkish sovereign to breaking that country's power. His grand vizier, Baltaji Mehmed Pasha, encircled Peter's army near the Prut River in July 1711, and Russia had to agree to resto...
</Question>
<Choice>Ahmed III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
greatest of the Mughal emperors of India, who reigned from 1556 to 1605 and who extended Mughal power over most of the Indian subcontinent. In order to preserve the unity of his empire, Akbar adopted programs that won the loyalty of the non-Muslim populations of his realm. He reformed and strengthened his central administration and also centralized his financial system and reorganized tax-collection processes. Although he never renounced Islam, he took an active interest in other religions, persuading Hindus, Parsis, and Christians, as well as Muslims, to engage in religious discussion before...
</Question>
<Choice>Akbar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Burmese“The Victorious”king (1752–60) who unified Myanmar (Burma) and founded the Alaungpaya, or Konbaung, dynasty, which held power until the British annexed Upper (northern) Burma on Jan. 1, 1886. He also conquered the independent Mon kingdom of Pegu (in the Irrawaddy River delta).Of humble origins, Alaungpaya was a village headman from the small town of Moksobomyo (present-day Shwebo), north of Ava, the Myanmar capital, when in April 1752 Binnya Dala, the Mon king of Pegu, captured Ava and put an end to Myanmar's ruling Toungoo dynasty. Refusing to become his vassal, Alaungpaya organized a...
</Question>
<Choice>Alaungpaya</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
cardinal archduke of Austria who as governor and sovereign prince of the Low Countries (1598–1621) ruled the Spanish Netherlands jointly with his wife, Isabella, infanta of Spain.The son of the Holy Roman emperor Maximilian II and Maria, daughter of Charles V, Albert was educated for an ecclesiastical career at the court of his uncle, King Philip II of Spain. Although appointed archbishop and cardinal of Toledo (Spain) in 1577, Albert served Philip not as a prelate but as a soldier and diplomat; he governed Portugal as Philip's viceroy from 1581 to 1595. After the death of his elder brother, E...
</Question>
<Choice>Albert VII</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
tsar of Russia from 1645 to 1676.The son of Michael, the first Romanov monarch of Russia (reigned 1613–45), Alexis received a superficial education from his tutor Boris Ivanovich Morozov before acceding to the throne at the age of 16. Morozov, who was also Alexis' brother-in-law, initially took charge of state affairs, but in 1648 a popular uprising in Moscow forced Alexis to exile Morozov.Alexis bowed to the rebels' demands and convened a land assembly (zemski sobor), which in 1649 produced a new Russian code of laws (Sobornoye Ulozheniye), which legally defined serfdom. Morozov's place as th...
</Question>
<Choice>Alexis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mongol khan, or chief, who terrorized China during the 16th century. He converted the Mongols to the reformed, or Dge-lugs-pa (Yellow Hat), sect of Tibetan Buddhism.Altan became chief of the eastern Mongols in 1543 and thereafter posed a constant threat to the northern borders of China under the Ming dynasty (1368–1644). In 1550 he led his forces across the Great Wall, which marked China's northwest border, and raided the outskirts of the capital at Peking. But he was forced to withdraw back into Mongolia a few days later.Altan soon began his effort to create a stable system of government in h...
</Question>
<Choice>Altan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
empress of Russia from 1730 to 1740.Daughter of Ivan V (reigned 1682–96) and niece of Peter I the Great (reigned 1682–1725), Anna was married to Frederick William, ruler of the Baltic seacoast duchy of Courland, on Oct. 31 (Nov. 11), 1710. Although her husband died on the journey to Courland after their wedding in St. Petersburg, Anna remained at Mitau (now Jelgava, Latvia), the capital of Courland, until 1730, when Peter II died and the Supreme Privy Council, the actual ruling body in Russia (1726–30), offered her the Russian throne.Having accepted the council's proposal as well as its stipul...
</Question>
<Choice>Anna (empress of Russia)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
regent of Russia (November 1740–November 1741) for her son, the emperor Ivan VI.A niece of Empress Anna (reigned 1730–40), Anna Leopoldovna married a nephew of the Holy Roman emperor Charles VI in 1739 and gave birth to a son, Ivan (Aug. 2 [Aug. 13], 1740), who was named heir to the Russian throne by Empress Anna in 1740, shortly before she died.A few weeks later, however, the empress's appointed regent, Ernst Johann Biron, was arrested by certain members of the ruling German clique in Russia, led by Burkhard Münnich and Andrey Osterman. Münnich and Osterman appointed Anna Leopoldovna regent a...
</Question>
<Choice>Anna (regent of Russia)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
queen of Great Britain and Ireland from 1702 to 1714. The last Stuart monarch, she wished to rule independently, but her intellectual limitations and chronic ill health caused her to rely heavily on her ministers, who directed England's efforts against France and Spain in the War of the Spanish Succession (1701–14). The bitter rivalries between Whigs and Tories that characterized her reign were intensified by uncertainty over the succession to her throne.Anne was the second daughter of James, duke of York (King James II, 1685–88), and Anne Hyde. Although her father was a Roman Catholic, she wa...
</Question>
<Choice>Anne</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
queen consort of King Louis XIII of France (reigned 1610–43) and regent during the opening years of the reign of her son King Louis XIV (from 1643).The eldest daughter of King Philip III of Spain and Margaret of Austria, Anne was married to the 14-year-old Louis XIII in November 1615. Throughout his life Louis treated her with a cool reserve. In 1625 the English George Villiers, 1st duke of Buckingham, created a scandal at the French court by revealing his passion for the Queen. Her plight worsened as the powerful Cardinal de Richelieu, Louis XIII's chief minister from 1624 to 1642, sought to...
</Question>
<Choice>Anne Of Austria</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Navarre, duke of Vendôme, and father of Henry IV of France.Son of Charles of Bourbon, duke of Vendôme, he married (1548) Jeanne d'Albret, daughter of Henry II, king of Navarre; as sole heir, she brought her husband the title of king of Navarre. Anthony was involved with his brother, Louis I de Bourbon, prince de Condé, in the Huguenot conspiracy of Amboise, but, nevertheless, he survived to be later named lieutenant general of the French armies (1560), having turned Roman Catholic. He commanded the army that besieged Rouen and there received a mortal wound.
</Question>
<Choice>Anthony Of Bourbon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
13th and last emperor of the Inca, who was victorious in a devastating civil war with his half brother, only to be captured, held for ransom, and then executed by Francisco Pizarro.Atahuallpa was a younger son of the Inca ruler Huayna Capac and an Ecuadoran princess; although not the legitimate heir, he seems to have been his father's favourite. When the old Inca chief died (c. 1527), the kingdom was divided between Atahuallpa, who ruled the northern part of the empire from Quito, and Huáscar, the legitimate heir, who ruled from Cuzco, the traditional Inca capital.Depicted by contemporary chro...
</Question>
<Choice>Atahuallpa</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Poland and elector of Saxony (as Frederick Augustus I). Though he regained Poland's former provinces of Podolia and the Ukraine, his reign marked the beginning of Poland's decline as a European power.The second son of Elector John George III of Saxony, Augustus succeeded his elder brother John George IV as elector in 1694. After the death of John III Sobieski of Poland (1696), Augustus became one of 18 candidates for the Polish throne. To further his chances, he converted to Catholicism, thereby alienating his Lutheran Saxon subjects and causing his wife, a Hohenzollern princess, to le...
</Question>
<Choice>Augustus II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Poland and elector of Saxony (as Frederick Augustus II), whose reign witnessed one of the greatest periods of disorder within Poland. More interested in ease and pleasure than in affairs of state, this notable patron of the arts left the administration of Saxony and Poland to his chief adviser, Heinrich von Brühl, who in turn left Polish administration chiefly to the powerful Czartoryski family.The only legitimate son of Frederick Augustus I of Saxony (Augustus II of Poland), he followed his father's example by joining the Roman Catholic Church in 1712. In 1719 he married Maria Josepha...
</Question>
<Choice>Augustus III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
emperor of India from 1658 to 1707, the last of the great Mughal emperors. Under him the Mughal Empire reached its greatest extent, although his policies helped lead to its dissolution.
</Question>
<Choice>Aurangzeb</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Arabic“Tiger”emperor (1526–30) and founder of the Mughal dynasty of India. A descendant of the Mongol conqueror Chinggis (Genghis) Khan and also of the Turkic conqueror Timur (Tamerlane), Babur was a military adventurer, a soldier of distinction, and a poet and diarist of genius, as well as a statesman.
</Question>
<Choice>Babur</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mughal emperor of India from 1707–12.As Prince Mu?a??am, the second son of the emperor Aurangzeb, he was the prospective heir after his elder brother defected to join their father's brother and rival, Shah Shuja?. Prince Mu?a??am was sent in 1663 to represent his father in the Deccan plateau region of southern and central India. He led an army in 1683–84 against the Marathas in the Portuguese enclave of Goa, south of Mumbai, but, lacking Portuguese support, made a disastrous retreat. After being persecuted for eight years under the rule of the powerful emperors Aurangzeb and Shah Jahan, he was...
</Question>
<Choice>Bahadur Shah I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prince of Transylvania whose unpopular anti-Turkish policy led to civil war.The son of Christopher Báthory (prince of Transylvania, 1575–81) and nephew of Stephen (István Báthory, king of Poland, 1575–86), Sigismund succeeded his father in 1581 and actually assumed control of government affairs in 1588. Acting on the advice of his foreign counselor Alfonso Carrillo, Báthory reversed the traditional policy of Transylvania (i.e., to play off the Ottoman sultan against the Holy Roman emperor and thereby preserve Transylvanian de facto independence) and adopted an anti-Turk position. Although this...
</Question>
<Choice>Báthory, Sigismund</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ottoman sultan (1481–1512) who consolidated Ottoman rule in the Balkans, Anatolia, and the eastern Mediterranean and successfully opposed the ?afavid dynasty of Persia.Bayezid II was the elder son of the sultan Mehmed II, the conqueror of Constantinople. On the death of his father in 1481, his brother Cem contested the succession. Bayezid, supported by a strong faction of court officials at Constantinople, succeeded in taking the throne. Cem eventually sought refuge with the Knights of Saint John at Rhodes and remained a captive until his death in 1495.Under the new reign an immediate reaction...
</Question>
<Choice>Bayezid II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the Toungoo dynasty (reigned 1551–81) in Myanmar (Burma). He unified his country and conquered the Shan States and Siam (now Thailand), making Myanmar the most powerful kingdom in mainland Southeast Asia.In 1550 a revolt broke out among the Mons of southern Myanmar, and Bayinnaung's brother-in-law, Tabinshwehti, was assassinated at Pegu in 1551 by a Mon prince. Bayinnaung marched to Toungoo, eliminated a pretender to the throne, and proclaimed himself king; then he marched south, captured the city of Pegu, and executed the rebel leader, Smim Htaw. The other Mon rulers then surrendered,...
</Question>
<Choice>Bayinnaung</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish cardinal and statesman who promoted a close alliance between Scotland and France and who was an implacable opponent of the Scottish Reformation.Beaton became archbishop of St. Andrews in 1539 and papal legate in Scotland in 1544. Beginning his political career in 1529, he eventually became the trusted counsellor of King James V. He dissuaded the King from following the Reformist religious policies of Henry VIII of England and helped arrange James's two successive marriages to French noblewomen. After James's death in 1542, Beaton's opposition to the pro-English policies of James Hamil...
</Question>
<Choice>Beaton, David</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
in full Gábor Iktári Bethlen, German Gabriel Bethlen Von Iktár Calvinist prince of Transylvania and briefly titular king of Hungary (August 1620 to December 1621), in opposition to the Catholic emperor Ferdinand II.Born into a leading Protestant family of northern Hungary, Bethlen as a young man was sent to the court of Prince Sigismund Báthory of Transylvania. Later he helped István Bocskay gain the throne of Transylvania and supported his successor, Gábor Báthory. Differences between Bethlen and Báthory, however, forced Bethlen to take refuge with the Turks. The Ottoman sultan Ahmed I, suzer...
</Question>
<Choice>Bethlen, Gábor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prince of Transylvania, who defended Hungarian interests when Hungary was divided into Ottoman and Habsburg spheres of influence.Brought up at the court of the Báthorys, Bocskay won the confidence of Sigismund Báthory, prince of Transylvania, whom he advised to form an alliance with the Holy Roman emperor (who was also the Habsburg king of Hungary) instead of with the Ottoman sultan. When in 1599 Báthory's successors deprived Bocskay of his estates, he fled to Vienna to seek protection and redress. He was alienated, however, by the emperor Rudolf II's attempts to deprive royal Hungary of its c...
</Question>
<Choice>Bocskay, István</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Myanmar, sixth monarch of the Alaungpaya, or Konbaung, dynasty, in whose reign (1782–1819) the long conflict began with the British.A son of Alaungpaya (reigned 1752–60), the founder of the dynasty, Bodawpaya came to power after deposing and executing his grandnephew Maung Maung. In 1784 Bodawpaya invaded Arakan, the maritime kingdom on the eastern coast of the Bay of Bengal, captured its king, Thamada, and deported more than 20,000 people into Myanmar as slaves. When Arakan was made a Myanmar province in 1785, the borders of Myanmar and British India were contiguous for the first time...
</Question>
<Choice>Bodawpaya</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French princess remembered for her beauty and amours, her influence during the civil wars of the Fronde, and her final conversion to Jansenism.Anne-Geneviève de Bourbon-Condé was the only daughter of Henri II de Bourbon, Prince de Condé, and Charlotte de Montmorency. She was born in the prison of Vincennes, into which her father and mother had been thrown for opposition to Marshal d'Ancre, the favourite of Marie de Médicis, who was then regent in the minority of Louis XIII. She was educated with great strictness in the convent of the Carmelites in the Rue Saint-Jacques at Paris. Her early year...
</Question>
<Choice>
Bourbon-Condé, Anne-Geneviève de, duchess de Longueville
</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mohawk Indian chief who served not only as a spokesman for his people but also as a Christian missionary and a British military officer during the American Revolution (1775–83).Brant was converted to the Anglican church after two years (1761–63) at Moor's Charity School for Indians in Lebanon, Connecticut, where he learned English and became acquainted with Western history and literature. He left school to become an interpreter for an Anglican missionary and later aided in translating the prayer book and the Gospel of Mark into Mohawk (1787).Brant's sister Molly was the wife of the British sup...
</Question>
<Choice>Brant, Joseph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prime minister and virtual ruler of electoral Saxony, who unsuccessfully attempted to strengthen the state, the rulers of which were also kings of Poland, by making the Polish crown hereditary and by acquiring a land corridor linking Poland with Saxony.Rising rapidly under Augustus II the Strong, king of Poland, Brühl held a number of high offices under the Saxon elector Frederick Augustus II (Augustus III of Poland). In 1746 Brühl was appointed prime minister, a post until then unknown in Saxony. His wealth and extravagance caused many charges of corruption.Brühl failed in both his dynastic a...
</Question>
<Choice>Brühl, Heinrich, Graf von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
queen consort of Henry II of France (reigned 1547–59) and subsequently regent of France (1560–74), who was one of the most influential personalities of the Catholic–Huguenot wars. Three of her sons were kings of France: Francis II, Charles IX, and Henry III.
</Question>
<Choice>Catherine de Médicis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
peasant woman of Baltic (probably Lithuanian) birth who became the second wife of Peter I the Great (reigned 1682–1725) and empress of Russia (1725–27).Orphaned at the age of three, Marta Skowronska was raised by a Lutheran pastor in Marienburg (modern Aluksne, Latvia). When the Russians seized Marienburg (1702) during the Great Northern War, Marta was taken prisoner. She later was handed over to a close adviser of Peter I. A short time later she and the tsar became lovers.In 1703, after the birth of their first child, she was received into the Russian Orthodox church and rechristened Catherin...
</Question>
<Choice>Catherine I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-born empress of Russia (1762–96), who led her country into full participation in the political and cultural life of Europe, carrying on the work begun by Peter the Great. With her ministers she reorganized the administration and law of the Russian Empire and extended Russian territory, adding the Crimea and much of Poland.
</Question>
<Choice>Catherine II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prime minister of Great Britain from November 1756 to May 1757, at the start of the Seven Years' War.Eldest son of William Cavendish, the 3rd Duke (1698–1755), he was elected to the House of Commons in 1741 and 1747, and in 1751 he moved to the House of Lords, as Lord Cavendish of Hardwick, in his father's barony. After becoming lord lieutenant and governor-general of Ireland (1754), he succeeded to the dukedom (1755); and the following year he agreed to become nominal prime minister. William Pitt had refused to serve in the ministry of the Duke of Newcastle, and the great Whig families balked...
</Question>
<Choice>Cavendish, William, 4th Duke of Devonshire</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Sardinia–Piedmont and an extremely skilled soldier whose aid other European countries often solicited for the many wars of his time.Having received a military and political education, Charles Emmanuel succeeded his father, Victor Amadeus II, in 1730. During the War of the Polish Succession (1733–38) he joined the side of France and Spain, occupied Milan, and scored a brilliant success at Guastalla (Sept. 19, 1734). By the ensuing Treaty of Vienna he obtained Novara and Tortona (1738).During the War of the Austrian Succession (1740–48), which engaged the whole European continent, Charle...
</Question>
<Choice>Charles Emmanuel III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Great Britain and Ireland (1625–49), whose authoritarian rule and quarrels with Parliament provoked a civil war that led to his execution.Charles was the second surviving son of James VI of Scotland and Anne of Denmark. He was a sickly child, and, when his father became king of England in March 1603, he was temporarily left behind in Scotland because of the risks of the journey. Devoted to his elder brother, Henry, and to his sister, Elizabeth, he became lonely when Henry died (1612) and his sister left England in 1613 to marry Frederick V, elector of the Rhine Palatinate (seeJames I)....
</Question>
<Choice>Charles I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Great Britain and Ireland (1660–85), who was restored to the throne after years of exile during the Puritan Commonwealth. The years of his reign are known in English history as the Restoration period. His political adaptability and his knowledge of men enabled him to steer his country through the convolutions of the struggle between Anglicans, Catholics, and dissenters that marked much of his reign.
</Question>
<Choice>Charles II (king of Great Britain and Ireland)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Spain from 1665 to 1700 and the last monarch of the Spanish Habsburg dynasty.Charles's reign opened with a 10-year regency under the queen mother, during which the government was preoccupied with combatting the ambitions of the French king Louis XIV in the Low Countries and with intrigues at court involving the Queen, her Jesuit confessor Johann Eberhard Nithard, her subsequent favourite Fernando de Valenzuela, and the King's bastard brother Juan José (1629–79) de Austria. Of the two phases in the King's personal government, the first, concerned with resistance to the French imperialis...
</Question>
<Choice>Charles II (king of Spain)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Spain (1759–88) and king of Naples (as Charles VII, 1734–59), one of the “enlightened despots” of the 18th century, who helped lead Spain to a brief cultural and economic revival.
</Question>
<Choice>Charles III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Spain (1788–1808) during the turbulent period of the French Revolution, who succeeded his father Charles III.Lacking qualities of leadership himself, Charles entrusted the government (1792) to Manuel de Godoy, a protégé of the queen, Maria Luisa of Parma. Their adherence to the First Coalition against Revolutionary France led to a French invasion in 1794. In July 1795 the conflict with France was ended by the Peace of Basle, which was followed the next year by the Treaty of San Ildefonso, an alliance between Spain and France against England. When Napoleon again occupied northern Spain...
</Question>
<Choice>Charles IV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of France from 1560, remembered for authorizing the massacre of Protestants on St. Bartholomew's Day, Aug. 23–24, 1572, on the advice of his mother, Catherine de Médicis.The second son of Henry II and Catherine, Charles became king on the death of his brother Francis II, but his mother was regent. Proclaimed of age on Aug. 17, 1563, after his 13th birthday (according to the custom of the kingdom), he remained under his mother's domination, being incapable of choosing and following a policy of his own. His health was poor and he was mentally unstable.To strengthen the prestige of the crown...
</Question>
<Choice>Charles IX (king of France)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
virtual ruler of Sweden (1599–1604) and king (1604–11) who reaffirmed Lutheranism as the national religion and pursued an aggressive foreign policy leading to war with Poland (1605) and Denmark (1611).The youngest son of the Swedish king Gustav I Vasa, Charles in 1568 was one of the leaders of a rebellion against the rule of his half brother Erik XIV that placed his other brother on the throne as John III. Charles subsequently clashed with his brother in asserting his authority in his duchy and in leading the opposition to the king's efforts to reconcile Lutheranism and Roman Catholicism in Sw...
</Question>
<Choice>Charles IX (king of Sweden)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Holy Roman emperor (1519–56), king of Spain (as Charles I, 1516–56), and archduke of Austria (as Charles I, 1519–21), who inherited a Spanish and Habsburg empire extending across Europe from Spain and the Netherlands to Austria and the Kingdom of Naples and reaching overseas to Spanish America. He struggled to hold his empire together against the growing forces of Protestantism, increasing Turkish and French pressure, and even hostility from the Pope. At last he yielded, abdicating his claims to the Netherlands and Spain in favour of his son Philip II and the title of emperor to his brother Fe...
</Question>
<Choice>Charles V</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Holy Roman emperor from 1711 and, as Charles III, archduke of Austria and king of Hungary. As pretender to the throne of Spain (as Charles III), he attempted unsuccessfully to reestablish the global empire of his 16th-century ancestor Charles V. He was the author of the Pragmatic Sanction, intended to enable his daughter Maria Theresa to succeed him after the extinction of the direct male line of the House of Habsburg.The second son of the emperor Leopold I, Charles was a claimant to the Spanish throne when it became vacant on the death of Charles II in 1700. After the outbreak of the War of t...
</Question>
<Choice>Charles VI</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
elector of Bavaria (1726–45), who was elected Holy Roman emperor (1742–45) in opposition to the Habsburg Maria Theresa's husband, Francis, grand duke of Tuscany.Succeeding to the Bavarian throne in 1726, Charles Albert renounced any claims to the Austrian succession when he recognized the emperor Charles VI's Pragmatic Sanction that established the Emperor's daughter Maria Theresa as heiress of the Habsburg dominions. Charles Albert, however, maintained mental reservations since his wife was the daughter of the emperor Joseph I, and the Bavarian Wittelsbach claim to the throne was a legitimate...
</Question>
<Choice>Charles VII</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Sweden who conducted the First Northern War (1655–60) against a coalition eventually embracing Poland, Russia, Brandenburg, the Netherlands, and Denmark. His aim was to establish a unified northern state.In 1642 Charles, the son of John Casimir and Charles IX's eldest daughter, Catharine, joined the Swedish armies in Germany under Lennart Torstenson and returned to Sweden in 1645, a few years before the end of the Thirty Years' War. Although he failed in his efforts to marry the Swedish queen Christina, then still a minor, she secured his appointment as commander of the Swedish forces...
</Question>
<Choice>Charles X Gustav</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Sweden who expanded royal power at the expense of the higher nobility and the lower estates, establishing an absolutist monarchy that ended only with the death of Charles XII in 1718.Charles, the only son of Charles X Gustav and Hedvig Eleonora of Holstein-Gottorp, was only five years old when he succeeded his father in 1660. A regency was established under which the higher nobility gained control of the government and blocked the repossession of alienated crown lands. Although Charles came of age in 1672, the regents continued to control foreign policy; they drew Sweden into the Dutch...
</Question>
<Choice>Charles XI</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Sweden (1697–1718), an absolute monarch who defended his country for 18 years during the Great Northern War and promoted significant domestic reforms. He launched a disastrous invasion of Russia (1707–09), resulting in the complete collapse of the Swedish armies and the loss of Sweden's status as a great power. He was, however, also a ruler of the early Enlightenment era, promoting domestic reforms of significance.
</Question>
<Choice>Charles XII</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
reign name (nianhao) of the 11th emperor (reigned 1505–21) of the Ming dynasty (1368–1644), during whose reign eunuchs achieved such power within the government that subsequent rulers proved unable to dislodge them.Zhu Houzhao ascended the throne in 1505, taking the reign name Zhengde. Devoting himself entirely to pleasure-seeking, he relied on his eunuchs for information on the government. Corruption became rampant, public offices were bought and sold, and excessive taxes were levied on the people. Because the eunuchs who dominated the government were for the most part northerners, the southe...
</Question>
<Choice>Cheng-te</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(b. 1507, China—d. 1566/67, China), reign name (nianhao) of the 11th emperor of the Ming dynasty (1368–1644), whose long reign (1521–66/67) added a degree of stability to the government but whose neglect of official duties ushered in an era of misrule.Notoriously cruel, Jiajing caused hundreds of officials who had the temerity to disagree with him to be tortured, demoted, or killed. He spent much of his time and money, especially in his later years, patronizing Daoist alchemists in the hopes of finding an elixir to prolong his life. The government was left in the hands of a few favourites who...
</Question>
<Choice>Chia-ching</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
reign name (nianhao) of the fourth emperor of the Qing (Manchu) dynasty (1644–1911/12), whose six-decade reign (1735–96) was one of the longest in Chinese history. He conducted a series of military campaigns that eliminated the Turk and Mongol threats to northeastern China (1755–60), enlarged his empire by creating the New Province (the present-day Uygur Autonomous Region of Xinjiang), and reinforced Chinese authority in the south and east.
</Question>
<Choice>Ch'ien-lung</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Denmark and Norway (1513–23) and of Sweden (1520–23) whose reign marked the end of the Kalmar Union (1397–1523), a political union of Denmark, Norway, and Sweden.After serving as viceroy in Norway (1502, 1506–12), Christian succeeded his father, John, king of Denmark and Norway, in 1513. He obtained office by agreeing to a royal charter that granted extensive privileges to the nobility, including effective control of the government by the noble-dominated Rigsråd (Council of the Realm). He soon bypassed the Rigsråd, however, and used the chancellery to grant commercial privileges to mer...
</Question>
<Choice>Christian II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Denmark and Norway (1534–59) who established the state Lutheran Church in Denmark (1536) and, by forming close ties between the church and the crown, laid the foundation for the absolutist Danish monarchy of the 17th century.The eldest son of Frederick I, king of Denmark and Norway, Christian was educated as a Lutheran and showed Protestant zeal as statholder (chief executive) in the Danish provinces of Schleswig and Holstein (1526). The predominantly Catholic Rigsråd (Council of the Realm) therefore rejected his bid for the throne when Frederick died in 1533, preferring Christian's yo...
</Question>
<Choice>Christian III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Denmark and Norway (1588–1648), who led two unsuccessful wars against Sweden and brought disaster upon his country by leading it into the Thirty Years' War. He energetically promoted trade and shipping, left a national heritage of fine buildings, and won repute as a plucky, hard-drinking man of grim wit and great resource.Christian, the son of Frederick II of Denmark and Sophia of Mecklenburg, succeeded to the throne on the death of his father in 1588, but until his coronation in 1596 his country was governed by a regency of four members of the Rigsråd, the Council of the Realm, who al...
</Question>
<Choice>Christian IV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Denmark and Norway, son of Frederick IV of Denmark and Louise of Mecklenburg-Güstrow, who ascended the throne after his father's death on Oct. 12, 1730.Tolerably gifted, he became a diligent and conscientious ruler, choosing able administrators; but he was shy, reserved, and unprepossessing in appearance. Like his consort, Sophie Magdalene of Brandenburg-Kulmbach (1700–70), he was imbued with German pietism and devoutly encouraged a pietistic national church. Frivolous amusements were banned at court, but the royal couple's love of splendour led to costly buildings, such as Christiansb...
</Question>
<Choice>Christian VI</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
mentally incompetent king of Denmark and Norway; his reign saw the brief domination of the kingdom by Count Johann Friedrich Struensee.The son of Frederick V, Christian VII came to the throne in 1766. His mental instability has been attributed to a brutal childhood governor and to morally corrupt court pages. After his 1766 marriage to Caroline Matilda, the daughter of Frederick, prince of Wales, he gave himself up to debauchery. Christian came under the influence of Struensee when the latter was appointed to accompany him on a 1768–69 European tour. In 1769 Struensee was named court physician...
</Question>
<Choice>Christian VII</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
queen of Sweden (1644–54) who stunned all Europe by abdicating her throne. She subsequently attempted, without success, to gain the crowns of Naples and of Poland. One of the wittiest and most learned women of her age, Christina is best remembered for her lavish sponsorship of the arts and her influence on European culture.Christina was the daughter of King Gustav II Adolf and Maria Eleonora of Brandenburg. After her father died in the Battle of Lützen, Christina, his only heir, became queen-elect before the age of six. By his orders she was educated as a prince, with the learned theologian Jo...
</Question>
<Choice>Christina</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
reign name (nianhao) of the 16th and last emperor (reigned 1627–44) of the Ming dynasty (1368–1644).The Chongzhen emperor ascended the throne at the age of 16 on the death of his brother, the Tianqi emperor (reigned 1620–27), and tried to revive the deteriorating Ming government. He banished Wei Zhongxian, the powerful eunuch who had dominated his brother's reign, and he eliminated some of the more corrupt officials. He could not, however, quell partisan strife within the bureaucracy and the army. The imperial generals were frequently more interested in quarreling with one another than in putt...
</Question>
<Choice>Ch'ung-chen</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
also called (1728–30) Baron Wilmington British politician, favourite of King George II and nominal prime minister of Great Britain from February 1742 to July 1743.Third son of James Spencer, 3rd earl of Northampton, he first entered Parliament in 1698; in 1715 he became speaker of the House of Commons and in 1716 a member of the privy council. In 1730 he was created earl of Wilmington by a king who befriended him and exaggerated his abilities. He became an aging compromise candidate for the prime ministry in 1742, when the real power lay with the Duke of Newcastle and John Carteret (later Earl...
</Question>
<Choice>Compton, Spencer, earl of Wilmington</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English soldier and statesman who led parliamentary forces in the English Civil Wars; he was lord protector of England, Scotland, and Ireland from 1653 to 1658 during the republican Commonwealth.As one of the generals on the parliamentary side in the English Civil War against King Charles I, Cromwell helped to bring about the overthrow of the Stuart monarchy, and, as lord protector, he raised his country's status once more to that of a leading European power from the decline it had gone through since the death of Queen Elizabeth I. A man of outstanding gifts and a forceful character, he was on...
</Question>
<Choice>Cromwell, Oliver</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
11th and last Aztec emperor, nephew and son-in-law of Montezuma II.Cuauhtémoc became emperor in 1520 on the death of Montezuma's successor, Cuitláhuac. Hernán Cortés, with powerful Indian allies, was then marching on Tenochtitlán, the Aztec capital. Cuauhtémoc's frontier forces were forced to retreat in 1521, and he defended his capital in a four-month siege that left most of the city destroyed and few Indians surviving. Captured by the Spanish, he was at first treated with deference. Later, Cuauhtémoc was tortured to reveal the location of hidden Aztec wealth. His stoicism and refusal to spea...
</Question>
<Choice>Cuauhtémoc</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
leader of the Dzungar tribes of Mongols (reigned 1676–97). He conquered an empire that included Tibet in the southwest and ranged across Central Asia to the borders of Russia on the northeast.Dga'-ldan was a descendant of Esen, a Mongol chieftain who harassed the northern border of China during the 15th century, and his father was a powerful Dzungar chief. As a younger son, Dga'-ldan was sent to Tibet, a Dzungar protectorate since 1636, where he was educated to be a Buddhist lama. In 1671, however, when his brother (who had become the tribal leader) was murdered, Dga'-ldan returned to Turkista...
</Question>
<Choice>Dga'-ldan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
any of three different pretenders to the Muscovite throne who, during the Time of Troubles (1598–1613), claimed to be Dmitry Ivanovich, the son of Tsar Ivan IV the Terrible (reigned 1533–84) who had died mysteriously in 1591 while still a child.After Fyodor I (reigned 1584–98), the last tsar of the Rurik dynasty, died and his brother-in-law Boris Godunov succeeded him, the first False Dmitry appeared and challenged Godunov's right to the throne. The first pretender is considered by many historians to have been Grigory (Yury) Bogdanovich Otrepyev, a member of the gentry who had frequented the h...
</Question>
<Choice>Dmitry, False</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prince of the Manchu people of Manchuria (present-day Northeast China) who played a major part in founding the Qing (Manchu) dynasty in China. He was the first regent for the first Qing emperor, Shunzhi.Dorgon was the 14th of the 16 sons of Nurhachi, founder of the Manchu state, who in 1616 proclaimed himself emperor of China but died in 1626 before making good his claim to the imperial title. Under his successor, Abahai (Nurhachi's eighth son), Dorgon received the title of an imperial prince, hosoi beile. He distinguished himself in the wars against the Chahar Mongols that began in 1628 and w...
</Question>
<Choice>Dorgon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of England and Ireland from 1547 to 1553.Edward was King Henry VIII's only legitimate son; his mother, Henry's third wife, Jane Seymour, died 12 days after his birth. Although Edward has traditionally been viewed as a frail child who was never in good health, some recent authorities have maintained that until several years before his death he was a robust, athletically inclined youth. His tutors found him to be intellectually gifted, a precocious student of Greek, Latin, French, and theology. On Jan. 28, 1547, Henry VIII died and Edward succeeded to the throne.Henry had decreed that durin...
</Question>
<Choice>Edward VI</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
empress of Russia from 1741 to 1761 (1762, New Style).The daughter of Peter I the Great (reigned 1682–1725) and Catherine I (reigned 1725–27), Elizabeth grew up to be a beautiful, charming, intelligent, and vivacious young woman. Despite her talents and popularity, particularly among the guards, she played only a minor political role during the reigns of Peter II (reigned 1727–30) and Empress Anna (reigned 1730–40). But when Anna Leopoldovna assumed the regency for her son Ivan VI (1740–41) and threatened Elizabeth with banishment to a convent, the young princess allowed herself to be influenc...
</Question>
<Choice>Elizabeth</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
queen of England (1558–1603) during a period, often called the Elizabethan Age, when England asserted itself vigorously as a major European power in politics, commerce, and the arts.Although her small kingdom was threatened by grave internal divisions, Elizabeth's blend of shrewdness, courage, and majestic self-display inspired ardent expressions of loyalty and helped unify the nation against foreign enemies. The adulation bestowed upon her both in her lifetime and in the ensuing centuries was not altogether a spontaneous effusion; it was the result of a carefully crafted, brilliantly executed...
</Question>
<Choice>Elizabeth I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Sweden (1560–68) who expanded the powers of the monarchy and pursued an aggressive foreign policy that led to the Seven Years' War of the North (1563–70) against Denmark.Succeeding his father, Gustav I Vasa, in 1560, Erik soon obtained passage of the Articles of Arboga (1561), curtailing the powers of his half brothers, who had been granted large duchies by Gustav I. He consolidated his authority by establishing a special royal court of appeal and installing a new constitution (1562) that defined the nobility's military obligations.Erik's major foreign policy objective was to free Swed...
</Question>
<Choice>Erik XIV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Lebanese ruler (1593–1633) who for the first time united the Druze and Maronite districts of the Lebanon Mountains under his personal rule; he is frequently regarded as the father of modern Lebanon.With the death of Fakhr ad-Din's father, Korkmaz, in 1585, a civil war broke out between the two predominant religious–political factions in the region, the Kaysis and the Yamanis. After Fakhr ad-Din and his Kaysi faction emerged victorious in 1591, he became determined to unite the perpetually feuding Maronite and Druze districts. Although he himself was of the Druze religion, he had the support of...
</Question>
<Choice>Fakhr ad-Din II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
regent of the Netherlands (1578–92) for Philip II, the Habsburg king of Spain. He was primarily responsible for maintaining Spanish control there and for perpetuating Roman Catholicism in the southern provinces (now Belgium). In 1586 he succeeded his father as duke of Parma and Piacenza, but he never returned to Italy to rule.
</Question>
<Choice>Farnese, Alessandro, Duke di Parma e Piacenza</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ethiopian emperor from 1632 to 1667, who ended a period of contact between his country and Europe, initiating a policy of isolation that lasted for more than two centuries.Fasilides succeeded to the throne on the abdication of Susenyos (1632), who had permitted an increase of Spanish and Roman Catholic influence in Ethiopia. Fasilides reestablished a close alliance between the Ethiopian Coptic Christian Church and the ruling house, expelled Catholic missionaries, and enlisted the aid of the Muslim rulers of the coastal states to bar all Europeans from the country. He also created a new capital...
</Question>
<Choice>Fasilides</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Holy Roman emperor (1558–64) and king of Bohemia and Hungary from 1526, who, with his Peace of Augsburg (1555), concluded the era of religious strife in Germany following the rise of Lutheranism by recognizing the right of territorial princes to determine the religion of their subjects. He also converted the elected crowns of Bohemia and Hungary into hereditary possessions of the house of Habsburg.The younger brother of the Holy Roman emperor Charles V, Ferdinand was granted Austria, with the regency of both the Habsburg German lands and Württemberg. For more than three decades he was Charles'...
</Question>
<Choice>Ferdinand I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Holy Roman emperor (1619–37), archduke of Austria, king of Bohemia (1617–19, 1620–27), and king of Hungary (1618–25). He was the leading champion of the Roman Catholic Counter-Reformation and of absolutist rule during the Thirty Years' War.
</Question>
<Choice>Ferdinand II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Holy Roman emperor who headed the so-called peace party at the Habsburg imperial court during the Thirty Years' War and ended that war in 1648 with the Peace of Westphalia.The eldest son of the emperor Ferdinand II and Maria Anna of Bavaria, the energetic and able Ferdinand took part in ministerial councils and affairs of state from 1626. Archduke of Austria from 1621, he was crowned king of Hungary in 1625 and of Bohemia in 1627. Denied command of the imperial armies by Generalissimo Albrecht von Wallenstein, he took part in the conspiracy against the generalissimo and was partly responsible...
</Question>
<Choice>Ferdinand III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish statesman and minister who became identified with the reform program of King Charles III.Moñino y Redondo was a leading advocate in Madrid when he was appointed fiscal of the council of Castile in 1766. Having cooperated in the expulsion of the Jesuits from Spain in 1767 and being known as a convinced regalist, he was sent as ambassador to Rome in 1772 with the purpose of procuring the general dissolution of the Society of Jesus. As a reward for his success in this mission, Charles III gave him the title of conde de Floridablanca in 1773.Floridablanca replaced Jerónimo Grimaldi as firs...
</Question>
<Choice>Floridablanca, José Moñino y Redondo, conde de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of France (1515–47), the first of five monarchs of the Angoulême branch of the House of Valois. A Renaissance patron of the arts and scholarship, a humanist, and a knightly king, he waged campaigns in Italy (1515–16) and fought a series of wars with the Holy Roman Empire (1521–44).
</Question>
<Choice>Francis I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Holy Roman emperor from Sept. 13, 1745; he was duke of Lorraine (as Francis Stephen) from 1729 to 1735 and grand duke of Tuscany from 1737. Although nominally outranking his wife, Maria Theresa, archduchess of Austria and queen of Hungary and Bohemia, the capable but easygoing Francis always was overshadowed by her strong personality.From 1723 Francis, whose dynasty in Lorraine was closely connected with the Austrian Habsburgs, lived at the Viennese court of the Holy Roman emperor Charles VI. His marriage to Maria Theresa, who was Charles's heiress, took place on Feb. 12, 1736. Charles consent...
</Question>
<Choice>Francis I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of France from 1559, who was dominated throughout his reign by the powerful Guise family.The eldest son of Henry II and Catherine de Médicis, Francis was married in April 1558 to Mary Stuart, queen of Scots and niece of François, duc de Guise, and of Charles, cardinal of Lorraine. A sickly and weak-willed young man, Francis became a tool of the Guises, who saw an opportunity for power and a chance to break the Huguenot strength within the kingdom. To defeat the Guises, Louis de Bourbon, prince de Condé and Huguenot leader, planned the conspiracy of Amboise (March 1560), an abortive coup d...
</Question>
<Choice>Francis II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first Swedish king to reign (1720–51) during the 18th-century Age of Freedom, a period of parliamentary government.Frederick was the eldest surviving son of the landgrave of Hesse-Kassel. He fought bravely for England during the War of the Spanish Succession (1701–14). His marriage in 1700 to Louise of Prussia ended with her death in 1705, and in 1715 he married Ulrika Eleonora, sister of Charles XII of Sweden, after first proposing in 1708. She succeeded to the Swedish throne at the death of Charles XII in 1718, but, devoted to Frederick, she abdicated in his favour in 1720, and he was electe...
</Question>
<Choice>Frederick</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Denmark (1523–33) and Norway (1524–33) who encouraged Lutheranism in Denmark but maintained a balance between opposing Lutheran and Roman Catholic factions. This equilibrium crumbled after his death.The younger son of Christian I, king of Denmark and Norway, Frederick divided the duchies of Schleswig (now in Germany and Denmark) and Holstein (now in Germany) in 1490 with his older brother John (Hans), who succeeded to the Danish throne in 1481. After failing to win sovereignty over half of Norway and parts of Denmark, Frederick settled in Gottorp, where he reformed the territory's admi...
</Question>
<Choice>Frederick I (king of Denmark and Norway)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
elector of Brandenburg (as Frederick III), who became the first king in Prussia (1701–13), freed his domains from imperial suzerainty, and continued the policy of territorial aggrandizement begun by his father, Frederick William, the Great Elector.In 1688 Frederick succeeded to the electorate and at once set out, assisted by the capable Eberhard von Danckelmann, his boyhood tutor, now prime minister, on the course that was to yield him a monarch's crown 13 years later. Frederick maintained a large, splendid court and an army out of proportion to his territories and position to further his pret...
</Question>
<Choice>Frederick I (king of Prussia)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Denmark and Norway (1559–88) who failed in his attempt to establish complete Danish hegemony in the Baltic Sea area in the Seven Years' War of the North (1563–70) but maintained enough control over the Baltic trade to guide Denmark to a period of prosperity in the later years of his reign.After joining his uncles John and Adolphus, dukes of the Danish provinces of Schleswig and Holstein, in June 1559 in conquering the peasant republic of Dithmarschen (now in Germany), Frederick succeeded his father, Christian III, in 1559 as king of Denmark and Norway. His competition with Sweden for s...
</Question>
<Choice>Frederick II (king of Denmark and Norway)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Prussia (1740–86), a brilliant military campaigner who, in a series of diplomatic stratagems and wars against Austria and other powers, greatly enlarged Prussia's territories and made Prussia the foremost military power in Europe. An enlightened absolute monarch, he favoured French language and art and built a French Rococo palace, Sans Souci, near Berlin.Frederick, the third king of Prussia, ranks among the two or three dominant figures in the history of modern Germany. Under his leadership Prussia became one of the great states of Europe. Its territories were greatly increased and it...
</Question>
<Choice>Frederick II (king of Prussia)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Denmark and Norway (1648–70) whose reign saw the establishment of an absolute monarchy, maintained in Denmark until 1848.In his youth Frederick served successively as bishop coadjutor (i.e., assistant bishop with the right of succession) of the German dioceses of Bremen, Verden, and Halberstadt. He commanded Danish forces in Schleswig-Holstein during Denmark's disastrous war with Sweden (1643–45) and succeeded to the throne shortly after the death (1648) of his father, Christian IV, agreeing to a charter that reduced the royal prerogatives.In 1655 the Swedish king Charles X Gustav went...
</Question>
<Choice>Frederick III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Denmark and Norway (1699–1730), who succeeded his father, King Christian V. He continued the Danish efforts to sever the House of Gottorp's link with Sweden, but his first attempt to do so, in 1700 at the outbreak of the Great Northern War, was checked by Charles XII of Sweden. Frederick then accepted the Treaty of Traventhal (1700), but he reentered the war in 1709, and at the Peace of Frederiksborg (1720) Denmark obtained English and French guarantees for the sole possession of the Duchy of Schleswig by the Danish crown, though remaining administratively separate. At home the King in...
</Question>
<Choice>Frederick IV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Denmark and Norway (1746–66) from the death of his father, Christian VI. The reign of this likable but ineffective king was marked by Danish neutrality in the Seven Years' War (1756–63) and a consequent improvement in the nation's foreign trade; by a narrow escape from war with Russia (1762); and by the start of government-sponsored reforms in farming methods. In addition, the arts flourished without pietistic restraint. Real power was exercised in Frederick's name by two outstanding ministers, Adam Gottlob, Count Moltke, and J.H.E. von Bernstorff.In 1743 Frederick married Louisa, a da...
</Question>
<Choice>Frederick V (king of Denmark and Norway)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
elector Palatine of the Rhine, king of Bohemia (as Frederick I, 1619–20), and director of the Protestant Union.Brought up a Calvinist, partly in France, Frederick succeeded his father, Frederick IV, both as elector and as director of the Protestant Union in 1610, with Christian of Anhalt as his chief adviser. In 1613 he married Elizabeth Stuart, daughter of James I of England. In 1618 the Protestant estates of Bohemia revolted against their king, the Catholic Holy Roman Emperor Matthias, and, after his death the following year, offered the crown to Frederick. Confident of support from the Germ...
</Question>
<Choice>Frederick V (elector Palatine of the Rhine)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
second Prussian king who transformed his country from a second-rate power into the efficient and prosperous state that his son and successor, Frederick II the Great, made a major military power on the Continent.The son of the elector Frederick III, later Frederick I, king of Prussia, Frederick William grew up at a glamorous court, but his own temperament was ascetic, and he disapproved of the court's dissolute atmosphere. In 1706 he married Sophia Dorothea, the daughter of George Louis, elector of Hanover (later George I of England). His experiences in the War of the Spanish Succession (1701–1...
</Question>
<Choice>Frederick William I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Prussia from August 17, 1786, under whom, despite his lack of exceptional military and political gifts, Prussia achieved considerable expansion.The son of Frederick the Great's brother Augustus William, he became heir presumptive on his father's death in 1758. He was intellectually receptive and devoted to the arts, but when he succeeded Frederick the Great as king, he was unable to perpetuate his uncle's system of personal government; the direction of the Prussian state fell to a few favourites. Nevertheless, Prussia grew: it acquired Ansbach and Bayreuth when the margrave Charles Ale...
</Question>
<Choice>Frederick William II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
tsar of Russia (reigned 1676–82) who fostered the development of Western culture in Russia, thereby making it easier for his successor, Peter I the Great (reigned 1682–1725), to enact widespread reforms based on Western models.The eldest son of Alexis (reigned 1645–76), Fyodor not only was educated in the traditional subjects of Russian and Church Slavonic but also was tutored in Polish and Latin by Simeon Polotsky, a noted theologian who had studied in Kiev and Poland. When Alexis died, Fyodor ascended the throne (Jan. 19 [Jan. 29], 1676), but his youth and poor health prevented him from acti...
</Question>
<Choice>Fyodor III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
elector of Hanover (1698–1727) and first Hanoverian king of Great Britain (1714–27).George Louis of Brunswick-Lüneburg was the son of Ernest Augustus, elector of Hanover, and Sophia of the Palatinate, a granddaughter of King James I of England. George married his cousin Sophia Dorothea of Celle in 1682, but in 1694, accusing her of infidelity, he divorced her and imprisoned her in the castle of Ahlden, where she died 32 years later. He succeeded his father as elector of Hanover in 1698. The English Parliament's Act of Settlement (1701), seeking to ensure a Protestant succession to the throne i...
</Question>
<Choice>George I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Great Britain and elector of Hanover from 1727 to 1760. Although he possessed sound political judgment, his lack of self-confidence caused him to rely heavily on his ministers, most notable of whom was Sir Robert Walpole.George Augustus was the only son of the German prince George Louis, elector of Hanover (King George I of Great Britain from 1714 to 1727), and Sophia Dorothea of Celle. He grew up in Hanover and married (1705) the beautiful and intelligent Caroline of Ansbach. Upon the accession of his father to the English throne he was designated prince of Wales. By 1717 George I and...
</Question>
<Choice>George II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Great Britain and Ireland (1760–1820) and elector (1760–1814) and then king (1814–20) of Hanover, during a period when Britain won an empire in the Seven Years' War but lost its American colonies, and then, after the struggle against Revolutionary and Napoleonic France, emerged as a leading power in Europe. During the last years of his life (from 1811) he was intermittently mad—his son, the future George IV, acting as regent.
</Question>
<Choice>George III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian statesman who was chief adviser to Tsar Fyodor I (reigned 1584–98) and was himself elected tsar of Muscovy (reigning 1598–1605) after the extinction of the Rurik dynasty. His reign inaugurated the devastating Time of Troubles (1598–1613) in the Russian lands.A member of the noble Tatar family Saburov-Godunov that had migrated to Muscovy in the 14th century, Boris Godunov began his career of service in the court of Ivan IV the Terrible (reigned 1533–84). After gaining Ivan's favour by marrying the daughter of a close associate of the tsar (1571), Godunov gave his sister Irina to be the...
</Question>
<Choice>Godunov, Boris</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British prime minister (1768–70) and a prominent figure in the period of the American Revolutionary War.Grandson of the 2nd duke, Charles Fitzroy (1683–1757), and great-grandson of the 1st, he was educated at Westminster School and Peterhouse, Cambridge. He was secretary of state in 1765 under the Marquess of Rockingham but retired the following year. William Pitt formed a ministry in which Grafton was first lord of the Treasury (1766). He led the ministry after Chatham's resignation in 1768. As a politician Grafton was diffident and ineffective. Political differences and the attacks of the pr...
</Question>
<Choice>Grafton, Augustus Henry Fitzroy, 3rd duke of</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English politician whose policy of taxing the American colonies, initiated by his Revenue Act of 1764 and the Stamp Act of 1765, started the train of events leading to the American Revolution.He entered Parliament in 1741, one of the “cousinhood” of men interrelated by blood or marriage and further united in their opposition to Sir Robert Walpole, who held power from 1721 to 1742. After holding a number of ministerial appointments, Grenville was recommended to George III by Lord Bute to be his successor as first lord of the Treasury (prime minister). Grenville's ministry (1763–65) was unhappy...
</Question>
<Choice>Grenville, George</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
titular queen of England for nine days in 1553. Beautiful and intelligent, she reluctantly allowed herself at age 15 to be put on the throne by unscrupulous politicians; her subsequent execution by Mary Tudor aroused universal sympathy.Lady Jane was the great-granddaughter of Henry VII through her mother, Lady Frances Brandon, whose own mother was Mary, the younger of King Henry VIII's two sisters. Provided with excellent tutors, she spoke and wrote Greek and Latin at an early age; she was also proficient in French, Hebrew, and Italian. When Lady Jane was barely nine years old she went to live...
</Question>
<Choice>Grey, Lady Jane</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Sweden (1523–60), founder of the Vasa ruling line, who established Swedish sovereignty independent of Denmark.
</Question>
<Choice>Gustav I Vasa</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Sweden (1611–32) who laid the foundations of the modern Swedish state and made it a major European power.
</Question>
<Choice>Gustav II Adolf</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Sweden (1771–92), who reasserted the royal power over the Riksdag (parliament).Gustav, the eldest son of King Adolf Fredrik, was an intelligent and cultured advocate of the Enlightenment. In 1766 he married Sofia Magdalena, daughter of King Frederick V of Denmark. Gustav succeeded in 1771 to a Swedish throne that had been weak since it was subordinated to the Riksdag in 1720. The new king began his reign with futile efforts to mediate between the contending factions of the Riksdag. But in August 1772 he seized effective power of the government and established a new constitution which,...
</Question>
<Choice>Gustav III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prime minister (1623–43) and court favourite (valido) of King Philip IV of Spain. He attempted to impose a strong centralizing policy and eventually provoked rebellion and his own fall.
</Question>
<Choice>
Guzmán y Pimental, Gaspar de, count-duke de Olivares
</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Portugal and Roman Catholic ecclesiastic whose brief reign (1578–80) was dominated by the problem of succession. His failure to decisively designate a successor left the Portuguese throne at his death prey to its Spanish claimant, King Philip II.Henry, son of Manuel I, chose a career in the church and became, successively, archbishop of Braga (1534), Évora (1540), and Lisbon (1544), attaining the rank of cardinal in 1545. For a time he headed the Portuguese Inquisition. He also became a staunch supporter of the Society of Jesus and founded the Jesuit university in Évora (1558).Henry se...
</Question>
<Choice>Henry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of France from 1547 to 1559, a competent administrator who was also a vigorous suppressor of Protestants within his kingdom.The second son of Francis I and Claude of France, Henry was sent with his brother Francis, the dauphin, as a hostage to Spain in 1526 and did not return to France until 1530, after the conclusion of the Peace of Cambrai. When the dauphin died in 1536, Henry became heir to the throne. Strong differences between Henry and his father were accentuated by the rivalry between Henry's mistress, Diane de Poitiers, and the king's, Anne, Duchess d'Étampes, as well as by Henry'...
</Question>
<Choice>Henry II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of France from 1574, under whose reign the prolonged crisis of the Wars of Religion was made worse by dynastic rivalries arising because the male line of the Valois dynasty was going to die out with him.The third son of Henry II and Catherine de Médicis, Henry was at first entitled duc d'Anjou. Given command of the royal army against the Huguenots during the reign of his brother, Charles IX, he defeated two Huguenot leaders, the prince de Condé (Louis I de Bourbon) at Jarnac in March 1569 and Gaspard de Coligny at Moncontour in October of that year. Henry was Catherine's favourite son, mu...
</Question>
<Choice>Henry III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Navarre (as Henry III, 1572–89) and first Bourbon king of France (1589–1610), who, at the end of the Wars of Religion, abjured Protestantism and converted to Roman Catholicism (1593) in order to win Paris and reunify France. With the aid of such ministers as the Duke de Sully, he brought new prosperity to France.
</Question>
<Choice>Henry IV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of England (1509–47) who presided over the beginnings of the English Renaissance and the English Reformation. His six wives were, successively, Catherine of Aragon (the mother of the future queen Mary I), Anne Boleyn (the mother of the future queen Elizabeth I), Jane Seymour (the mother of Henry's successor, Edward VI), Anne of Cleves, Catherine Howard, and Catherine Parr.
</Question>
<Choice>Henry VIII</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
third king (1763–76) of the Alaungpaya, or Konbaung, dynasty in Myanmar (Burma). He pursued a policy of expansion at the expense of practically all his neighbours.Hsinbyushin's most important single project was the subjugation of Siam (now Thailand). In 1764 he campaigned eastward, taking Chiang Mai (Chiengmai) and Vientiane before invading the Chao Phraya River valley. When the Siamese capital of Ayutthaya fell in April 1767, he deported thousands of prisoners to Myanmar. According to the Siamese chronicles, “the King of Hanthawaddy [Bayinnaung] waged war like a monarch, but the King of Ava [...
</Question>
<Choice>Hsinbyushin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
second Mughal ruler of India, who was more an adventurer than a consolidator of his empire. The son and successor of Babur, who had founded the Mughal dynasty, Humayun ruled from 1530 to 1540 and again from 1555 to 1556.Humayun inherited the hope rather than the fact of empire, because the Afghans and Rajputs were merely restrained but not reconciled to Mughal supremacy by the Mughal victories at Panipat (1526), Khanua (1527), and the Ghaghara (1529). Bahadur Shah of Gujarat, encouraged by Afghan and Mughal émigrés, challenged the Mughals in Rajasthan, and, although Humayun occupied Gujarat in...
</Question>
<Choice>Humayun</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ottoman sultan whose unstable character made him prey to the ambitions of his ministers and relatives and to his own self-indulgence; as a consequence, the Ottoman state was weakened by war, misrule, and rebellion during his reign (1640–48).Early in his reign under the guidance of the able but ambitious grand vizier Kemankes Kara Mustafa Pasa, Ibrahim established peaceful relations with Persia and Austria (1642) and recovered the Sea of Azov hinterland from the Cossacks. After the execution of Kara Mustafa (1644), Ibrahim, acting on the advice of his new ministers, sent an expedition to Crete;...
</Question>
<Choice>Ibrahim</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
last Afghan sultan of Delhi of the Lodi dynasty. He was a suspicious tyrant who increasingly alienated his nobles during his reign.The son of Sikandar, Ibrahim succeeded to the throne on his father's death (Nov. 21, 1517) and was quickly faced with continuing disputes between the royal family and Afghan nobles. One noble, Dawlat Khan Lodi, governor of the Punjab, fearing for his own safety, called in the Mughal king of Kabul, Babur, who advanced toward Delhi and defeated and killed Ibrahim in the first battle of Panipat. This victory led to the founding of the Mughal Empire in India.
</Question>
<Choice>Ibrahim Lodi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
second ruler of the ?Alawi dynasty of Morocco; his long reign (1672–1727) saw the consolidation of ?Alawi power, the development of an effective army trained in European military techniques, and the introduction of French influence in Morocco.Virtually nothing is known about Isma?il's youth. In 1672, with the sudden death of his half brother, Mawlay al-Rashid (founder of the dynasty), Isma?il, then acting viceroy in Fès, immediately seized the treasury and had himself proclaimed ruler. His claim was challenged by three rivals—a brother, a nephew, and al-Khi?r Ghilan, a tribal leader of norther...
</Question>
<Choice>Isma'il</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
grand prince of Moscow (1533–84) and the first to be proclaimed tsar of Russia (from 1547). His reign saw the completion of the construction of a centrally administered Russian state and the creation of an empire that included non-Slav states. Ivan engaged in prolonged and largely unsuccessful wars against Sweden and Poland, and, in seeking to impose military discipline and a centralized administration, he instituted a reign of terror against the hereditary nobility.
</Question>
<Choice>Ivan IV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
nominal tsar of Russia from 1682 to 1696.The younger son of Tsar Alexis (reigned 1645–76) by his first wife, Mariya Ilinichna Miloslavskaya, Ivan was a chronic invalid, deficient mentally and physically, who suffered from scurvy and poor eyesight and in his later years was partially paralyzed. When his elder brother Tsar Fyodor III died in 1682, Ivan's half brother Peter, the son of Alexis and his second wife, Natalya Kirillovna Naryshkina, was named tsar. But Ivan's sister Sophia, determined to maintain the Miloslavsky family in power, encouraged the streltsy (sovereign's bodyguard) to riot a...
</Question>
<Choice>Ivan V</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mughal emperor of India from 1605 to 1627.Born Prince Salim, Jahangir was early marked for the succession by his father, Akbar. Impatient for power, however, he revolted in 1599 while Akbar was engaged in the Deccan. Akbar on his deathbed confirmed Jahangir as his successor.Jahangir continued his father's traditions. A war with the Rajput principality of Mewar was ended in 1614 on generous terms. Campaigns against Ahmadnagar, initiated under Akbar's rule, were continued fitfully, with Mughal arms and diplomacy often thwarted by the able ?abshi, Malik ?Ambar. In 1617 and 1621, however, Prince K...
</Question>
<Choice>Jahangir</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
African king who founded a dynasty in Gonja, in what is now northern Ghana, in the early 17th century.Originally a Mande invader, Jakpa established a loosely knit federation of states that extended over the entire northern part of present-day Ghana and parts of Togo and Benin. Jakpa's invasion of Ghana was probably the result of a dispute within an Islamic force (of which he himself was part) then attempting to convert nations in what are now Mali and Burkina Faso (formerly Upper Volta). His kingdom was of great influence in West Africa because of its strategic location on the east–west trade...
</Question>
<Choice>Jakpa, Sumalia Ndewura</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Scotland (as James VI) from 1567 to 1625 and first Stuart king of England from 1603 to 1625, who styled himself “king of Great Britain.” James was a strong advocate of royal absolutism, and his conflicts with an increasingly self-assertive Parliament set the stage for the rebellion against his successor, Charles I.James was the only son of Mary, Queen of Scots, and her second husband, Henry Stewart, Lord Darnley. Eight months after James's birth his father died when his house was destroyed by an explosion. After her third marriage, to James Hepburn, Earl of Bothwell, Mary was defeated...
</Question>
<Choice>James I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Great Britain from 1685 to 1688, and the last Stuart monarch in the direct male line. He was deposed in the Glorious Revolution (1688–89) and replaced by William III and Mary II. That revolution, engendered by James's Roman Catholicism, permanently established Parliament as the ruling power of England.James II was the second surviving son of Charles I and Henrietta Maria. He was created duke of York in January 1634. During the English Civil Wars he lived at Oxford—from October 1642 until the city surrendered in June 1646. He was then removed by order of Parliament to St. James's Palace...
</Question>
<Choice>James II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Scotland from 1488 to 1513. An energetic and popular ruler, he unified Scotland under royal control, strengthened royal finances, and improved Scotland's position in European politics.James succeeded to the throne after his father, James III, was killed in a battle against rebels on June 11, 1488. The 15-year-old monarch immediately began to take an active part in government. He extended his authority to the sparsely populated areas of western and northern Scotland and by 1493 had humbled the last lord of the Isles.Although his reign was internally peaceful, it was disturbed by wars wi...
</Question>
<Choice>James IV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Scotland from 1513 to 1542.During the period of his minority, which lasted throughout the first half of his reign, James was a pawn in the struggle between pro-French and pro-English factions; after he assumed personal control of the government, he upheld Roman Catholicism against the Protestant nobles and allied his country with France.James was 17 months old when he succeeded to the throne of his father, James IV (ruled 1488–1513). In the power struggle that developed between the pro-French regent, John Stewart, duke of Albany, and the head of the English party, Archibald Douglas, ea...
</Question>
<Choice>James V</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(Cardinal) prelate, religious reformer, and twice regent of Spain (1506, 1516–17). In 1507 he became both a cardinal and the grand inquisitor of Spain, and during his public life he sought the forced conversion of the Spanish Moors and promoted crusades to conquer North Africa.Jiménez was the son of a poor hidalgo (lower nobility) tax collector and was christened Gonzalo. He studied at the University of Salamanca and, after taking holy orders, spent a number of years in Rome (1459–66), where he disliked the humanists at the papal court but was impressed by their learning. Pope Paul II gave him...
</Question>
<Choice>Jiménez de Cisneros, Francisco, Cardenal</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
queen of Castile (from 1504) and of Aragon (from 1516), though power was exercised for her by her husband, Philip I, her father, Ferdinand II, and her son, the emperor Charles V (Charles I of Spain).Joan was the third child of Ferdinand II of Aragon and Isabella I of Castile and became heiress in 1500 on the death of her brother and elder sister. She had married Philip of Burgundy, son of the emperor Maximilian, as part of Ferdinand's policy of securing allies against France. They had two sons, Charles, born in 1500, who succeeded as emperor and king of Spain, and Ferdinand, his lieutenant and...
</Question>
<Choice>Joan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king and counterking of Hungary (1526–40) who rebelled against the House of Habsburg.John began his public career in 1505 as a member of the Diet of Rákos; it was upon his motion that the Diet voted that no foreign prince would ever again be elected king of Hungary after the death of King Ulászló II, who also was king of Bohemia as Vladislas II. Appointed voivode (governor) of Transylvania in 1511, John brutally suppressed the peasant uprising of 1514 and, thereby, increased his popularity with the gentry. Consequently the second Diet of Rákos appointed him governor of the infant king Louis II...
</Question>
<Choice>John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Poland (1648–68) and pretender to the Swedish throne, whose reign was marked by heavy losses of Polish territory incurred in wars against the Ukrainians, Tatars, Swedes, and Russians.The second son of Sigismund III Vasa, king of Poland and of Sweden, John Casimir fought on the Habsburg side against France during the Thirty Years' War from 1635 until, on his way to Spain to assume the office of admiral, he was arrested by the French and imprisoned for two years (1638–40). After his release he decided to forgo military life and became a Jesuit novice (1646), but he resigned his position...
</Question>
<Choice>John II Casimir Vasa</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Portugal from 1521 to 1557. His long reign saw the development of Portuguese seapower in the Indian Ocean, the occupation of the Brazilian coast, and the establishment of the Portuguese Inquisition and of the Society of Jesus.Shortly after succeeding his father, Manuel I, John married Catherine, sister of Charles V, Holy Roman Emperor and king of Spain, while Charles married John's sister Isabella. These marriages paved the way for the eventual succession of Philip II of Spain to the Portuguese throne in 1580. By the Treaty of Madrid (1529), Portugal secured the Moluccas, or Spice Isla...
</Question>
<Choice>John III (king of Portugal)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Sweden (1568–92), a deeply religious ruler who attempted to reconcile the Swedish Lutheran Church with the Catholic leadership in Rome and to revive discarded elements of the Catholic liturgy.After being named duke of Finland by his father in 1556, John, the elder son of the second marriage of the Swedish king Gustav I Vasa, pursued a foreign policy independent of the crown, leading to a conflict with his half brother Erik XIV, king of Sweden from 1560. Erik limited John's authority and imprisoned him in 1563 after the Duke had acquired a base in Poland by marrying Catherine (1562), si...
</Question>
<Choice>John III (king of Sweden)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
elective king of Poland (1674–96), a soldier who drove back the Ottoman Turks and briefly restored the kingdom of Poland-Lithuania to greatness for the last time.
</Question>
<Choice>John III Sobieski</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Portugal from 1640 as a result of the national revolution, or restoration, which ended 60 years of Spanish rule. He founded the dynasty of Bragança (Braganza), beat off Spanish attacks, and established a system of alliances.John, duke of Bragança, the wealthiest nobleman in Portugal, married Luisa de Guzmán, daughter of the Spanish duke of Medina Sidonia. The Bragança duchy, founded in 1461, was a collateral of the extinct royal House of Aviz; and, when the restorers of independence overthrew the Spanish governor on Dec. 1, 1640, they offered John the crown. On December 15 he was enthr...
</Question>
<Choice>John IV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Portugal from 1706 to 1750, whose relatively peaceful reign saw an increase in the wealth and power of the crown and a generous patronage of learning, culture, and the church.John inherited Portugal's involvement in the War of the Spanish Succession (1701–14) from his father, Peter II (1683–1706), but peace was finally made with France (1713) and Spain (1715). For the remainder of John's long reign, except for a brief campaign against the Turks, the country remained at peace. The great wealth derived from the gold and diamonds of Brazil, Portugal's colony, freed him from financial depe...
</Question>
<Choice>John V</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Holy Roman emperor from 1705, who unsuccessfully fought to retain the Spanish crown for the House of Habsburg.The eldest son of the emperor Leopold I, Joseph became king of Hungary in 1687 and king of the Romans, the imperial successor-designate, in 1690. When Charles II, the last Spanish Habsburg, died in 1700, Joseph supported the candidacy of his own younger brother Charles (the future emperor Charles VI) against the French king Louis XIV's grandson Philip (later Philip V of Spain). During the long War of the Spanish Succession (1701–14), Joseph succeeded to the imperial throne, in May 1705...
</Question>
<Choice>Joseph I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Holy Roman emperor (1765–90), at first coruler with his mother, Maria Theresa (1765–80), and then sole ruler (1780–90) of the Austrian Habsburg dominions. An “enlightened despot,” he sought to introduce administrative, legal, economic, and ecclesiastical reforms—with only measured success.
</Question>
<Choice>Joseph II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
reign name (nianhao) of the second emperor (reigned 1661–1722) of the Qing (Manchu) dynasty (1644–1911/12). To the Chinese empire he added areas north of the Amur River (Heilong Jiang) and portions of Outer Mongolia, and he extended control over Tibet. He opened four ports to foreign trade and encouraged the introduction of Western education and arts and of Roman Catholicism.
</Question>
<Choice>K'ang-hsi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman, scientist, humanist, scholar, and the greatest member of the distinguished Romanian-Russian family of Cantemir. He was prince of Moldavia (1710–11) and later adviser of Peter the Great of Russia.The son of Prince Constantin Cantemir of Moldavia, Kantemir early won the favour of his country's Turkish overlords and hoped eventually to unite the principalities of Moldavia and Walachia under his rule. Named prince of Moldavia in 1710, he soon allied himself with Russia (April 1711), believing Turkish power to be nearing its end. Sharp Russian reverses in the ensuing Russo-Turkish war, h...
</Question>
<Choice>Kantemir, Dmitry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first Zand ruler of Iran. He restored peace to the kingdom after the strife following the collapse of the ?afavid dynasty.Of humble tribal origin, Karim Khan became one of the generals of his predecessor, Nader Shah. In the chaotic aftermath of Nader Shah's assassination in 1747, Karim Khan became a major contender for power but was challenged by several adversaries. In order to add legitimacy to his claim, Karim Khan in 1757 placed on the throne the infant Shah Isma?il III, the grandson of the last official ?afavid king. Isma?il was a figurehead king, real power being vested in Karim Khan, wh...
</Question>
<Choice>Karim Khan Zand</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian state chancellor during the eventful decades from the Seven Years' War (1756–63) to the beginning of the coalition wars against revolutionary France (1792). Kaunitz was responsible for the foreign policy of the Habsburg monarchy, and he served as principal adviser on foreign affairs to the empress Maria Theresa and to her successors.Destined for the church, Kaunitz studied law instead. After a tour of Europe he entered the Austrian foreign service in 1740, advancing to minister to the Sardinian court in 1742. In Turin, Italy, he learned diplomacy from the unscrupulous king of Sardinia...
</Question>
<Choice>Kaunitz, Wenzel Anton von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British statesman and prime minister (July 1782 to April 1783) during the reign of George III.The son of John Fitzmaurice, who took the additional name of Petty on succeeding to the Irish estates of his uncle and who was created earl of Shelburne (1753), William was educated privately and at Christ Church, Oxford (1755–57), and, entering the army, served in the Seven Years' War. While abroad he was elected to Parliament for the family borough of Chipping Wycombe (1760). In 1761 he was reelected and was also returned to the Irish Parliament for County Kerry, but his father's death in May of tha...
</Question>
<Choice>
Lansdowne, William Petty-Fitzmaurice, 1st marquess of
</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
secretary of state for war (1643–77) and then chancellor who created the royal army that enabled King Louis XIV to impose his absolute rule on France and establish French hegemony in Europe.The son of a Parisian magistrate, Le Tellier became a procureur (attorney) for King Louis XIII in 1631 and intendant (royal agent) to the French army in Italy in 1640. In April 1643, a month before the four-year-old Louis XIV succeeded to the throne, Le Tellier was made secretary of state for war by the chief minister, Cardinal Jules Mazarin. During the aristocratic uprising known as the Fronde (1648–53), h...
</Question>
<Choice>Le Tellier, Michel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Holy Roman emperor during whose lengthy reign (1658–1705) Austria emerged from a series of struggles with the Turks and the French to become a great European power, in which monarchical absolutism and administrative centralism gained ascendancy.
</Question>
<Choice>Leopold I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Holy Roman emperor from 1790 to 1792, one of the most capable of the 18th-century reformist rulers known as the “enlightened despots.”The third son of the Habsburg Maria Theresa and the emperor Francis I, Leopold succeeded his father as duke of Tuscany when his eldest brother became emperor as Joseph II in 1765. Like Joseph, Leopold was influenced by the ideas of the Enlightenment and was determined to construct an efficient state apparatus at the expense of feudal interests. During his 25-year reign over the Grand Duchy of Tuscany, he rationalized his states' taxation and tariff systems and e...
</Question>
<Choice>Leopold II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman, lawyer, and humanist who, as chancellor of France from 1560 to 1568, was instrumental in the adoption by the French government of a policy of toleration toward the Huguenots.L'Hospital studied law at Toulouse but was forced into exile because of his father's association with the traitor Charles de Bourbon; he subsequently continued his legal studies at Padua and Bologna. He was able to return to France about 1534, and in 1537 he became a councillor in the Parlement of Paris (supreme court). Henry II made him his envoy to the Council of Trent in 1547, and in 1553, on the recommendati...
</Question>
<Choice>L'Hospital, Michel de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
last of the paramount Mongol khans (ruled 1604–34).Ligdan was a member of the Chahar royal family in which the Mongol supreme khanate was vested. He lived at a time when the Mongols were abandoning their traditional shamanism to convert to Tibetan Buddhism. He had Buddhist temples constructed and religious texts translated from Tibetan into Mongolian.Ligdan's authority as khan was not recognized beyond his own tribe, and his attempts to maintain a degree of control over nearby Mongols were ignored. He was known as a formidable fighter, however, and was feared by his neighbours. Attacks from en...
</Question>
<Choice>Ligdan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Hungary and of Bohemia from 1516, who was the last of the Jagiello line to rule those countries and the last king to rule all of Hungary before the Turks conquered a large portion of it.The only son of Vladislas II of Hungary and Bohemia, Louis was sickly as a child but intelligent. To assure the succession, he was crowned king of Hungary (June 4, 1508) and of Bohemia (May 11, 1509), and became king on his father's death (March 1516). He was declared of age to rule on Dec. 11, 1521. He married Maria of Austria the following January 13, and both pursued a life of riotous pleasure, soon...
</Question>
<Choice>Louis II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of France from 1498, noted for his disastrous Italian wars and his domestic popularity.Son of Charles, duc d'Orléans, and Marie de Clèves, Louis succeeded his father as duke in 1465. In 1476 he was forced to marry the saintly but misshapen Jeanne of France, daughter of his second cousin King Louis XI. During the minority of King Charles VIII he launched a revolt and was imprisoned (1488). Restored to royal favour, he commanded troops at Asti during Charles VIII's invasion of Italy (1494–95).After becoming king of France on the death of Charles, he annulled his marriage in order to marry C...
</Question>
<Choice>Louis XII</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of France from 1610 to 1643, who cooperated closely with his chief minister, the Cardinal de Richelieu, to make France a leading European power.The eldest son of King Henry IV and Marie de Médicis, Louis succeeded to the throne upon the assassination of his father in May 1610. The queen mother was regent until Louis came of age in 1614, but she continued to govern for three years thereafter. As part of her policy of allying France with Spain, she arranged the marriage (November 1615) between Louis and Anne of Austria, daughter of the Spanish king Philip III. By 1617 the king, resentful at...
</Question>
<Choice>Louis XIII</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of France (1643–1715) who ruled his country, principally from his great palace at Versailles, during one of its most brilliant periods and who remains the symbol of absolute monarchy of the classical age. Internationally, in a series of wars between 1667 and 1697, he extended France's eastern borders at the expense of the Habsburgs and then, in the War of the Spanish Succession (1701–14), engaged a hostile European coalition in order to secure the Spanish throne for his grandson.
</Question>
<Choice>Louis XIV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of France from 1715 to 1774, whose ineffectual rule contributed to the decline of royal authority that led to the outbreak of the Revolution in 1789.Louis was the great-grandson of King Louis XIV (ruled 1643–1715) and the son of Louis, duc de Bourgogne, and Marie-Adélaïde of Savoy. Because his parents and his only surviving brother had all died in 1712, he became king at the age of five on the death of Louis XIV (Sept. 1, 1715). Until he attained his legal majority in February 1723, France was governed by a regent, Philippe II, duc d'Orléans. In 1721 Orléans betrothed Louis to the infanta...
</Question>
<Choice>Louis XV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the last king of France (1774–92) in the line of Bourbon monarchs preceding the French Revolution of 1789. The monarchy was abolished on Sept. 21, 1792; later Louis and his queen consort, Marie-Antoinette, were guillotined on charges of counterrevolution.
</Question>
<Choice>Louis XVI</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Portugal from 1495 to 1521, whose reign was characterized by religious troubles (all Moors and Jews refusing baptism were expelled), by a policy of clever neutrality in the face of quarrels between France and Spain, and by the continuation of overseas expansion, notably to India and Brazil.Manuel was fortunate to have reigned at all; he was the ninth child of Dom Fernando, who was the younger brother of Afonso V. Manuel's father died a year after Manuel was born. King Afonso had one of Manuel's sisters married to his heir, John II, and another to the powerful Duke of Bragança. On his a...
</Question>
<Choice>Manuel I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Habsburg ruler who, as regent of the Netherlands (1507–15, 1519–30) for her nephew Charles (later the Holy Roman emperor Charles V), helped consolidate Habs-burg dominion there.The daughter of the Habsburg archduke Maximilian (later the Holy Roman emperor Maximilian I) and his consort, Mary, duchess of Burgundy, Margaret was first betrothed in 1483 to the dauphin, later Charles VIII of France. After he repudiated her (1491), she married (April 1497) the infante John, heir to the Spanish kingdoms, who died only a few months later. Finally, in 1501, she married Philibert II, duke of Savoy, who d...
</Question>
<Choice>Margaret Of Austria</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
duchess of Parma and Habsburg regent who, as governor-general of the Netherlands (1559–67), attempted to appease the growing discontent with Spanish rule.The illegitimate daughter of the Holy Roman emperor Charles V (Charles I of Spain) and Johanna van der Gheenst, Margaret was married in 1536 to Alessandro de' Medici, Duke of Florence, who was murdered less than a year later. She then married (1538) Ottavio Farnese (Duke of Parma after 1547) and was appointed governor of the Netherlands in 1559 by her half-brother, Philip II of Spain. Opposition to Spanish rule was already strong because of t...
</Question>
<Choice>Margaret of Parma</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
wife of King James IV of Scotland, mother of James V, and elder daughter of King Henry VII of England. During her son's minority, she played a key role in the conflict between the pro-French and pro-English factions in Scotland, constantly shifting her allegiances to suit her financial interests.She married James IV in August 1503, but the scanty dowry provided by her father ruined any opportunity for improved relations between England and Scotland. James was killed fighting the English in 1513, and Margaret then ruled for her infant son, James V. Her marriage in 1514 to Archibald Douglas, ear...
</Question>
<Choice>Margaret Tudor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
queen of Naples and wife of King Ferdinand IV of Naples. She held the real power in Naples, and, under the influence of her favourite, Sir John Acton, 6th Baronet, who was reputed to be her lover, she adopted a pro-British, anti-French policy.The daughter of the empress Maria Theresa of Austria, Maria Carolina married in 1768 Ferdinand IV, who allowed her to assume much of the power in the kingdom. By a clause in the marriage contract, she entered the council of state, the kingdom's ruling body, when she had given birth to a male heir (1777). She soon brought about the downfall of the liberal...
</Question>
<Choice>Maria Carolina</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the first queen regnant of Portugal (1777–1816).Maria was the daughter of King Joseph. In 1760 she married her uncle who, as king consort after Maria's accession (February 1777), became Peter III. Maria attempted to correct the harshness of her father's minister, the marquês de Pombal, freeing his political prisoners and banishing him to Pombal; but an inquiry ended in his pardon. She abandoned some of his trading enterprises but developed small industries in Portugal and new crops in Brazil.The deaths of Peter in 1786 and of Maria's elder son Joseph in 1788, combined with news of the excesses...
</Question>
<Choice>Maria I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
archduchess of Austria and queen of Hungary and Bohemia (1740–80), wife and empress of the Holy Roman emperor Francis I (reigned 1745–65), and mother of the Holy Roman emperor Joseph II (reigned 1765–90). Upon her accession, the War of the Austrian Succession (1740–48) erupted, challenging her inheritance of the Habsburg lands. This contest with Prussia was followed by two more, the Seven Years' War (1756–63) and the War of the Bavarian Succession (1778–79), which further checked Austrian power.
</Question>
<Choice>Maria Theresa</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
queen consort of King Henry IV of France (reigned 1589–1610) and, from 1610 to 1614, regent for her son, King Louis XIII (reigned 1610–43).Marie was the daughter of Francesco de' Medici, grand duke of Tuscany, and Joanna of Austria. Shortly after Henry IV divorced his wife, Margaret, he married Marie (October 1600) in order to obtain a large dowry that would help him pay his debts. In 1601 Marie gave birth to the dauphin Louis (the future Louis XIII), and during the following eight years she bore the king five more children. Nevertheless, their relationship was strained. Marie resented Henry's...
</Question>
<Choice>Marie De Médicis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
queen of Scotland (1542–67) and queen consort of France (1559–60). Her unwise marital and political actions provoked rebellion among the Scottish nobles, forcing her to flee to England, where she was eventually beheaded as a Roman Catholic threat to the English throne.
</Question>
<Choice>Mary</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the first queen to rule England (1553–58) in her own right. She was known as Bloody Mary for her persecution of Protestants in a vain attempt to restore Roman Catholicism in England.
</Question>
<Choice>Mary I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
queen of England, Scotland, and Ireland (1689–94) and wife of King William III. As the daughter of King James II, she made it possible for her Dutch husband to become co-ruler of England after he had overthrown James's government.Although her father and mother were converts to Roman Catholicism, Mary was brought up a Protestant. In November 1677 she was married to her cousin William of Orange, stadholder of Holland and champion of Protestantism in Europe. She then settled in Holland. Her inability to bear children and William's infidelity made the early years of her marriage unhappy, but event...
</Question>
<Choice>Mary II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Holy Roman emperor from 1612, who, in a reversal of the policy of his father, Maximilian II, sponsored a Catholic revival in the Habsburg domains that, despite his moderating influence, eventually led to the outbreak of the Thirty Years' War.The third son of the archduke Maximilian of Austria (later emperor), Matthias received no territories on his father's death. This incapable and unreliable Habsburg ruler was invited by the Catholic nobility of the Spanish Netherlands to replace Don Juan of Austria as governor general (1577). Unable to arrange a compromise peace between Spain and the Protes...
</Question>
<Choice>Matthias</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
chancellor of France who succeeded in temporarily (1771–74) depriving the Parlements (high courts of justice) of the political powers that had enabled them to block the reforms proposed by the ministers of King Louis XV. By rescinding Maupeou's measures, King Louis XVI (reigned 1774–92) lost his opportunity to institute fundamental reforms that might have prevented the outbreak of the French Revolution.Maupeou was born into a prominent family of the noblesse de robe (judicial nobility). Trained in law, he became president of the Parlement of Paris in 1763, when his father, René-Charles de Maup...
</Question>
<Choice>Maupeou, René-Nicolas-Charles-Augustin de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
archduke of Austria, German king, and Holy Roman emperor (1493–1519), who made his family, the Habsburgs, dominant in 16th-century Europe. He added vast lands to the traditional Austrian holdings, securing the Netherlands by his own marriage, Hungary and Bohemia by treaty and military pressure, and Spain and the Spanish empire by the marriage of his son Philip. He also fought a series of wars against the French, mostly in Italy. His grandson succeeded to the vast Habsburg realm and the imperial crown as Charles V.
</Question>
<Choice>Maximilian I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Holy Roman emperor from 1564, whose liberal religious policies permitted an interval of peace between Roman Catholics and Protestants in Germany after the first struggles of the Reformation. A humanist and patron of the arts, he largely failed to achieve his political goals, both at home and abroad.Maximilian, the eldest son of the future emperor Ferdinand I and the nephew of the emperor Charles V, received his education in Spain. In a dispute over the Habsburg succession order, he was at first placed behind Charles V's son Philip (the future Philip II of Spain), but, by a 1553 agreement, he d...
</Question>
<Choice>Maximilian II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ottoman sultan whose reign (1648–87) was marked first by administrative and financial decay and later by a period of revival under the able Köprülü viziers. Mehmed IV, however, devoted himself to hunting rather than to affairs of state.Mehmed succeeded his mentally ill father, Ibrahim, at the age of six. Power was exercised by factions led by his grandmother and mother while the chiefs of the Janissary corps dominated the state administration. During this period revolts broke out in Constantinople and Anatolia, and a series of grand viziers sought in vain to solve the empire's financial crisis...
</Question>
<Choice>Mehmed IV Avci</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
sachem (intertribal leader) of a confederation of indigenous peoples that included the Wampanoag and Narraganset. Metacom led one of the most costly wars of resistance in New England history, known as King Philip's War (1675–76).Metacom was the second son of Massasoit, a Wampanoag sachem who had managed to keep peace with the English colonizers of Massachusetts and Rhode Island for many decades. Upon Massasoit's death (1661) and that of his eldest son, Wamsutta (English name Alexander), the following year, Metacom became sachem. He succeeded to the position during a period characterized by inc...
</Question>
<Choice>Metacom</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
tsar of Russia from 1613 to 1645 and founder of the Romanov dynasty, which ruled Russia until 1917.Son of Fyodor Nikitich Romanov (later the Orthodox patriarch Philaret), Michael was related to the last tsar of the Rurik dynasty, Fyodor I (reigned 1584–98) through his grandfather Nikita Romanov, who was Fyodor's maternal uncle. When the zemsky sobor (assembly of the land) met in 1613 to elect a new tsar after the Time of Troubles—a period of chaotic internal disorders, foreign invasions, and a rapid succession of rulers following the death of Fyodor I—it chose Michael Romanov as tsar (February...
</Question>
<Choice>Michael (tsar of Russia)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Romanian national hero, prince of Walachia, who briefly united much of the future national patrimony under his rule.Acceding to the princely throne of Walachia in 1593, Michael submitted in May 1595 to the suzerainty of the prince of Transylvania, Sigismund Báthory, in order to secure support against Ottoman rule. He routed the Turks at Calugareni (August 1595) and Giurgiu (October 1595). In 1598 he took an oath of fealty to the Habsburg emperor, Rudolf II, and also concluded a peace with the Turks. The following year he attacked his new Transylvanian suzerain, Andreas Báthory, and defeated hi...
</Question>
<Choice>Michael (prince of Walachia)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Poland (1669–73), whose reign was marked by struggles between the pro-Habsburg and pro-French political factions.A native Pole and descendant of Korybut, brother of King Wladyslaw II Jagiello, Michael was freely elected by the unanimous vote of the Polish nobility; but he was chosen chiefly for the merit of his father, Jérémi Wisniowiecki, a great border magnate who had victoriously kept down the Cossacks, and he proved to be a passive tool in the hands of the Habsburgs. In view of this, the French party rallied round Jan Sobieski, a military commander of rising fame. The dissensions b...
</Question>
<Choice>Michael Wisniowiecki</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
ninth Aztec emperor of Mexico, famous for his dramatic confrontation with the Spanish conquistador Hernán Cortés.In 1502 Montezuma succeeded his uncle Ahuitzotl as the leader of an empire that had reached its greatest extent, stretching to what is now Honduras and Nicaragua, but that was weakened by the resentment of the subject tribes to the increasing demands for tribute and victims for the religious sacrifices. Montezuma was commander of the army and organized extensive expeditions of conquest in deference to Huitzilopochtli, the god of war and of the sun. Through astrologers, the god insti...
</Question>
<Choice>Montezuma II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English humanist and statesman, chancellor of England (1529–32), who was beheaded for refusing to accept King Henry VIII as head of the Church of England. He is recognized as a saint by the Roman Catholic Church.
</Question>
<Choice>More, Sir Thomas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish lord who played a leading role in the overthrow of Mary, Queen of Scots (reigned 1542–67). As regent of Scotland for young king James VI (later James I of England) from 1572 to 1578, he restored the authority of the central government, which had been weakened by years of civil strife.The son of Sir George Douglas, James succeeded to the earldom of his father-in-law, James Douglas, 3rd Earl of Morton, in 1548. In 1557 he was part of a group of Scottish nobles who signed a “band,” or covenant, in support of the Scottish faith. Although he was a Protestant, Morton was in 1563 appointed c...
</Question>
<Choice>Morton, James Douglas, 4th Earl of</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
ineffective, pleasure-seeking Mughal emperor of India from 1719 to 1748.The son of Shah Jahan, Mu?ammad Shah was made emperor in 1719 by the powerful Sayyid brothers, ?Abdullah and ?usayn ?Ali, who had killed the emperor Farrukh-Siyar. In 1720 the assassination of ?usayn ?Ali and the defeat of ?Abdullah at the battle of Hasanpur (southwest of Delhi) liberated Mu?ammad Shah from effective Sayyid control. In 1721 he married the daughter of Farrukh-Siyar. After Nizam al-Mulk A?af Jah, who was the court-appointed vizier, had left court in disgust in 1724, the provinces steadily slipped out of impe...
</Question>
<Choice>Muhammad Shah</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ottoman sultan in 1574–95 whose reign saw lengthy wars against Iran and Austria and social and economic deterioration within the Ottoman state.Externally Murad continued the military offensive of his predecessors. He took Fez (now Fès, Mor.) from the Portuguese in 1578. He fought an exhausting war against Iran (1578–90), which extended his rule over Azerbaijan, Tiflis (now Tbilisi, Georgia), Nahavand, and Hamadan (now in Iran). In Europe he began a long war against Austria (1593–1606), which saw an alliance in 1594 of the Ottoman vassal rulers of Moldavia, Transylvania, and Walachia with Austr...
</Question>
<Choice>Murad III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ottoman sultan from 1623 to 1640 whose heavy-handed rule put an end to prevailing lawlessness and rebelliousness and who is renowned as the conqueror of Baghdad.Murad, who came to the throne at age 11, ruled for several years through the regency of his mother, Kösem, and a series of grand viziers. Effective rule, however, remained in the hands of the turbulent spahis (from Turkish sipahiyan, quasi-feudal cavalries) and the Janissaries, who more than once forced the execution of high officials. Corruption of government officials and rebellion in the Asiatic provinces, coupled with an empty trea...
</Question>
<Choice>Murad IV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ottoman sultan from 1695 to 1703, whose determination to regain territories lost after the unsuccessful attempt to take Vienna in 1683 led to the continuation of the war against the Holy League (Austria, Poland, and Venice).Mustafa's military campaigns met with early success. After recovering the island of Chios from Venice, he made gains against Austria in 1695 and 1696. The Russians occupied Azov (at the mouth of the Don River) in 1696, however, and he was defeated by the Austrians at Senta (seeZenta, Battle of) in 1697. The Treaty of Carlowitz (1699) radically reduced Turkey's Balkan holdin...
</Question>
<Choice>Mustafa II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ottoman sultan (1757–74) who attempted governmental and military reforms to halt the empire's decline and who declared a war on Russia that (after his death) culminated in a disastrous defeat.Though Mustafa and his able grand vizier, Ragib Mehmed Pasha, understood the necessity for reform, their efforts were directed toward the results, not the causes, of the Ottoman decline. They were unable to curb tax abuses; hence, their fiscal reforms proved ineffective. Administrative reforms foundered on the central government's inability to extend its authority over the local rulers (a?yan) of its prov...
</Question>
<Choice>Mustafa III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Iranian ruler and conqueror who created an Iranian empire that stretched from the Indus River to the Caucasus Mountains.Nadr Qoli Beg had an obscure beginning in the Turkish Afshar tribe, which was loyal to the ?afavid shahs of Iran. After serving under a local chieftain, Nadr formed and led a band of robbers, showing marked powers of leadership. In 1726, as head of this group of bandits, he led 5,000 followers in support of the ?afavid shah ?ahmasp II, who was seeking to regain the throne his father had lost four years earlier to the Ghilzay Afghan usurper Ma?mud. Nadr reformed Iran's militar...
</Question>
<Choice>Nadir Shah</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Siam (1656–88), who was best known for his efforts in foreign affairs and whose court produced the first “golden age” of Thai literature.Narai was a son of King Prasat Thong by a queen who was a daughter of King Song Tham, and he came to the throne after violent palace upheavals had cut short the reigns of his elder brother and his uncle. He was an effective ruler who dealt successfully with Siam's traditional Southeast Asian rivals and was ambitious to thrust his kingdom onto the stage of world politics. Anxious to break the domination of the Dutch East India Company over Siam's exter...
</Question>
<Choice>Narai</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Siam (1590–1605), regarded as a national hero by the Thai people for having liberated the country from the Myanmar (Burmese).In 1569 the Myanmar king Bayinnaung (reigned 1551–81) conquered Siam and placed Naresuan's father, Maha Thammaracha, on the throne as his vassal. The capital, Ayutthaya, was pillaged, thousands of Siamese were deported to Myanmar (Burma) as slaves, and Siam then suffered numerous invasions from Cambodia. At the age of 16 Naresuan was also made a vassal of Myanmar and appointed governor of the northern province of Phitsanulok. After campaigning with the Myanmar ar...
</Question>
<Choice>Naresuan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prime minister from 1770 to 1782, whose vacillating leadership contributed to the loss of Great Britain's American colonies in the American Revolution (1775–83).The son of a Tory nobleman, the 1st earl of Guilford, North was educated at Eton and Trinity College, Oxford. Elected member of Parliament for Banbury at the age of 22, he represented the town (of which his father was high steward) for nearly 40 years. The Duke of Newcastle, when prime minister, made him a lord of the treasury in 1759, and North held this office under the succeeding prime ministers, the Earl of Bute and George Grenvill...
</Question>
<Choice>North, Frederick North, Lord</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
chieftain of the JianzhouJuchen, a Manchurian tribe, and one of the founders of the Manchu, or Qing, dynasty. His first attack on China (1618) presaged his son Dorgon's conquest of the Chinese empire.The Juchen (Chinese: Nüzhen, or Ruzhen) were a Tungus people who belonged to those border groups at the periphery of the Chinese empire that normally were under the influence of the Chinese imperial court. Nurhachi's tribe was the so-called Jianzhou Juchen, one of five Juchen tribes of Manchuria (now Northeast China). The Jianzhou Juchen lived to the east of the Chinese border in the Changbai Moun...
</Question>
<Choice>Nurhachi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
regent of France for the young King Louis XV from 1715 to 1723.The son of Philippe I, duc d'Orléans, and Elizabeth Charlotte of the Palatinate, Philippe d'Orléans was known as the duc de Chartres during his father's lifetime. Although he served with the French army against the English and Dutch in the War of the Grand Alliance (1689–97), his uncle, Louis XIV, excluded him from the high military commands to which he considered himself entitled. The duc de Chartres retaliated by studiously neglecting his wife, Françoise-Marie de Bourbon, the king's favourite legitimized daughter. His irreverence...
</Question>
<Choice>Orléans, Philippe II, duc d'</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
founder and first ruler of the Asante (Ashanti) empire (in present-day Ghana) who as chief of the small state of Kumasi came to realize (c. 1680–90) that a fusion of the small separate Asante kingdoms was necessary to withstand their powerful Denkyera neighbours to the south.Osei Tutu had been a hostage in the Denkyera court but had escaped eastward to the powerful state of Akwamu, where he was exposed to new ideas of political and military organization. When he returned to Kumasi, some Akwamu accompanied him. One was a priest, Okomfo Anokye, who is usually given credit for introducing the leg...
</Question>
<Choice>Osei Tutu</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
chancellor of Sweden (1612–54), successively under King Gustav II Adolf and Queen Christina. He was noted for his administrative reforms and for his diplomacy and military command during the Thirty Years' War. He was created a count in 1645.
</Question>
<Choice>Oxenstierna, Axel, Greve</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
emperor of Russia from 1796 to 1801.Son of Peter III (reigned 1762) and Catherine II the Great (reigned 1762–96), Paul was reared by his father's aunt, the empress Elizabeth (reigned 1741–61). After 1760 he was tutored by Catherine's close adviser, the learned diplomat Nikita Ivanovich Panin, but the boy never developed good relations with his mother, who wrested the imperial crown from her mentally feeble husband in 1762 and, afterward, consistently refused to allow Paul to participate actively in government affairs.Having married Sophia Dorothea of Württemberg (Russian name Maria Fyodorovna)...
</Question>
<Choice>Paul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prime minister of Great Britain from 1743 to 1754. A somewhat colourless politician, he worked for peace abroad and introduced important financial reforms.The son of Thomas, 1st Lord Pelham, he was educated at Hart Hall (later Hertford College), Oxford, and then served briefly in the army. First elected to Parliament in 1717, Pelham became a supporter of Robert Walpole (prime minister 1730–42), who helped him obtain appointments as lord of the Treasury (1721), secretary for war (1724), and paymaster to the forces (1730). After Walpole resigned under pressure from the House of Commons in 1742,...
</Question>
<Choice>Pelham, Henry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prime minister of Great Britain from 1754 to 1756 and from 1757 to 1762. Through his control of government patronage, he wielded enormous political influence during the reigns of the kings George I and George II.Pelham-Holles inherited the barony of Pelham of Laughton from his father in 1712 (having assumed the name Pelham-Holles in 1711). By the time he came of age in 1714, he had become one of the wealthiest Whig landowners in England, with holdings in 12 counties and a rental income of nearly £40,000 a year. He helped bring about the succession of King George I (reigned 1714–27) and as a re...
</Question>
<Choice>Pelham-Holles, Thomas, 1st Duke of Newcastle</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
tsar of Russia, who reigned jointly with his half-brother Ivan V (1682–96) and alone thereafter (1696–1725) and who in 1721 was proclaimed emperor (imperator). He was one of his country's greatest statesmen, organizers, and reformers.Peter was the son of Tsar Alexis by his second wife, Natalya Kirillovna Naryshkina. Unlike his half-brothers, sons of his father's first wife, Mariya Ilinichna Miloslavskaya, Peter proved a healthy child, lively and inquisitive. It is probably significant to his development that his mother's former guardian, Artamon Sergeyevich Matveyev, had raised her in an atmos...
</Question>
<Choice>Peter I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Portugal whose reign as prince regent (1668–83) and as king (1683–1706) was marked by the consolidation of royal absolutism and the reduction of the significance of the Cortes (National Assembly); at the same time he encouraged economic development and guided his nation through a troubled period in Europe.After the death of his father, John IV, in 1656, Peter's feebleminded and profligate elder brother Afonso VI brought Portugal to a very low condition. In November 1667 Afonso was sent into confinement in the Azores, and Peter became regent. Shortly thereafter, his brother's marriage (...
</Question>
<Choice>Peter II (king of Portugal)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
emperor of Russia from 1727 to 1730. Grandson of Peter I the Great (ruled 1682–1725), Peter II was named heir to the Russian throne by Catherine I (ruled 1725–27) and was crowned at the age of 11 (May 18 [May 7, Old Style], 1727).Because Catherine had named the Supreme Privy Council to act as regent for the youth, Aleksandr D. Menshikov, who had been a close adviser to both Peter I and Catherine I and had become the most prominent member of the council, dominated the first months of Peter's reign. Menshikov installed the young emperor in his own household and arranged for his daughter and Pete...
</Question>
<Choice>Peter II (emperor of Russia)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
emperor of Russia from Jan. 5, 1762 (Dec. 25, 1761, O.S.), to July 9 (June 28, O.S.), 1762.Son of Anna, one of Peter I the Great's daughters, and Charles Frederick, duke of Holstein-Gottorp, the young duke was brought to Russia by his aunt Elizabeth shortly after she became empress of Russia (Dec. 5–6, 1741). Renamed Peter (Pyotr Fyodorovich), he was received into the Russian Orthodox Church (Nov. 18 [Nov. 7, O.S.], 1742) and proclaimed the heir to the Russian throne. On Aug. 21, 1745, he married Sophie Frederike Auguste, a princess from Anhalt-Zerbst, in Germany, who took the name Catherine (...
</Question>
<Choice>Peter III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Castile for less than a month before his death and the founder of the Habsburg dynasty in Spain.Philip was the son of the future Holy Roman emperor Maximilian I of Habsburg and Mary of Burgundy. At his mother's death (1482) he succeeded to her Netherlands dominions, with Maximilian acting as regent for him during his minority. When Philip became of age, his interest in the Netherlands was soon subordinated to his hopes for the Spanish succession. In 1496 Philip was married to Joan the Mad, daughter of Ferdinand II the Catholic of Aragon and Isabella I the Catholic of Castile; Joan late...
</Question>
<Choice>Philip I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the Spaniards (1556–98) and king of the Portuguese (as Philip I, 1580–98), champion of the Roman CatholicCounter-Reformation. During his reign the Spanish Empire attained its greatest power, extent, and influence, though he failed to suppress the revolt of the Netherlands (beginning in 1566) and lost the “Invincible Armada” in the attempted invasion of England (1588).
</Question>
<Choice>Philip II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Spain and of Portugal (as Philip II) whose reign (1598–1621) was characterized by a successful peaceful foreign policy in western Europe and internally by the expulsion of the Moriscos (Christians of Moorish ancestry) and government by the King's favourites.Philip was the son of Philip II of Spain by his fourth consort, his Habsburg cousin Anna of Austria. Though pious, benevolent, and highly virtuous in private conduct, Philip, after he became king (Sept. 13, 1598), showed himself to be indolent and indifferent to his responsibilities. His father revealed his disappointment when he re...
</Question>
<Choice>Philip III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Spain (1621–65) and of Portugal (1621–40), during the decline of Spain as a great world power.He succeeded his father, Philip III of Spain, in 1621, and, for the first 22 years of his reign, Philip's valido, or chief minister, was the Conde-Duque de Olivares, who took the spread of the Thirty Years' War as an opportunity not only for resuming hostilities against the Dutch at the end of the Twelve Years' Truce of 1609 (1621) but also for an ambitious attempt to restore Spanish hegemony in Europe, in close alliance with the imperial branch of the Habsburg dynasty. The Spanish armies won...
</Question>
<Choice>Philip IV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Spain from 1700 (except for a brief period from January to August 1724) and founder of the Bourbon dynasty in Spain. During his reign Spain regained much of its former influence in international affairs.Philip was a son of the dauphin Louis (son of Louis XIV of France) and of Marie Anne, daughter of Ferdinand, elector of Bavaria. Philip's whole career was influenced by the fact that he was a grandson of Louis XIV of France and a great grandson of Philip IV, king of Spain. Philip held the title of duc d'Anjou until 1700, when he emerged as a person of political importance. In that year...
</Question>
<Choice>Philip V</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British statesman, twice virtual prime minister (1756–61, 1766–68), who secured the transformation of his country into an imperial power.
</Question>
<Choice>Pitt, William, the Elder</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British prime minister (1783–1801, 1804–06) during the French Revolutionary and Napoleonic wars. He had considerable influence in strengthening the office of the prime minister.
</Question>
<Choice>Pitt, William, The Younger</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ottawa Indian chief who became a great intertribal leader when he organized a combined resistance—known as Pontiac's War (1763–64)—to British power in the Great Lakes area.Little is known of Pontiac's early life, but by 1755 he had become a tribal chief. His commanding manner and talent for strategic planning also enabled him to become the leader of a loose confederacy among the Ottawa, the Potawatomi, and the Ojibwa. In 1760 he met Major Robert Rogers, a British colonial ranger on his way to occupy Michilimackinac (St. Ignace, Mich.) and other forts surrendered by the French during the French...
</Question>
<Choice>Pontiac</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
North American Indian leader, father of Pocahontas. He presided over the Powhatan empire at the time the English established the Jamestown Colony (1607).Powhatan had inherited rulership of an empire of six tribes from his father. After succeeding his father, Powhatan brought about two dozen other tribes into the empire that was named for him; at the peak of his power, he is estimated to have ruled between 13,000 and 34,000 people. Powhatan was an astute and energetic ruler, but he was also noted as being strict and occasionally cruel toward his subjects. In the Algonquian language of his peopl...
</Question>
<Choice>Powhatan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
member of the ruling Shah family of the Gurkha (Gorkha) principality, Nepal, who conquered the three Malla kingdoms of Kathmandu, Patan, and Bhadgaon in 1769 and consolidated them to found the modern state of Nepal. He also established the capital of Nepal at Kathmandu.In 1742 Prithvi Naraya? became king of Gurkha. An ambitious ruler, he was able to quickly enlarge his territory by conquering the quarrelsome and disunited principalities around Gurkha. Prithvi Naraya?'s initial attempts to establish hegemony over the three Malla kingdoms were abortive, however; the raja of Kathmandu enlisted th...
</Question>
<Choice>Prithvi Narayan Shah</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prince of Transylvania who headed a nearly successful national rising of all Hungary against the Habsburg empire.He was born of an aristocratic Magyar family. Both his father and his stepfather had led insurrections against the Habsburgs, and Rákóczi grew up in an atmosphere of fervent Magyar patriotism. He was separated from his mother after the surrender of Munkács to the Austrians (1688) and taken to Vienna and placed in a Jesuit college in Bohemia to be brought up in Austrian ways.Rákóczi returned to his Hungarian estates in 1694, having forgotten much of his heritage. Encouraged by other...
</Question>
<Choice>Rákóczi, Ferenc, II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prince of Transylvania from 1630, who, as a champion of Protestantism, fought for and won religious freedom in Hungary and made his principality virtually an independent state.György was the youngest son of Zsigmond Rákóczi, prince of Transylvania (1607–08). György took a leading part in the campaigns of Transylvania's Prince Gábor Bethlen against the Habsburgs. After Bethlen's death he was elected prince (Nov. 26, 1630) and continued Transylvania's anti-Habsburg policy. In 1644, in alliance with Sweden, he declared war against the Habsburg emperor Ferdinand III and in the Peace of Linz (Dec....
</Question>
<Choice>Rákóczi, György, I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prince of Transylvania from 1648, who had the laws of the principality codified, but whose foreign policy led to the restoration of Turkish hegemony over Transylvania.György II succeeded his illustrious father György I as prince in 1648 and continued his policy of seeking alliances with the hospodars (lords) of Moldavia to the east and Walachia to the south. In 1656, however, he joined Charles X Gustavus of Sweden in attacking Poland, hoping to be elected Polish king, an act in defiance of the Ottoman Turks, who had suzerainty over Transylvania. The Turks ordered their vassals, the Crimean Tat...
</Question>
<Choice>Rákóczi, György, II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
also called Phraphutthayotfa Chulalok Siamese king (1782–1809) and founder of the Chakkri dynasty (q.v.), which reigns in Thailand.Rama I was the son of a high court official and his part-Chinese wife. At the time of the Burmese invasion of Siam in 1766–67, he was serving as chief judge in Rat Buri province. After the fall of Ayutthaya (1767), the Thai capital, he joined the service of Taksin, the new Siamese king, and soon became the new military commander of the northern provinces (Chao Phraya Chakkri) and his most effective general. He spent most of the next decade leading Thai armies in th...
</Question>
<Choice>Rama I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prime minister of Great Britain from July 1765 to July 1766 and from March to July 1782. He led the parliamentary group known as Rockingham Whigs, which opposed Britain's war (1775–83) against its colonists in North America.He succeeded to his father's title of marquess in 1750 and served from 1751 to 1762 as gentleman of the bedchamber for George II (reigned 1727–60) and George III (reigned 1760–1820). In July 1765 George III dismissed George Grenville as head of the ministry and appointed Rockingham in his place. The new prime minister obtained repeal of the Stamp Act, which had imposed an u...
</Question>
<Choice>
Watson-Wentworth, Charles, 2nd marquess of Rockingham
</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Holy Roman emperor from 1576 to 1612; his ill health and unpopularity prevented him from restraining the religious dissensions that eventually led to the Thirty Years' War (1618–48).The eldest surviving son of the emperor Maximilian II and Maria, who was the daughter of the emperor Charles V, Rudolf was crowned king of Hungary in 1572 (as Rudolf) and of Bohemia in 1575 (as Rudolf II). He succeeded his father as emperor and as archduke of Austria (as Rudolf V) on Oct. 12, 1576.Subject to fits of severe depression, Rudolf soon retired to Prague, where he lived in seclusion, dabbling in the arts...
</Question>
<Choice>Rudolf II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Portugal from 1557, a fanatically religious ruler who lost his life in a crusade against the Muslims in Morocco. After his death, many of his subjects believed that he would return to deliver them from Spanish rule, a messianic faith known as Sebastianism (Sebastianismo).Sebastian was the posthumous son of John, heir to the Portuguese throne, and succeeded his grandfather, John III, at the age of three. He was austerely educated by Jesuits and, as he grew into manhood, saw himself as Christ's captain, destined to win victories over the Muslims. Neither his grandmother, Queen Catherine,...
</Question>
<Choice>Sebastian</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ottoman sultan (1512–20) who extended the empire to Syria, the Hejaz, and Egypt and raised the Ottomans to leadership of the Muslim world.Selim came to the throne in the wake of civil strife in which he, his brother, and their father, Bayezid II, had been involved. Selim eliminated all potential claimants to the sultanate, leaving only his ablest son, Süleyman, as his heir. He then turned eastward, where Isma?il I, founder of the ?afavid dynasty in Iran, posed a political and ideological threat by espousing Shi?ism (the second largest branch of Islam) as opposed to the Sunni Islam of the Ottom...
</Question>
<Choice>Selim I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ottoman sultan from 1566, whose reign saw peace in Europe and Asia and the rise of the Ottomans to dominance in the Mediterranean but marked the beginning of the decline in the power of the sultans. He was unable to impose his authority over the Janissaries and was overruled by the women of his harem.Selim, the son of Süleyman I the Magnificent, came to the throne in the wake of palace intrigues and bitter civil strife with his brothers. He was more inclined to a life of pleasure than to the difficult task of governing, and he entrusted the affairs of state to his able grand vizier (chief mini...
</Question>
<Choice>Selim II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ottoman sultan from 1789 to 1807, who undertook a program of Westernization and whose reign felt the intellectual and political ferment created by the French Revolution.A poet and an accomplished composer of Ottoman classical music, Selim had enjoyed greater freedom prior to his accession than the Ottoman princes before him. Influenced by his father, Mustafa III (reigned 1757–74), Selim had acquired a zeal for reform.When Selim succeeded his uncle Abdülhamid I (April 7, 1789), he attempted to end the social, economic, and administrative chaos facing the empire. He set up a committee of reforme...
</Question>
<Choice>Selim III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the Protector of England during part of the minority of King Edward VI (reigned 1547–53). While admiring Somerset's personal qualities and motives, scholars have generally blamed his lack of political acumen for the failure of his policies.After the marriage of his sister, Jane Seymour, to King Henry VIII in 1536, he rose rapidly in royal favour. He became earl of Hertford in 1537, and in 1542 he was appointed lord high admiral, a post he soon relinquished. He commanded the English forces that invaded Scotland in 1544 and sacked Edinburgh; a year later he won a brilliant victory over the Frenc...
</Question>
<Choice>Seymour, Edward, 1st duke of Somerset</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
nominal Mughal emperor of India from 1759 to 1806.Son of the emperor ?Alamgir II, he was forced to flee Delhi in 1758 by the minister ?Imad al-Mulk, who kept the emperor a virtual prisoner. He took refuge with Shuja? al-Dawlah, nawab of Oudh (Ayodhya), and after his father's assassination in 1759 he proclaimed himself emperor. With the intention of seeking to capture Delhi, he demanded tribute from Bihar and Bengal and thereby came into conflict with the East India Company. After Shuja? al-Dawlah's defeat at Buxar (in modern Bihar state) in 1764, however, Shah ?Alam became the company's pensio...
</Question>
<Choice>Shah 'Alam II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mughal emperor of India (1628–58) and builder of the Taj Mahal.He was the third son of the Mughal emperor Jahangir and the Rajput princess Manmati. Marrying in 1612 Arjumand Banu Begum, niece of Jahangir's wife Nur Jahan, he became, as Prince Khurram, one of the influential Nur Jahan clique of the middle period of Jahangir's reign. In 1622 Shah Jahan, ambitious to win the succession, rebelled, ineffectually roaming the empire until reconciled to Jahangir in 1625. After Jahangir's death in 1627, the support of A?af Khan, Nur Jahan's brother, enabled Shah Jahan to proclaim himself emperor at Agr...
</Question>
<Choice>Shah Jahan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
emperor of north India (1540–45) in the Islamic Sur (Afghan) dynasty of 1540–57 who organized a long-lived bureaucracy responsible to the ruler and created a carefully calculated revenue system. For the first time during the Islamic conquest the relationship between the people and the ruler was systematized, with little oppression or corruption.One of eight sons of ?asan Khan, a horse breeder, Farid rebelled against his father and left home to enlist as a soldier in the service of Jamal Khan, the governor of Jaunpur. He later worked for the Mughal king of Bihar, who rewarded him for bravery wi...
</Question>
<Choice>Sher Shah of Sur</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
reign name (nianhao) of the first emperor (reigned 1644–61) of the Qing (Manchu) dynasty (1644–1911/12).The ninth son of Abahai (1592–1643), the great ruler of the Manchu kingdom of Manchuria, Fulin succeeded to the throne in 1643 at the age of five (six by Chinese reckoning) and ruled under the regency of Dorgon (1612–50), a paternal uncle. In 1644, Manchu troops under Dorgon's command captured Beijing, the former capital of the Ming dynasty (1368–1644), and the young ruler was proclaimed emperor of the Qing dynasty with the reign title of Shunzhi. Dorgon continued to exercise absolute author...
</Question>
<Choice>Shun-chih</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king who established Polish suzerainty over Ducal Prussia (East Prussia) and incorporated the duchy of Mazovia into the Polish state.Sigismund I, the fifth son of Casimir IV and Elizabeth of Habsburg, had ruled Glogów, Silesia, since 1499 and became margrave of Lusatia and governor of all Silesia in 1504. In a short time his judicial and administrative reforms transformed those territories into model states. He succeeded his brother Alexander I as grand prince of Lithuania and king of Poland in 1506. Although he established fiscal and monetary reforms, he often clashed with the Polish Diet ove...
</Question>
<Choice>Sigismund I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polish Zygmunt August last Jagiellon king of Poland, who united Livonia and the duchy of Lithuania with Poland, creating a greatly expanded and legally unified kingdom.The only son of Sigismund I the Old and Bona Sforza, Sigismund II was elected and crowned coruler with his father in 1530. He ruled the duchy of Lithuania from 1544 and became king of Poland after his father's death in April 1548. After his first wife died childless (1545), he secretly married Barbara Radziwill, of a Lithuanian magnate family (1547). When he announced his marriage in 1548, the szlachta (Polish gentry) tried to f...
</Question>
<Choice>Sigismund II Augustus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Poland (1587–1632) and of Sweden (1592–99) who sought to effect a permanent union of Poland and Sweden but instead created hostile relations and wars between the two states lasting until 1660.The elder son of King John III Vasa of Sweden and Catherine, daughter of Sigismund I the Old of Poland, Sigismund belonged to the Vasa dynasty through his father and to the Jagiellon dynasty through his mother, who brought him up as a Catholic. He was elected king of Poland in August 1587, succeeding his uncle King Stephen Báthory. To obtain the throne he had to accept a reduction of royal power a...
</Question>
<Choice>Sigismund III Vasa</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian king (reigned 1674–80), founder of the Maratha kingdom of India. The kingdom's security was based on religious toleration and on the functional integration of the Brahmans, Marathas, and Prabhus.
</Question>
<Choice>Sivaji</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
regent of Russia from 1682 to 1689.The eldest daughter of Tsar Alexis (ruled 1645–76) and his first wife, Mariya Miloslavskaya, Sophia was tutored by the Belorussian monk Simeon Polotsky, from whom she received an exceptionally good education. When her brother Fyodor III died (April 27 [May 7], 1682), her half brother Peter, son of Alexis and his second wife, Natalya Naryshkina, was proclaimed tsar. Sophia, as leader of the Miloslavsky family, however, objected to a government dominated by the Naryshkins and incited the discontented streltsy (household troops) to riot. After several members of...
</Question>
<Choice>Sophia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Poland (1704–09, 1733) during a period of great problems and turmoil. He was a victim of foreign attempts to dominate the country.Stanislaw was born into a powerful magnate family of Great Poland, and he had the opportunity to travel in western Europe as a young man. In 1702 King Charles XII of Sweden invaded Poland as part of a continuing series of conflicts between the powers of northern Europe. Charles forced the Polish nobility to depose Poland's king, Augustus II (Frederick Augustus I of Saxony), and then placed Stanislaw on the throne (1704).Poland, weak and fragmented, had becom...
</Question>
<Choice>Stanislaw I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
last king of an independent Poland (1764–95). He was unable to act effectively while Russia, Austria, and Prussia dismembered his nation.He was born the sixth child of Stanislaw Poniatowski, a Polish noble, and his wife, Princess Konstancja Czartoryska. After a careful education he traveled in western Europe as a young man. In 1757 he was sent by his mother's enormously powerful family to St. Petersburg to obtain Russian support for their plan to dethrone the Polish king Augustus III. While at the Russian court, he apparently did little for the family's interests but succeeded in becoming the...
</Question>
<Choice>Stanislaw II August Poniatowski</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prince of Transylvania (1571–76) and king of Poland (1575–86) who successfully opposed the Habsburg candidate for the Polish throne, defended Poland's eastern Baltic provinces against Russian incursion, and attempted to form a great state from Poland, Muscovy, and Transylvania.The son of another István Báthory, the governor of Transylvania for the Habsburg king of Hungary, Stephen entered the service of John Sigismund Zápolya, prince of the newly independent Transylvania, in 1556. He eventually became army commander in chief, and despite Habsburg objections the Hungarians elected him prince of...
</Question>
<Choice>Stephen Báthory</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
half brother of Mary Stuart, Queen of Scots, who became regent of Scotland after her abdication.The illegitimate son of King James V and Lady Margaret Douglas, Stewart led the Protestant lords in their conflict with Mary Stuart's mother, Mary of Lorraine, the queen regent. When Mary Stuart assumed control of the government upon the death of her mother in 1560, however, he supported her, despite her Roman Catholicism. In 1562 she made him Earl of Moray and Earl of Mar, but he lost her favour by supporting the Calvinist reformer John Knox and by opposing the queen's marriage (July 1565) to Henry...
</Question>
<Choice>Stewart, James, 1st Earl of Moray</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish royal favourite who dominated King George III of Great Britain during the first five years of his reign. As prime minister (1762–63), he negotiated the peace ending the Seven Years' War (1756–63) with France, but he failed to create a stable administration.Succeeding to his father's earldom in 1723, he remained aloof from politics until he met (1747) and won the favour of Frederick Louis, prince of Wales, son of King George II. Upon Frederick's death in 1751, Bute became the constant companion and confidant of the prince's son George, heir to the throne, whose tutor he had been. After...
</Question>
<Choice>Stuart, John, 3rd Earl of Bute</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
regent of Sweden from 1513 to 1520. He repeatedly defeated both Danish forces and his domestic opponents, who favoured a union with Denmark, before falling in battle against the Danish king Christian II.During the regency (1503–12) of Sten's father, Svante (Nilsson) Sture, the nation was continuously at war with Denmark, and the noble-dominated state council (Riksråd) became increasingly powerful. With anti-Danish, peasant support, Sten wrested power from the state council in 1513, ending the regency of Erik Trolle, leader of the pro-union (with Denmark) faction. Using propaganda and effective...
</Question>
<Choice>Sture, Sten, The Younger</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
sultan of the Ottoman Empire from 1520 to 1566, who not only undertook bold military campaigns that enlarged his realm but also oversaw the development of what came to be regarded as the most characteristic achievements of Ottoman civilization in the fields of law, literature, art, and architecture.
</Question>
<Choice>Süleyman I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king who unified Myanmar (reigned 1531–50). He was the second monarch of the Toungoo dynasty, which his father, Minkyinyo, had founded in 1486.In 1535 Tabinshwehti began a military campaign against the kingdom of Pegu in southern Myanmar, capturing the city of Bassein in the Irrawaddy delta. Four years later Pegu fell, and Takayutpi, the Pegu king, fled to Prome (northwest of the present Yangon [Rangoon]). Employing Portuguese soldiers of fortune, Tabinshwehti captured the towns of Martaban and Moulmein in 1541, and in the following year he took Prome. With most of the southern princes his vas...
</Question>
<Choice>Tabinshwehti</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Thai general, conqueror, and later king (1767–82) who reunited Thailand, or Siam, after its defeat at the hands of the Myanmar (Burmese) in 1767.Of Chinese-Thai parentage, Taksin became the protégé of a Thai nobleman who enrolled him in the royal service. In 1764 he gained the rank of phraya as the governor of the province of Tak, and to distinguish him from previous governors he was called Phraya Taksin. He and his provincial troops were among the forces besieged in Ayutthaya by the Myanmar in 1766–67, but before the city fell he fled the capital and made his way to the southeast of the kingd...
</Question>
<Choice>Taksin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
reign name (niaohao) of the 16th and penultimate emperor (reigned 1620–27) of the Ming dynasty, under whose rule the infamous eunuch Wei Zhongxian (1568–1627) dominated the government while the dynasty disintegrated.Ascending the throne at the age of 15, the Tianqi emperor preferred carpentry to governmental affairs. He handed the powers of government to Wei, a former butler in the empress dowager's service and a friend of the young emperor's nurse. Wei became the most powerful eunuch in Chinese history, replacing hundreds of officials and creating a network of spies. He even had temples erect...
</Question>
<Choice>T'ien-chi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
sultan of Mysore, who won fame in the wars of the late 18th century in southern India.Tippu was instructed in military tactics by French officers in the employ of his father, Hyder Ali, who was the Muslim ruler of Mysore. In 1767 Tippu commanded a corps of cavalry against the Marathas in the Carnatic (Karnataka) region of western India, and he fought against the Marathas on several occasions between 1775 and 1779. During the second Mysore war he defeated Col. John Brathwaite on the banks of the Coleroon River (February 1782). He succeeded his father in December 1782 and in 1784 concluded peace...
</Question>
<Choice>Tippu Sultan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
second Tokugawa shogun, who completed the consolidation of his family's rule, eliminated Christianity from Japan, and took the first steps toward closing the country to all trade or other intercourse with foreign countries.In order to assure a smooth succession, the first Tokugawa shogun, Ieyasu, named his third and most even-tempered son, Hidetada, to the shogunate in 1605, two years after the establishment of the Tokugawa regime. Hidetada ruled in name only, however, for Ieyasu continued to control the actual workings of the government until his death in 1616, after which Hidetada finished t...
</Question>
<Choice>Tokugawa Hidetada</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
third Tokugawa shogun in Japan, the one under whom the Tokugawa regime assumed many of the characteristics that marked it for the next two and a half centuries.Iemitsu became shogun in 1623, when his father, Hidetada, retired in his favour, though Hidetada retained authority until his death in 1632. At the time of Iemitsu's accession, the daimyos, or great feudal lords, no longer threatened Tokugawa power as they had at the beginning of his grandfather's reign. Iemitsu was the first shogun to treat them with disdain. He further strengthened the shogunate by eliminating the few remaining prerog...
</Question>
<Choice>Tokugawa Iemitsu</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the founder of the last shogunate in Japan—the Tokugawa, or Edo, shogunate (1603–1867).
</Question>
<Choice>Tokugawa Ieyasu</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
eighth Tokugawa shogun, who is considered one of Japan's greatest rulers. His far-reaching reforms totally reshaped the central administrative structure and temporarily halted the decline of the shogunate.Yoshimune was originally the head of Kii, one of the three hereditary Japanese feudal fiefs ruled by descendants of the original Tokugawa ruler not in the main line of succession to the shogunate. A lack of sons in the main branch of the family, however, resulted in Yoshimune's succession to the position of shogun in 1716. Upon assuming his new office, he tried to institute the program he had...
</Question>
<Choice>Tokugawa Yoshimune</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish queen whose short reign (1718–20) led to Sweden's Age of Freedom—a 52-year decline of absolutism in favour of parliamentary government.Ulrika Eleonora was a sister of the unmarried king Charles XII; after the death of her elder sister Hedvig Sofia in 1708, she became heir to the Swedish throne. Ulrika Eleonora was married to Frederick of Hessen-Kassel in 1715. Ulrika's devotion to her husband led her to subordinate her own ambitions to those of Frederick. Thus, although Ulrika became queen in 1718 after Charles's death, she abdicated in 1720 in favour of her husband, who came to the Sw...
</Question>
<Choice>Ulrika Eleonora</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
grand prince of Moscow from 1505 to 1533. Succeeding his father, Ivan III (ruled Moscow 1462–1505), Vasily completed his father's policy of consolidating the numerous independent Russian principalities into a united Muscovite state by annexing Pskov (1510), Ryazan (1517), and Starodub and Novgorod-Seversk (now Novgorod-Seversky) by 1523. He also strengthened his growing state by capturing Smolensk from Lithuania in 1514. His forces were defeated by the Lithuanians at Orsha (1514), however, and Muscovy also suffered devastating raids by Tatars of both the Crimea and Kazan. Nevertheless, Vasily...
</Question>
<Choice>Vasily III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
original name Vasily Ivanovich, Knyaz (Prince) Shuysky, or Shuisky boyar who became tsar (1606–10) during Russia's Time of Troubles.A member of an aristocratic family descended from Rurik, the legendary founder of the dynasty that ruled Russia until 1598, Vasily Shuysky achieved prominence in 1591 when he conducted the investigation of the death of Dmitry Ivanovich, the brother and heir of Tsar Fyodor I (ruled Russia 1584–98) and determined that the nine-year-old child had killed himself with a knife while suffering an epileptic fit. In 1605, however, after Boris Godunov, Fyodor's chief advise...
</Question>
<Choice>Vasily Shuysky</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
duke of Savoy who through his diplomacy became the first king of Sardinia-Piedmont and thus established the foundation for the future Italian national state.Victor Amadeus grew up under the protection of a regency that was headed by his mother, Marie de Savoie-Nemours (d. March 15, 1724), who pursued a pro-French policy; and he married Anna d'Orléans, a niece of Louis XIV. When the War of the Grand Alliance broke out, Victor Amadeus in 1690 joined the Austrian and Spanish Habsburgs against Louis. But when the Spanish refused to agree to his acquisition of Milan, he made a separate peace with F...
</Question>
<Choice>Victor Amadeus II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Bohemia from 1471 and of Hungary from 1490 who achieved the personal union of his two realms.The eldest son of Casimir IV Jagiello, king of Poland, Vladislas was elected king of Bohemia in 1471. The early part of his reign was spent in conflict with the Hungarian king Matthias Corvinus, who in 1478 (Treaty of Olomouc) won title to the previously Bohemian crownlands of Moravia, Silesia, and Lusatia. After Matthias died, however, Vladislas was elected king of Hungary as Ulászló II in 1490. During his compliant and vacillating reign, in both Bohemia and Hungary, the nobility widely extend...
</Question>
<Choice>Vladislas II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British statesman (in power 1721–42), generally regarded as the first British prime minister. He deliberately cultivated a frank, hearty manner, but his political subtlety has scarcely been equaled.
</Question>
<Choice>Walpole, Robert, 1st earl of Orford</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
reign name (nianhao) of the emperor of China from 1572 to 1620, during the latter portion of the Ming dynasty (1368–1644).The Wanli emperor was a recluse whose apparent inattention to government affairs contributed to the abuses of power by provincial officials and other political figures that came to dominate that era of Chinese history. The violence and corruption among leaders of the northern provinces led to much popular dissatisfaction and unrest, preparing the way for the invasion from the north by the Manchu, who subsequently conquered all of China and established the Qing dynasty (1644...
</Question>
<Choice>Wan-li</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American general and commander in chief of the colonial armies in the American Revolution (1775–83) and subsequently first president of the United States (1789–97). (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America.)Washington's father, Augustine Washington, had gone to school in England, had tasted seafaring life, and then settled down to manage his growing Virginia estates. His mother was Mary Ball, whom Augustine, a widower, had married early the previous year. Washington's paternal lineage had some distinction; an early forebear wa...
</Question>
<Choice>Washington, George</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
stadholder of the United Provinces of the Netherlands as William III (1672–1702) and king of England, Scotland, and Ireland (1689–1702), reigning jointly with Queen Mary II (until her death in 1694). He directed the European opposition to Louis XIV of France and, in Great Britain, secured the triumph of Protestantism and of Parliament.
</Question>
<Choice>William III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Poland (1632–48), a popular monarch who did much to heal the wounds and solve the problems created by his father, Sigismund III Vasa, an obstinate man and religious bigot who created internal friction in Poland and pursued a series of profitless wars abroad. Wladyslaw sought to make Poland secure during a period of change in northern Europe and Russia.When Wladyslaw was 15, his father manipulated the youth's election as tsar of Russia while Polish forces held Moscow during the Time of Troubles following the death of Boris Godunov. His election, which never resulted in his assumption of...
</Question>
<Choice>Wladyslaw IV Vasa</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
reign name (nianhao) of the third emperor (reigned 1722–35) of the Qing dynasty (1644–1911/12), during whose rule the administration was consolidated and power became concentrated in the emperor's hands.As the fourth son of the Kangxi emperor, Yinzhen was not immediately in line for the throne; but when the designated heir apparent became mentally deranged, the future emperor saw an opportunity to seize the throne and began to intrigue against his brothers. Several of the chronicles of the period allege that Yinzhen murdered his father. In any case, he succeeded to the throne (as the Yongzheng...
</Question>
<Choice>Yung-cheng</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polish advisor to King Sigismund II Augustus and Stephen Báthory and later an opponent of Sigismund III Vasa. He was a major force in the royal politics of Poland throughout his life.Educated in France and Italy, he returned to Poland in 1565 and was appointed secretary to King Sigismund II. After Sigismund's death (1572), he became one of the best-liked leaders of the nobility. Opposing the magnates who wished to offer the throne to the Austrian Habsburgs, he supported the candidature of the French prince Henry and, after Henry's flight from Poland, supported the anti-Habsburg Stephen Báthory...
</Question>
<Choice>Zamoyski, Jan</Choice>
</item>
</topics>