<topics>
<item>
<Question>
lawyer, statesman, and prime minister of Canada from 1891 to 1892.Educated at McGill University, Montreal, Abbott became a lawyer in 1847 and was made queen's counsel in 1862. He served as dean of the McGill faculty of law from 1855 to 1880. He was elected to the Legislative Assembly of the then-united province of Canada in 1857 and continued to represent his native county, Argenteuil, until 1887, except during 1874–80. In 1862 he served briefly as solicitor general in the government of John Sandfield Macdonald and Louis Sicotte before going over to the Conservatives after confederation in 186...
</Question>
<Choice>Abbott, Sir John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
amir of Afghanistan (1880–1901) who played a prominent role in the fierce and long-drawn struggle for power waged by his father and his uncle, A??am Khan, against his cousin Shir ?Ali, the successor of Dost Mo?ammad Khan.?Abdor Ra?man was the son of Afzal Khan, whose father, Dost Mo?ammad Khan, had established the Barakzai dynasty in Afghanistan. Shir ?Ali's victory in 1869 drove ?Abdor Ra?man into exile in Russian Turkistan, where he lived at Samarkand until Shir ?Ali's death in 1879, a year after the outbreak of the war between the British and the Afghans. ?Abdor Ra?man returned to Afghanist...
</Question>
<Choice>'Abdor Rahman Khan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ottoman sultan (1861–76) who continued the westernizing reforms that had been initiated by his predecessors until 1871, after which his reign took an absolutist turn.Like his brother Abdülmecid I, whom he succeeded as sultan on June 25, 1861, Abdülaziz was an ardent admirer of the material progress in western Europe. Educated in the Ottoman tradition, however, he could not always accept the adoption of Western institutions and customs. Abdülaziz was a member of the Mawlawiyah (Mevlevi) order of dervishes (Muslim mystics).Between 1861 and 1871, reforms were continued under the leadership of Abd...
</Question>
<Choice>Abdülaziz</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ottoman sultan from 1876 to 1909, under whose autocratic rule the reform movement of Tanzimat (Reorganization) reached its climax and who adopted a policy of pan-Islamism in opposition to Western intervention in Ottoman affairs.A son of Sultan Abdülmecid I, he came to the throne at the deposition of his mentally deranged brother, Murad V, on Aug. 31, 1876. He promulgated the first Ottoman constitution on Dec. 23, 1876, primarily to ward off foreign intervention at a time when the Turks' savage suppression of the Bulgarian uprising (May 1876) and Ottoman successes in Serbia and Montenegro had a...
</Question>
<Choice>Abdülhamid II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ottoman sultan from 1839 to 1861 who issued two major social and political reform edicts known as the Hatt-i Serif of Gülhane (Noble Edict of the Rose Chamber) in 1839 and the Hatt-i Hümayun (Imperial Edict) in 1856, heralding the new era of Tanzimat (“Reorganization”).Well educated, liberal minded, and the first sultan to speak French, Abdülmecid continued the reform program of his father, Mahmud II, and was strongly assisted by his ministers Mustafa Resid Pasa, Mehmed Emin Âli Pasa, and Fuad Pasa. The reform edicts were in part directed toward winning the support of European powers. The edic...
</Question>
<Choice>Abdülmecid I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
early advocate of American independence from Great Britain, major figure in the Continental Congress (1774–77), author of the Massachusetts constitution (1780), signer of the Treaty of Paris (1783), first American ambassador to the Court of St. James (1785–88), first vice president (1789–97) and second president (1797–1801) of the United States. Although Adams was regarded by his contemporaries as one of the most significant statesmen of the revolutionary era, his reputation faded in the 19th century, only to ascend again during the last half of the 20th century. The modern edition of his corr...
</Question>
<Choice>Adams, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
eldest son of President John Adams and sixth president of the United States (1825–29). In his prepresidential years he was one of America's greatest diplomats (formulating, among other things, what came to be called the Monroe Doctrine); in his postpresidential years (as U.S. congressman, 1831–48) he conducted a consistent and often dramatic fight against the expansion of slavery. (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America.)
</Question>
<Choice>Adams, John Quincy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prince of Serbia from 1842 to 1858.The third son of Karadjordje (Karageorge, or Karaðorðe), who had led the movement to win Serb autonomy from the Ottoman Turks (1804–13), Alexander lived in exile until 1842, when the Skupština (Serb parliament) elected him prince of Serbia. Assuming the throne despite Russian challenges to his election and Turkish refusals to make his office hereditary, Alexander allowed his administration to be dominated by an oligarchy consisting of an elite group of senators. In an effort to modernize the Serb bureaucracy, it attempted to improve the principality's educati...
</Question>
<Choice>Alexander (prince of Serbia)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Serbia (1889–1903), whose unpopular authoritarian reign resulted not only in his assassination but also in the end of the Obrenovic dynasty.The only child of Prince (later King) Milan (reigned 1868–89) and his consort, Natalie, Alexander ascended the Serbian throne on March 6 (Feb. 22), 1889, after his father had abdicated and named a regency council for the youthful Alexander. On April 13 (April 1), 1893, Alexander dismissed the regency council and assumed active control of the government.Initially well received, Alexander soon alienated a large segment of his supporters by excluding...
</Question>
<Choice>Alexander (king of Serbia)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the first prince of modern autonomous Bulgaria.The son of Prince Alexander of Hesse (previously created prince of Battenberg upon his morganatic marriage) and a favourite nephew of Alexander II of Russia, Alexander served during 1877 with the Russian forces in the Russo-Turkish War (1877–78), which resulted in the autonomy of Bulgaria. In accordance with the provisions of the Congress of Berlin (1878), Alexander was elected constitutional prince of the newly autonomous Bulgarian state on April 29, 1879, but he had to deal with a strong Russian interference in domestic affairs. Saddled with wha...
</Question>
<Choice>Alexander I (prince of Bulgaria)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
emperor of Russia (1801–25), who alternately fought and befriended Napoleon I during the Napoleonic Wars but who ultimately (1813–15) helped form the coalition that defeated the emperor of the French. He took part in the Congress of Vienna (1814–15), drove for the establishment of the Holy Alliance (1815), and took part in the conferences that followed.
</Question>
<Choice>Alexander I (emperor of Russia)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
emperor of Russia (1855–81). His liberal education and distress at the outcome of the Crimean War, which had demonstrated Russia's backwardness, inspired him toward a great program of domestic reforms, the most important being the emancipation (1861) of the serfs. A period of repression after 1866 led to a resurgence of revolutionary terrorism and to Alexander's own assassination.
</Question>
<Choice>Alexander II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
emperor of Russia from 1881 to 1894, opponent of representative government, and supporter of Russian nationalism. He adopted programs, based on the concepts of Orthodoxy, autocracy, and narodnost (a belief in the Russian people), that included the Russification of national minorities in the Russian Empire as well as persecution of the non-Orthodox religious groups.The future Alexander III was the second son of Alexander II and of Maria Aleksandrovna (Marie of Hesse-Darmstadt). In disposition he bore little resemblance to his softhearted, impressionable father and still less to his refined, chi...
</Question>
<Choice>Alexander III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish king whose short reign (1874–85) gave rise to hopes for a stable constitutional monarchy in Spain.The eldest surviving son of Queen Isabella II and, presumably, her consort, the duque de Cádiz, Alfonso accompanied his mother into exile following her deposition by the revolution of September 1868. He received his education at the Theresianum in Vienna and at the Royal Military College, Sandhurst, England. Isabella abdicated her rights in his favour in June 1870, but it was not until four years later (December 29, 1874) that Alfonso was proclaimed king of Spain. He returned to his countr...
</Question>
<Choice>Alfonso XII</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Spain from Nov. 16, 1870, until his abdication on Feb. 11, 1873, after which the first Spanish republic was proclaimed.The second son of the future King Victor Emmanuel II of Sardinia-Piedmont (later, of Italy), he was originally called Amadeus I, duke of Aosta. His candidacy for the Spanish throne (vacant after the deposition of Isabella II in September 1868) was supported by Juan Prim, the Spanish prime minister, and Francisco Serrano, the regent. It was opposed by adherents of Isabella's son Alfonso de Borbón (later King Alfonso XII) and advocates of a republic. Elected king by the...
</Question>
<Choice>Amadeus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Brazilian statesman who played a key role in Brazil's attainment of independence from Portugal. He is known to Brazilians as the “Patriarch of Independence.”Andrada went to Portugal as a student and became a distinguished scholar there, earning an international reputation as a naturalist and geologist. He remained in Portugal until he was 56, serving as a professor at the University of Coimbra and as the permanent secretary of the Lisbon Academy. He was deeply influenced by the principles of the Enlightenment.Returning to Brazil in 1819, Andrada devoted himself to politics and quickly became t...
</Question>
<Choice>Andrada e Silva, José Bonifácio de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hungarian prime minister and Austro-Hungarian foreign minister (1871–79), who helped create the Austro-Hungarian dualist form of government. As a firm supporter of Germany, he created, with the imperial German chancellor Otto von Bismarck, the Austro-German alliance of 1879, which became the cornerstone of Austria's foreign policy until the monarchy's eventual collapse in 1918.A member of the radical Hungarian reform party under Lajos Kossuth, Andrássy entered the Hungarian Diet in 1847. He commanded a battalion in the revolt against Austria of 1848–49. Fleeing into exile on Hungary's surrende...
</Question>
<Choice>Andrássy, Gyula, Count</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
ruler of the Lao kingdom of Vientiane who tried unsuccessfully to secure independence for central and southern Laos from its Siamese overlords.In his youth Anu, along with his brother Inthavong, fought with the Siamese against the Burmese. His military ability and bravery won him the respect and trust of the Siamese, who chose him to succeed Inthavong as king of Vientiane in 1805. In the early years of his reign he strengthened his internal administration and undertook major public works and the enlargement of his capital city. He also cultivated good relations with the neighbouring kingdom of...
</Question>
<Choice>Anu, Chao</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
21st president of the United States. Elected vice president on the Republican ticket of 1880, Arthur acceded to the presidency upon the assassination of President James A. Garfield. As president, he confounded his critics and dismayed many of his friends among the Stalwart faction of the Republican Party by supporting the Pendleton Civil Service Act (1883), which provided for the open appointment and promotion of federal employees based on merit rather than patronage. (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America.)Arthur was the so...
</Question>
<Choice>Arthur, Chester A.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
aristocrat, painter, author, and statesman who was a leader of the movement that advocated an Italian national revival (Risorgimento) by the expulsion of all foreign influences from the then-divided Italian states. His political influence far outweighed his artistic achievements.After spending his youth dedicated to painting (1820–30 at Rome), d'Azeglio wrote two obscurely political novels, Ettore Fieramosca (1833) and Niccolò de'Lapi (1841). These marked him as a relatively moderate leader of the Risorgimento. His chief work, Gli ultimi casi de Romagna (1846; “The Last Chances for Romagna”),...
</Question>
<Choice>Azeglio, Massimo Taparelli, Marquess d'</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polish-born statesman in the Austrian service, who, as prime minister (1895–97) of the Austrian half of the Austro-Hungarian Dual Monarchy, sponsored policies to appease Slav nationalism within the empire but was defeated by German nationalist reaction.After studying law at the University of Kraków, Badeni, one of the richest Galician landowners, entered the ministry of the interior in 1866. He became governor of Kraków in 1879 and was appointed governor of Galicia (Austrian Poland) in 1888, where he acquired the reputation of a tough administrator. He was appointed prime minister and minister...
</Question>
<Choice>Badeni, Kasimir Felix, Graf von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician who served five terms as president of the Dominican Republic and is noted principally for his attempts to have the United States annex his country.Báez was a member of a wealthy and prominent family in the Dominican Republic. He was educated in Europe and began his political career in 1843 by helping lead the revolt that established the independence of the Dominican Republic from Haiti, with which it shares the island of Hispaniola. At this time, Báez believed that his nation could maintain its independence only by becoming a French protectorate, and to secure that end he was sent t...
</Question>
<Choice>Báez, Buenaventura</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Myanmar (Burma) from 1819 to 1837. The seventh monarch of the Konbaung, or Alaungpaya, dynasty, he was defeated in the First Anglo-Burmese War (1824–26). As a result of his defeat, the provinces of Arakan and Tenasserim were lost to the British.Bagyidaw was the grandson of King Bodawpaya, who had narrowly avoided war with the British over the frontier between Bengal and Arakan. Bagyidaw was an ineffectual king, but his general, Maha Bandula, influenced him to follow Bodawpaya's policy of aggressive expansion in northeastern India. He conquered Assam and Manipur, making them Myanmar tri...
</Question>
<Choice>Bagyidaw</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the last Mughal emperor of India (reigned 1837–58). He was a poet, musician, and calligrapher, more an aesthete than a political leader.He was the second son of Akbar Shah II and Lal Bai. For most of his reign he was a client of the British and was without real authority. He figured briefly, and unwillingly, in the Indian Mutiny of 1857–58; during the mutiny, rebel troops from the city of Meerut seized Delhi and compelled Bahadur Shah to accept nominal leadership of the revolt. At the age of 82, and in fear of his life, he acquiesced. After the rebellion was put down by the British, he was exi...
</Question>
<Choice>Bahadur Shah II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman who was joint leader with Louis-Hippolyte LaFontaine of the first and second Reform administrations in Canada, which established the principle of responsible, or cabinet, government in Canada.Called to the bar in 1825, Baldwin began his political career as a member (1829–30) of the Legislative Assembly of Upper Canada for York. In 1836 he served briefly on the Executive Council of Upper Canada and supported the union of Canada, condemning the Rebellion of 1837. He served (1840) on the Executive Council under Charles Poulett Thomson (later Baron Sydenham) but resigned, joining the opp...
</Question>
<Choice>Baldwin, Robert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prime minister of New Zealand (1891–93) who unified the Liberal Party, which held power for 20 years; he also played a major role in the enactment of social welfare legislation.After working as an ironmonger in Birmingham, Eng., the self-educated Ballance emigrated to Wanganui, N.Z., in 1865. There he was editor of the Wanganui Herald and fought against the native Maoris. Entering Parliament in 1875, he advocated abolition of provincial governments. As colonial treasurer in 1878, he introduced a land tax to raise revenue more equitably. As minister of lands, defense, and native affairs in 1884...
</Question>
<Choice>Ballance, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
liberal reformer and president of Chile (1886–91) whose conflict with his legislature precipitated a civil war in 1891.Balmaceda was elected to the Chilean congress from the Liberal Party in 1870. While serving in the cabinet of President Domingo Santa María (1881–86), he pushed anticlerical measures and promoted public works. As president he advanced public education and railroad construction but inherited the legislative revolt against the executive begun in the 1860s. His attempts to prevent congressional limitation of the presidential powers led to civil war in 1891. Congress, with navy su...
</Question>
<Choice>Balmaceda, José Manuel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
sultan of Zanzibar (1870–88), a shrewd and ambitious ruler, who, for most of his reign, looked to Britain for protection and assistance but eventually saw his domains divided between Germany and his former protector.Although not the first heir to the throne of his father, Sa?id ibn Sultan, Barghash had made plans to seize the throne at his father's death in 1856; he was, however, forestalled by the rightful heir, his brother Majid, and spent two years in exile in Bombay. Shortly after Barghash came to power (1870), his longtime friend John Kirk became British consul. Kirk, a strong advocate of...
</Question>
<Choice>Barghash</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
president of Guatemala (1873–85), who carried out liberal domestic policies by dictatorial means and persistently advocated Central American unity, to be imposed by force if diplomacy proved inadequate.Trained for the law, Barrios became Guatemalan army commander and the power behind the president, Miguel García Granados, in 1871, when the Conservative Party government was overthrown. After replacing García Granados in 1873, Barrios carried out sweeping reforms based on his liberal philosophies. His presidency became known as “the Reform.” He subjugated the local aristocracy; expelled the Jesu...
</Question>
<Choice>Barrios, Justo Rufino</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Lebanese prince who established hegemony over Lebanon in the first half of the 19th century and ruled it under Ottoman and, later, Egyptian suzerainty from 1788 to 1840.Although born into the princely Shihab family, Bashir grew up in poverty but married into great wealth. In 1788 the Lebanese emir was forced to abdicate, and the local nobility selected Bashir to fill the post. As emir, Bashir had to raise tribute for A?mad al-Jazzar, an official nominated by the Ottoman sultan to administer the district of Lebanon. After the death of al-Jazzar (1804), the financial demands were much less sever...
</Question>
<Choice>Bashir Shihab II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British prime minister from April 2 to Dec. 19, 1783, and from March 31, 1807, to Oct. 4, 1809; on both occasions he was merely the nominal head of a government controlled by stronger political leaders.The eldest son of William, 2nd Duke of Portland (whom he succeeded in 1762), he was educated at Westminster and Christ Church, Oxford. In 1761 he entered Parliament and from July 1765 to December 1766 was lord chamberlain of the household. Appointed by the then prime minister, Charles Watson-Wentworth, 2nd Marquess of Rockingham, Portland served briefly (April–August 1782) as lord lieutenant of...
</Question>
<Choice>
Bentinck, William Henry Cavendish, 3rd Duke of Portland
</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prime minister and foreign minister of Saxony (1858–66) and of the Austrian Empire (1867–71), who negotiated the Ausgleich, or “Compromise” (1867), establishing the Austro-Hungarian monarchy, and who also helped restore the Habsburgs' international position.A descendant of the Saxon line of an ancient aristocratic family, Beust studied law, philosophy, history, and politics at Göttingen and Leipzig. Relatively progressive, he was inclined toward liberal constitutionalism and in 1830 began his diplomatic career, which led him to Saxon missions in Berlin, Paris, Munich, London, and, in 1848, Ber...
</Question>
<Choice>Beust, Friedrich Ferdinand, Graf von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prime minister of Prussia (1862–73, 1873–90) and founder and first chancellor (1871–90) of the German Empire. Once the empire was established, he actively and skillfully pursued pacific policies in foreign affairs, succeeding in preserving the peace in Europe for about two decades. But in domestic policies his patrimony was less benign, for he failed to rise above the authoritarian proclivities of the landed squirearchy to which he was born.
</Question>
<Choice>Bismarck, Otto von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
leader of a faction of Sauk and Fox Indians. Supported by part of the two tribes, Black Hawk contested the disposition of 50 million acres (20 million hectares) of territory that had supposedly been granted to the United States by tribal spokesmen in 1804. His decision to defy government orders to vacate tribal villages and fertile fields along the Rock River in Illinois resulted in the brief but tragic Black Hawk War of 1832.Antagonistic to whites settling in his people's territory, Black Hawk joined the British in a number of engagements in the War of 1812. Thereafter U.S. officials cultivat...
</Question>
<Choice>Black Hawk</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
South American soldier and statesman who led the revolutions against Spanish rule in the Viceroyalty of New Granada. He was president of Gran Colombia (1819–30) and dictator of Peru (1823–26).The son of a Venezuelan aristocrat of Spanish descent, Bolívar was born to wealth and position. After his father died when the boy was three years old and his mother died six years later, his uncle administered his inheritance and provided him with tutors. At the age of 16, Bolívar was sent to Europe to complete his education. For three years he lived in Spain and in 1801 married the daughter of a Spanish...
</Question>
<Choice>Bolívar, Simón</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
lawyer, diplomat, soldier, and Napoleon I's eldest surviving brother, who was successively king of Naples (1806–08) and king of Spain (1808–13).Like his brothers, Joseph embraced the French republican cause and, with the victory of Corsican patriot Pasquale Paoli, was forced to leave Corsica to seek refuge in France. In 1796 he accompanied Napoleon in the early part of his Italian campaign and had some part in the negotiations with Sardinia that led to the armistice of Cherasco. He then took part in the French expedition for the recovery of Corsica and assisted in the reorganization of the isl...
</Question>
<Choice>Bonaparte, Joseph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
publisher, political leader, and prime minister of Canada (1894–96).At age 10 Bowell moved with his parents to Belleville, Ont., where he became a printer's apprentice at a local newspaper—the Intelligencer—which he came, eventually, to own. He joined the Orange Order and was a grand master for many years. In 1867 he was elected to the Canadian House of Commons from North Hastings as a Conservative and served until 1892. Bowell was a Cabinet minister in three governments (for customs, militia, and trade and commerce, successively) before he was chosen prime minister and formed his own governme...
</Question>
<Choice>Bowell, Sir Mackenzie</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician and soldier who served as president of Haiti in 1818–43 and tried unsuccessfully to stop a severe decline in the Haitian economy.Boyer, a mulatto (of mixed African and European descent), was educated in France. He served with the mulatto leader Alexandre Sabès Pétion and the black leader Henry Christophe after they had killed the Haitian independence leader and self-proclaimed emperor Jean-Jacques Dessalines in 1806. He then served with Pétion against Christophe, and, after these two leaders had died, he succeeded in unifying the country in 1821.During his presidency, Boyer tried to...
</Question>
<Choice>Boyer, Jean-Pierre</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman and president (1864–88) of the Orange Free State who expanded the boundaries of the state at the expense of the Sotho and sought harmony between the Boer republics and the British colonies in Southern Africa.Brand was the son of Sir Christoffel Brand, speaker of the House of Assembly of Cape Colony. He was educated at South African College, Cape Town, and the University of Leiden in The Netherlands. He returned to Cape Town in 1849 to begin a successful law practice.Brand became a member of the Cape Colony Parliament and in 1864 was called to the Orange Free State to replace Marthinu...
</Question>
<Choice>Brand, Sir Johannes Henricus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
soldier and statesman, one of the founders of republican Mexico, serving as its president or acting president at various times.Bravo and his family joined the peasant leader José María Morelos y Pavón and his band in 1811 and thus became one of the first of the wealthy Creole families (i.e., of Spanish origin but born in Mexico) to support the war against Spain. Bravo commanded the Mexican forces during the War of Independence against Spain (1810–21). He then joined the first independent government of Mexico, that of Agustín de Iturbide (1821–23), as a member of the executive group that founde...
</Question>
<Choice>Bravo, Nicolás</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
15th president of the United States (1857–61), a moderate Democrat whose efforts to find a compromise in the conflict between the North and the South failed to avert the Civil War (1861–65). (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America.)
</Question>
<Choice>Buchanan, James</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
president of Chile (1841–51) whose administration was notable for public works improvements, economic progress, and cultural advances. When he was a general, his military victory against the Bolivian–Peruvian Confederation in 1839 assured his election to the presidency. Although the spokesman of the Conservative oligarchy, Bulnes found posts for many liberals in his government, and social and political stability made Chile a haven for many intellectual refugees from other dictatorships. The new interest in learning produced a generation of young intellectuals who openly opposed the oligarchica...
</Question>
<Choice>Bulnes, Manuel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British statesman known for his liberal policies as foreign secretary (1807–09, 1822–27) and as prime minister for four months during 1827.
</Question>
<Choice>Canning, George</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish historian, statesman, and prime minister, whose political activity brought about the restoration of Spain's Bourbon dynasty. He was the author of Spain's 1876 constitution.Upon the death of his father, Cánovas came to Madrid to live under the protection of his relative, the writer Serafín Estébanez Calderón, and of the banker José Salamanca. In 1852 he was introduced to General Leopoldo O'Donnell, whose political mentor he later became. His first political act was his involvement in the conspiracy of O'Donnell (1854), the program for which (Manifesto of Manzanares) was the work of Cáno...
</Question>
<Choice>Cánovas del Castillo, Antonio</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
distinguished soldier who was Bismarck's successor as Germany's imperial chancellor during 1890–94.Caprivi was educated in Berlin and entered the army in 1849; he took part in the Austrian campaign of 1866, being attached to the staff of the I Army. In 1870–71, in the Franco-German War, he was chief of staff to the X Army Corps (part of the II Army) and took part in battles before Metz as well as in those around Orléans. In 1883 he was made chief of the admiralty, in which post he commanded the fleet and represented the department in the Reichstag. He resigned in 1888 and was appointed command...
</Question>
<Choice>Caprivi, Leo, Graf von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first king of Romania, whose long reign (as prince, 1866–81, and as king, 1881–1914) brought notable military and economic development along Western lines but failed to solve the basic problems of an overwhelmingly rural country.As a German prince, Carol was educated in Dresden and Bonn and in 1864 served as an officer of the Prussian army in the war against Denmark. With the tacit approval of his cousin, the French emperor Napoleon III, he was offered the throne of Romania after the deposition of the reigning prince, Alexandru Cuza (February 1866), and in April 1866 was elected prince by pleb...
</Question>
<Choice>Carol I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
wife of King George IV of the United Kingdom who—like her husband, who was also her cousin—was the centre of various scandals.The daughter of Charles William Ferdinand, duke of Brunswick-Lüneburg, Caroline married George (then prince of Wales) on April 8, 1795, but they separated soon after the birth of their only child, Princess Charlotte (Jan. 7, 1796). In December 1805 a committee of the Privy Council acquitted her of the charge of having given birth to a son by another man.Excluded from the court while her husband was regent (1811–20) for his insane father, George III, Caroline lived chief...
</Question>
<Choice>Caroline Of Brunswick-lüneburg</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
aristocratic leader in the early struggle for the independence of Chile and first president of that country.By a coup d'état in 1811, Carrera placed himself at the head of the national government and later the same year made himself dictator. Soon, however, internecine strife developed in the independence movement that permitted the restoration of Spanish rule. Bernardo O'Higgins was elevated to the leadership of the forces opposing Carrera, who in 1813 was removed from power by the junta in favour of O'Higgins; early in 1814, however, Carrera regained control. During the ensuing invasion of S...
</Question>
<Choice>Carrera, José Miguel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
dictator of Guatemala (1844–48 and 1851–65) and one of the most powerful figures of 19th-century Central America.Carrera, a mestizo (of mixed European and Indian ancestry), had no formal education. He fought in the civil war in Central America in the 1820s and rose rapidly in the ranks. He adopted strong conservative beliefs as a soldier. With the support of the Indian peasantry, who revered him, and the lower clergy, who despised the anticlerical liberal government, he captured Guatemala City in 1838 and took power, which he exercised completely and ruthlessly until his death.Carrera—deeply r...
</Question>
<Choice>Carrera, Rafael</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman, Canadian prime minister jointly with John A. Macdonald (1857–58; 1858–62), and promoter of confederation and the improvement of Anglo-French relations in Canada.Cartier practiced as a lawyer until 1837, when he took part in the rebellion that sent him into several months of exile in the United States. Elected as a Liberal reformer to the Canadian legislature in 1848, he was appointed provincial secretary for Canada East (formerly Lower Canada) in 1855 and two years later attorney general.His alliance with Macdonald, in which Cartier represented Canada East, developed the Liberal-Con...
</Question>
<Choice>Cartier, Sir George Étienne, Baronet</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman and author, one of the most powerful champions of Spanish republicanism in the latter half of the 19th century. He was president of the first Spanish Republic from September 1873 to January 1874.Castelar studied at the University of Madrid, where he became professor of history and was active in politics. He achieved fame as an orator and notoriety for his speeches against the monarchy; this latter activity lost him his chair in April 1865. After the abortive republican uprising of 1866, he was sentenced to death but escaped to France. After the successful revolution of 1868, he retur...
</Question>
<Choice>Castelar y Ripoll, Emilio</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Piedmontese statesman, a conservative whose exploitation of international rivalries and of revolutionary movements brought about the unification of Italy (1861) under the House of Savoy, with himself as the first prime minister of the new kingdom.
</Question>
<Choice>Cavour, Camillo Benso, conte di</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
last great king of the independent Zulus (reigned 1872–79), whose strong military leadership and political acumen restored the power and prestige of the Zulu nation, which had declined during the reign of his father, Mpande (Panda). As absolute ruler of a rigidly disciplined army of 40,000 men, Cetshwayo was considered a threat to British colonial interests; the Zulu War (1879) and subsequent destruction of Zulu power removed that threat.Cetshwayo distinguished himself early in life, taking part in the 1838 Zulu attempt to evict the invading Boers from Natal, and in the early 1850s he was invo...
</Question>
<Choice>Cetshwayo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Cambodia who sought to balance Siam (Thailand) against Vietnam. Both countries had traditionally contested for the Cambodian territory that lay between their domains.When Chan's father, King Eng, died in 1796, the Thais had superiority. In 1802 Chan was recognized as the king of Cambodia by the Thais, and he was crowned in the Thai capital of Bangkok in 1806. The advisers to the young king sought to preserve peace; it was their primary concern that neither Vietnam nor Siam use Cambodia as a site to wage wars or overrun and divide the country between them. Therefore, Chan followed a pol...
</Question>
<Choice>Chan II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of a troubled Portugal that was beset by colonial disputes, grave economic difficulties, and political unrest during his reign (1889–1908).The son of King Louis and of Maria Pia of Savoy, daughter of Victor Emmanuel II of Italy, he married Marie Amélie of Orléans, a granddaughter of the French king Louis-Philippe, in 1886 and succeeded his father on Oct. 19, 1889. Forces generated by mistakes made before his time proved to be the undoing of this talented and intelligent man, who was also known for his paintings and oceanographical studies. At home, republicans, disaffected monarchists, an...
</Question>
<Choice>Charles</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Sardinia–Piedmont (1831–49) during the turbulent period of the Risorgimento, the movement for the unification of Italy. His political vacillations make him an enigmatic personality.Exiled from Italy, Charles Albert, who belonged to a collateral branch of the House of Savoy, was brought up in Paris and Geneva, where he was exposed to the ideas of the French Revolution. Succeeding his father as prince of Carignano in 1800, he was named count by Napoleon in 1810. When his cousin Victor Emmanuel I was restored to the throne of Piedmont, Charles Albert returned to Milan, where the young lib...
</Question>
<Choice>Charles Albert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
duke of Savoy and king of Sardinia–Piedmont (1821–31).The 11th child of Victor Amadeus III, he succeeded to his position when his brother Victor Emmanuel I abdicated in the face of an uprising of revolutionaries who demanded a new constitution. The revolution collapsed upon the intervention of Austrian troops, however, and Charles Felix ruled as an absolute sovereign for 10 years. He was the last ruler of the main Savoy line, being succeeded by Charles Albert.
</Question>
<Choice>Charles Felix</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of France from 1824 to 1830. His reign dramatized the failure of the Bourbons, after their restoration, to reconcile the tradition of the monarchy by divine right with the democratic spirit produced in the wake of the Revolution.The fifth son of the dauphin Louis and Maria Josepha of Saxony, Charles was given the title of comte d'Artois. He spent his early life in scandalous dissipation; his service with the French Army at the siege of Gibraltar in 1782 was undertaken rather for distraction than from serious concern with a military career. Eventually he abandoned his libertine lifestyle a...
</Question>
<Choice>Charles X</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Sweden from 1809 and, from 1814 to 1818, first king of the union of Sweden and Norway (called Karl II in Norway). The second son of King Adolf Frederick of Sweden, he was created duke of Södermanland by his elder brother, King Gustav III, and later served as admiral of the fleet during the Russo-Swedish War (1788–90). In 1792, after the murder of his brother, he became regent for his nephew, the 13-year-old Gustav IV. Charles was little gifted and lacked strength of character, so that real power passed to advisers until Gustav himself began to exert influence. The latter's unsuccessful...
</Question>
<Choice>Charles XIII</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French Revolutionary general and marshal of France (1804), who was elected crown prince of Sweden (1810), becoming regent and then king of Sweden and Norway (1818–44). Active in several Napoleonic campaigns between 1805 and 1809, he subsequently shifted allegiances and formed Swedish alliances with Russia, Great Britain, and Prussia, which defeated Napoleon at the Battle of Leipzig (1813).Bernadotte was the son of a lawyer. At the age of 17 he enlisted in the French army. By 1790 he had become an ardent supporter of the Revolution and rose rapidly from sublieutenant in 1792 to brigadier genera...
</Question>
<Choice>Charles XIV John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Sweden and Norway from 1859 to 1872 (called Karl IV in Norway). Succeeding his father, Oscar I, on July 8, 1859, Charles was an intelligent and artistically inclined ruler much liked in both kingdoms. The royal power, however, was considerably reduced during his reign as the Riksdag (parliament) and executive assumed increasing power. Among important new liberal measures that enjoyed his support was the introduction of a bicameral legislature. A champion of Pan-Scandinavianism and political solidarity among the three northern kingdoms, Charles unwisely gave a half promise of help—which...
</Question>
<Choice>Charles XV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
reign name (nianhao) of the fifth emperor of the Qing dynasty (1644–1911/12), during whose reign (1796–1820) a partial attempt was made to restore the flagging state of the empire.He was proclaimed emperor and assumed the reign title of Jiaqing in 1796, after the abdication of his father, the Qianlong emperor (reigned 1735–96). Power, however, remained in the hands of his father and his corrupt minister Heshen until 1799; the Jiaqing emperor's duties were confined to directing ceremonial functions.Meanwhile, the great White Lotus Rebellion (1796–1804) had broken out in central and western Chin...
</Question>
<Choice>Chia-ch'ing</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Danish king who came to the throne at the height of a crisis over Schleswig-Holstein in 1863 and who later resisted the advance of full parliamentary government in Denmark.Christian was the son of Duke William of Schleswig-Holstein-Sonderburg-Beck (and after 1825 Duke of Glücksburg). He entered the Danish army in 1835, serving in the Schleswig War (1848–50). In 1842 he married Louise of Hesse-Kassel, cousin of the childless Danish king, Frederick VII, and he was named successor to the throne of Denmark, Schleswig-Holstein, and Lauenburg in the London protocol of 1852. When Christian came to th...
</Question>
<Choice>Christian IX</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Denmark during the rise of the liberal opposition to absolutism in the first half of the 19th century.While still crown prince of Denmark and recent stadtholder (governor) of Norway, Christian accepted election as king of Norway in 1814 by the Norwegian independence faction, which refused to recognize the cession of Norway to Sweden. After leading a futile resistance against the Swedes, however, Christian was forced to abdicate. Christian's liberal sympathies emerged clearly in this episode, and, when he returned to Denmark, he was looked upon with suspicion by conservative state offic...
</Question>
<Choice>Christian VIII</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
a leader in the war of Haitian independence (1791–1804) and later president (1807–11) and self-proclaimed King Henry I (1811–20) of northern Haiti.The facts of Christophe's early life are questionable and confused. An official document issued on his own order gives the birth date and birthplace conventionally cited, but these and other facts are debated by historians. He may have been born free but been enslaved as a youth. In any event, he reached Haiti sometime in his teens. In 1780, during the American Revolution, he may have fought in a French unit at Savannah, Georgia, either as an enlist...
</Question>
<Choice>Christophe, Henry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Siam who avoided colonial domination and embarked upon far-reaching reforms.Chulalongkorn was the ninth son of King Mongkut, but since he was the first to be born to a royal queen, he was recognized as heir to the throne. He was only 15 years old when his father died in October 1868, and he succeeded to the throne under the regency of Somdet Chao Phraya Si Suriyawong (q.v.). Over the next five years he was prepared to assume his duties by observing court business and by travels to British Malaya and the Dutch East Indies in 1871 and to Malaya, Burma (Myanmar), and India in 1871–72.Foll...
</Question>
<Choice>Chulalongkorn</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
consort of the Xianfeng emperor (reigned 1850–61), mother of the Tongzhi emperor (reigned 1861–75), adoptive mother of the Guangxu emperor (reigned 1875–1908), and a towering presence over the Chinese empire for almost half a century. Ruling through a clique of conservative, corrupt officials and maintaining authority over the Manchu imperial house (Qing dynasty, 1644–1911/12), she became one of the most powerful women in the history of China.Cixi was one of the Xianfeng emperor's low-ranking concubines, but in 1856 she bore his only son. On Xianfeng's death, the six-year-old boy became the To...
</Question>
<Choice>Cixi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
22nd and 24th president of the United States (1885–89 and 1893–97) and the only president ever to serve two discontinuous terms. Cleveland distinguished himself as one of the few truly honest and principled politicians of the Gilded Age. His view of the president's function as primarily that of blocking legislative excesses made him quite popular during his first term, but that view cost him public support during his second term when he steadfastly denied a positive role for government in dealing with the worst economic collapse the nation had yet faced. (For a discussion of the history and na...
</Question>
<Choice>Cleveland, Grover</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sioux Indian chief of the Oglala tribe who was an able tactician and determined warrior in the Sioux resistance to the white man's invasion of the northern Great Plains.As early as 1865 Crazy Horse was a leader in his people's defiance of U.S. plans to construct a road to the goldfields in Montana. He participated in the massacre of Captain William J. Fetterman and his troop of 80 men (Dec. 21, 1866) as well as in the Wagon Box fight (Aug. 2, 1867), both near Fort Phil Kearny, in Wyoming Territory. Refusing to honour the reservation provisions of the Second Treaty of Fort Laramie (1868), Crazy...
</Question>
<Choice>Crazy Horse</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian statesman who, after being exiled from Naples and Sardinia-Piedmont for revolutionary activities, eventually became premier of a united Italy.Crispi grew up in Sicily, where he studied law; but, disillusioned by conditions there, he went to Naples, where he became active in republican agitation. He helped plan the successful 1848 uprising in Sicily and became one of the deputies in the new government before the island was regained by the Bourbon King Ferdinand II in 1849.Crispi fled to Turin, where he became a journalist. Suspected of complicity in an uprising in Milan in 1853, he was...
</Question>
<Choice>Crispi, Francesco</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first prince of united Romania, architect of national rural reform and peasant emancipation.The scion of an old boyar family, Cuza studied in Paris, Pavia, and Bologna, participated in revolutionary agitation against Russo-Turkish rule in his native Moldavia (1848), obtained the rank of colonel, and subsequently achieved prominence as a delegate to the Moldavian assembly (divan ad hoc) in 1857. Two years later, despite the Great Powers' determination that the Romanian principalities should enjoy separate autonomy, he was successively elected prince of Moldavia (January 1859) and of Walachia (F...
</Question>
<Choice>Cuza, Alexandru Ion</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
president of the Confederate States of America throughout its existence during the American Civil War (1861–65). After the war, he was imprisoned for two years and indicted for treason but never tried.
</Question>
<Choice>Davis, Jefferson</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French political figure and leader of the moderate constitutional monarchists during the Bourbon Restoration.A lawyer by profession, Decazes had previously served as a local magistrate (1806), a councillor to Louis Bonaparte in Holland (1807), and judge of the Parisian appeals court (1811).When the Bourbons were restored after the fall of Napoleon I, Decazes was appointed prefect of police in Paris (July 1815) and shortly thereafter was made director of national police affairs. He was an intimate adviser to King Louis XVIII and, because of his opposition to the White Terror (an outburst of rev...
</Question>
<Choice>Decazes, Élie, Duke, Duke Af Glücksberg</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian statesman, a leftist figure in the Risorgimento who later served three times as premier of Italy. He provided a fairly stable government by the tactics of trasformismo, which brought together members of different parties in the same Cabinet.After graduating from law school at Pavia (1834), he spent several years running his family's estate. In 1848, the year of revolutionary upheavals in Europe, he was elected deputy to the first Piedmontese Parliament, a position he held continuously until his death. As a deputy he consistently opposed Count Cavour, the premier of the kingdom of Piedm...
</Question>
<Choice>Depretis, Agostino</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English statesman, important as leader of the Conservative Party during the long period 1846–68, thrice prime minister, and one of England's greatest parliamentary orators; nevertheless, he has no great political reputation.Entering Parliament as a Whig in 1820, Derby held office under Viscount Goderich (1827–28) and became chief secretary for Ireland under Lord Grey in 1830, joining the Cabinet in 1831. In 1834 he resigned over the Irish Church question, but he served under Sir Robert Peel (1841) only to resign again (1845) over the repeal of the Corn Laws. He succeeded to the earldom in 1851...
</Question>
<Choice>Derby, Edward Stanley, 14th earl of</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
emperor of Haiti who proclaimed his country's independence in 1804.Dessalines was brought to the French West Indian colony of Saint-Domingue (Haiti) as a slave. He worked as a field hand for a black master until 1791, when he joined the slave rebellion that broke out in the colony amid the turmoil caused by the French Revolution. In the decade that followed he distinguished himself as a lieutenant of the black leader Toussaint Louverture, who established himself as governor-general of Saint-Domingue with nominal allegiance to Revolutionary France. When Toussaint was deposed in 1802 by a French...
</Question>
<Choice>Dessalines, Jean-Jacques</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
soldier and president of Mexico (1877–80, 1884–1911), who established a strong centralized state that he held under firm control for more than three decades.A mestizo (part Indian), Díaz was of humble origin. He began training for the priesthood at age 15, but upon the outbreak of war with the United States (1846–48) he joined the army. An illustrious military career followed, including service in the War of the Reform (1857–60) and the struggle against the French in 1861–67, when Maximilian became emperor. Earlier (1849), Díaz studied law with the encouragement of the Liberal Benito Juárez, w...
</Question>
<Choice>Díaz, Porfirio</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Zulu king (1828–40) who assumed power after taking part in the murder of his half brother Shaka in 1828.Very little is known of Zulu politics prior to 1828, but by 1827 the kingdom was rife with factional rivalries that centred on some of Shaka's brothers and white mercenary traders. The killing of Shaka was unpopular with many Zulu, and, as the new king, Dingane initially focused on eliminating Shaka's supporters. He established his capital at Mgungundlovu, near the White Mfolozi (Umfolozi) River. During the 1830s Dingane continued an earlier Zulu liaison with the Portuguese at Delagoa Bay; a...
</Question>
<Choice>Dingane</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
African chief or king of the Mthethwa of Southern Africa. Few hard facts are known about Dingiswayo—not even the approximate dates of his birth, his assumption of chieftaincy, or his death—but it is clear that he was dominant during the first two decades of the 19th century (though he may have been influential in the 1790s, or even earlier).It is likely that Dingiswayo became chieftain of the Mthethwa clan of the North (Natal) Nguni division of the Bantu people about 1807. During his rule, the Mthethwa incorporated or formed close alliances with other groups, including the Zulu. Trading relati...
</Question>
<Choice>Dingiswayo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British statesman and novelist who was twice prime minister (1868, 1874–80) and who provided the Conservative Party with a twofold policy of Tory democracy and imperialism.
</Question>
<Choice>Disraeli, Benjamin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
writer, poet, politician, and prime minister of New Zealand (1862–63), whose idealization of the Maori in his writings contrasts with his support of the punitive control of Maori land.Following study at Cambridge and being admitted to the bar, Domett travelled to New Zealand (1842) and, after a half-hearted attempt at farming, devoted his time to journalism and public affairs. He became editor of the Nelson Examiner (1843) and began his involvement with the administration of settler land by accepting appointment by Governor, later Prime Minister, Sir George Grey (q.v.) as member of the legisla...
</Question>
<Choice>Domett, Alfred</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
ruler of Afghanistan (1826–63) and founder of the Barakzay dynasty, who maintained Afghan independence during a time when the nation was a focus of political struggles between Great Britain and Russia.Dost Mo?ammad was one of a number of sons of Payenda Khan, head of the Barakzay clan. In 1816 the clan rose in rebellion against the Afghan ruler Ma?mud Shah, who had put to death his prime minister, a member of the clan. Following eight years of civil war, the clan claimed victory. Dost Mo?ammad emerged as its most powerful member, and he ascended the throne in 1826.With Great Britain and Russia...
</Question>
<Choice>Dost Mohammad Khan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Cambodia by 1841, formally invested in 1848, the last Cambodian king to reign before the French-imposed protectorate.Duong was the younger brother of King Chan II, who had ruled uncertainly in joint vassalage to Siam (Thailand) and Vietnam. Between 1841 and 1847 these two neighbours confronted each other in Cambodia in alternating periods of war and uneasy truce. With neither able to gain a decisive victory, they agreed to a dual hegemony over the Khmer state. By mutual agreement, Duong was crowned king at the new capital, Oudong (Odongk), in 1848.Duong's reign is idealized by modern C...
</Question>
<Choice>Duong</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
empress consort of Austria from April 24, 1854, when she married the emperor Francis Joseph I. She was also queen of Hungary (crowned June 8, 1867) after the Austro-Hungarian Ausgleich, or Compromise. Her assassination brought her rather unsettled life to a tragic end.Elizabeth was the daughter of the Bavarian duke Maximilian Joseph. In August 1853 she met her cousin Francis Joseph, then aged 23, who quickly fell in love with the 15-year-old Elizabeth, who was regarded as the most beautiful princess in Europe. Soon after their marriage she became involved in many conflicts with her mother-in-l...
</Question>
<Choice>Elizabeth</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Hanover, from 1837 to 1851, the fifth son of George III of England.Ernest Augustus studied at Göttingen, entered the Hanoverian army, and served as a leader of cavalry when war broke out between Great Britain and France in 1793. When Hanover withdrew from the war in 1795 he returned to England, being made lieutenant general in the British army in 1799. In the same year he was created duke of Cumberland.In 1810 Ernest Augustus was severely injured by an assailant, probably his valet Sellis, who was found dead; subsequently two men were imprisoned for asserting that the duke had murdered...
</Question>
<Choice>Ernest Augustus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish general and statesman, victor in the First Carlist War, and regent.The son of working-class parents, Espartero entered the army at age 15 and fought with Spanish forces in the French Revolutionary and Napoleonic wars and in the rebellious Americas. On the death of Ferdinand VII he showed himself a strong supporter of the queen regent María Cristina and enthusiastically joined the forces opposed to Don Carlos (Carlos María Isidro de Borbón). He was made commander in chief and, for his victory over the Carlists at the Battle of Luchana (December 1836), was named conde de Luchana. Later h...
</Question>
<Choice>Espartero, Baldomero, príncipe de Vergara</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman and conservative prime minister of Denmark from 1875 to 1894.In 1864 Estrup entered the Landsting (upper chamber) as a member of the National Landowners' Party. As minister of the interior from 1865, he made major improvements in the railways and in Esbjerg harbour. He influenced the writing of the new constitution of July 1866, which gave landowners extensive power in the Landsting. Estrup then became the leader of a powerful conservative group known as Højre (“Right”) in the Landsting. In 1875, backed by the majority and by the king, Christian IX, he became prime minister and forme...
</Question>
<Choice>Estrup, Jacob Brønnum Scavenius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
emperor of Austria from 1835 to 1848, when he abdicated his throne.Ferdinand was the eldest son of the Holy Roman emperor Francis II (later Francis I of Austria) and Maria Theresa of Naples-Sicily. Despite Ferdinand's feeblemindedness and epilepsy, Francis, seeking to protect the principles of succession to the monarchy, insisted that Ferdinand be his heir. Ferdinand was crowned king of Hungary in 1830. On March 2, 1835, he succeeded to the throne of Austria. Because of the emperor's limited abilities, government affairs were controlled by a body of counselors, known as the “state conference,”...
</Question>
<Choice>Ferdinand</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the Two Sicilies (1816–25) who earlier (1759–1806), as Ferdinand IV of Naples, led his kingdom in its fight against the French Revolution and its liberal ideas. A relatively weak and somewhat inept ruler, he was greatly influenced by his wife, Maria Carolina of Austria, who furthered the policy of her favourite adviser, the Englishman Sir John Acton.Ferdinand became king of Naples as a boy when his father ascended the Spanish throne (1759) as Charles III. A regency ruled during Ferdinand's minority and continued the liberal reforms of the previous king. In 1767 Ferdinand reached his ma...
</Question>
<Choice>Ferdinand I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Spain in 1808 and from 1814 to 1833. Between 1808 and 1813, during the Napoleonic Wars, Ferdinand was imprisoned in France by Napoleon.Ferdinand was the son of Charles IV and Maria Luisa of Parma, who placed their whole confidence in Manuel de Godoy. From 1795 Godoy had flaunted the title of prince of the Peace for his capitulation to France in the Peace of Basel. Ferdinand's tutor stirred up his jealousy and encouraged him to seek the protection of Napoleon. Charles IV was sufficiently alarmed to arrest Ferdinand but forgave him. When Godoy allowed French troops to enter Spain, Charle...
</Question>
<Choice>Ferdinand VII</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French statesman of the early Third Republic, notable both for his anticlerical education policy and for his success in extending the French colonial empire.Ferry pursued his father's profession of law and was called to the Paris bar in 1855. Soon, however, he made a name for himself as a biting critic of the Second Empire, especially by his articles (1867–68) in the newspaper Le Temps attacking Baron George-Eugène Haussmann's administration of Paris.During the Franco-German War (1870–71), Ferry administered the département of Seine, holding the powers of prefect, and was appointed mayor of Pa...
</Question>
<Choice>Ferry, Jules</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
13th president of the United States (1850–53), whose insistence on federal enforcement of the Fugitive Slave Act of 1850 alienated the North and led to the destruction of the Whig Party. Elected vice president in 1848, he became chief executive on the death of President Zachary Taylor (July 1850). (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America.)Fillmore was born in a log cabin to a poor family and was apprenticed to a wool carder at age 15. He received little formal education until he was 18, when he managed to obtain six consecutiv...
</Question>
<Choice>Fillmore, Millard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
nominal leader of the coup that toppled Emperor Pedro II. He became the first president of the Brazilian republic.The son of an army officer, Fonseca was trained for a military career. He distinguished himself in the Paraguayan War (1864–70) and subsequently rose to the rank of general. Named field marshal in 1884 and both military commander in and administrative head of Rio Grande do Sul estado (state) after 1886, he viewed himself as the heir to the duke of Caxias as Brazil's leading military figure. Although he was politically conservative and personally loyal to the emperor, he felt that i...
</Question>
<Choice>Fonseca, Manuel Deodoro da</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
explorer and statesman who led pioneer expeditions into Australia's western interior. As Western Australia's first premier (1890–1901), he sponsored public works construction and negotiated the state's entry into the Australian Commonwealth in 1901.After entering Western Australia's survey department in 1865, Forrest in 1869 led a search expedition for the missing explorer Ludwig Leichhardt and, in 1870, an expedition from Perth along the Great Australian Bight to Adelaide. In 1874 he completed a 2,700-mile (4,300-kilometre) crossing of the continent from Champion Bay to the telegraph line bet...
</Question>
<Choice>Forrest, Sir John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
author and statesman who helped shape the Constitution Act of 1852, which established home rule for New Zealand. He also served four short terms as the nation's prime minister (1856, 1861–62, 1869–72, 1873).After emigrating to New Zealand in 1842, Fox became an agent for the New Zealand Company the following year and its principal agent in 1848. His lobbying in England (1851–52) was probably responsible for the addition of Taranaki to the five original provinces in the Constitution of 1852, which granted self-government. His account of the events leading up to the constitution, The Six Colonie...
</Question>
<Choice>Fox, Sir William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
dictator of Paraguay whose intensely personal rule and policy of self-sufficiency left the nation both isolated and without alternative political institutions.Francia was trained in theology but turned to the practice of law. In 1811 he became secretary to the junta that had overthrown Spanish rule and in 1813 served as co-ruler. The next year he was elected dictator, and in 1816 he obtained the dictatorship for life.Not content with freedom from Spain, Francia in 1813 declared independence from Argentina, though Paraguay's only tie to the outer world lay on the river route through Buenos Aire...
</Question>
<Choice>Francia, José Gaspar Rodríguez de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the last Holy Roman emperor (1792–1806) and, as Francis I, emperor of Austria (1804–35); he was also, as Francis, king of Hungary (1792–1830) and king of Bohemia (1792–1836). He supported the conservative political system of Metternich in Germany and Europe after the Congress of Vienna (1815).Son of the future emperor Leopold II and Maria Luisa of Spain, Francis received his political education from his uncle, Emperor Joseph II, who disliked his nephew's unimaginative outlook and stubbornness but praised his application and sense of duty and justice. Ascending to the throne on the death of his...
</Question>
<Choice>Francis II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
emperor of Austria (1848–1916) and king of Hungary (1867–1916), who divided his empire into the Dual Monarchy, in which Austria and Hungary coexisted as equal partners. In 1879 he formed an alliance with Prussian-led Germany, and in 1914 his ultimatum to Serbia led Austria and Germany into World War I.
</Question>
<Choice>Francis Joseph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first king of Saxony and duke of Warsaw, who became one of Napoleon's most loyal allies and lost much of his kingdom to Prussia at the Congress of Vienna.Succeeding his father in 1763 as the elector Frederick Augustus III, he brought order and efficiency to his country's finances and administration. In foreign policy, he was neutralist but drifted toward Prussia, whose side he took in the Bavarian succession dispute (1778–79), when it prevented Bavaria's cession to Austria. For his cooperation he received substantial financial compensation from Prussia. In 1785, Frederick Augustus joined the P...
</Question>
<Choice>Frederick Augustus I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
reform-minded king of Saxony and nephew of Frederick Augustus I, who favoured German unification but was frightened into a reactionary policy by the revolutions of 1848–49.Frederick Augustus shared the regency with his uncle, King Anton, from 1830 to 1836, when he succeeded to the throne. The constitution of 1831, granting a measure of representative government, was partly his work. He continued to advocate reform after his accession but, lacking resolution, accomplished very little. Frederick Augustus sympathized with the plan for German unity espoused by the Frankfurt National Assembly in 18...
</Question>
<Choice>Frederick Augustus II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Denmark from 1808 to 1839 and of Norway from 1808 to 1814.The son of the mentally incompetent king Christian VII and Queen Caroline Matilda, Frederick was reared largely by his father's stepmother, the queen dowager Juliana Maria, who, with her son Prince Frederick and Ove Höegh-Guldberg, virtually ruled Denmark until 1784. In April of that year the Crown Prince brought about changes in the government that transferred the real power to him. Frederick supported reform measures to grant personal liberty and legal protection to the peasants and instituted several other social and economic...
</Question>
<Choice>Frederick VI</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Denmark from 1848 who renounced absolute rule and adopted a representative government.The son of the future king Christian VIII and Charlotte of Mecklenburg-Schwerin, Frederick in 1839 was appointed governor of the island of Fyn. As a crown prince, he had two unhappy marriages: first, in 1828, to his second cousin Wilhelmina Maria, a daughter of Frederick VI (dissolved in 1837); then, in 1841, to Caroline of Mecklenburg-Strelitz (dissolved in 1846).On Jan. 20, 1848, Frederick succeeded his father. After the popular demonstrations of March 1848, he appointed a Liberal ministry and on Ju...
</Question>
<Choice>Frederick VII</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Prussia from 1797, the son of Frederick William II. Neglected by his father, he never mastered his resultant inferiority complex, but the influence of his wife, Louisa of Mecklenburg-Strelitz, whom he married in 1793, occasionally moved him outside his essentially pedestrian character.His policy of neutrality in the Wars of the Second and Third Coalitions accelerated the decline of Prussia's prestige. Domestic reforms before the Battle of Jena foreshadowed later reforms without, however, altering the absolutist structure of the state. Until 1807 he clung to the traditional cabinet gove...
</Question>
<Choice>Frederick William III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Prussia from 1840 until 1861, whose conservative policies helped spark the Revolution of 1848. In the aftermath of the failed revolution, Frederick William followed a reactionary course. In 1857 he was incapacitated by a stroke, and his brother, the future William I, became regent (1858–61).
</Question>
<Choice>Frederick William IV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Belgian statesman and Liberal Party reformer who was twice prime minister (1868–70 and 1878–84).An exponent of doctrinaire economic liberalism and a strong advocate of free trade, Frère-Orban played a prominent part in the Liberal movement while practicing law in Liège. He was sent in 1847 to the Chamber of Representatives as a member from that city. From 1847 to 1894 he served as the leading Liberal member of the lower house in addition to holding many ministerial posts. As minister of finance (1848–52), he founded the Banque Nationale, abolished the newspaper tax, reduced the postage, and mo...
</Question>
<Choice>Frère-Orban, Hubert Joseph Walther</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French republican statesman who helped direct the defense of France during the Franco-German War of 1870–71. In helping to found the Third Republic, he made three essential contributions: first, by his speeches and articles, he converted many Frenchmen to the ideals of moderate democratic republicanism. Second, by his political influence and personal social contacts, he gathered support for an elective democratic political party, the Republican Union. Finally, by backing Adolphe Thiers, who was elected provisional head of government by the National Assembly of 1871, against royalists and Bonap...
</Question>
<Choice>Gambetta, Léon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
initiator of a church-oriented dictatorship in Ecuador (1861–75). His rule, oppressive but often effective in its reformist aims, eventually cost him his life.García Moreno was educated at the university in Quito and in Europe. Versed in political theory, he early took an active role in Ecuador's turbulent politics. He became convinced that the remedy for his nation's political and economic plight was the application of moral principles by a powerful leader.Aided by a general and former president of Ecuador, Juan José Flores, he seized power in 1860. During his two terms as president (1861–65,...
</Question>
<Choice>García Moreno, Gabriel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
20th president of the United States (March 4–September 19, 1881), who had the second shortest tenure in presidential history. When he was shot and incapacitated, serious constitutional questions arose concerning who should properly perform the functions of the presidency. (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America.)Garfield was the son of Abram Garfield and Eliza Ballou, who continued to run the family's impoverished Ohio farm after her husband's death in 1833. The last president born in a log cabin, Garfield dreamed of foreign...
</Question>
<Choice>Garfield, James A.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Conservative political leader who was three-time prime minister (1885–86, 1886–92, 1895–1902) and four-time foreign secretary (1878, 1885–86, 1886–92, 1895–1900), who presided over a wide expansion of Great Britain's colonial empire.Robert Cecil was the second surviving son of the 2nd Marquess of Salisbury, who had married Frances Gascoyne, an heiress to large landed estates. Cecil's elder brother suffered from a debilitating illness all his life and died in 1865; thus Lord Robert Cecil became heir to the estates, and, on the death of his father in 1868, he became the 3rd Marquess of Salisbury...
</Question>
<Choice>
Gascoyne-Cecil, Robert Arthur Talbot, 3rd marquess of Salisbury
</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Greece, whose long reign (1863–1913) spanned the formative period for the development of Greece as a modern European state. His descendants occupied the throne until the military coup d'état of 1967 and eventual restoration of the republic in 1973.Born Prince William, the second son of King Christian IX of Denmark and the brother of Queen Alexandra of England, he was nominated to the Greek throne by Britain, France, and Russia after the first Greek king, Otto, was deposed in 1862. The National Assembly accepted William as king of the Hellenes in March 1863, and he ascended the throne a...
</Question>
<Choice>George I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland and king of Hanover from Jan. 29, 1820, previously the sovereign de facto from Feb. 5, 1811, when he became regent for his father, George III, who had become insane.The eldest son of George III and Charlotte Sophia of Mecklenburg-Strelitz, he had become by age 17, as he said, “rather too fond of women and wine.” His way of life and his close friendship with Charles James Fox and other loose-living Whig politicians caused his father to regard him with contempt. In 1784 the prince met the only woman whom he ever deeply loved, Maria Fitzherb...
</Question>
<Choice>George IV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
last king of Hanover (1851–66), only son of Ernest Augustus, king of Hanover and Duke of Cumberland.His youth was passed in England and in Berlin until 1837, when his father became king of Hanover. He lost sight in one eye during a childhood illness and in the other by an accident in 1833. Blindness debarred him from a knowledge of the world; he formed a fantastic conception of the dignity of the house of Welf and had ideas of founding a great Welf state in Europe. From his accession in November 1851 he was constantly disputing with the diet, contrary to whose wishes he refused Prussia's deman...
</Question>
<Choice>George V</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
emperor and founder of the Nguyen dynasty, the last dynasty of Vietnam before conquest by France.Nguyen Anh—the nephew of Hue Vuong, the legitimate heir to the throne, who died in prison during a civil war in 1766—became a great general. He was aided in winning his kingdom by French mercenaries and other Western soldiers of fortune, whose assistance he accepted only after long deliberation. With French forces and advanced European armaments and technical equipment, Nguyen Anh won decisive victories over rival claimants at Hue and Hanoi in 1802. On June 1 he proclaimed himself emperor, assuming...
</Question>
<Choice>Gia Long</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish royal favourite and twice prime minister, whose disastrous foreign policy contributed to a series of misfortunes and defeats that culminated in the abdication of King Charles IV and the occupation of Spain by the armies of Napoleon Bonaparte.Born into an old but poor noble family, Godoy followed his brother to Madrid in 1784 and, like him, entered the royal bodyguard. He attracted the attention of Maria Luisa of Parma, wife of the heir to the throne, and soon became her lover. When her husband ascended the throne in 1788 as Charles IV, the domineering Maria Luisa persuaded Charles to a...
</Question>
<Choice>Godoy, Manuel de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the leader of Mexican liberalism in the mid-19th century, notable for his social reforms of 1833–34, which earned him the enmity of the clergy, the army, and the gentry. After training as a physician, he was influenced by French liberal political ideas and participated in the Mexican struggle for independence during the 1820s. In 1833 he was elected vice president in the administration of Antonio López de Santa Anna.When Santa Anna left the capital, Gómez Farías, in effective control of the government, immediately obtained legislation that reduced the number of generals, ended the special priv...
</Question>
<Choice>Gómez Farías, Valentín</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(Knyaz) statesman who served as Russia's foreign minister during the quarter century following the Crimean War (1853–56), when Russia was trying to regain its stature as a powerful European nation.A cousin of the Crimean War general Mikhail Dmitriyevich Gorchakov. Aleksandr Gorchakov grew up in the European atmosphere of salon and court life in St. Petersburg. Entering the diplomatic service in 1817, he became a member of the Russian delegations to the international congresses of Troppau, Laibach, and Verona (1820–22), and, despite the efforts of the foreign minister Count Karl Robert Nesselro...
</Question>
<Choice>Gorchakov, Aleksandr Mikhaylovich, Prince</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. general, commander of the Union armies during the late years (1864–65) of the American Civil War, and 18th president of the United States (1869–77). (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America.)
</Question>
<Choice>Grant, Ulysses S.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British politician, son of prime minister George Grenville; he was himself head of the coalition “Ministry of all the Talents,” Feb. 11, 1806–March 25, 1807. His greatest achievement was the abolition of the British overseas slave trade by a bill that became law the day he left office.Entering the House of Commons in 1782, Grenville became its speaker in January 1789, home secretary in June of that year, and president of the Board of Control in March 1790. Created Baron Grenville on Nov. 25, 1790, he then became leader of the House of Lords. From June 8, 1791, to Feb. 10, 1801, he served under...
</Question>
<Choice>Grenville, William Wyndham Grenville, Baron</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French Republican political figure whose term as president (1879–87) confirmed the establishment of the Third Republic (1870–1940) in France.Grévy served in the Constituent Assembly of 1848 where, fearing the rise of Louis-Napoléon (later Emperor Napoleon III), he advocated a weak executive, a viewpoint he held throughout his career. He was out of office in 1851–68, practicing law but also engaging in Republican political activities. In 1868 he was elected to the Corps Législatif, where he quickly emerged as a leader of the liberal opposition. After the fall of the Second Empire in 1870, he se...
</Question>
<Choice>Grévy, Jules</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British politician, leader of the Whig (liberal) Party, and prime minister (1830–34), who presided over the passage of the Reform Act of 1832, modernizing the franchise and the electoral system.
</Question>
<Choice>Grey, Charles Grey, 2nd Earl</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
hero of the Mexican efforts to secure independence.Guerrero began his military career in 1810, and soon the early Mexican independence leader José Maria Morelos commissioned him to promote the revolutionary movement in the highlands of southwestern Mexico. After Morelos' execution by the Spanish in 1815, Guerrero continued to lead his guerrilla forces against the Spanish until 1821, when he joined forces with Agustín de Iturbide and with him issued the Plan of Iguala, which became the political platform for the conservative wing of the Mexican independence movement. The Mexican forces triumphe...
</Question>
<Choice>Guerrero, Vicente</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French political figure and historian who, as leader of the conservative constitutional monarchists during the July Monarchy (1830–48), was the dominant minister in France.Guizot's father was executed by the National Convention in 1794, and Guizot went into exile with his mother. In 1805, after six years in Geneva, Guizot returned to Paris, where he studied law and frequented anti-Napoleonic literary circles. In 1812 he was appointed professor of history at the University of Paris.Joining the first Bourbon Restoration (1814), Guizot emerged as an influential proponent of constitutional monarch...
</Question>
<Choice>Guizot, François</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish king whose intemperate foreign policy led to his overthrow in a coup d'état (1809) and the loss of the eastern part of Sweden and Finland.The son of the assassinated Gustav III, Gustav IV came to the throne in 1792 under the regency of his uncle Charles, duke of Södermanland.In 1805 Gustav IV brought Sweden into the European coalition against Napoleon. When Russia became allied with France through the Treaty of Tilsit in 1807, Russian tsar Alexander I tried to persuade Gustav to join the Continental System against Great Britain. The situation grew more dangerous when, also in 1807, Den...
</Question>
<Choice>Gustav IV Adolf</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Venezuelan president and typical Latin American caudillo (military leader or dictator) of his era.Guzmán Blanco was the son of a famous journalist and politician, Antonio Leocadio Guzmán, who had married into the Blanco family of Caracas' upper class. He began his career by consolidating the support of provincial caudillos behind his leadership, increasing his power when he gained appointment as a special finance commissioner to negotiate loans with London bankers. In 1870 he seized control of the government as head of the Regeneración (Regeneration) movement, and in 1873 he had himself electe...
</Question>
<Choice>Guzmán Blanco, Antonio</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Danish politician whose policies led Denmark into a disastrous war with Germany.Hall was educated in the law, and in 1848 he became a leader of the National Liberal Party. He served as minister of church, education, and culture in 1854–57. He supported his party's old Eider policy favouring the incorporation of the duchy of Schleswig into the Danish state. As prime minister, from 1857 (and also as foreign minister from 1858) he tried to draw Schleswig closer to Denmark, despite Prussian objections. Hall pushed through the November constitution of 1863, which incorporated Schleswig into Denmark...
</Question>
<Choice>Hall, Carl Christian</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British foreign secretary and prime minister (1852–55) whose government involved Great Britain in the Crimean War against Russia (1853–56).Orphaned at age 11, George Gordon (who added his deceased first wife's family name to his own surname in 1818) was reared by his guardians, the politicians William Pitt the Younger and Henry Dundas (afterward Viscount Melville), and inherited the earldom and associated titles from his grandfather in 1801. In 1813 he was appointed special ambassador to Austria. He was a central figure in European diplomacy at that time, helping to form the coalition that def...
</Question>
<Choice>Hamilton-Gordon, George, 4th Earl of Aberdeen</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Prussian statesman and administrator, who preserved the integrity of the Prussian state during the Napoleonic Wars. Domestically he was able to continue the reforms introduced by Karl, Freiherr vom Stein; in foreign affairs he exchanged Prussia's alliance with France for an alliance with Russia in 1813, and in 1814–15 he represented Prussia at the peace negotiations in Paris and Vienna. Hardenberg vainly fought for the establishment of a constitution but gained lasting fame for his liberalization of financial, economic, and agricultural policies and for his conduct of foreign affairs, which cr...
</Question>
<Choice>Hardenberg, Karl August, Fürst von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
23rd president of the United States (1889–93), a moderate Republican who won an electoral majority while losing the popular vote by more than 100,000 to Democrat Grover Cleveland. Harrison signed into law the Sherman Antitrust Act (1890), the first legislation to prohibit business combinations in restraint of trade. (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America.)Harrison was the son of John Scott Harrison, a farmer, and Elizabeth Irwin Harrison and grandson of the ninth president, William Henry Harrison (elected 1840). In 1852 he g...
</Question>
<Choice>Harrison, Benjamin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
ninth president of the United States (1841), whose Indian campaigns, while he was a territorial governor and army officer, thrust him into the national limelight and led to his election in 1840. He was the oldest man, at age 67, ever elected president up to that time, the last president born under British rule, and the first to die in office—after only one month's service. His grandson Benjamin Harrison was the 23rd president of the United States (1889–93). (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America. See alsoCabinet of President...
</Question>
<Choice>Harrison, William Henry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
19th president of the United States (1877–81), who brought post-Civil War Reconstruction to an end in the South and who tried to establish new standards of official integrity after eight years of corruption in Washington, D.C. He was the only president to hold office by decision of an extraordinary commission of congressmen and Supreme Court justices appointed to rule on contested electoral ballots. (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America.)Hayes was the son of Rutherford Hayes, a farmer, and Sophia Birchard. After graduating...
</Question>
<Choice>Hayes, Rutherford B.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
president of the Dominican Republic who allowed most of his country's economy to fall under U.S. control. The republic's fiscal disorder led to American intervention after Heureaux's assassination.Heureaux received some schooling in a Methodist mission and then joined a revolt against Spain in the early 1860s, distinguishing himself as a soldier. Following Dominican independence and years of internal chaos, Heureaux became president in 1882 and exiled Luperón, his former leader. In 1884 and 1886 he selected his country's presidents while he continued to direct the government; from 1887 to his...
</Question>
<Choice>Heureaux, Ulises</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
imperial German chancellor and Prussian prime minister from October 1894 to October 1900, the “Uncle Chlodwig” whose fatherly relationship with the emperor William II did not enable him to prevent his sovereign's demagogic excesses.A Bavarian Roman Catholic, he was a member of a princely house and bore the titles of Fürst zu Hohenlohe-Schillingsfürst and Prinz von Ratibor und Corvey. He was briefly with the Prussian civil service, then a member of the Bavarian upper house, and in 1848 he served as a diplomat in the provisional German government in Frankfurt.In December 1866, after Prussia's de...
</Question>
<Choice>
Hohenlohe-Schillingsfürst, Chlodwig Karl Viktor, Fürst zu
</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(count of) Austrian statesman who served briefly as prime minister of Austria (1871).After service in the provincial administrations of Carniola (now in Slovenia) and Trentino, Italy, Hohenwart was appointed Statthalter (governor) of Upper Austria (1868). A Roman Catholic partisan in politics and an opponent of governmental centralization, he was appointed prime minister and minister of the interior in February 1871. His programs for wider Slavic autonomy within the Austrian part of the realm, first in Galicia but especially in Bohemia, caused opposition by the German liberal majority in the R...
</Question>
<Choice>Hohenwart, Karl Siegmund, Graf von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. lawyer and politician, a leader of the struggle by U.S. emigrants in Mexican territory to win control of Texas (1834–36) and make it part of the United States.In his youth Houston moved with his family to a farm in rural Tennessee after the death of his father in 1807. He ran away in his mid-teens and lived for nearly three years with the Cherokee Indians in eastern Tennessee, where he took the name Black Raven and learned the native language, skills, and customs. Houston thus developed a rapport with the Indians that was unique for his day. As a consequence, after service in the War of 1...
</Question>
<Choice>Houston, Sam</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
queen of Spain (1833–68) whose troubled reign was marked by political instability and the rule of military politicians. Isabella's failure to respond to growing demands for a more progressive regime, her questionable private life, and her political irresponsibility contributed to the decline in monarchical strength and prestige that led to her deposition in the Revolution of 1868.The elder daughter of Ferdinand VII by his fourth wife, María Cristina, Isabella was proclaimed queen on her father's death in 1833. Her right to succeed to the throne was disputed by supporters of her uncle, Don Carl...
</Question>
<Choice>Isabella II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese elder statesman (genro) and premier (1885–88, 1892–96, 1898, 1900–01), who played a crucial role in building modern Japan. He helped draft the Meiji constitution (1889) and brought about the establishment of a bicameral national Diet (1890). He was created a marquess in 1884 and a duke (or prince) in 1907.
</Question>
<Choice>Ito Hirobumi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mexican caudillo (military chieftain) who became the leader of the conservative factions in the Mexican independence movement and, as Agustín I, briefly emperor of Mexico.Like many young men of the upper classes in Spanish America, Iturbide entered the royalist army, becoming an officer in the provincial regiment of his native city in 1797. In 1810 Miguel Hidalgo y Costilla offered him a post with his revolutionary army, but Iturbide refused and pledged himself to the Spanish cause instead. His defense of Valladolid against the revolutionary forces of José María Morelos dealt a crushing blow t...
</Question>
<Choice>Iturbide, Agustín de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
military hero and seventh president of the United States (1829–37). He was the first U.S. president to come from the area west of the Appalachians and the first to gain office by a direct appeal to the mass of voters. His political movement has since been known as Jacksonian Democracy. (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America.)
</Question>
<Choice>Jackson, Andrew</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
draftsman of the Declaration of Independence of the United States and the nation's first secretary of state (1789–94), second vice president (1797–1801), and, as the third president (1801–09), the statesman responsible for the Louisiana Purchase. An early advocate of total separation of church and state, he also was the founder and architect of the University of Virginia and the most eloquent American proponent of individual freedom as the core meaning of the American Revolution. (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America.)Long...
</Question>
<Choice>Jefferson, Thomas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British prime minister from June 8, 1812, to Feb. 17, 1827, who, despite his long tenure of office, was overshadowed by the greater political imaginativeness of his colleagues, George Canning and Viscount Castlereagh (afterward 2nd Marquess of Londonderry), and by the military prowess of the Duke of Wellington.Entering the House of Commons in 1790, Jenkinson soon became a leading Tory, serving as a member of the Board of Control for India (1793–96), master of the Royal Mint (1799–1801), foreign secretary (1801–04), home secretary (1804–06, 1807–09), and secretary for war and the colonies (1809...
</Question>
<Choice>Jenkinson, Robert Banks, 2nd Earl of Liverpool</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prince regent of Portugal from 1799 to 1816, and king from 1816 to 1826, whose reign saw the revolutionary struggle in France, the Napoleonic invasion of Portugal (during which he established his court in Brazil), and the implantation of representative government in both Portugal and Brazil.John was the younger son of Queen Maria I, becoming heir on the death of his elder brother and taking power in 1792 as a result of the mental illness of his mother. In 1799 her illness was declared incurable, and he assumed the title of prince regent, which he used until her death in March 1816. John marrie...
</Question>
<Choice>John VI</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
17th president of the United States (1865–69), who took office upon the assassination of President Abraham Lincoln during the closing months of the American Civil War (1861–65). His lenient Reconstruction policies toward the South embittered the Radical Republicans in Congress and led to his political downfall and to his impeachment, though he was acquitted. (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America.)
</Question>
<Choice>Johnson, Andrew</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nez Percé chief who, faced with settlement by whites of tribal lands in Oregon, led his followers in a dramatic effort to escape to Canada.The Nez Percé tribe was one of the most powerful in the Pacific Northwest and in the first half of the 19th century one of the most friendly to whites. Many Nez Percé, including Chief Joseph's father, were converted to Christianity and Chief Joseph was educated in a mission school. The advance of white settlers into the Pacific Northwest after 1850 caused the United States to press the Indians of the region to surrender their lands and accept resettlement o...
</Question>
<Choice>Joseph, Chief</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
consort of Napoleon Bonaparte and empress of the French.Joséphine, the eldest daughter of Joseph Tascher de La Pagerie, an impoverished aristocrat who had a commission in the navy, lived the first 15 years of her life on the island of Martinique. In 1779 she married a rich young army officer, Alexandre, vicomte de Beauharnais, and moved to Paris. Although she bore him two children, Hortense and Eugène, the vain Alexandre was ashamed of her provincial manners and lack of sophistication and declined to present her at the court of Marie-Antoinette at Versailles; his indifference grew so great tha...
</Question>
<Choice>Joséphine</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
national hero of Mexico, president of Mexico (1861–72), who, for three years (1864–67), fought against foreign occupation under the emperor Maximilian and who sought constitutional reforms to create a democratic federal republic.
</Question>
<Choice>Juárez, Benito</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
favourite queen of Kamehameha I and acting regent of Hawaii in 1823–32.Kaahumanu was of distinguished parentage, her mother having been married to the late king of Maui. Early in life she was betrothed to Kamehameha I, whom her father had served as counselor. They married and had a stormy but enduring relationship. She supported him in his efforts to unite the islands of the archipelago under his central authority and shared largely in their governance. After her husband's death in 1819, Kaahumanu became kuhina nui (premier) to his successor, Liholiho Kamehameha II, and instigated many reforms...
</Question>
<Choice>Kaahumanu</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hawaiian conqueror and king who, by 1810, had united all the Hawaiian islands and founded the Kamehameha dynasty, the most enduring and best-documented line of Hawaiian rulers.First named Paiea, meaning “Hard-Shelled Crab,” the future sovereign was the son of Keoua, a high chief, and of Kekuiapoiwa, a daughter of the former king Alapai. A Hawaiian tradition tells that a bright star, Kokoiki, appeared just before the great conqueror was born. The date of the legend coincides with the appearance of Halley's Comet in 1758. When Kokoiki was viewed by the kahunas, Hawaii's mystic seers, it was prop...
</Question>
<Choice>Kamehameha I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Hawaii from 1819 to 1824, son of Kamehameha I.In 1820 he admitted the first company of missionaries (from New England), who, within two years, had learned the language, reduced it to writing, and printed the first textbook. Kamehameha resisted conversion to Christianity, allegedly because he refused to give up four of his five wives as well as rum drinking. In 1823 he sailed on a visit to England, in a delegation that included two of his wives. Stricken with measles in London in June 1824, Kamehameha and his favourite wife, Kamamalu, died there.
</Question>
<Choice>Kamehameha II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Hawaii from 1825 to 1854, brother of Kamehameha II.Only 10 years of age when he succeeded to the throne, he was initially under the regency of Kamehameha I's favourite wife, Kaahumanu, who had been regent ever since Kamehameha II had visited England in 1824 and died there. Converted to Christianity in 1824, she became known for her wise and beneficent rule. On her death in 1832 the regency fell to Kamehameha I's daughter Kinau, but in the following year Kamehameha III assumed power in his own right.After hearing a series of lectures on government delivered by an American clergyman, Wil...
</Question>
<Choice>Kamehameha III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hawaiian sovereign known for his firm opposition to the annexation of his kingdom by the United States. As Kamehameha IV, he strove to curb the political power of the American Protestant missionaries in the Hawaiian Islands. Dedicated to protecting his people, who were rapidly dying out because of disease, he sponsored many social and economic reforms. He established Hawaii's commercial and political relations with other nations on a solid base and tried to balance each country's influence on island life.The son of Kekuanaoa, governor of Oahu, and Kinau, a woman chief who had been kuhina nui (...
</Question>
<Choice>Kamehameha IV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Hawaii from 1863 to 1872.Succeeding to the throne on the death of his younger brother, Kamehameha IV, he immediately revealed his intention to rule with a strong hand, refusing at his inauguration to take the oath to maintain the existing, comparatively liberal constitution. After calling and dismissing a constitutional convention, he himself wrote and promulgated a new constitution (1864), which remained in effect for 23 years. He also imported the first wave of Japanese labourers, by a contract made in 1868. In the later years of his reign he grew so obese (weighing about 375 pounds...
</Question>
<Choice>Kamehameha V</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sauk Indian orator and politician who became chief by ceding Indian lands to win white support and by rallying opposition to his own tribe's resistance leaders.Born of the Fox clan, Keokuk early exhibited physical prowess, keen intelligence, and a gift of persuasion. He rose to prominence in the tribal council, and, during the War of 1812, he tried to seize power from Black Hawk, who had left the Sauk village to fight with the British. Thus began a lifelong struggle between these two leaders, who disagreed completely on how to meet the challenge posed by advancing white settlement. Black Hawk...
</Question>
<Choice>Keokuk</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
chief who led the people of the Griqua nation from their home in the Orange Free State (now part of South Africa) to found a new nation, Griqualand East, on the east coast of what is now South Africa. He considered himself an independent ally of the British, but colonial pressures ultimately led to the annexation of Griqualand East by the Cape Colony.In 1837 Adam Kok succeeded to the rule of the Griqua nation of Dutch-speaking former slaves and Africans of mixed descent. He was friendly to the British administration in the Cape Colony, and he received recognition of his sovereignty in 1848. Pr...
</Question>
<Choice>Kok III, Adam</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
farmer, soldier, and statesman, noted in South African history as the builder of the Afrikaner nation. He was president of the Transvaal, or South African Republic, from 1883 until his flight to Europe in 1900, after the outbreak of the South African (Boer) War.
</Question>
<Choice>Kruger, Paul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
reign name (nianhao) of the ninth emperor (reigned 1874/75–1908) of the Qing dynasty (1644–1911/12), during whose reign the empress dowager Cixi (1835–1908) totally dominated the government and thereby prevented the young emperor from modernizing and reforming the deteriorating imperial system.When Tongzhi, the previous emperor, died, his mother, Cixi, chose Zaitian, her five-year-old nephew, as emperor. She adopted the boy as her son so that she could act as regent and dominate the government as she had since 1861. Although this action broke the sacred dynastic law of succession, opposition t...
</Question>
<Choice>Kuang-hsü</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
ChinesePrince Gongleading official in the closing years of the Qing dynasty (1644–1911/12), who tried to repair a weakened government and to effect a rapprochement with the West.A brother of the Xianfeng emperor (reigned 1850–61), Prince Gong was assigned to make peace with the British and French forces who had occupied the capital at Beijing in 1860, during the second Opium War (the Arrow War). After successfully concluding treaty negotiations, he urged that China try to understand and adopt some Western military techniques. As a result, the emperor created the Zongli Yamen (“Office for Gener...
</Question>
<Choice>Kung Ch'in-wang</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian general and statesman who, while in the service of Sardinia–Piedmont, played an important role in the Risorgimento.A graduate of the Turin Military Academy, La Marmora entered the army in 1823 and first distinguished himself in the Italian wars of independence against Austria, especially at Borghetto and Peschiera (May 1848). He also commanded the Sardinian forces in the Crimea (1855). On Aug. 5, 1848, he rescued the Sardinian king Charles Albert from Milanese revolutionaries, who had resented the King's armistice with the Austrians. He was promoted to general in October and served as...
</Question>
<Choice>La Marmora, Alfonso Ferrero</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Canadian statesman, joint prime minister with Robert Baldwin of the united province of Canada in 1842–43 and again during the “great ministry” of 1848–51, when responsible, or cabinet, government was finally achieved.LaFontaine was called to the bar in Lower Canada in 1828, and two years later he began his political career when elected to the provincial assembly for Terrebonne. He supported the French-Canadian grievances against the British governor in chief, but he did not condone the Rebellion of 1837. With a second outbreak of rebellion in 1838, LaFontaine was imprisoned but released withou...
</Question>
<Choice>LaFontaine, Sir Louis Hippolyte, Baronet</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British prime minister from July 16 to Nov. 14, 1834, and from April 18, 1835, to Aug. 30, 1841. He was also Queen Victoria's close friend and chief political adviser during the early years of her reign (from June 20, 1837). Although a Whig and an advocate of political rights for Roman Catholics, he was essentially conservative. Not believing that the world could be bettered through politics, he was always more interested in literature and theology.Lamb's mother, Elizabeth (née Milbanke), was a confidante of the poet Lord Byron and an aunt of Byron's future wife Anne Isabella (“Annabella”) Mil...
</Question>
<Choice>Lamb, William, 2nd Viscount Melbourne</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian statesman and political activist of the Risorgimento who was premier in 1870 when Rome became the capital of a united Italy and who helped organize the political forces of the centre-left.After graduating from the University of Turin as a doctor of medicine, Lanza concentrated on agricultural improvement in Piedmont. In 1848 he enlisted as a volunteer in a Piedmontese force sent to help the Lombards against the Austrians. Elected a deputy of the Piedmontese Chamber, he opposed the peace treaty (Aug. 9, 1849) with Austria and became one of the most effective leaders of the centre-left....
</Question>
<Choice>Lanza, Giovanni</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first king of the Belgians (1831–65), who helped strengthen the nation's new parliamentary system and, as a leading figure in European diplomacy, scrupulously maintained Belgian neutrality.The fourth son of Francis, duke of Saxe-Coburg-Saalfeld, Leopold served with the allies against Napoleon's forces during the Napoleonic Wars (1800–15); in 1816 he married Charlotte, the only child of the future king George IV of Great Britain. Although the princess died in 1817, Leopold continued to live in England until 1831, when he accepted his election as king of the Belgians, having declined the Greek c...
</Question>
<Choice>Leopold I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the Belgians from 1865 to 1909; he led the first European efforts to develop the Congo River basin, making possible the formation of the Congo Free State in 1885, annexed in 1908 as the Belgian Congo (now Congo [Kinshasa]).The eldest son of Leopold I, first king of the Belgians, and his second wife, Marie-Louise of Orléans, Leopold became duke of Brabant in 1846 and served in the Belgian Army. In 1853 he married Maria Henrietta, daughter of the Austrian archduke Joseph, palatine of Hungary, and became king of the Belgians on his father's death in December 1865. Although the domestic af...
</Question>
<Choice>Leopold II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first and only reigning Hawaiian queen and the last Hawaiian sovereign to govern the islands, which were annexed by the United States in 1898.Lydia Kamakaeha was of a high-ranking family. Her mother, Keohokalole, was an adviser of King Kamehameha III. Reared in the missionary tradition deemed appropriate for Hawaiian princesses, she received a thoroughly modern education, which was augmented by a tour of the Western world. After a time as a member of the court of Kamehameha IV, she was married in September 1862 to John Owen Dominis, son of a Boston sea captain and himself an official in the Ha...
</Question>
<Choice>Liliuokalani</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
16th president of the United States (1861–65), who preserved the Union during the American Civil War and brought about the emancipation of the slaves. (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America.)(In February 2009, on the 200th anniversary of Abraham Lincoln's birth, Britannica asked two prominent contributors to answer some Lincoln-related questions on the Britannica Blog. Noted historian James McPherson, author Tried by War and of Britannica's article “Translating Thought in Action: Grant's Personal Memoirs,” addresses Lincoln'...
</Question>
<Choice>Lincoln, Abraham</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
second and last king (1870–94) of the Southern African Ndebele (Matabele) nation. Lobengula—the son of the founder of the Ndebele kingdom, Mzilikazi—was unable to prevent his kingdom from being destroyed by the British in 1893.After Mzilikazi died in September 1868, the succession of Lobengula was not accepted by Mangwane (one of Mzilikazi's older sons) and some of the izinduna (chiefs), and he succeeded to the throne only in 1870 after a period of serious civil war. Lobengula faced a rebellion in June 1870, and in 1872 he repelled an invasion by Mangwane and a pretender backed by the British...
</Question>
<Choice>Lobengula</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
dictator of Paraguay during the Paraguayan War (also known as the War of the Triple Alliance), in which Paraguay was practically destroyed by Brazil, Argentina, and Uruguay.López, the eldest son of the dictator Carlos Antonio López, seized power upon his father's death (September 10, 1862) and quickly established his own supremacy with the help of the army. Showing little understanding of his country's need to remain neutral in squabbles between the two South American giants, Brazil and Argentina, early in 1863 he allowed himself to be drawn into boundary disputes with both countries and to be...
</Question>
<Choice>López, Francisco Solano</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Bavaria from 1825 to 1848, a liberal and a German nationalist who rapidly turned conservative after his accession, best known as an outstanding patron of the arts who transformed Munich into the artistic centre of Germany.Louis, the well-educated eldest son of King Maximilian I, was a fervent German nationalist as a youth and served only reluctantly at Napoleon's headquarters in the wars against Prussia and Russia (1806–07) and Austria (1809). In Bavaria he came to head the anti-French party, and at the Congress of Vienna (1814–15) he unsuccessfully advocated the return of Alsace and L...
</Question>
<Choice>Louis I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
eccentric king of Bavaria from 1864 to 1886 and an admirer and patron of the composer Richard Wagner. He brought his territories into the newly founded German Empire (1871) but concerned himself only intermittently with affairs of state, preferring a life of increasingly morbid seclusion and developing a mania for extravagant building projects.Louis was the elder son of King Maximilian II of Bavaria and Marie of Prussia. Politically a romantic conservative, he came to the throne after his father's death in 1864 before he had completed his studies. Louis entered the Seven Weeks' War (1866) on t...
</Question>
<Choice>Louis II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of France by title from 1795 and in fact from 1814 to 1824, except for the interruption of the Hundred Days, during which Napoleon attempted to recapture his empire.Louis was the fourth son of the dauphin Louis, the son of Louis XV, and received the title comte de Provence; after the death of his two elder brothers and the accession of his remaining elder brother as Louis XVI in 1774, he became heir presumptive. The birth of two sons to Louis XVI, however, temporarily put a stop to his royal ambitions. When the Revolution broke out in 1789, he remained in Paris, possibly to exploit the si...
</Question>
<Choice>Louis XVIII</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the French from 1830 to 1848; basing his rule on the support of the upper bourgeoisie, he ultimately fell from power because he could not win the allegiance of the new industrial classes.Louis-Philippe was the eldest son of Louis-Philippe Joseph de Bourbon-Orléans, Duke de Chartres, and Adélaïde de Bourbon-Penthièvre. At first styled Duke de Valois, he became Duke de Chartres when his father inherited the title Duke d'Orléans in 1785. On the outbreak of the French Revolution in 1789, Louis-Philippe joined the group of progressive nobles who supported the Revolutionary government. He be...
</Question>
<Choice>Louis-Philippe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the first prime minister of the Dominion of Canada (1867–73, 1878–91), who led Canada through its period of early growth. Though accused of devious and unscrupulous methods, he is remembered for his achievements.Macdonald emigrated from Scotland to Kingston, in what is now Ontario, in 1820. He was called to the bar in 1836. After the British Parliament united Upper and Lower Canada as Canada West (now in Ontario) and Canada East (now in Quebec) in the Act of Union of 1840, Macdonald was elected to the assembly of the Province of Canada as a Conservative for Kingston in 1844. From 1848 to 1854,...
</Question>
<Choice>Macdonald, Sir John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish-born politician, the first Liberal prime minister of Canada (1873–78).Mackenzie emigrated in 1842 from Scotland to Canada West (now Ontario), where he worked as a stone mason and established himself as a building contractor at Sarnia. His interest in reform led to his becoming editor in 1852 of the Lambton Shield, a local Liberal newspaper. He became friendly with George Brown, editor of The Globe (Toronto) and leader of the Reform Party. Mackenzie supported the confederation movement. After the Dominion of Canada was created in 1867, he was elected by Lambton to the dominion's first...
</Question>
<Choice>Mackenzie, Alexander</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
marshal of France and second president of the Third French Republic. During his presidency the Third Republic took shape, the new constitutional laws of 1875 were adopted, and important precedents were established affecting the relationship between executive and legislative powers.A descendant of an Irish family that fled to France during the time of the Stuarts, Mac-Mahon began his army career in 1827 in Algeria and distinguished himself in the storming of Constantine (1837) and in the Crimean War (1853–56). The climax of his military career came in the Italian campaign of 1859, when his vict...
</Question>
<Choice>Marie-Edme-Patrice-Maurice, comte de Mac-Mahon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
fourth president of the United States (1809–17) and one of the Founding Fathers of his country. At the Constitutional Convention (1787), he influenced the planning and ratification of the U.S. Constitution and collaborated with Alexander Hamilton and John Jay in the publication of the Federalist papers. As a member of the new House of Representatives, he sponsored the first 10 amendments to the Constitution, commonly called the Bill of Rights. He was secretary of state under President Thomas Jefferson when the Louisiana Territory was purchased from France. The War of 1812 was fought during his...
</Question>
<Choice>Madison, James</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
president of Mexico from 1982 to 1988.Miguel de la Madrid received a degree in law from the National Autonomous University of Mexico (UNAM) in Mexico City in 1957 and a master's degree in public administration from Harvard University in 1965. He worked for the National Bank of Foreign Commerce and the Bank of Mexico, and, until 1968, he taught law at the UNAM.A member of Mexico's ruling party, the Institutional Revolutionary Party (Partido Revolucionario Institucional; PRI), from 1963, de la Madrid first entered government service in the Treasury (1965). From 1970 to 1972 he worked for Petróle...
</Question>
<Choice>Madrid, Miguel de la</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ottoman sultan (1808–39) whose westernizing reforms helped to consolidate the Ottoman Empire despite defeats in wars and losses of territory.Mahmud was brought to the throne (July 28, 1808) in a coup led by Bayrakdar Mustafa Pasa, ?ayn (local notable) of Rusçuk (now Ruse, Bulg.), who had first wanted to restore Mahmud's uncle, the reform-minded sultan Selim III, until he was strangled by the conservatives. Before the year was out, however, the Janissaries revolted, killing Bayrakdar, Mahmud's grand vizier (chief minister), and delaying his reform program until the mid-1820s.Early in his reign...
</Question>
<Choice>Mahmud II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
queen consort of Ferdinand VII of Spain from 1829 to 1833 and queen regent from 1833 to 1840.Maria was the daughter of Francis I, king of the Two Sicilies, and married Ferdinand in 1829. In 1830 Maria convinced her husband to change the law of succession to allow their daughter, Isabella, to become queen, an action that deprived the king's brother, Don Carlos (Carlos María Isidro), of the Spanish throne and thus eventually precipitated the First Carlist War.On the death of Ferdinand (Sept. 29, 1833), María Cristina became regent with absolute power, but within a few days the First Carlist War...
</Question>
<Choice>María Cristina De Borbón</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
queen of Portugal (1834–53).Maria was the daughter of Peter I of Brazil, IV of Portugal, who, on inheriting both countries from his father, entered a conditional abdication of Portugal in her favour (1826). His plan was that she should marry his younger brother Michael, who would accept and apply Peter's constitution, the Charter. But Michael seized power, declaring himself king; and only upon abdicating the Brazilian empire (1831) was Peter able to proceed to Europe, occupy the island of Terceira in the Azores, and launch an expedition to conquer the mainland in Maria's name. He seized Porto...
</Question>
<Choice>Maria II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian archduchess who became empress of the French (impératrice des Français), as the second wife of the emperor Napoleon I; she was later duchess of Parma, Piacenza, and Guastalla.Marie-Louise, a member of the House of Habsburg, was the eldest daughter of the Holy Roman emperor Francis II (Francis I of Austria) and Maria Theresa of Naples-Sicily and niece of Marie-Antoinette, queen of France. Klemens von Metternich, the Austrian statesman, seems to have suggested her to Napoleon, who was looking for a wife with royal blood and had already decided to dissolve his childless marriage with the...
</Question>
<Choice>Marie-Louise</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
general and politician whose pronunciamiento (military revolution) on December 29, 1874, restored Spain's Bourbon dynasty.Martínez Campos received a military education and after 1852 served on Spain's general staff. A competent soldier, he took part in the international expedition of General Juan Prim to Mexico (1861) and fought Cuban rebels (until 1872). On his return to Spain, he briefly taught military science and then was sent to put down rebellions in Valencia (1872), Alicante, and Cartagena.After Alfonso XII, the son of the deposed Isabella II, had declared Spain a constitutional monarch...
</Question>
<Choice>Martínez Campos, Arsenio</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
archduke of Austria and the emperor of Mexico, a man whose naive liberalism proved unequal to the international intrigues that had put him on the throne and to the brutal struggles within Mexico that led to his execution.The younger brother of Emperor Francis Joseph, he served as a rear admiral in the Austrian navy and as governor-general of the Lombardo-Venetian kingdom. In 1863 he accepted the offer of the Mexican throne, falsely believing that the Mexican people had voted him their king; in fact, the offer was the result of a scheme between conservative Mexicans, who wished to overturn the...
</Question>
<Choice>Maximilian</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
25th president of the United States (1897–1901). Under McKinley's leadership, the United States went to war against Spain in 1898 and thereby acquired a global empire, including Puerto Rico, Guam, and the Philippines. (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America.)
</Question>
<Choice>McKinley, William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
emperor of Japan from 1867 to 1912, during whose reign Japan was dramatically transformed from a feudal country into one of the great powers of the modern world.The second son of the emperor Komei, Mutsuhito was declared crown prince in 1860; following the death of his father in 1867, he was raised to the throne. In 1868 his coronation ceremony was carried out, and he took the name Meiji, by which the era of his reign is also known. Meiji's accession to the throne coincided with the end of the Tokugawa shogunate and the restoration to the emperor of supreme executive authority in the country....
</Question>
<Choice>Meiji</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Shewa (or Shoa; 1865–89), and emperor of Ethiopia (1889–1913). One of Ethiopia's greatest rulers, he expanded the empire almost to its present-day borders, repelled an Italian invasion in 1896, and carried out a wide-ranging program of modernization.
</Question>
<Choice>Menilek II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(prince of),Austrian statesman, minister of foreign affairs (1809–48), and a champion of conservatism, who helped form the victorious alliance against Napoleon I and who restored Austria as a leading European power, hosting the Congress of Vienna in 1814–15.
</Question>
<Choice>Metternich, Klemens, Fürst von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
younger son of King John VI of Portugal, regent of Portugal from February 1828 and self-proclaimed king from July 1828 to 1834, though his royal title was not everywhere recognized.Michael went with the rest of the royal family to Brazil in 1807, escaping from Napoleon's armies, but returned with them in 1821 to Portugal. He was then—and remained—much under the influence of his Spanish mother, Queen Carlota Joaquina. On his return, King John VI accepted the liberal constitution of 1821, but Queen Carlota refused to take the oath. When in 1823 the French overthrew the radical regime in Spain, M...
</Question>
<Choice>Michael</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prince of Serbia (1839–42, 1860–68) and modern Serbia's most enlightened ruler, who instituted the rule of law and attempted to found a Balkan federation aimed against the Ottoman Empire.The second son of Miloš Obrenovic, Michael succeeded to the Serbian throne on the death of his elder brother, Milan, on July 8, 1839, but fled into exile after a revolt in 1842. Having travelled widely, he returned on his father's restoration to the throne (1858), served as commander in chief of the army, and became prince again on Miloš' death in 1860. An enlightened, though increasingly authoritarian, ruler,...
</Question>
<Choice>Michael III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prince (1868–82) and then king (1882–89) of Serbia.Succeeding his cousin Prince Michael III of Serbia on July 2, 1868, Milan was dominated during the first years of his reign by a regency that adopted a seemingly liberal constitution in 1869, tried to develop close relations with Austria, and made Milan generally unpopular. When Milan assumed personal control of the government (August 1872), however, he further alienated public opinion by his frivolous extravagance; by his unfaithfulness to his wife, the Russian-born Natalie Petrovna Keshko, whom he married in 1875; and by his refusal to accom...
</Question>
<Choice>Milan IV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Serbian peasant revolutionary who became prince of Serbia (1815–39 and 1858–60) and who founded the Obrenovic dynasty.Miloš Teodorovic, originally a herdsman, worked for his half brother Milan Obrenovic, then joined Karadjordje, who was leading the Serbs in a rebellion against their Ottoman Turkish rulers (1804–13). In 1805 Miloš was appointed a commander in the rebel forces, but after his half brother was killed (1810), possibly by Karadjordje, he took the surname Obrenovic and assumed an enmity toward Karadjordje. When Karadjordje fled into Hungary following the collapse of his revolt (1813)...
</Question>
<Choice>Miloš</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Myanmar from 1853 to 1878. His reign was notable both for its reforms and as a period of cultural flowering in the period before the imposition of complete colonial rule.Mindon was a brother of Pagan (reigned 1846–53), who had ruled during the Second Anglo-Burmese War in 1852. As soon as he became king, Mindon sued for peace and began negotiations with the British on the status of Pegu (in southern Myanmar), which the British had occupied during the war. Frustrated in his attempts to persuade them to return Pegu, the king was obliged to accept a much-reduced dominion, cut off from the...
</Question>
<Choice>Mindon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman who was twice prime minister of united Italy (1863–64, 1873–76).In his youth, while visiting an aunt in Paris, Minghetti came under the influence of exiled Italian patriots. Returning home he entered the University of Bologna, where he devoted himself to courses in science but was soon also attracted to the humanities and politics. He was drawn to Rome to assist in seeking reforms from the government of the Papal States under the liberal Pius IX, and he became a member of the revolutionary government of the Roman Republic (1847). He resigned in 1848 to join the Piedmont-Sardinian arm...
</Question>
<Choice>Minghetti, Marco</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
emperor (1820–41) of central Vietnam who was known for his anti-Western policies, especially his persecution of Christian missionaries.Prince Chi Dam was the fourth son of Emperor Gia Long (reigned 1802–20) and his favourite concubine and thus was not in line for the throne. He was chosen by Gia Long as his successor, however, because of his outspoken criticism of Europeans. Chi Dam took the reign name Minh Mang.As a strict Confucian, Minh Mang believed that Christian doctrine undermined the basic principles of Vietnamese religious and political life, especially the worship of and obedience to...
</Question>
<Choice>Minh Mang</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician, soldier, and author, who as president of Argentina was instrumental in uniting a war-torn nation and inaugurating an era of peace and economic progress in the last half of the 19th century.Growing up in Buenos Aires under the dictatorship of Juan Manuel de Rosas, Mitre began a 15-year exile in 1837. Travelling to Uruguay, Bolivia, and Peru, he served in military campaigns, edited the newspaper El Mercurio, and wrote constantly against the Rosas regime. In 1852 he returned to Argentina as the leader of the Uruguayan forces in the Battle of Caseros, which led to the downfall of Rosas...
</Question>
<Choice>Mitre, Bartolomé</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Siam (1851–68) who opened his country to Western influence and initiated reforms and modern development.Mongkut was the 43rd child of King Rama II, but as the first son to be born of a queen he was favoured to succeed to the throne. When his father died in 1824, however, Mongkut was barely 20, and the royal accession council instead chose his older and more experienced half brother to reign as King Phranangklao (Rama III). To hold aloof from politics, Mongkut chose to become a Buddhist monk. A few years later he encountered a particularly pious monk who inspired Mongkut to turn to the...
</Question>
<Choice>Mongkut</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
fifth president of the United States (1817–25), who issued an important contribution to U.S. foreign policy in the Monroe Doctrine, a warning to European nations against intervening in the Western Hemisphere. The period of his administration has been called the Era of Good Feelings. (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America.)
</Question>
<Choice>Monroe, James</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German statesman who developed modern Bavaria.The son of a Savoyard nobleman, Montgelas entered the service of Charles II Augustus, duke of Zweibrücken, and was from 1795 closely attached to the latter's successor, Maximilian IV Joseph, who, on becoming elector of Bavaria in 1799, installed him as prime minister. Montgelas wanted to establish Bavaria as an independent power between Austria and France. The Napoleonic Wars gave him the opportunity to bring Bavaria to France's side in 1805. While Bavaria's membership in the second Confederation of the Rhine permitted independent internal administ...
</Question>
<Choice>Montgelas de Garnerin, Maximilian Joseph, Graf von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
president of Chile, an enlightened statesman who throughout his two terms (1851–61) angered liberals and conservatives alike yet accomplished many constructive reforms.After studying law at the National Institute, where he also served as rector (1835–40), Montt was elected to the Chilean Congress in 1840. He served as minister of the interior and minister of justice under President Manuel Bulnes (1841–51).In 1851 Montt won the presidency, but the liberals thought his election was fraudulent and instigated an armed revolt, which was quickly subdued. Montt represented the conservative oligarchy...
</Question>
<Choice>Montt, Manuel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
president of the United Provinces of Central America (1830–40), who was the outstanding military and political hero of Central America from 1827 until his death.Self-educated, Morazán began his political career in his native Honduras. In 1827, at age 35, he led the Liberal Party's forces in a revolt against Manuel José Arce, first president of the United Provinces (established in 1823). The Liberal forces defeated the Conservative army in 1829) at Guatemala City, the capital, and in 1830 Morazán was elected president. He introduced many reforms designed to limit the power of the Roman Catholic...
</Question>
<Choice>Morazán, Francisco</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
founder and first paramount chief of the Sotho (Basuto, Basotho) nation. One of the most successful Southern African leaders of the 19th century, Moshoeshoe combined aggressive military counteraction and adroit diplomacy against colonial invasions. He created a large African state in the face of attacks by the Boers and the British, raiders from the south east coastal lowlands of Africa, and local African rivals.Moshoeshoe was the son of Mokhachane, the chief of the Mokoteli. As a young man, Moshoeshoe—then known by his post circumcision name of Letlama (“The Binder”)—won a reputation for lead...
</Question>
<Choice>Mshweshwe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Southern African king and son of Sobhuza I. Mswati II was the greatest of the Dlamini-Ngwane kings, and the Swazi (as the Dlamini-Ngwane came to be called) take their name from him. He extended his kingdom northward into Rhodesia (now Zimbabwe), including territory since lost by the Swazi.Mswati was the son of Sobhuza I by his wife Thandile. He succeeded to the kingship on his father's death sometime in 1839–40, but he began his effective rule when he was circumcised (a rite of passage signifying attainment of maturity) in 1845. He dealt with internal rebellion, pressures resulting from Boer i...
</Question>
<Choice>Mswati</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ottoman sultan from May to August 1876, whose liberal disposition brought him to the throne after the deposition of his autocratic uncle Abdülaziz.A man of high intelligence, Murad received a good education and was widely read in both Turkish and European literature. In 1867 he accompanied Abdülaziz on his European tour and made a favourable impression; during the tour he secretly contacted exiled nationalist-liberal Young Turks, for which Abdülaziz placed him under close surveillance.Upon Abdülaziz' deposition by a group of ministers led by Midhat Pasa, the great advocate of constitutional go...
</Question>
<Choice>Murad V</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French cavalry leader who was one of Napoleon's most celebrated marshals and who, as king of Naples (1808–15), lent stimulus to Italian nationalism.The son of an innkeeper, he studied briefly for a career in the church but enlisted in a cavalry regiment in 1787 and, when war broke out in 1792, won rapid promotion. In October 1795 he was on hand in Paris at the moment that Napoleon Bonaparte was entrusted with the mission of suppressing a royalist insurrection; Murat's contribution in bringing up cannon won him a place as aide-de-camp to Bonaparte for the Italian campaign of 1796–97. In Italy a...
</Question>
<Choice>Murat, Joachim</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ottoman sultan from 1807 to 1808 who participated in the reactionary conservative coalition that overthrew his reforming cousin, the sultan Selim III.A fanatical and ambitious man of low intelligence, Mustafa, under the influence of the shaykh al-islam (head of the Muslim religious hierarchy) and the Janissaries, ended Selim's reforms and killed most of the reformers. Meanwhile Bayrakdar Mustafa Pasa of Rusçuk (modern Ruse, Bulg.), a reformist supporter, marched to Constantinople to restore Selim III. Mustafa, informed of Bayrakdar's intentions, killed Selim. He himself was immediately deposed...
</Question>
<Choice>Mustafa IV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
South African king who founded the powerful Ndebele (Matabele) kingdom in what is now Zimbabwe. The greatest Bantu warrior after Shaka, king of the Zulus, Mzilikazi took his Kumalo people more than 500 miles (800 km) from what is now South Africa to the region now known as Zimbabwe, creating en route an immense and ethnically diverse nation. Mzilikazi was a statesman of considerable stature, able to weld the many conquered tribes into a strong, centralized kingdom.Originally a lieutenant of Shaka, he revolted against the Zulu king in 1823 and withdrew his people northward to safety from their...
</Question>
<Choice>Mzilikazi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French general, first consul (1799–1804), and emperor of the French (1804–1814/15), one of the most celebrated personages in the history of the West. He revolutionized military organization and training; sponsored the Napoleonic Code, the prototype of later civil-law codes; reorganized education; and established the long-lived Concordat with the papacy.Napoleon's many reforms left a lasting mark on the institutions of France and of much of western Europe. But his driving passion was the military expansion of French dominion, and, though at his fall he left France little larger than it had been...
</Question>
<Choice>Napoleon I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
nephew of Napoleon I, president of the Second Republic of France (1850–52), and then emperor of the French (1852–70). He gave his country two decades of prosperity under a stable, authoritarian government but finally led it to defeat in the Franco-German War (1870–71).
</Question>
<Choice>Napoleon III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish general and conservative political leader, who supported Queen Isabella II and served six times as prime minister of Spain from 1844–66.Narváez was born into a prominent military family and joined the royal guards at 15. He rose rapidly through the military ranks in the 1820s, when he defended the monarchy in the military revolt against Ferdinand VII. During the First Carlist War (1833–39) Narváez was one of Regent María Cristina de Borbón's most capable military leaders. In 1838 he was elected to the Spanish Cortes (parliament), led an unsuccessful rising at Sevilla against the Progre...
</Question>
<Choice>Narváez, Ramón María, duque de Valencia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian emperor (1825–55), often considered the personification of classic autocracy; for his reactionary policies, he has been called the emperor who froze Russia for 30 years.
</Question>
<Choice>Nicholas I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Cambodia (1860–1904) who, under duress, placed his country under the control of the French in 1863.Norodom was the eldest son of King Duong. He was educated in Bangkok, capital of the Thai kingdom, where he studied Pali and Sanskrit Buddhist scriptures and the sacred canons of Theravada Buddhism. The purpose of his early training was to strengthen ties between Siam (Thailand) and Cambodia.Cambodia had been under the joint vassalage of Vietnam and Siam since 1802. According to established protocol, Cambodian kings were crowned jointly, with representatives of the two suzerains attending...
</Question>
<Choice>Norodom</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Egyptian statesman of Armenian descent who was instrumental in the negotiation of important treaties with the European powers and in the division of authority between Egyptian and British administrators.Raised and educated in Europe, Nubar learned numerous foreign languages and became intimately familiar with European culture and customs—skills that served him well later in his life. It was his uncle, who served as Mu?ammad ?Ali's chief interpreter, who brought Nubar to Egypt. Nubar's first important work involved the Suez Canal. The Ottoman khedive (viceroy) of Egypt, Isma?il Pasha (ruled 186...
</Question>
<Choice>Nubar Pasha</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish soldier-politician who played a prominent role in the successful Spanish military insurrections of 1843 and 1854 and headed the Spanish government three times between 1856 and 1866. Though he lacked a coherent political program, he was a staunch supporter of Queen Isabella II (reigned 1833–68) and pursued conservative policies while in office.A descendant of the O'Donnells who left Ireland after the Battle of the Boyne (1690), O'Donnell gained fame and high rank during the First Carlist War (1833–39). He went into exile in France in 1840 but returned three years later to help overthrow...
</Question>
<Choice>O'Donnell, Leopoldo, Duque De Tetuán</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
South American revolutionary leader and first Chilean head of state (“supreme director,” 1817–23), who commanded the military forces that won independence from Spain.Bernardo O'Higgins was born in Chillán, a town in southern Chile, then a colony of Spain. As noted in his Certificate of Baptism, he was the illegitimate son of Ambrosio O'Higgins, a Spanish officer of Irish origin who became governor of Chile and later viceroy of Peru; his mother was Isabel Riquelme, a prominent lady of Chillán.Bernardo's father had only indirect contact with his son, who used his maternal surname until his fathe...
</Question>
<Choice>O'Higgins, Bernardo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
second president of Uruguay (1835–38), a member of the Treinta y Tres Orientales, the legendary 33 nationalists who successfully fought for Uruguayan independence in the Cisplatine War (1825–28).Although he had been allied with José Fructuoso Rivera, the first president of Uruguay, their ambitions eventually clashed. As president, Oribe sought to extend government control over rural districts ruled by Rivera. Angered by this challenge and by accusations of financial mismanagement during his term in office, Rivera rose in revolt in 1836, eventually forcing Oribe's resignation in October 1838. O...
</Question>
<Choice>Oribe, Manuel Ceferino</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first king of the modern Greek state (1832–62), who governed his country autocratically until he was forced to become a constitutional monarch in 1843. Attempting to increase Greek territory at the expense of Turkey, he failed and was overthrown.The second son of King Louis I of Bavaria, Otto was chosen king of Greece by the great powers at the conference of London in May 1832. The Greek National Assembly confirmed his selection in August 1832, and he arrived in Greece on Feb. 6, 1833, accompanied by several Bavarian advisers. He instituted a new legal code and organized a regular army, but th...
</Question>
<Choice>Otto</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Venezuelan soldier and politician, a leader in the country's independence movement and its first president. In the crucial early years of Venezuelan independence, he led the country as a dictator.Páez was a mestizo (mixed American Indian and European ancestry) llanero, one of the horsemen of the plains. Beginning as a ranch hand, he quickly acquired both land and cattle. In 1810 he joined the revolutionary movement against Spain as the leader of a band of llaneros. Becoming chief Venezuelan commander to Simón Bolívar, the liberator of northern South America, Páez and his men helped secure vict...
</Question>
<Choice>Páez, José Antonio</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
a dominant political figure in Australia during the second half of the 19th century, often called the father of Australian federation. He served five terms as premier of New South Wales between 1872 and 1891.Parkes became politically prominent in 1849 as a spokesman for ending the transportation of convicts to Australia from England. The following year he launched the Empire, a newspaper he ran until 1858 and through which he campaigned for fully representative government. He first held public office in 1854 and served almost without interruption as a representative and often as a minister or...
</Question>
<Choice>Parkes, Sir Henry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
founder of the Brazilian empire and first emperor of Brazil, from Dec. 1, 1822, to April 7, 1831, also reckoned as King Pedro (Peter) IV of Portugal.Generally known as Dom Pedro, he was the son of King John VI of Portugal. When Napoleon conquered Portugal in 1807, Pedro accompanied the royal family in its flight to Brazil. He remained there as regent when King John returned to Portugal in 1821.Pedro surrounded himself with ministers who counseled independence. When the Portuguese Cortês (Parliament), preferring colonial status for Brazil, demanded that Pedro return to Lisbon to “complete his p...
</Question>
<Choice>Pedro I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
second and last emperor of Brazil (1831–89), whose benevolent and popular reign lasted nearly 50 years.On April 7, 1831, when he was five years old, his father, Pedro I (Pedro, or Peter, IV of Portugal), abdicated in his favour; and for nine years Brazil was governed by a turbulent regency. To restore political stability, Pedro was declared of age on July 23, 1840, and crowned emperor on July 18, 1841. Although the disturbances in the provinces that had plagued the regency continued for the next five years, the young emperor's intellectual curiosity and profound concern for his subjects soon b...
</Question>
<Choice>Pedro II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British prime minister (1834–35, 1841–46) and founder of the Conservative Party. Peel was responsible for the repeal (1846) of the Corn Laws that had restricted imports.
</Question>
<Choice>Peel, Sir Robert, 2nd Baronet</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
lawyer, politician, and British prime minister from 1809 until his assassination in 1812.The second son of the 2nd Earl of Egmont, Perceval was educated at Harrow and at Trinity College, Cambridge. He was called to the bar by Lincoln's Inn in 1786 and became a king's counsel in 1796. In that same year he entered Parliament, where his rise to power was facilitated through his contacts with William Pitt the Younger. On the formation of the government of Henry Addington (1801–04), which succeeded that of Pitt, he was appointed solicitor general. From 1802 and through Pitt's second administration...
</Question>
<Choice>Perceval, Spencer</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Haitian independence leader and president, remembered by the Haitian people for his liberal rule and by South Americans for his support of Simón Bolívar during the struggle for independence from Spain.The son of a wealthy French colonist and a mulatto, Pétion served in the French colonial army before the French Revolution and then joined the revolutionary troops of Toussaint Louverture and, later, those of the mulatto general André Rigaud. Fleeing to France after Toussaint defeated Rigaud, who had set up a mulatto state in the southern provinces, Pétion returned in 1802 with the French army se...
</Question>
<Choice>Pétion, Alexandre Sabès</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
14th president of the United States (1853–57). He failed to deal effectively with the corroding sectional controversy over slavery in the decade preceding the American Civil War (1861–65). (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America.)The son of a governor of New Hampshire, Benjamin Pierce, and the former Anna Kendrick, Franklin Pierce attended Bowdoin College in Maine, studied law in Northampton, Massachusetts, and was admitted to the bar in 1827. He married Jane Means Appleton, whose father was president of Bowdoin, in 1834.Pier...
</Question>
<Choice>Pierce, Franklin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
11th president of the United States (1845–49). Under his leadership the United States fought the Mexican War (1846–48) and acquired vast territories along the Pacific coast and in the Southwest. (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America.)
</Question>
<Choice>Polk, James K.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chilean politician and for seven years virtual dictator who was instrumental in establishing political order and instituting economic progress in Chile. Disliked by some Chileans during his lifetime, he became a symbol of Chilean unity after his death.Born into a middle-class family, Portales amassed a small fortune early in life. In 1824 he was awarded a monopoly on tobacco, tea, and liquors that proved immensely profitable but aroused the anger of the Chilean landowners. Upon termination of the monopoly after a few years, Portales founded two newspapers to expound his authoritarian doctrines...
</Question>
<Choice>Portales, Diego</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Boer statesman, soldier, and founder of the town of Pretoria (1855). He was the first president of the South African Republic and also served as president of the Orange Free State, the only man to hold both offices. His plans to unite the sister republics, however, failed.Marthinus, the eldest son of the Great Trek leader Andries Pretorius, was a man of little formal education. He joined his father in the conquest of Natal in1838, in which he fought against the Zulus. When his father, whom he had accompanied north to the Transvaal, died in 1853, Marthinus succeeded him as commandant general of...
</Question>
<Choice>Pretorius, Marthinus Wessel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
also called Phraphutthaloetla Naphalai the second ruler (1809–24) of the present Chakkri dynasty, under whose rule relations were reopened with the West and Siam began a forward policy on the Malay peninsula. A gifted poet and dramatist, Rama II wrote a famous version of Inao, dramatic version of a popular traditional story, as well as episodes of the Ramakien and popular dance dramas such as Sang Thong.
</Question>
<Choice>Rama II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
also called Phranangklao king of Siam (1824–51) who made Siam's first tentative accommodations with the West, and under whom the country's boundaries reached their maximum extent.Rama III was the eldest son of King Rama II by a royal concubine, and in his youth he was given responsibility for overseeing foreign trade and relations. On his father's death in 1824, Rama III was much older and more experienced than his younger brother Mongkut (q.v.; who because he was born of a queen had a stronger claim on the throne), and the accession council chose him to succeed to the throne. His earlier expe...
</Question>
<Choice>Rama III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
founder and maharaja (1801–39) of the Sikh kingdom of the Punjab.Ranjit Singh was the only child of Maha Singh, on whose death in 1792 he became chief of the Shukerchakias, a Sikh group. His inheritance included Gujranwala town and the surrounding villages, now in Pakistan. At 15 he married the daughter of a chieftain of the Kanhayas, and for many years his affairs were directed by his ambitious mother-in-law, the widow Sada Kaur. A second marriage, to a girl of the Nakkais, made Ranjit Singh preeminent among the clans of the Sikh confederacy.In July 1799 he seized Lahore, the capital of the P...
</Question>
<Choice>Ranjit Singh</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
a principal chief of the Oglala Teton Dakota (Sioux), who successfully resisted (1865–67) the U.S. government's development of the Bozeman Trail to newly discovered goldfields in Montana Territory.Red Cloud had no hereditary title of his own but emerged as a natural leader and spokesman of his people through the force of his own character and through bravery in battle. Determined to protect the Indians' prime hunting grounds, Red Cloud in 1865 led the opposition of both Sioux and Cheyenne when the U.S. government began to build and fortify a road from Fort Laramie, in present Wyoming, by way o...
</Question>
<Choice>Red Cloud</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Seneca chief whose magnificent oratory masked his schemes to maintain his position despite double-dealing against his people's interests. His first Indian name was Otetiani, and he assumed the name Sagoyewatha upon becoming a chief. “Red Jacket” was his English name, a result of the succession of red coats he wore while on the British side during the American Revolution.Red Jacket retreated at the approach of General John Sullivan's American troops in 1779, and he even attempted to conclude a separate peace with the Americans. For these actions, Red Jacket was considered a coward by many of hi...
</Question>
<Choice>Red Jacket</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
financier, statesman, and empire builder of British South Africa. He was prime minister of Cape Colony (1890–96) and organizer of the giant diamond-mining company De Beers Consolidated Mines, Ltd. (1888). By his will he established the Rhodes scholarships at Oxford (1902).
</Question>
<Choice>Rhodes, Cecil</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first president of the Argentine republic. Although one of his country's ablest leaders, he was unable to unite the warring provinces or to control the provincial caudillos (bosses).Active in resistance to British invasion in 1806, he also supported the 1810 movement for independence from Spain, becoming secretary to the revolutionary junta. In 1811 he dominated the revolutionary triumvirate—organizing the militia, disbanding the Spanish courts, freeing the press from censorship, and ending the slave trade. In 1814 he was sent to Europe to secure British aid for the United Provinces of La Plat...
</Question>
<Choice>Rivadavia, Bernardino</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American-born, first president of Liberia (1848–56).A native of Virginia, Roberts was the son of free “blacks” whose heritage was more than seven-eighths white. At the age of 20 he immigrated to Liberia with his mother and younger brothers, became a merchant, and also became an unofficial aide to the white governor of the colony, Thomas H. Buchanan, a member of the American Colonization Society, which sought the return of American freedmen to Africa. On Buchanan's death in 1842, Roberts was appointed the first black governor of the colony.In efforts to establish the political and economic stab...
</Question>
<Choice>Roberts, Joseph Jenkins</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prime minister of Great Britain from August 1827 to January 1828. He received from the radical journalist William Cobbett the sardonic nicknames “Prosperity Robinson” (for his unwarranted optimism on the eve of the 1825 economic crisis) and “Goody Goderich.”Educated at Harrow and Cambridge, he began his political career as private secretary to the lord lieutenant of Ireland and rose to be president of the Board of Trade (1818–23) and chancellor of the Exchequer (1823–27). In George Canning's ministry (April–August 1827) he was secretary for war and the colonies and leader of the House of Lords...
</Question>
<Choice>Robinson, Frederick John, 1st Earl of Ripon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Cherokee chief who, after devoting his life to resisting U.S. seizure of his people's lands in Georgia, was forced to assume the painful task of shepherding the Cherokees in their removal to the Oklahoma Territory.Born of a Scottish father and a mother who was part Cherokee, the blue-eyed, fair-skinned Tsan-Usdi (Little John) grew up as an Indian, although he was educated at Kingston Academy in Tennessee. In the early 19th century he became the leader of the Cherokee resistance to the white man's acquisition of their valuable land, some 43,000 square miles (111,000 square kilometres) on which...
</Question>
<Choice>Ross, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French statesman who had some success in balancing the budget during periods of his seven terms as minister of finance and two terms as premier.Having launched the republican journal L'Égalité in 1870, Rouvier, a supporter of Léon Gambetta—one of the founding fathers of the Third Republic—served as deputy in the National Assembly from 1871 to 1902. A financial technician, he served on budget commissions, often as chairman, and as minister for commerce and the colonies (1881–82) and for commerce (1884–85). Resisting pressure from rightists to include General Georges Boulanger in his cabinet, Ro...
</Question>
<Choice>Rouvier, Maurice</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
also called (until 1861) Lord John Russellprime minister of Great Britain (1846–52, 1865–66), an aristocratic liberal and leader of the fight for passage of the Reform Bill of 1832.Russell was the third son of John Russell, 6th Duke of Bedford. (As the younger son of a peer, he was known for most of his life as Lord John Russell; he himself was created earl in 1861.) He thus came of a family that had long demonstrated its public spirit. The depth of his liberalism probably owed much to an untypical education. Poor health forbade the rigours of an English public school, and later, his father, w...
</Question>
<Choice>Russell, John, 1st Earl Russell</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
seven-time prime minister of Spain (1871–72, 1874, 1881–83, 1885–90, 1892–95, 1897–99, 1901–02).Born into a family of modest means, Sagasta became an engineer. He was exiled twice for opposing Queen Isabella II's rule but returned in 1868 to help in the revolution that overthrew her. From 1880 he led the new Liberal Party. His attempt to conciliate both the Cubans and the United States by a tardy offer of Cuban home rule, along with other concessions, did not avert the disastrous Spanish-American War, and Spaniards criticized him for the humiliating peace treaty.
</Question>
<Choice>Sagasta, Práxedes Mateo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
ruler of Muscat and Oman and of Zanzibar (1806–56), who made Zanzibar the principal power in East Africa and the commercial capital of the western Indian Ocean.
</Question>
<Choice>Sa'id ibn Sultan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Muslim reformer and military leader who founded a powerful kingdom in West Africa and resisted French colonial expansion in the late 19th century.In 1868 Samory, a member of the Mande group, proclaimed himself a religious chief and led a band of warriors in establishing a powerful chiefdom in the Kankan region of Guinea. A gifted commander and administrator, he expanded his rule until at its height in the early 1880s it extended from the Upper Volta region in the west to the Fouta Djallon in the east.Samory opposed French ambitions to build an empire in West Africa. He first fought the French...
</Question>
<Choice>Samory</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
army officer and statesman who was the storm centre of Mexico's politics during such events as the Texas revolt (1836) and the Mexican-American War (1846–48).The son of a minor colonial official, Santa Anna served in the Spanish army and rose to the rank of captain. He fought on both sides of nearly every issue of the day. In 1821 he supported Agustín de Iturbide and the war for Mexican independence, but in 1823 he helped overthrow Iturbide. In 1828 he backed Vicente Guerrero for president, only to help depose him later.Santa Anna gained much prestige in 1829 when he fought against Spain's att...
</Question>
<Choice>Santa Anna, Antonio López de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
soldier and statesman who fought beside Simón Bolívar in the war for South American independence and who served as president of the newly formed New Granada (Colombia) from 1833 until 1837.Santander left law school in 1810 to join the patriot army and was promoted rapidly. He escaped the Spanish reconquest of 1816 by fleeing to the eastern lowlands and returned in 1819 as brigadier general in Bolívar's invading force. Santander remained as vice president of New Granada in the Republic of Colombia, or Gran Colombia (which also included Venezuela and Ecuador). During much of the time before 1827...
</Question>
<Choice>Santander, Francisco de Paula</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
educator, statesman, and writer who rose from a position as a rural schoolmaster to become president of Argentina (1868–74). As president, he laid the foundation for later national progress by fostering public education, stimulating the growth of commerce and agriculture, and encouraging the development of rapid transportation and communication. As a writer, he is best remembered for his sociological-biographical study Civilización y barbarie: vida de Juan Facundo Quiroga, y aspecto físico, costumbres, y hábitos de la República Argentina (1845; Life in the Argentine Republic in the Days of the...
</Question>
<Choice>Sarmiento, Domingo Faustino</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian statesman who restored the Habsburg empire as a great European power after its almost complete collapse during the revolutions of 1848–49.Entering the Austrian army in 1818, Schwarzenberg transferred to the diplomatic service in 1824 and became a protégé of the chief minister Prince Klemens von Metternich, serving in the Austrian embassies to Portugal, Russia, France, England, Sardinia, and the Two Sicilies.With the outbreak of the 1848 revolutions in Italy, Schwarzenberg joined the Austrian army of Field Marshal Joseph, Count Radetzky, in northern Italy and was wounded at Goito. When...
</Question>
<Choice>Schwarzenberg, Felix, Prince zu</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
New Zealand statesman who as prime minister (1893–1906) led a Liberal Party ministry that sponsored innovating legislation for land settlement, labour protection, and old age pensions.After working in iron foundries in England, Seddon went to Australia in 1863 to work at the Bendigo goldfields in Victoria. He moved to Hokitika, N.Z., in 1866, again for gold mining, and in 1869 he became an advocate for miners in goldfield disputes. His prominence in local politics gained him a seat in Parliament in 1879. Serving as minister of mines and public works in the Liberal ministry of John Ballance (18...
</Question>
<Choice>Seddon, Richard John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
one of the chief military politicians of 19th-century Spain. He played an important part in the Revolution of 1868, which dethroned the Bourbon Spanish queen Isabella II.Serrano joined the army at the age of 12 and fought with the forces of Isabella II against her uncle Don Carlos (First Carlist War, 1833–39). He later came to exercise influence on the queen but was eventually removed from court. He took part in the successful revolution by the moderate General Leopoldo O'Donnell in 1854. He served as captain general of Cuba (1859–62), and in 1867, upon the death of O'Donnell, Serrano succeede...
</Question>
<Choice>Serrano y Domínguez, Francisco, duque de la Torre</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British colonizer and politician who served as the first premier of New Zealand (1856) after the colony had been granted responsible government.As a solicitor in London he became secretary and deputy chairman of the Canterbury Association for the Colonisation of New Zealand and was sent out to New Zealand in 1852. He remained in the colony, opened a solicitor's office, and became a member of the House of Representatives in 1854.Sewell became prime minister on May 7, 1856, but he resigned on May 13 because his ministry failed to obtain sufficient support in the House. He later served as colonia...
</Question>
<Choice>Sewell, Henry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Zulu chief (1816–28), founder of Southern Africa's Zulu Empire. He is credited with creating a fighting force that devastated the entire region. His life is the subject of numerous colourful and exaggerated stories, many of which are debated by historians.
</Question>
<Choice>Shaka</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
emir of Afghanistan from 1863 to 1879 who tried with only limited success to maintain his nation's equilibrium in the great power struggles between Russia in the north and British India in the south.The third son of Dost Mo?ammad Khan, Shir ?Ali succeeded to the throne upon his father's death. Only after a bewildering series of intra-family struggles, revolts, and civil war, however, was his hold on the throne secure.Shir ?Ali attempted to maintain Afghanistan as a noninvolved buffer state in the continuing conflicts between Russia and Great Britain. The British finally concluded, however, tha...
</Question>
<Choice>Shir 'Ali Khan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British prime minister from March 1801 to May 1804. Honest but unimaginative and inflexibly conservative, he proved unable to cope with the problems of the Napoleonic Wars, and later, in his decade as home secretary, he made himself unpopular by his harsh measures against political and economic malcontents.The son of a prominent physician who treated the Earl of Chatham (William Pitt the Elder), Addington was a friend of the younger Pitt from childhood. A member of the House of Commons from 1784, he became its speaker in 1789. The younger Pitt, whose position favouring Roman Catholic emancipat...
</Question>
<Choice>Sidmouth, Henry Addington, 1st Viscount</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Teton Dakota Indian chief under whom the Sioux tribes united in their struggle for survival on the North American Great Plains. He is remembered for his lifelong distrust of white men and his stubborn determination to resist their domination.Sitting Bull was born into the Hunkpapa division of the Teton Sioux. He joined his first war party at age 14 and soon gained a reputation for fearlessness in battle. He became a leader of the powerful Strong Heart warrior society and, later, was a participant in the Silent Eaters, a select group concerned with tribal welfare. As a tribal leader Sitting Bul...
</Question>
<Choice>Sitting Bull</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Haitian slave, president, and later emperor of Haiti, who represented the black majority of the country against the mulatto elite.Soulouque was born a slave while Haiti was still under French rule. He participated in a successful revolt in 1803 that expelled the French, and he remained in the army of the newly formed nation. In 1847 he was named president, with the backing of a group of mulatto leaders who thought he would be a suitable puppet leader. In 1849, however, he ousted them and created a following of his own. He adopted the title of emperor and ruled as Faustin I.Soulouque made sever...
</Question>
<Choice>Soulouque, Faustin-Élie</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman who from 1887 to 1894 served as the despotic prime minister of Bulgaria; he was often referred to as the Bulgarian Bismarck.The son of an innkeeper, Stambolov early joined the Bulgarian underground revolutionary movement against Turkish rule and led small anti-Turkish risings in 1875 and 1876. He fought with Bulgarian irregulars against Turkey in the Russo-Turkish War (1877–78), and, soon after Bulgaria gained autonomy in 1878, he was elected to the new Bulgarian assembly (Sobranye). Elected president of the assembly in 1884, he successfully urged upon Bulgaria's prince, Alexander I,...
</Question>
<Choice>Stambolov, Stefan Nikolov</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(imperial baron of)Rhinelander-born Prussian statesman, chief minister of Prussia (1807–08), and personal counselor to the Russian tsar Alexander I (1812–15). He sponsored widespread reforms in Prussia during the Napoleonic Wars and influenced the formation of the last European coalition against Napoleon.
</Question>
<Choice>Stein, Karl, Reichsfreiherr vom und zum</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
liberator of Ecuador and Peru, and one of the most respected leaders of the Latin American wars for independence from Spain. He served as Simón Bolívar's chief lieutenant and eventually became the first constitutionally elected leader of Bolivia.At the age of 15 Sucre entered the struggles for independence in Venezuela and Colombia. He displayed great skill at military tactics, and by 1820 he had become chief of staff to the Venezuelan leader of Latin American revolt against Spanish rule, Simón Bolívar. That same year he was promoted by Bolívar to the rank of general and assigned to free south...
</Question>
<Choice>Sucre, Antonio José de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
father of the Korean king Kojong.As regent from 1864 to 1873, Taewon-gun inaugurated a far-ranging reform program to strengthen the central administration; he modernized and increased its armies and rationalized the administration. Opposed to any concessions to Japan or the West, Taewon-gun, though out of power, helped organize the anti-Japanese outbreak in 1882. Considered a troublemaker, he was then kidnapped and taken to China for three years. By the time he returned, his power and many of his reforms had been eliminated.
</Question>
<Choice>Taewon-gun</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
reign name (nianhao) of the sixth emperor of the Qing dynasty of China, during whose reign (1820–50) attempts to prevent governmental decline met with little success.The monarch ascended the throne in 1820, assuming the reign name Daoguang in 1821. The imperial treasury had been greatly depleted during previous reigns, and he tried to restore China's finances by personal austerity. The need to repair the dikes along the Huang He (Yellow River) to prevent flooding and further famine became urgent, as did repair of the Grand Canal, which brought rice from South China to the capital at Beijing. Y...
</Question>
<Choice>Tao-kuang</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
12th president of the United States (1849–50). Elected on the ticket of the Whig Party as a hero of the Mexican-American War (1846–48), he died only 16 months after taking office. (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America.)Taylor's parents, Richard Taylor and Mary Strother, migrated to Kentucky from Virginia shortly after Zachary, the third of their nine children, was born. After spending his boyhood on the Kentucky frontier, Taylor enlisted in the army in 1806 and was commissioned first lieutenant in the infantry in 1808. In 1...
</Question>
<Choice>Taylor, Zachary</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Shawnee Indian chief, orator, military leader, and advocate of intertribal Indian alliance who directed Indian resistance to white rule in the Ohio River valley. In the War of 1812 he joined British forces for the capture of Detroit and the invasion of Ohio. A decisive battle against William Henry Harrison's U.S. troops ended in Tecumseh's defeat and death.
</Question>
<Choice>Tecumseh</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English Whig-Liberal statesman whose long career, including many years as British foreign secretary (1830–34, 1835–41, 1846–51) and prime minister (1855–58, 1859–65), made him a symbol of British nationalism.
</Question>
<Choice>Temple, Henry John, 3rd Viscount Palmerston</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
emperor of Ethiopia (1855–68) who has been called Ethiopia's first modern ruler. Not only did he reunify the various Ethiopian kingdoms into one empire, but he also attempted to focus loyalty around the government rather than the Ethiopian church, which he sought to bring under royal control. He worked to abolish the feudal system and create a new nobility of merit, dependent on the ruler alone. Although he failed in these aims, his example was ultimately followed by his successors.Not of noble birth, Tewodros came to the throne through warfare against the feudal chiefs. One of his first acts...
</Question>
<Choice>Tewodros II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
last king of Burma, whose short reign (1878–85) ended with the occupation of Upper Burma by the British.Thibaw was a younger son of King Mindon (reigned 1853–78) and studied (1875–77) in a Buddhist monastery. As king he was strongly influenced by his wife, Supayalat, and her mother, and his accession to the throne was accompanied by much violence and civil strife. In an attempt to enlist the aid of the French against the British, who had annexed Lower Burma during his father's reign, Thibaw's government sent a mission to Paris in 1883. Two years later a commercial treaty was concluded, and a F...
</Question>
<Choice>Thibaw</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French statesman, journalist, and historian, a founder and the first president (1871–73) of the Third Republic. His historical works include a 10-volume Histoire de la révolution française and a 20-volume Histoire du consulat et de l'empire.
</Question>
<Choice>Thiers, Adolphe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
jurist and statesman who was premier of Canada from 1892 to 1894.Thompson was called to the bar in Nova Scotia in 1865 and appointed queen's counsellor in 1879. He entered politics in 1877 as Liberal-Conservative member for Antigonish in the provincial legislature, becoming attorney general in 1878; he became premier of Nova Scotia in 1882 but was defeated in the same year. After serving as judge in the provincial Supreme Court, he was appointed minister of justice in 1885 in Sir John Macdonald's federal administration, having been elected to the Dominion Parliament for Antigonish.Thompson suc...
</Question>
<Choice>Thompson, Sir John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
leading Dutch political figure of the mid-19th century who, as prime minister (1849–53, 1862–66, 1871–72), consolidated the parliamentary system created by the constitution of 1848.Thorbecke began his career as a lecturer at universities in Germany and the Low Countries, and he published treatises on history and law. His liberal ideas, influenced by the historical-juridical school of the German scholar Friedrich Karl von Savigny, were expressed in his Aanteekening op de grondwet (1839; “A Note on the Constitution”). He was the chief author of the constitution of 1848, which transformed The Net...
</Question>
<Choice>Thorbecke, Johan Rudolf</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hungarian statesman and longtime premier who led the coalition that ruled Hungary for the last 30 years of his life. He made his country a strong, unified, and economically viable state within the Austro-Hungarian system of dual government.A member of an old Calvinist landowning family, Tisza participated in the first Hungarian parliamentary government during the Revolution of 1848–49. Exiled after the restoration of Austrian rule, he returned to Hungary and took a major part in the struggle for Hungarian national autonomy within the Austro-Hungarian system of dual government. At a time of eco...
</Question>
<Choice>Tisza, Kálmán</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the last Tokugawa shogun of Japan, who helped make the Meiji Restoration (1868)—the overthrow of the shogunate and restoration of power to the emperor—a relatively peaceful transition.Born into the ruling Tokugawa family, Keiki was the son of Tokugawa Nariaki, who was the head of the feudal fief of Mito. The Hitotsubashi family, a Tokugawa branch that, like the Mito extension, was eligible to succeed to the shogunate, had no male heirs during this period. Thus, when Keiki, seventh son of Nariaki, was adopted into the Hitotsubashi family, he greatly increased his chance to succeed to the shogun...
</Question>
<Choice>Tokugawa Yoshinobu</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman who sought with limited success to foster broad-scale national development in Greece during the last quarter of the 19th century. Together with a rival, Theódoros Dhiliyiánnis, he dominated Greek politics during this period.Trikoúpis studied literature and law in Athens (Modern Greek: Athína) and Paris before entering the Greek diplomatic service. In 1862 he represented the Greek community of London at the Constituent Assembly in Athens; elected to the Chamber of Deputies in 1865, he was appointed foreign minister the next year.Trikoúpis sought to develop resources and an industrial...
</Question>
<Choice>Trikoúpis, Kharílaos</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
emperor of Vietnam who followed a policy of conservatism and isolation and whose persecution of Christian missionaries foreshadowed the French conquest of Vietnam.The son of Emperor Thieu Tri, Prince Nguyen Phuoc Hoang Nham was chosen over his older brother to succeed his father. He ascended the throne in 1847, taking the reigning name Tu Duc. He continued his father's persecution of missionaries and opposition to trading and diplomatic relations with European powers. Executions reached such proportions that the French in 1856 sent a formal letter of protest to the court of Hue.The decapitatio...
</Question>
<Choice>Tu Duc</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
reign name (niaohao) of the eighth emperor (reigned 1861–1874/75) of the Qing dynasty (1644–1911/12), during whose reign occurred a short revitalization of the beleaguered Qing government, known as the Tongzhi Restoration.Ascending the throne at the age of five (six by Chinese reckoning), the young ruler assumed the reign title of Tongzhi (“Union for Order”). He ruled under the regency of a triumvirate that was headed by his mother, the empress dowager Cixi (1835–1908).The restoration under the Tongzhi emperor followed the examples of the great restorations in the middle of the Han (206 BC–AD...
</Question>
<Choice>T'ung-chih</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
premier of Nova Scotia from 1864 to 1867 and prime minister of Canada in 1896, who was responsible for the legislation that made Nova Scotia a province of Canada in 1867. As Canada's minister of railways and canals (1879–84), Tupper introduced the bill giving the Canadian Pacific Railway its charter in 1881.In 1855 Tupper, a physician by occupation, was elected to the Nova Scotia Legislative Assembly. He became provincial secretary (1857–60, 1863–67) and later premier. Tupper was interested in the union of the British North American provinces, and he worked to make Nova Scotia a province of Ca...
</Question>
<Choice>Tupper, Sir Charles, 1st Baronet</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
10th president of the United States (1841–45) who took office upon the death of President William Henry Harrison. A maverick Democrat who refused allegiance to the program of party leader Andrew Jackson, Tyler was rejected in office by both the Democratic Party and the Whig Party and functioned as a political independent. (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America.)Tyler was the son of John Tyler, member of the Virginia House of Delegates during the American Revolution and later governor of Virginia, and Mary Armistead. After gr...
</Question>
<Choice>Tyler, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
duke of Savoy and king of Italy who led his country out of its isolation and into the Triple Alliance with Austria-Hungary and Germany. He supported nationalistic and imperialistic policies that led to disaster for Italy and helped create the atmosphere in which he was assassinated.Having received a totally military education, Umberto first fought in the war against Austria (1866). The calm and decisive leadership he showed in saving his troops at the Italian debacle at Custoza (June 1866) won him great popularity. His marriage to his cousin Margherita Teresa Giovanna, princess of Savoy (April...
</Question>
<Choice>Umberto I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
eighth president of the United States (1837–41) and one of the founders of the Democratic Party. He was known as the “Little Magician” to his friends (and the “Sly Fox” to his enemies) in recognition of his reputed cunning and skill as a politician. (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America.)Van Buren was the son of Abraham Van Buren, a farmer and tavern keeper, and Maria Hoes Van Alen, both of Dutch descent. Apprenticed to the lawyer Francis Silvester in 1796, Van Buren began his own practice in Kinderhook in 1803. In 1807 he...
</Question>
<Choice>Van Buren, Martin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
duke of Aosta, duke of Savoy, and king of Sardinia (1802–21) on his brother Charles Emmanuel IV's abdication.He participated in the First Coalition against Revolutionary France (1792–97). All his dominions save Sardinia were occupied by the French during 1802–14. His kingdom was later restored, with the addition of Genoa, by the Final Act of the Congress of Vienna (June 9, 1815), but he abdicated (1821) in favour of another brother, Charles Felix.
</Question>
<Choice>Victor Emmanuel I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Sardinia–Piedmont who became the first king of a united Italy.Brought up in the court of his father, Charles Albert, and given a conventional monarchical education emphasizing religious and military training, he was married to his cousin Maria Adelaide, daughter of an Austrian archduke. After the Revolution of 1848, when war broke out with Austria, Victor Emmanuel was given command of a division. In the luckless campaign that followed he proved a brave soldier but an indifferent general.Ascending the throne on his father's abdication, he consolidated his position by suppressing the rep...
</Question>
<Choice>Victor Emmanuel II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
queen of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland (1837–1901) and empress of India (1876–1901). She was the last of the House of Hanover and gave her name to an era, the Victorian Age. During her reign the English monarchy took on its modern ceremonial character. She and her husband, Prince Consort Albert of Saxe-Coburg-Gotha, had nine children, through whose marriages were descended many of the royal families of Europe.Victoria first learned of her future role as a young princess during a history lesson when she was 10 years old. Almost four decades later Victoria's governess recalled...
</Question>
<Choice>Victoria</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mexican soldier and political leader who was the first president of the Mexican Republic.Victoria left law school to join the movement for independence from Spain, fighting under José María Morelos in 1812. He changed his name to show his devotion to the cause of Mexican independence (the image of the Virgin of Guadalupe, the patron saint of Mexico, had been adopted as a symbol of the insurgency). After the death of Morelos, Victoria waged guerrilla war against the Spaniards from the mountains around Veracruz and Puebla. When Agustín de Iturbide came to power (1821), Victoria at first supporte...
</Question>
<Choice>Victoria, Guadalupe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
New Zealand statesman, journalist, and businessman known for his bold project to regenerate New Zealand's economy in the 1870s through large-scale public works financed by British loans.Attracted by gold discoveries in Victoria, Vogel emigrated to Australia in 1852 and became successful in business and journalism. He moved to Otago, N.Z., in 1861 after being badly defeated for public office and soon guided the Otago Daily Times to a leading position in the colony. Elected to Parliament in 1863, he led the opposition (1865–68) and became colonial treasurer in 1869 in the ministry of William Fox...
</Question>
<Choice>Vogel, Sir Julius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician who, as premier of France, settled the Dreyfus Affair. He was also responsible for the legalization of trade unions in France (1884).A rising conservative lawyer, known for his eloquence and mastery of legal detail, Waldeck-Rousseau was elected a deputy in 1879. In 1881 he became minister of the interior in the Cabinet of Léon Gambetta, one of the founders of the Third Republic, and he filled the same post, under Jules Ferry, from 1883 to 1885. In 1884 he sponsored the Loi Waldeck-Rousseau, which made trade unions legal, though with important restrictions. After another term as depu...
</Question>
<Choice>Waldeck-Rousseau, René</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
adventurer, filibuster, and revolutionary leader who succeeded in making himself president of Nicaragua (1856–57).In 1850 he migrated to California, where his interest in a colonization scheme in Lower California developed into filibustering plans. On Oct. 15, 1853, he sailed from San Francisco with a small force. After landing at La Paz, he proclaimed Lower California and Sonora an independent republic. Lack of supplies and Mexican resistance forced him back to the United States in May 1854. Exactly a year later he sailed again, this time to Nicaragua at the invitation of a revolutionary fact...
</Question>
<Choice>Walker, William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British army commander during the Napoleonic Wars and later prime minister of Great Britain (1828–30). He first rose to military prominence in India, won successes in the Peninsular War in Spain (1808–14), and shared in the victory over Napoleon at the Battle of Waterloo (1815).Wellington twice reached the zenith of fame with a period of unexampled odium intervening. By defeating Napoleon at Waterloo he became the conqueror of the world's conqueror. After Waterloo he joined a repressive government, and later, as prime minister, he resisted pressure for constitutional reform. False pride, howev...
</Question>
<Choice>Wellesley, Arthur, 1st Duke of Wellington</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German emperor from 1871, as well as king of Prussia from 1861, a sovereign whose conscientiousness and self-restraint fitted him for collaboration with stronger statesmen in raising his monarchy and the house of Hohenzollern to predominance in Germany.He was the second son of the future king Frederick William III of Prussia. In 1814 he fought at Bar-sur-Aube in the German War of Liberation against Napoleon I. Subsequently he devoted himself to the Prussian Army and military affairs. In 1840, on the accession of his childless elder brother, Frederick William IV, he became prince of Prussia and...
</Question>
<Choice>William I (emperor of Germany)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of The Netherlands and grand duke of Luxembourg (1815–40) who sparked a commercial and industrial revival following the period of French rule (1795–1813), but provoked the Belgian revolt of 1830 through his autocratic methods.The son of William V, prince of Orange, William married Wilhelmina, daughter of his uncle, Frederick William II of Prussia, in 1791 and emigrated with his family to England in 1795 after the French invasion of the Dutch Republic. He gained title to the bishopric of Fulda and other smaller areas in Germany in negotiations with the French emperor Napoleon I in 1802 but...
</Question>
<Choice>William I (king of The Netherlands)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of The Netherlands and grand duke of Luxembourg (1840–49) whose reign saw the reestablishment of fiscal stability and the transformation of The Netherlands to a more liberal monarchy through the constitution of 1848.Exiled to England with his family in 1795, William served in the British Army (1811–12) as the Duke of Wellington's aide-de-camp in the Peninsular War (1808–14); he also commanded the Netherlands troops in the Battle of Waterloo (1815). In 1816 he married the grand duchess Anna Pavlovna, sister of the Russian emperor Alexander I. Popular in the southern or Belgian part of the...
</Question>
<Choice>William II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
conservative king of The Netherlands and grand duke of Luxembourg (1849–90) who was influential in forming Dutch ministries until 1868 but was unable to prevent liberal control of the government.The eldest son of King William II, William married his cousin Sophia, daughter of King William I of Württemberg, in 1839 and succeeded to the throne in 1849. He opposed the constitution of 1848, which created a parliamentary form of government, but was nevertheless forced to allow Johan Thorbecke, major proponent of the constitution, to head the new government. Thorbecke resigned in 1853 when William a...
</Question>
<Choice>William III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Great Britain and Ireland and king of Hanover from June 26, 1830. Personally opposed to parliamentary reform, he grudgingly accepted the epochal Reform Act of 1832, which, by transferring representation from depopulated “rotten boroughs” to industrialized districts, reduced the power of the British crown and the landowning aristocracy over the government.The third son of King George III, he entered the Royal Navy at the age of 13, fought in the American Revolution, and, while serving in the West Indies, formed a close friendship with the future naval hero Horatio (afterward Viscount) N...
</Question>
<Choice>William IV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
emperor of Ethiopia (1872–89). Like his predecessor, Tewodros II (reigned 1855–68), Yohannes IV was a strong, progressive ruler, but he spent most of his time repelling military threats from Egypt, Italy, and the Mahdists of the Sudan.Superior weaponry allowed Yohannes, a dejazmatch (earl) of Tigray in northern Ethiopia, to fight his way to the Ethiopian throne on January 21, 1872, four years after Tewodros's death. His main rival was Menilek II, king of Shewa, who did not recognize Yohannes as emperor until 1878/79, after a military defeat. Menilek's eclipse, however, was only temporary. In 1...
</Question>
<Choice>Yohannes IV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian prime minister from 1901 to 1903 and an associate of the early-20th-century liberal leader Giovanni Giolitti; Zanardelli was a champion of parliamentary rights and followed a conciliatory policy toward labour in a time of great unrest.A combatant in the volunteer corps during the war of 1848, he returned to Brescia after the defeat of Novara, and for a time earned a livelihood by teaching law, but was molested by the Austrian police and forbidden to teach because of his refusal to contribute pro-Austrian articles to the press. Elected deputy in 1859, he received various administrative...
</Question>
<Choice>Zanardelli, Giuseppe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
African king (reigned c. 1815–48) who led his Jere people on a monumental migration of more than 1,000 miles (1,600 km) that lasted more than 20 years. A leader of incomparable stature, he took his initially small group (later called the Ngoni) from its original home near modern Swaziland to the western part of present-day Tanzania, forming it into one of the most powerful kingdoms of eastern Africa.Around the turn of the 1820s, the Jere chieftaincy was involved in raiding associated with the slave trade at Delagoa Bay and at Inhambane. Zwangendaba, the son of the Jere chief Hlatshwayo, led a...
</Question>
<Choice>Zwangendaba</Choice>
</item>
</topics>