<topics>
<item>
<Question>
sultan of Morocco from 1894 to 1908, whose reign was marked by an unsuccessful attempt to introduce European administrative methods in an atmosphere of increasing foreign influence.Abd al-Aziz was proclaimed sultan upon the death of his father, Hassan I, but did not begin direct rule until after the death in 1900 of his grand vizier, Ba Ahmed (Ahmad ibn Musa). Upon his actual accession, Abd al-Aziz sought European advice in an attempt to modernize the country and in particular to reform the methods of taxation. These endeavours, defeated because of the complete lack of administrators trained i...
</Question>
<Choice>Abd al-Aziz</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
sultan of Morocco (1908–12), the brother of Sultan Abd al-Aziz, against whom he revolted beginning in 1907.Appointed caliph of Marrakech by Abd al-Aziz, Abd al-Hafid had no difficulty there in rousing the Muslim community against his brother's Western ways. With Marrakech his, Abd al-Hafid routed his brother's forces and pensioned off the sultan. Recognized as sultan by the Western powers (1909), Abd al-Hafid invoked French aid against another pretender in 1912 and then was forced to recognize a French protectorate over Morocco.
</Question>
<Choice>Abd al-Hafid</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ottoman sultan from 1876 to 1909, under whose autocratic rule the reform movement of Tanzimat (Reorganization) reached its climax and who adopted a policy of pan-Islamism in opposition to Western intervention in Ottoman affairs.A son of Sultan Abdülmecid I, he came to the throne at the deposition of his mentally deranged brother, Murad V, on Aug. 31, 1876. He promulgated the first Ottoman constitution on Dec. 23, 1876, primarily to ward off foreign intervention at a time when the Turks' savage suppression of the Bulgarian uprising (May 1876) and Ottoman successes in Serbia and Montenegro had a...
</Question>
<Choice>Abdülhamid II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman who became the first ruler (1946–51) of the Hashemite Kingdom of Jordan.?Abdullah, the second son of ?usayn ibn ?Ali, the ruler of the Hejaz, was educated in Istanbul in what was then the Ottoman Empire. After the Young Turk Revolution of 1908, he represented Mecca in the Ottoman parliament. Early in 1914 he joined the Arab nationalist movement, which sought independence for Arab territories in the Ottoman Empire. In 1915–16 he played a leading role in clandestine negotiations between the British in Egypt and his father that led to the proclamation (June 10, 1916) of the Arab revolt...
</Question>
<Choice>'Abdullah I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the first Social Credit Party premier of Alberta, during and after the Great Depression.Trained as a teacher, Aberhart was a high-school principal and Protestant lay preacher in Calgary, Alta. (1910–35). Beginning in the mid-1920s he became widely known as a radio evangelist, earning the sobriquet “Bible Bill.” In 1927 he founded the Calgary Prophetic Bible Institute and in 1932 employed his evangelical rhetoric in promoting the unorthodox Social Credit monetary-reform and political theories of the British economist C.H. Douglas.In order to solve economic problems and to build a new society, A...
</Question>
<Choice>Aberhart, William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the Belgians (1909–34), who led the Belgian army during World War I and guided his country's postwar recovery.The younger son of Philip, count of Flanders (brother of King Leopold II), Albert succeeded to the throne in 1909—Leopold's son and Albert's father and older brother having died earlier. Before World War I, Albert worked to strengthen the army, gaining passage in 1913 of a military conscription bill. He reaffirmed Belgian neutrality to France and Germany in the summer of 1914 and rejected the German emperor William II's ultimatum of Aug. 2, 1914, demanding free passage of Germa...
</Question>
<Choice>Albert I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish statesman, prime minister, and president of the Second Republic (1931–36), whose attempts to moderate the policies of the various factions led eventually to his deposition and exile.Elected to the Cortes (parliament) in 1905, Alcalá Zamora became minister of works in 1917 and minister of war in 1922. The Spanish defeat at Anual in Morocco led to an enquiry, as a result of which Gen. Primo de Rivera seized power, dissolved parliament, suppressed the report, and concluded the war. Alcalá Zamora blamed King Alfonso XIII for the dictatorship and became a republican, joining the socialists...
</Question>
<Choice>Alcalá Zamora, Niceto</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chilean president (1920–25, 1932–38) who early defended workers' groups, especially the nitrate miners of the north, but later, as a member of the Liberal Party, became more conservative.The son of an Italian immigrant, Alessandri was graduated in law from the University of Chile in 1893 and in 1897 was elected to the Chamber of Deputies. He was at various times minister of industry, minister of finance, congressman (six times), senator (twice), and president.Alessandri was elected president in 1920 as the candidate of a liberal coalition. After growing frustrated with Chile's largely conserva...
</Question>
<Choice>Alessandri Palma, Arturo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats, and Slovenes (1921–29) and of Yugoslavia (1929–34), who struggled to create a united state out of his politically and ethnically divided collection of nations.The second son of Peter Karadjordjevic (Karageorgevic, or Karaðorðevici)—king of Serbia 1903–18 and king of the Serbs, Croats, and Slovenes 1918–21—and Zorka of Montenegro, Alexander spent his early youth in Geneva with his father, then in exile from Serbia, and in 1899 went to St. Petersburg, where he entered the Russian imperial corps of pages in 1904. In 1909, however, when his elder brother renou...
</Question>
<Choice>Alexander I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish king (1902–31) who by authorizing a military dictatorship hastened his own deposition by advocates of the Second Republic.The posthumous son of Alfonso XII, Alfonso XIII was immediately proclaimed king under the regency of his mother, María Cristina. Although lively and intelligent, he was raised in an ultraclerical and reactionary atmosphere by his doting mother. He reacted early against the boredom of court life and began his lifelong attachment to the Spanish army. In 1902, on his 16th birthday, he assumed full authority as king.Alfonso relished his position of authority. He continu...
</Question>
<Choice>Alfonso XIII</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman and political leader who served as president of Argentina from 1922 until 1928.Alvear belonged to a distinguished Argentine family. He was educated at the University of Buenos Aires, where he received a doctor of jurisprudence degree. He was a cofounder in 1890 of the Radical Civic Union (UCR), the political party representing the liberal-democratic viewpoint in Argentina. He took part in revolutions of 1890, 1893, and 1905 that helped to establish liberal democracy in Argentina; he then served as minister of public works in 1911, as a member of Parliament in 1912–17, and as Argentin...
</Question>
<Choice>Alvear, Marcelo T. de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
ruler of Afghanistan (1919–29) who led his country to full independence from British influence.A favoured son of the Afghan ruler ?abibollah Khan, Amanollah took possession of the throne immediately after his father's assassination in 1919, at a time when Great Britain exercised an important influence on Afghan affairs. In his coronation address Amanollah declared total independence from Great Britain. This led to war with the British (seeAnglo-Afghan Wars), but fighting was confined to a series of skirmishes between an ineffective Afghan army and a British Indian army exhausted from the heavy...
</Question>
<Choice>Amanollah Khan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
eighth king of the Chakkri dynasty of Siam, whose mysterious death was one of the most traumatic events in the history of modern Thailand.Ananda was only 10 years old and a schoolboy in Switzerland when he succeeded his uncle, King Prajadhipok, in 1935. World War II prevented his return to Thailand to assume his constitutional duties until 1946. Shortly thereafter, early in the morning of June 9, he was found dead in his bed of a gunshot wound. The case was never fully explained, and the controversy over it contributed to the weakening of civilian constitutional government and helped precipita...
</Question>
<Choice>Ananda Mahidol</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Romanian marshal and statesman who became dictator of the pro-German government during World War II.After World War I, Antonescu served as military attaché in Paris and in London and, in 1934, as chief of the Romanian general staff. Named minister of defense in 1937, he retained office with the establishment of King Carol II's corporatist dictatorship (1938), only to be dismissed after a few weeks as a sympathizer of the principal Romanian fascist group, the Iron Guard. On the domestic front, he was an anticommunist and an anti-Semite, but he favoured France and Great Britain in international...
</Question>
<Choice>Antonescu, Ion</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Liberal prime minister of Great Britain (1908–16), who was responsible for the Parliament Act of 1911, limiting the power of the House of Lords, and who led Britain during the first two years of World War I.Asquith was the second son of Joseph Asquith, a small businessman in the wool trade and an ardent Congregationalist, who died in 1860. Asquith was educated at the City of London School from 1863 to 1870, when he won a classical scholarship at Balliol College, Oxford. At Balliol he obtained the highest academic honours, and he became a fellow of his college in 1874. Deciding upon a legal car...
</Question>
<Choice>Asquith, H H, 1st Earl Of Oxford And Asquith</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Turkish“Kemal, Father of Turks”soldier, statesman, and reformer who was the founder and first president (1923–38) of the Republic of Turkey. He modernized the country's legal and educational systems and encouraged the adoption of a European way of life, with Turkish written in the Latin alphabet and with citizens adopting European-style names.One of the great figures of the 20th century, Atatürk rescued the surviving Turkish remnant of the defeated Ottoman Empire at the end of World War I. He galvanized his people against invading Greek forces who sought to impose the Allied will upon the war-...
</Question>
<Choice>Atatürk, Kemal</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British Labour Party leader (1935–55) and prime minister (1945–51). He presided over the establishment of the welfare state in Great Britain and the granting of independence to India, the most important step in the conversion of the British Empire into the Commonwealth of Nations. He was perhaps the leading Labour politician of the 20th century. He transformed his party into the natural opponent of the Conservative Party and thus polarized British politics.
</Question>
<Choice>Attlee, Clement</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
soldier and moderate statesman whose presidency (1940–46) saw a consolidation of the social reforms of the Mexican Revolution and the beginning of an unprecedented period of friendship with the United States.Ávila Camacho joined the army of Venustiano Carranza in 1914 and rose rapidly through the ranks. A skilled organizer and administrator, he was appointed head of the Ministry of War and Navy under President Abelardo Rodríguez and minister of national defense under President Lázaro Cárdenas (1937). Resigning from his post in 1939, he won the nomination of the government party, the PRM (Parti...
</Question>
<Choice>Ávila Camacho, Manuel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish minister and president of the Second Republic whose attempts to fashion a moderately liberal government were halted by the outbreak of the Spanish Civil War.Azaña studied law in Madrid and became a civil servant, journalist, and writer, figuring prominently in Ateneo, a Madrid literary club. He translated George Borrow's The Bible in Spain and was awarded the national prize for literature in 1926 for his biography of the novelist Juan Valera. His novel El jardín de los frailes (1927; “The Garden of the Monks”) was a vehicle for his strongly anticlerical opinions.In 1930 he began to org...
</Question>
<Choice>Azaña y Díaz, Manuel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician who in 1937 became the first Burmese premier under British rule; he later was head of state in the pro-Japanese government during World War II (August 1943–May 1945).Ba Maw was educated at Rangoon College, Calcutta University, the University of Cambridge, and the University of Bordeaux, Fr., where he received a doctorate in 1924. Admitted to the English bar the same year, he first came into prominence as defense lawyer for the Burmese rebel leader Saya San in 1931.During the early 1930s Ba Maw became a prominent opponent of Britain's plan to remove Burma (Myanmar) from the jurisdict...
</Question>
<Choice>Ba Maw</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
general and statesman during the dictatorship of Benito Mussolini (1922–43). In September 1943 he extricated Italy from World War II by arranging an armistice with the Allies.Badoglio entered the Italian Army in 1890 as an artillery officer and fought in the Ethiopian campaign of 1896 and in the Italo-Turkish War (1911–12). In World War I he distinguished himself by planning and directing the capture of Monte Sabotino on August 6, 1916. Although his forces suffered defeat in the Battle of Caporetto on October 24, 1917, he emerged from the war a high-ranking general and conducted the armistice...
</Question>
<Choice>Badoglio, Pietro</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British Conservative politician, three times prime minister between 1923 and 1937; he headed the government during the General Strike of 1926, the Ethiopian crisis of 1935, and the abdication crisis of 1936.A relative of the author Rudyard Kipling and the painter Sir Edward Burne-Jones, Baldwin was the only son of Alfred Baldwin, chairman of the Great Western Railway and head of a large concern that included iron and steel manufactories and collieries. Young Baldwin was educated at Harrow and at Trinity College, Cambridge. He managed his father's diversified heavy industries for several years....
</Question>
<Choice>Baldwin, Stanley</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British statesman who maintained a position of power in the British Conservative Party for 50 years; he was prime minister from 1902 to 1905, and as foreign secretary from 1916 to 1919 he is perhaps best remembered for his World War I statement (the Balfour Declaration) expressing official British approval of Zionism.The son of James Maitland Balfour and a nephew of Robert Cecil, 3rd marquess of Salisbury, Balfour was a member of a highly intellectual, wealthy, and aristocratic circle. He was educated at Eton and at Trinity College, Cambridge, and, upon leaving Cambridge, he entered Parliament...
</Question>
<Choice>Balfour, Arthur James, 1st earl Balfour</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hungarian politician who played a key role in bringing his country into World War II as an ally of Germany.After completing his legal studies in 1913, Bárdossy entered the Hungarian civil service. In 1924 he became director of the press department of the Foreign Ministry; in 1930 he was appointed secretary at the embassy in London; and in 1934 he was made ambassador to Romania. Hungary's head of state, Admiral Miklós Horthy, made him foreign minister early in 1941. In December 1940 Hungary had concluded a treaty of “eternal friendship” with Yugoslavia. Adolf Hitler's demand for Hungarian help...
</Question>
<Choice>Bárdossy, László</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman who guided the Australian federation movement to a successful conclusion and became the first prime minister of the resulting commonwealth in 1901.Barton in 1879 entered the New South Wales Legislative Assembly, where he served as speaker (1883–87); he was attorney general in 1889 and 1891–93. In 1891 he assumed leadership of the federation movement and, in the federal convention of that year, helped shape the draft that became the foundation for the eventual commonwealth constitution. The constitution bill passed the New South Wales assembly in 1893, and for the next four years Bart...
</Question>
<Choice>Barton, Sir Edmund</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
soldier and political leader who twice ruled Cuba—first in 1933–44 with an efficient government and again in 1952–59 as a dictator, jailing his opponents, using terrorist methods, and making fortunes for himself and his associates.The son of impoverished farmers, Batista worked in a variety of jobs until he joined the army in 1921, starting as a stenographer. He rose to the rank of sergeant and developed a large personal following. In September 1933 he organized the “sergeants' revolt”; it toppled the provisional regime of Carlos Manuel de Céspedes, which had replaced the dictatorial regime of...
</Question>
<Choice>Batista, Fulgencio</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman who, as president of Uruguay (1903–07 and 1911–15), is generally credited with transforming his country into a stable democratic welfare state.Batlle y Ordóñez was the son of a president of Uruguay (1868–72), General Lorenzo Batlle, and a grandson of José Batlle y Carréo, a leading citizen of colonial Montevideo. He was educated at the University of Montevideo and at the Sorbonne. He began his political career on June 16, 1886, when he founded the newspaper El Día. Shortly thereafter he joined the Colorado Party, one of the two ruling political parties of Uruguay, and in 1890 he star...
</Question>
<Choice>Batlle y Ordóñez, José</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman, foreign minister, and president, a founder of modern Czechoslovakia who forged its Western-oriented foreign policy between World Wars I and II but capitulated to Hitler's demands during the Czech crisis of 1938.After studying at Prague, Paris, and Dijon, Beneš received a doctorate of laws in 1908 and taught at the Prague Commercial Academy and the Czech University of Prague before World War I. Influenced by the nationalist ideas of Tomáš Masaryk, who wished to liberate the Czechs and Slovaks from Austrian rule, Beneš followed his mentor to Switzerland during World War I and then est...
</Question>
<Choice>Beneš, Edvard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman and prime minister of Canada (1930–35) during the Great Depression.Bennett graduated from Dalhousie University with a degree in law in 1893 and practiced in his native province of New Brunswick. In 1897 he moved westward and entered politics, serving in the legislative assemblies of the Northwest Territories and Alberta. In 1911 he entered the Canadian House of Commons, representing Calgary, Alberta, and later became director general of national service (1916) and minister of justice (1921).Bennett became the leader of the Conservative Party in 1927 and prime minister after the 1930...
</Question>
<Choice>Bennett, Richard Bedford Bennett, Viscount</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish general who served briefly as prime minister (January 1930–February 1931) before the establishment of the Second Republic.Berenguer entered the army in 1889, served in Cuba and Morocco, and was promoted to general in 1909. He was minister of war in 1918 when, after a long interval, the army began to express its political views. He then served as high commissioner in Morocco, but he was held responsible for the disastrous defeat at Annual (Anwal) in 1921 and was removed from active service. In 1924 he was appointed head of King Alfonso XIII's military household. When the dictatorship of...
</Question>
<Choice>Berenguer, Dámaso, conde de Xauen</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German imperial chancellor before and during World War I who possessed talents for administration but not for governing.A member of a Frankfurt banking family, Bethmann Hollweg studied law at Strassburg, Leipzig, and Berlin and entered the civil service. He was appointed Prussian minister of the interior in 1905 and state secretary in the Imperial Office of the Interior in 1907. He succeeded Bernhard, Fürst (prince) von Bülow, who resigned as chancellor on July 14, 1909.Bethmann's domestic policies were mildly liberal for their time and place, but he almost invariably yielded to persons more e...
</Question>
<Choice>Bethmann Hollweg, Theobald von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the first Socialist (and the first Jewish) premier of France, presiding over the Popular Front coalition government in 1936–37.Blum was born into an Alsatian Jewish family. Educated at the École Normale Supérieure, he proceeded to study law at the Sorbonne, graduating in 1894 with the highest honours, and thereafter he made his name as a brilliant literary and dramatic critic. The Dreyfus affair brought him into active politics on the side of the republican Dreyfusards, and his close association with Jean Jaurès, whom he greatly admired, eventually led to his joining Jaurès's French Socialist...
</Question>
<Choice>Blum, Léon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman who served terms as Italian prime minister before and after the fascist regime of Benito Mussolini and who led the anti-Fascist movement during World War II.Elected to Parliament in 1909 as Socialist deputy for Mantua, he was expelled from the Socialist Party in 1912 with the reform leader Leonida Bissolati for his moderate, democratic views and for his support for the Libyan war. In response, Bonomi joined the Reformist Socialist group. During World War I he served as a volunteer and became war minister in 1920 in the government of Giovanni Giolitti, negotiating the Treaty of Rapall...
</Question>
<Choice>Bonomi, Ivanoe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
eighth prime minister of Canada (1911–20) and leader of the Conservative Party (1901–20), who played a decisive role—notably by insisting on separate Canadian membership in the League of Nations—in transforming the status of his country from that of colony to that of nation. He was knighted in 1914.Borden cut short his formal education before his 15th year, when he accepted the post of assistant master of the private school he was attending. His teaching career ended in 1874, when he became articled to a Halifax law firm. Admitted to the bar of Nova Scotia in 1878, he rose to a commanding posi...
</Question>
<Choice>Borden, Sir Robert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Bulgaria from 1918 to 1943, who during the last five years of his reign headed a thinly veiled royal dictatorship.The son of Ferdinand I of Bulgaria and Maria Luisa of Bourbon-Parma, Boris, despite his Roman Catholic parentage, was brought up in the Orthodox faith for political and dynastic reasons. He succeeded his father as king of Bulgaria when he abdicated Oct. 4, 1918. An opponent of Bulgaria's dictatorial prime minister, the Agrarian Union leader Aleksandur Stamboliyski, Boris is generally considered to have played some role in the coup that removed Stamboliyski from power in Jun...
</Question>
<Choice>Boris III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
soldier and statesman who was the first prime minister of the Union of South Africa (1910–19) and a staunch advocate of a policy of reconciliation between Boers and Britons, as well as of limiting the political rights of black South Africans.The son of a voortrekker (Boer pioneer settler of the interior), he grew up in the Orange Free State, where he received his only formal education at a German mission school. In 1884 he helped to found the New Republic in the Vryheid district in Zululand (now northern KwaZulu-Natal). There he purchased a farm and married Annie Emmett, granddaughter of an Ir...
</Question>
<Choice>Botha, Louis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French politician and statesman, an ardent promoter of the League of Nations, who was awarded the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1920.Trained in law, Bourgeois entered the civil service in 1876 and by 1887 had advanced to the position of prefect of police for the Seine département. In 1888 he was elected to the National Assembly as a deputy from the Marne district. After serving in a number of ministerial posts, he became premier (Nov. 1, 1895–April 21, 1896). Later, he was the head of the Radical-Socialist Party. He represented the Marne (1905–23) in the Senate and was its president from 1920 to 19...
</Question>
<Choice>Bourgeois, Léon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish statesman and pioneer of social democracy whose conciliatory international diplomacy in the first two decades of the 20th century was recognized by the award of the 1921 Nobel Prize for Peace, which he shared with Norwegian diplomat Christian Lous Lange.After studying science in Stockholm and Uppsala, Branting in 1883 began work for the radical newspaper Tiden, becoming its editor shortly thereafter. In 1886 he assumed the editorship of the Social-Demokraten, and, when the Social Democratic Party was formed in 1889, he was prominent among its founders. After the death of activist Axel...
</Question>
<Choice>Branting, Karl Hjalmar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman who served 11 times as premier of France, holding a total of 26 ministerial posts between 1906 and 1932. His efforts for international cooperation, the League of Nations, and world peace brought him the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1926, which he shared with Gustav Stresemann of Germany.As a law student, Briand became associated with left-wing causes, writing for such publications as Le Peuple, La Lanterne, and Petite République, and in 1904 he joined Jean Jaurès in founding L'Humanité. In 1894 Briand succeeded in getting the sharply divided French trade unionists to adopt the general st...
</Question>
<Choice>Briand, Aristide</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman and diplomat who was prime minister of Australia from 1923 to 1929. He then became his country's leading emissary to Great Britain.Bruce studied at the University of Cambridge and then practiced law in England. After serving in the British army during World War I, he entered the Australian Parliament in 1918 and was his country's representative to the League of Nations (1921). After serving as federal treasurer from 1921 to 1923, he became prime minister upon the resignation of William Morris Hughes, forming a coalition of the National and Country parties. During his administration,...
</Question>
<Choice>Bruce, Stanley Melbourne Bruce, Viscount</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
conservative German statesman who was chancellor and foreign minister shortly before Adolf Hitler came to power (1930–32). Unable to solve his country's economic problems, he hastened the drift toward rightist dictatorship by ignoring the Reichstag and governing by presidential decree.The son of an industrialist, Brüning received his doctorate from the University of Bonn in 1915 and then rose to the command of a machine-gun company in World War I. After the war he served as business manager of the League of German Trade Unions from 1920 to 1930. A Roman Catholic, Brüning was a member of the Ca...
</Question>
<Choice>Brüning, Heinrich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German imperial chancellor and Prussian prime minister from October 17, 1900, to July 14, 1909; in cooperation with Emperor William II (Kaiser Wilhelm II), he pursued a policy of German aggrandizement in the years preceding World War I.The son of an imperial secretary of state for foreign affairs under Chancellor Otto von Bismarck, Bülow studied law at Lausanne (Switzerland), Berlin, and Leipzig and entered the German foreign service in 1874. He held a number of diplomatic posts, becoming German ambassador in Rome, Italy, in 1893. Bülow's real rise to power occurred in June 1897, when William...
</Question>
<Choice>Bülow, Bernhard, Fürst von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French statesman who was an early supporter of a national income tax and whose opposition to World War I led to his imprisonment for treason in 1920.The son of Eugène Caillaux, who was twice a conservative minister (1874–75 and 1877), he obtained his law degree in 1886 and then joined the Finance Ministry as a deputy inspector. After an initial failure he was elected to the Chamber of Deputies from the Sarthe département in 1898.Having acquired a reputation as a fiscal expert, Caillaux twice served as minister of finance (1899–1902, 1906–09). Although he failed in his attempt to establish an i...
</Question>
<Choice>Caillaux, Joseph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
military and political leader who modernized the revolutionary armies and later became president of Mexico. He was the founder of the Partido Nacional Revolucionario (PNR; National Revolutionary Party), which became the major Mexican political party (renamed in 1938 the Partido de la Revolución Mexicana and in 1946 the Partido Revolucionario Institucional).He began his career as an elementary schoolteacher but joined the struggle of Francisco Madero against the dictatorship of Porfirio Díaz in 1910. Calles was an extremely gifted organizer and leader and was a general in the battles, first aga...
</Question>
<Choice>Calles, Plutarco Elías</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British prime minister from December 5, 1905, to April 5, 1908. His popularity unified his own Liberal Party and the unusually strong cabinet that he headed. He took the lead in granting self-government to the Transvaal (1906) and the Orange River Colony (1907), thereby securing the Boers' loyalty to the British Empire despite their recent defeat by the British in the South African War (1899–1902).A member of the House of Commons from 1868, Campbell-Bannerman (who in 1871 added his mother's family surname to that of his father) served as financial secretary to the War Office (1871–74, 1880–82)...
</Question>
<Choice>Campbell-Bannerman, Sir Henry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish statesman and prime minister whose anticlerical “Padlock Law” forbade the establishment of new religious orders and introduced obligatory military service.Canalejas's political career began with his election to the Cortes (parliament) in 1881 for the district of Soria. In the following years, Canalejas represented the districts of Agreda, Algeciras, and Alcoy and Madrid. He was undersecretary to the presidency (1883), minister of public works and of justice (1888), minister of finance (1894–95), and co-minister of agriculture, industry, and commerce (1902). He became prime minister aft...
</Question>
<Choice>Canalejas, José</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
president of Mexico (1934–40), noted for his efforts to carry out the social and economic aims of the Mexican Revolution. He distributed land, made loans available to peasants, organized workers' and peasants' confederations, and expropriated and nationalized foreign-owned industries.Cárdenas was largely of Indian descent. After a rudimentary education, he received his first job in a local branch of the Public Revenue Office.In February 1913 President Francisco Madero, who had led the struggle to overthrow the long dictatorship of Porfirio Díaz, was taken prisoner and assassinated on the order...
</Question>
<Choice>Cárdenas, Lázaro</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Portuguese general and statesman who rose to political prominence in the wake of the successful military revolt of 1926 and who, as president of Portugal from 1928 to 1951, served as a symbol of continuity during the regime (1932–68) of António de Oliveira Salazar.Carmona, a graduate (1888) of the Royal Military College, had risen to the rank of general by 1922. He took part in the successful army coup of May 1926 and, after serving briefly as foreign minister, became premier in July. He named as finance minister Salazar, who soon came to overshadow Carmona himself. After a bloody rebellion ha...
</Question>
<Choice>Carmona, António Oscar de Fragoso</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first king of Romania, whose long reign (as prince, 1866–81, and as king, 1881–1914) brought notable military and economic development along Western lines but failed to solve the basic problems of an overwhelmingly rural country.As a German prince, Carol was educated in Dresden and Bonn and in 1864 served as an officer of the Prussian army in the war against Denmark. With the tacit approval of his cousin, the French emperor Napoleon III, he was offered the throne of Romania after the deposition of the reigning prince, Alexandru Cuza (February 1866), and in April 1866 was elected prince by pleb...
</Question>
<Choice>Carol I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Romania (1930–40), whose controversial reign ultimately gave rise to a personal, monarchical dictatorship.The eldest son of King Ferdinand I, Carol became crown prince upon the death of his great uncle, King Carol I (October 1914). His domestic life was a constant source of scandal, marked as it was by a morganatic marriage with an officer's daughter, Zizi Lambrino; a second unhappy marriage to Helen, daughter of King Constantine I of Greece; and a continuing liaison with a Jewish adventuress, Magda Lupescu—an affair that finally obliged him to renounce his rights to the throne and go...
</Question>
<Choice>Carol II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
a leader in the Mexican civil war following the overthrow of the dictator Porfirio Díaz. He became the first president of the new Mexican Republic. A moderate who was tainted by his association with Díaz and his alliance with newer forces of economic exploitation, Carranza opposed the sweeping changes that followed the revolution.The son of a landowner, Carranza became active in local and state politics in 1877. In 1910, as governor of Coahuila, he joined the struggle of Francisco Madero against Díaz and in 1913 led the forces against Victoriano Huerta, who had assassinated Madero. After Huert...
</Question>
<Choice>Carranza, Venustiano</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British prime minister from May 28, 1937, to May 10, 1940, whose name is identified with the policy of “appeasement” toward Adolf Hitler's Germany in the period immediately preceding World War II.The son of the statesman Joseph Chamberlain and younger half brother of Sir Austen Chamberlain, he managed his father's sisal plantation on Andros Island, Bahamas, and then prospered in the metalworking industry in Birmingham. Chosen lord mayor of that city in 1915, he organized in 1916 a municipal savings bank, the only one in Great Britain. In December 1916 he joined David Lloyd George's World War I...
</Question>
<Choice>Chamberlain, Neville</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
emperor (Kaiser) of Austria and, as Charles IV, king of Hungary, the last ruler of the Austro-Hungarian monarchy (Nov. 21, 1916–Nov. 11, 1918).A grandnephew of the emperor Francis Joseph I, Charles became heir presumptive to the Habsburg throne upon the assassination of his uncle Francis Ferdinand (June 28, 1914), whose children were barred from succession because of his morganatic marriage. After his accession, Charles, a peace-loving man, made attempts to take Austria-Hungary out of World War I through secret overtures to the Allied powers, the most promising being through his brother-in-law...
</Question>
<Choice>Charles (emperor of Austria)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of a troubled Portugal that was beset by colonial disputes, grave economic difficulties, and political unrest during his reign (1889–1908).The son of King Louis and of Maria Pia of Savoy, daughter of Victor Emmanuel II of Italy, he married Marie Amélie of Orléans, a granddaughter of the French king Louis-Philippe, in 1886 and succeeded his father on Oct. 19, 1889. Forces generated by mistakes made before his time proved to be the undoing of this talented and intelligent man, who was also known for his paintings and oceanographical studies. At home, republicans, disaffected monarchists, an...
</Question>
<Choice>Charles (king of Portugal)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
soldier and statesman, head of the Nationalist government in China from 1928 to 1949, and subsequently head of the Chinese Nationalist government in exile on Taiwan.Chiang was born into a moderately prosperous merchant and farmer family in the coastal province of Chekiang. He prepared for a military career first (1906) at the Paoting Military Academy in North China and subsequently (1907–11) in Japan. From 1909 to 1911 he served in the Japanese army, whose Spartan ideals he admired and adopted. More influential were the youthful compatriots he met in Tokyo; plotting to rid China of the Qing (M...
</Question>
<Choice>Chiang Kai-shek</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman, prime minister of Australia from 1945 to 1949, and leader of the Australian Labor Party (1945–51). His ministry was noted for banking reform and expansion of social services and immigration, aiding the country's growth in the postwar period.Having been a railway driver as a young man, Chifley worked for a rail-workers' union in New South Wales. He then served in Parliament (1928–31) and, failing reelection, engaged in many public activities. His participation on the royal commission on banking (1935–37) shaped his later financial policies.When the Labor Party regained control of the...
</Question>
<Choice>Chifley, Joseph Benedict</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Denmark (1912–47) who symbolized the nation's resistance to the German occupation during World War II.The eldest son of the future King Frederick VIII and Louise of Sweden and Norway, Christian became chief of the royal guard in 1898 and married Alexandrine of Mecklenburg-Schwerin. Becoming crown prince in 1906, Christian led the opposition to the sale of the Danish West Indies (now the U.S. Virgin Islands) to the United States, which ultimately took place in 1917. He assumed the throne on his father's death in 1912.Christian attended the first in a series of meetings of Scandinavian k...
</Question>
<Choice>Christian X</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British statesman, orator, and author who as prime minister (1940–45, 1951–55) rallied the British people during World War II and led his country from the brink of defeat to victory.After a sensational rise to prominence in national politics before World War I, Churchill acquired a reputation for erratic judgment in the war itself and in the decade that followed. Politically suspect in consequence, he was a lonely figure until his response to Adolf Hitler's challenge brought him to leadership of a national coalition in 1940. With Franklin D. Roosevelt and Joseph Stalin he then shaped Allied st...
</Question>
<Choice>Churchill, Sir Winston</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman and journalist who was a dominant figure in the French Third Republic and, as premier (1917–20), a major contributor to the Allied victory in World War I and a framer of the postwar Treaty of Versailles.
</Question>
<Choice>Clemenceau, Georges</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prime minister of New Zealand from 1925 to 1928, who later, as minister of public works (1931–33) and of finance (1933–35), instituted rigorous policies to combat the economic depression of the 1930s.While farming in Auckland, Coates became active in farmers' organizations and was elected to Parliament in 1911. After distinguished service during World War I, he was named minister of justice and postmaster general in the Reform administration of W.F. Massey (1919). He led the ministries of public works (1920–26) and native affairs (1921–28) and became prime minister in 1925 on Massey's death. I...
</Question>
<Choice>Coates, Joseph Gordon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French premier (1902–05) who presided over the separation of church and state in the wake of the Dreyfus affair.A seminarian in his youth, Combes published his doctoral thesis, La Psychologie de saint Thomas d'Acquin, in 1860, but before ordination he left the church. He studied medicine and settled in Pons, where he was elected mayor in 1875. In 1885 he was elected to the Senate from the Charente-Inférieure département, where he chose to sit with the anticlerical Radical Party.In 1895 Combes joined the Léon Bourgeois government as minister of education. When he left that post (April 1896), he...
</Question>
<Choice>Combes, Émile</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Greece from 1913 to 1917 and from 1920 to 1922. His neutralist, but essentially pro-German, attitude during World War I caused the Western Allies and his Greek opponents to depose him in 1917, and, having lent himself to Greece's disastrous policy of territorial expansion into Anatolia after his restoration, he again lost his throne in 1922.The eldest son of King George I of the Hellenes, Constantine received his higher education in Germany. Although the troops under his command were defeated in the Greco-Turkish War of 1897, and he, as commander in chief of the army (after 1900), fail...
</Question>
<Choice>Constantine I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
early prime minister (1913–14) of a federated Australia who helped found the nation's military institutions.Cook emigrated to New South Wales in 1885 and worked as a coal miner until 1891, when he was elected to the New South Wales Legislative Assembly as a member of the Labor Party. After leaving the party over the tariff issue in 1894, he held posts in the state cabinet until 1899.Beginning his 20-year tenure in the federal Parliament in 1901, Cook became leader of the Free Trade Party in 1908 and the following year formed a coalition with the Liberal government headed by Alfred Deakin. In D...
</Question>
<Choice>Cook, Sir Joseph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
30th president of the United States (1923–29). Coolidge acceded to the presidency after the death in office of Warren G. Harding, just as the Harding scandals were coming to light. He restored integrity to the executive branch of the federal government while continuing the conservative pro-business policies of his predecessor. (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America.)Coolidge was the only son of John Calvin Coolidge and Victoria Moor Coolidge. His father, whose forebears had immigrated to America about 1630, was a storekeeper...
</Question>
<Choice>Coolidge, Calvin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Irish statesman and first president (1922–32) of the Irish Free State.At an early age, Cosgrave was attracted to the Irish nationalist movement Sinn Féin. He became a member of the Dublin Corporation in 1909 and was subsequently reelected in the Sinn Féin interest. When Britain entered World War I, he joined the Irish Volunteers; but when this group split in 1914, Cosgrave sided with a radical Sinn Féin minority against the moderates led by John Redmond.Cosgrave took part in the Easter Rising (1916) and was afterward interned by the British for a short time. In 1917 he was elected to Parliamen...
</Question>
<Choice>Cosgrave, William Thomas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prime minister (taoiseach) of Ireland from 1948 to 1951 and from 1954 to 1957.A prosperous lawyer who had served as attorney general, he owed his selection as prime minister to a coalition of several parties (including his own Fine Gael) and prominent independent politicians united in opposition to Eamon De Valera's Fianna Fáil (Republican Party). During his first term as prime minister, he introduced into the Dáil Éireann (Irish Assembly) the Republic of Ireland Act (1948), by which Ireland withdrew from the Commonwealth of Nations. His second government was marked by a sharp increase in acts...
</Question>
<Choice>Costello, John A</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
soldier and statesman, a leading advocate of maintaining the union between Ireland and Great Britain, and the first prime minister of Northern Ireland (from June 22, 1921, until his death).Craig became a stockbroker, served with an Irish unit in the South African (Boer) War, and in 1906 entered Parliament as a Unionist. In the acute Irish Home Rule controversy after 1910, he emerged as a leader of the Ulster Unionists and worked with Sir Edward Carson for the exclusion of Ulster from Home Rule. In addition to his part in the threats to establish a provisional government of Ulster, Craig was in...
</Question>
<Choice>Craigavon, James Craig, 1st Viscount</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German politician and business leader, general director of the Hamburg-American Line, and chancellor of the Weimar Republic during the Franco-Belgian invasion of the Ruhr (1923).Appointed government assessor in the German imperial treasury department (1907), Cuno subsequently served as a government adviser charged with drafting and presenting bills to the Reichstag (national parliament). During the first years of World War I, he headed the department of grain management (until July 1916), then served in the food ministry and, finally again, in the treasury department as general adviser on the...
</Question>
<Choice>Cuno, Wilhelm</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman, prime minister of Australia during most of World War II, and leader of the Australian Labor Party (1934–45).After involving himself in trade union and anti-conscription activity in Melbourne (1911–15), Curtin became editor of a Perth newspaper, the Westralian Worker. In 1928 he entered the federal Parliament as a member of the Labor Party, becoming its leader in 1935. By unifying the party thereafter, Curtin prepared for its assumption of power in 1941.Curtin served as a member of the Advisory War Council in 1940 and became prime minister and minister for defense the following year....
</Question>
<Choice>Curtin, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French politician who as premier signed the Munich Pact (Sept. 30, 1938), an agreement that enabled Nazi Germany to take possession of the Sudetenland (a region of Czechoslovakia) without fear of opposition from either Britain or France.Daladier was elected to the Chamber of Deputies in 1919 as a member of the Radical Party from Vaucluse département. Daladier quickly made his mark in Paris. In June 1924 he joined the first Herriot government as the minister of colonies. In the turbulent years from 1925 to 1933 he served in several different Cabinets as minister of war, minister of public instr...
</Question>
<Choice>Daladier, Édouard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
archbishop of Athens and regent of Greece during the civil war of 1944–46, under whose regency came a period of political reconstruction. He was a private in the army during the Balkan Wars (1912) and was ordained priest in 1917.In 1922 Damaskinos became bishop of Corinth, and in 1938 he was elected archbishop of Athens. His election was voided by Premier John Metaxas because of his opposition to Metaxas' regime, and Bishop Chrysanthos of Trebizond was appointed instead. Damaskinos was exiled but then recalled in July 1941, after Greece had been occupied by the Germans during World War II, to...
</Question>
<Choice>Damaskinos</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician and prime minister of Italy (1945–53) who contributed to the material and moral reconstruction of his nation after World War II.From the age of 24 De Gasperi directed the journal Il Nuovo Trentino, in which he defended Italian culture and the economic interests of his own region. In 1911 he was elected to the Austrian parliament as an Italian representative, joining other Italian deputies who sought the annexation of the Trentino by Italy. When the annexation of the Trentino was effected (1919), De Gasperi was elected deputy to the Italian parliament in 1921 as one of the founders o...
</Question>
<Choice>De Gasperi, Alcide</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Irish politician and patriot, prime minister (1932–48, 1951–54, 1957–59), and president (1959–73) of Ireland. An active revolutionary from 1913, he became president of Sinn Féin in 1918 and founded the Fianna Fáil party in 1926. In 1937 he took the Irish Free State out of the British Commonwealth and made his country a “sovereign” state, renamed Ireland, or Éire. His academic attainments also inspired wide respect; he became chancellor of the National University of Ireland in 1921.
</Question>
<Choice>de Valera, Eamon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prime minister of Australia (1903–04, 1905–08, 1909–10), who shaped many of the policies of the new commonwealth, especially those dealing with restriction of nonwhite immigration, social welfare, and protection of domestic industry.In 1880 Deakin entered the legislative assembly in Victoria, where he served for the next 20 years. He sponsored an important irrigation bill in 1886 and acts protecting factory workers in 1885 and 1896. A leader in the federation movement, he attended the conferences of 1891 and 1897–98 that drafted the constitution bill making Australia a commonwealth. He then we...
</Question>
<Choice>Deakin, Alfred</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
soldier and president of Mexico (1877–80, 1884–1911), who established a strong centralized state that he held under firm control for more than three decades.A mestizo (part Indian), Díaz was of humble origin. He began training for the priesthood at age 15, but upon the outbreak of war with the United States (1846–48) he joined the army. An illustrious military career followed, including service in the War of the Reform (1857–60) and the struggle against the French in 1861–67, when Maximilian became emperor. Earlier (1849), Díaz studied law with the encouragement of the Liberal Benito Juárez, w...
</Question>
<Choice>Díaz, Porfirio</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Bulgarian communist leader who became the post-World War II prime minister of Bulgaria. He also won worldwide fame for his defense against Nazi accusations during the German Reichstag Fire trial of 1933.A printer and trade union leader, Dimitrov led the Bulgarian socialist parliamentary opposition to the voting of national war credits in 1915, and he played a major role in the formation of the Bulgarian Communist Party in 1919. Briefly imprisoned for sedition in 1918, he later journeyed to the Soviet Union, where he was elected to the executive committee of the Comintern (Communist Internation...
</Question>
<Choice>Dimitrov, Georgi Mikhailovich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian statesman and, from 1932 to 1934, chancellor of Austria, who destroyed the Austrian Republic and established an authoritarian regime based on conservative Roman Catholic and Italian Fascist principles.After studying law and economics in Vienna and Berlin, Dollfuss became secretary to the Lower Austrian Peasant Federation and, in 1927, director of the Lower Austrian chamber of agriculture. He was a member of the conservative and clerically oriented Christian Social Party, the core of whose constituency came from Austria's conservative peasantry. Dollfuss rose rapidly in Austrian politi...
</Question>
<Choice>Dollfuss, Engelbert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the 13th president of the French Third Republic whose term was cut short by an assassin's bullet.In 1889 Doumer was elected as a Radical deputy from the Yonne département, and his reputation as a fiscal expert led to his appointment (1895) as minister of finance in the Cabinet of Léon Bourgeois. Unsuccessful in his efforts to introduce a national income tax, he was appointed governor general of Indochina the following year.Doumer was one of the most active and, from the French point of view, effective governors general of Indochina. Unlike many of his predecessors and successors he occupied hi...
</Question>
<Choice>Doumer, Paul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French political figure whose term as 12th president of the Third Republic was marked by nearly constant political instability.After service as an official in Indochina and Africa (1885–93), Doumergue was elected as a Radical-Socialist member of the Chamber of Deputies from Nîmes (1893). In June 1902 he was appointed to the first of his 11 ministerial posts. In 1910 he was elected to the Senate. On Dec. 13, 1913, he formed his own Cabinet, and, although it collapsed within seven months, he remained in various ministerial positions until March 1917. He then returned to the Senate and was its pr...
</Question>
<Choice>Doumergue, Gaston</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Canadian politician who controlled Quebec's provincial government as its premier from 1936 until his death, except for the war years of 1940–44.Educated at Notre Dame and Laval universities in Montreal, Duplessis was admitted to the bar in 1913 and made King's Counsel in 1931. He practiced law in Trois-Rivières and was elected to the Quebec legislature in 1927 as a Conservative. By 1933 he was head of the provincial Conservative Party. Advocating French-Canadian autonomy, he led his followers into a new nationalist party, the Union Nationale, which won the 1936 election. He became premier and...
</Question>
<Choice>Duplessis, Maurice</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
leader of the Social Democratic movement in Germany and a moderate socialist, who was a leader in bringing about the constitution of the Weimar Republic, which attempted to unite Germany after its defeat in World War I. He was president of the Weimar Republic from 1919 to 1925.Ebert was the son of a master tailor. He learned the saddler's trade and traveled through Germany as a journeyman saddler. He soon became a Social Democrat and trade unionist, representing so-called revisionist—gradualist, liberal—“trade-union” socialism, without, however, displaying a deep interest in the ideological st...
</Question>
<Choice>Ebert, Friedrich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland and of the British dominions and emperor of India from 1901, an immensely popular and affable sovereign and a leader of society.The second child and eldest son of Queen Victoria and the Prince Consort Albert of Saxe-Coburg-Gotha, Albert Edward, created prince of Wales and earl of Chester by his mother when he was one month old, attended the universities of both Oxford and Cambridge. His dalliance with an actress while serving with an Army unit in Ireland (June–September 1861) caused Victoria to hold him partly responsible for the death of...
</Question>
<Choice>Edward VII</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prince of Wales (1911–36) and king of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland and of the British dominions and emperor of India from Jan. 20 to Dec. 10, 1936, when he abdicated in order to marry Wallis Warfield Simpson of the United States (seeWindsor, Wallis Warfield, Duchess of). He was the only British sovereign ever voluntarily to resign the crown.The eldest child of George, duke of York (later King George V), and Princess Mary of Teck (later Queen Mary), he became heir to the throne on the accession of his father (May 6, 1910). Although trained (1907–11) for the Royal Navy, he was...
</Question>
<Choice>Edward VIII</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
jurist and politician who became dictator and ruled Guatemala from 1898 to 1920 through a standing army, secret police, and systematic oppression.After a church-directed education, he practiced law for a time in Guatemala City and was appointed a judge on the Supreme Court. He then entered politics, was elected to the Congress, and served successively as minister of public instruction, of justice, and of the interior. When President José María Reina Barrios was assassinated in 1898, Estrada Cabrera was appointed provisional president and then elected president. He served his first term respect...
</Question>
<Choice>Estrada Cabrera, Manuel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italy's last prime minister before the Fascist leader Benito Mussolini gained power (Oct. 31, 1922).After studying law, Facta became a journalist. He was elected deputy in 1891. He served as undersecretary first of justice and then of the interior in Giovanni Giolitti's coalition cabinet (1903–05). In succeeding ministries he was three times minister of finance and during the first six months of 1919 was minister of justice.Facta formed his own cabinet in February 1922 but was defeated by an anti-Fascist coalition in July for not taking sufficiently strong action against Mussolini's Fascists....
</Question>
<Choice>Facta, Luigi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Egypt from 1936 to 1952. Although initially quite popular, the internal rivalries of his administration and his alienation of the military—coupled with his increasing excesses and eccentricities—led to his downfall and to the formation of a republic.Farouk, the son and successor of King Fu?ad I, was educated in Egypt and England before ascending the throne in 1936. As king he continued his father's rivalry with the popular-based Wafd party, with which he clashed over many issues, including administrative functions, appointments, and even the form used for his coronation.After the outbr...
</Question>
<Choice>Farouk I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Arab statesman and king of Iraq (1921–33) who was a leader in advancing Arab nationalism during and after World War I.Fay?al was the son of ?usayn ibn ?Ali, amir and grand sharif of Mecca who ruled the Hejaz from 1916 to 1924. When World War I provided an opportunity for rebellion for many Arab leaders who had come to resent Ottoman rule, including certain Syrian Arabs who looked to ?usayn for leadership because he was not under direct Ottoman rule, Fay?al in 1915 travelled to Damascus to reach an understanding with the secret Arab nationalist societies there about the terms under which they w...
</Question>
<Choice>Faysal I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prince (1887–1908) and first king (1908–18) of modern Bulgaria.The youngest son of Prince Augustus (August) I of Saxe-Coburg-Gotha, Ferdinand was elected prince of Bulgaria on July 7, 1887, as successor to the first ruler of that autonomous principality, Alexander I, who was forced by a pro-Russian coup d'état to abdicate the preceding year. Though dominated by his prime minister, Stefan Stambolov, during the early years of his reign, he became an important factor influencing national affairs after his minister's humiliating fall from power (1894). Ferdinand's dynastic position, which long suf...
</Question>
<Choice>Ferdinand</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
three-time Labor prime minister of Australia (1908–09, 1910–13, 1914–15) who sponsored important legislation in the fields of social welfare, economic development, labour relations, and defense.Fisher emigrated from England to Queensland in 1885, worked as a coal miner and union leader, and was elected to the state legislature in 1893. In 1901 he served in the first federal Parliament and, briefly, in the first Labor government in 1904, assuming party leadership in 1907. His second term as prime minister was a fruitful one, advancing on the program of his predecessor, Alfred Deakin. Legislatio...
</Question>
<Choice>Fisher, Andrew</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
farmer and politician who served as prime minister of New Zealand during the depression years (1930–35).Forbes held a seat in the House of Representatives for thirty-five years as member for Hurunui (1908–43). He began his political career as a member of the Liberal Party, and when that party declined he became in 1928 a leader of the newly created United Party. However, he stepped aside when the ailing 72-year-old former prime minister, Sir Joseph Ward, formed a government of the United Party with Labour support (1928). Forbes was minister of lands and agriculture but de facto head of the Cab...
</Question>
<Choice>Forbes, George William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
emperor of Austria (1848–1916) and king of Hungary (1867–1916), who divided his empire into the Dual Monarchy, in which Austria and Hungary coexisted as equal partners. In 1879 he formed an alliance with Prussian-led Germany, and in 1914 his ultimatum to Serbia led Austria and Germany into World War I.
</Question>
<Choice>Francis Joseph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
general and leader of the Nationalist forces that overthrew the Spanish democratic republic in the Spanish Civil War (1936–39); thereafter he was the head of the government of Spain until 1973 and head of state until his death in 1975.
</Question>
<Choice>Franco, Francisco</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman, labour leader, and prime minister (1940–49) whose leadership during World War II increased New Zealand's international stature.While working in London in 1908, Fraser joined the Independent Labour Party, but unemployment led him to emigrate to New Zealand in 1910, where he worked on the wharves in several ports and was active in union organizing in Auckland and in the harshly repressed Waihi and Wellington strikes of 1912–13. He helped organize the Social Democratic Party in 1913 and its successor, the Labour Party, in 1916. He was imprisoned for sedition (1916–17) when he opposed c...
</Question>
<Choice>Fraser, Peter</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French political figure who served in 12 different governments, including four terms as premier; he was primarily responsible for important military reforms instituted in the last decade of the 19th century.Freycinet graduated from the École Polytechnique and entered government service as a mining engineer, eventually rising to the position of inspector general of mines in 1883. Upon the establishment of the French Republic in September 1870, during the Franco-German War, he offered his services to Léon Gambetta, who appointed him prefect of Tarnet-Garonne and, in October, chief of the militar...
</Question>
<Choice>Freycinet, Charles-Louis de Saulces de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the first king of Egypt (1922–36) following its independence from Great Britain.The youngest son of Isma?il Pasha, Fu?ad spent most of his childhood with his exiled father in Naples. Following his education at the military academy in Turin, Italy, he served in a number of administrative posts, including nominal rector (1908–13) of the Egyptian University (now Cairo University). In 1914 he came under consideration as a candidate for the Albanian throne, but he was ultimately bypassed in favour of a Christian ruler.In 1917, while Egypt was still a British protectorate, Fu?ad was selected to succ...
</Question>
<Choice>Fu'ad I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
leader of the Indian nationalist movement against British rule, considered to be the father of his country. He is internationally esteemed for his doctrine of nonviolent protest to achieve political and social progress.Gandhi was the youngest child of his father's fourth wife. His father, Karamchand Gandhi, who was the dewan (chief minister) of Porbandar, the capital of a small principality in Gujarat in western India under British suzerainty, did not have much in the way of a formal education. He was, however, an able administrator who knew how to steer his way between the capricious princes,...
</Question>
<Choice>Gandhi, Mohandas Karamchand</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman who served three times as Austrian prime minister.A graduate of the University of Vienna, Gautsch von Frankenthurn entered the imperial Ministry of Education (1874) and served as Austrian minister of education in the cabinets of Eduard, Count von Taaffe (1885–93), and Kasimir, Count von Badeni (1895–97). With the fall of Badeni, he was appointed prime minister (November 1897), but the failure of his proposed reform of the Bohemian language laws prompted his resignation (March 1898).After several years as president of the government accounting office, Gautsch von Frankenthurn was reca...
</Question>
<Choice>Gautsch von Frankenthurn, Paul, Baron</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Iraqi lawyer and politician who was prime minister of Iraq (1933, 1940–41, 1941) and one of the most celebrated political leaders of the Arab world during his time.The son of an aristocratic Sunnite family, Gaylani studied law at Baghdad Law School. After several years of practice, he entered public life, holding several cabinet posts in the 1920s and '30s, including minister of justice (1924) and minister of the interior (1925–28). After briefly serving as prime minister in 1933, he was reappointed to the post in 1940. At the time World War II (1939–45) was under way, and Gaylani, a strident...
</Question>
<Choice>Gaylani, Rashid 'Ali al-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Greece, whose long reign (1863–1913) spanned the formative period for the development of Greece as a modern European state. His descendants occupied the throne until the military coup d'état of 1967 and eventual restoration of the republic in 1973.Born Prince William, the second son of King Christian IX of Denmark and the brother of Queen Alexandra of England, he was nominated to the Greek throne by Britain, France, and Russia after the first Greek king, Otto, was deposed in 1862. The National Assembly accepted William as king of the Hellenes in March 1863, and he ascended the throne a...
</Question>
<Choice>George I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Greece from September 1922 to March 1924 and from October 1935 until his death. His second reign was marked by the ascendancy of the military dictator Ioannis Metaxas.The eldest son of King Constantine I, George was excluded from the succession during World War I for his allegedly pro-German sympathies, but he came to the throne when his father was deposed by General Nikólaos Plastíras in September 1922. Feeling ran high against the royal family, however, and, after a royalist coup d'état had been suppressed in October 1923, George felt compelled to leave Greece on December 19 with his...
</Question>
<Choice>George II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the United Kingdom from 1910 to 1936, the second son of Prince Albert Edward, later King Edward VII.He served in the navy until the death (1892) of his elder brother, Prince Albert Victor, brought the need for more specialized training as eventual heir to the throne. Created Duke of York (May 1892), he married (July 1893) Princess Mary of Teck, who had been his brother's fiancée. Created Duke of Cornwall and Prince of Wales after his father's accession (1901), he succeeded his father on May 6, 1910, and was crowned on June 22, 1911.Formidable difficulties faced the new king early in hi...
</Question>
<Choice>George V</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the United Kingdom from 1936 to 1952.The second son of the future king George V, the prince served in the Royal Navy (1913–17), the Royal Naval Air Service (1917–19), and the Royal Air Force (1919) and then attended Trinity College, Cambridge (1919–20). On June 3, 1920, he was created duke of York. He sponsored the annual Duke of York's Camp (1921–39), at which equal numbers of public (private) school boys and boys from industrial areas spent a week together as his guests. On April 26, 1923, he married Lady Elizabeth Angela Marguerite Bowes-Lyon, youngest daughter of the 14th earl of S...
</Question>
<Choice>George VI</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman and five times prime minister under whose leadership Italy prospered. He had many enemies, however, and retained power by using the highly criticized technique called giolittismo, which is associated with corruption and violence on election days and with personal deals rather than with party loyalty.After graduating in law from the University of Turin (1860), Giolitti entered the civil service and spent the next 20 years gaining experience in finance and as an administrator. Somewhat reluctantly, he became a deputy in the Italian parliament (1882), a position he held until his death....
</Question>
<Choice>Giolitti, Giovanni</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
dictator of Venezuela from 1908 until 1935, reputed to have been the wealthiest man in South America.Although a nearly full-blooded Indian with almost no formal education, Gómez became a figure of local prominence in the Andean region. Joining the private army of Cipriano Castro in 1899, he was appointed vice president when Castro captured Caracas and the government. In 1908, when Castro was recuperating from illness in Europe, Gómez seized power and ruled either as president or through puppet figures until his death.Under Gómez, Venezuela achieved a measure of independence and economic progre...
</Question>
<Choice>Gómez, Juan Vicente</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Czechoslovak Communist politician and journalist, successively deputy premier (1945–46), premier (1946–48), and president (1948–53) of Czechoslovakia.The illegitimate son of a peasant, Gottwald was sent to Vienna at the age of 12 to become an apprentice carpenter and cabinetmaker. By the age of 16 he had become a socialist. During World War I he served in the Austro-Hungarian army, deserting, however, to the Russians before the end of the war. When he returned to the new state of Czechoslovakia in 1918, he joined the left wing of the Czechoslovak Social Democratic Party, the wing that in 1921...
</Question>
<Choice>Gottwald, Klement</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
political economist, prime minister of Poland (1920, 1923–25), and statesman who reorganized Poland's monetary and financial system.A Socialist in his youth, Grabski later joined the National Democracy Party and was elected a member of three successive sessions of the Duma (1906–12), the legislative body of the Russian Empire, of which Poland was then a part. After Poland had become detached from Russia, Grabski was elected to the Polish constituent assembly (January 1919) but was soon sent to join the Polish delegation at the peace conference in Paris. Returning to Warsaw, he became minister...
</Question>
<Choice>Grabski, Wladyslaw</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
journalist and Irish nationalist, principal founder of the powerful Sinn Féin (“We Ourselves”) movement, vice president of the Irish Republic from January 21, 1919, and its president from January 10, 1922, until his death.After working as a typesetter in Dublin and then (1896–98) as a miner and journalist in South Africa, Griffith edited political newspapers such as The United Irishman, Sinn Féin, Eire, and Nationality, and spent his life in near poverty.Griffith sought to divert the Irish from their attempt to win self-government through legislative action in the British House of Commons. Ins...
</Question>
<Choice>Griffith, Arthur</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Sweden from 1907 to 1950.The eldest son of King Oscar II and Sophie of Nassau, he was created duke of Värmland and from 1872 acted as crown prince. In 1881 he married Victoria, daughter of the grand duke Frederick I of Baden. Succeeding on his father's death (Dec. 8, 1907), he took as his motto “With the people for the Fatherland” and proved a capable constitutional monarch in a period of expanding democracy within his country.During the Courtyard Crisis in February 1914, Gustav declared his support for demands that Sweden strengthen its defenses. He was accused of overstepping his aut...
</Question>
<Choice>Gustav V</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first king of Norway following the restoration of that country's full independence in 1905.The second son of the future king Frederick VIII of Denmark, he was originally called Prince Charles (Carl) of Denmark. He was trained for a naval career. In 1896 he married Princess Maud, daughter of England's Edward VII. He was offered the Norwegian crown in 1905, after the dissolution of the Swedish–Norwegian union, and he agreed to accept it only if he were approved in a Norwegian plebiscite. Overwhelmingly approved on Nov. 12, 1905, he was elected king by the Storting (parliament) on November 18. He...
</Question>
<Choice>Haakon VII</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
emperor of Annam (now Vietnam) in 1884–86 who rejected the role of a figurehead in the French colonial regime.Ung Lich was a nephew of the emperor Tu Duc, whose death in 1883 led to a disputed succession. After several equally legitimate heirs had been assassinated or deposed, Ung Lich ascended the throne through the intricate intrigues of two mandarin power seekers, the regents Nguyen van Tuong and Ton That Thuyet, who sought to use the young prince to undermine French control. With the consent of France, the 14-year-old Ung Lich was crowned emperor of Annam in 1884, taking the royal name Ham...
</Question>
<Choice>Ham Nghi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese politician and prime minister (1929–30) at the outset of the Great Depression.He was adopted into the Hamaguchi family at an early age. After his graduation from the Tokyo Imperial University in 1895, he joined the government in the Finance Ministry. Rising rapidly through the ranks, he entered politics and in 1914 was elected to the Diet (parliament). In 1924 he became finance minister in the government of Kato Takaaki and then minister of home affairs. Soon he was elected president of the liberal Minseito (Democratic Party), and in July 1929 he was made prime minister.Although Hamag...
</Question>
<Choice>Hamaguchi Osachi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman who, as prime minister of Sweden, maintained his country's neutrality during World War I.After teaching civil law at Uppsala University (1891–95), Hammarskjöld worked in the Ministry of Justice and acted as head of that ministry in 1901–02. He was appointed president of the Göta Supreme Court in 1902 and became a member of the Permanent Court of Arbitration at The Hague in 1904, where he served until 1946. In 1905 he acted as minister of education and as a delegate to the negotiations in Karlstad over the dissolution of the union of Sweden and Norway. After acting as Swedish minister...
</Question>
<Choice>Hammarskjöld, Hjalmar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Social Democratic statesman who, as four-time premier of Sweden between 1932 and 1946, led the nation out of the economic depression of the early 1930s, initiated key social-welfare legislation, and helped maintain Sweden's neutrality during World War II.A store clerk with little formal education, Hansson joined the Social Democratic Youth Association in 1903 and became editor of its weekly journal, Fram (“Forward”). As a writer (1909–17) and editor (1917) of the Social Democrat Party organ Social-Demokraten and as a member of the Riksdag (parliament) after 1918, he argued for disarmament and...
</Question>
<Choice>Hansson, Per Albin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
29th president of the United States (1921–23). Pledging a nostalgic “return to normalcy” following World War I, Harding won the presidency by the greatest popular vote margin to that time. He died during his third year in office and was succeeded by Vice President Calvin Coolidge. His brief administration accomplished little of lasting value, however, and soon after his death a series of scandals doomed the Harding presidency to be judged among the worst in American history. (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America.)Born on a...
</Question>
<Choice>Harding, Warren G.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
army officer and later prime minister of Japan.Hayashi was a graduate of the Military Academy and Military Staff College and held many responsible posts.In 1931, as commander of Japanese troops in Korea, Hayashi ordered his forces to march into Manchuria, beginning the Japanese encroachment upon China that culminated in World War II in the Pacific. The action was undertaken without permission of the government in Tokyo. Hayashi was promoted to full general in 1932. In 1934 he succeeded General Araki Sadao as minister of war, and, attempting to purge the army of Araki's supporters, who had stro...
</Question>
<Choice>Hayashi Senjuro</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French statesman and man of letters who was the longtime leader of the Radical Party; he served in nine different cabinets and was premier of France three times (1924–25, 1926, 1932).The son of an army officer, Herriot was educated at the École Normale Supérieure, from which he graduated in 1894. He taught at the lycée of Nantes and then at Lyon, where he won a high reputation as a scholar and teacher. This reputation was enhanced by his study of Madame Récamier et ses amis (1904; “Madame Recamier and Her Friends”) and by the acute literary criticism in his Précis de l'histoire des lettres fra...
</Question>
<Choice>Herriot, Édouard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(count of) conservative German statesman and philosopher who became imperial chancellor during the last year of World War I but was little more than a caretaker for the military, which actually controlled the country.A devout Catholic scholar, Hertling exercised considerable influence on Catholic social philosophy both from his university chairs at Bonn and then Munich and as head of the Görres-Gesellschaft (Görres-Society), which he founded to advance Catholic studies. He served in the Reichstag (federal parliament) as a deputy of the Catholic Centre Party (1875–90 and 1896–1912) and was its...
</Question>
<Choice>Hertling, Georg, Graf von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
soldier and statesman who held the post of prime minister of the Union of South Africa (seeSouth Africa) from 1924 to 1939. His political principles, as first stated in his speeches in 1912, were “South Africa First” (even before the British Empire) and the “Two Streams Policy,” under which each part of the white South African nation—i.e., the British and the Afrikaner (Dutch)—would be free from domination by the other.Hertzog was trained in law (Victoria College, Stellenbosch, and Amsterdam University) and practiced in Pretoria (1892–95) until appointed to the high court of the Orange Free St...
</Question>
<Choice>Hertzog, J B M</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
liberal democratic legislator, first president of West Germany, author, and leader of the Free Democratic Party (Freie Demokratische Partei, FDP). He also helped draft a new constitution for postwar West Germany.After receiving a political science degree from the University of Munich (1905), Heuss was an editor on several newspapers and taught at the Hochschule für Politik in Berlin. A member of the Deutsche Demokratische Partei (German Democratic Party, DDP) during the Weimar period, he served in the Reichstag (federal lower house) in 1924–28 and 1930–33. His books were burned as “un-German”...
</Question>
<Choice>Heuss, Theodor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German field marshal during World War I and second president of the Weimar Republic (1925–34). His presidential terms were wracked by political instability, economic depression, and the rise to power of Adolf Hitler, whom he appointed chancellor in 1933.Hindenburg was the son of a Prussian officer of old Junker (aristocratic) stock. His mother, however, was from a middle-class family—a fact he preferred to ignore. A cadet at the age of 11, he served in the Austro-Prussian (Seven Weeks') War of 1866 and in the Franco-German War of 1870–71. He retired as a general in 1911 after an honourable but...
</Question>
<Choice>Hindenburg, Paul von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
leader of the National Socialist (Nazi) Party (from 1920/21) and chancellor (Kanzler) and Führer of Germany (1933–45). He was chancellor from January 30, 1933, and, after President Paul von Hindenburg's death, assumed the twin titles of Führer and chancellor (August 2, 1934).Hitler's father, Alois (born 1837), was illegitimate. For a time he bore his mother's name, Schicklgruber, but by 1876 he had established his family claim to the surname Hitler. Adolf never used any other surname.
</Question>
<Choice>Hitler, Adolf</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
founder of the Indochina Communist Party (1930) and its successor, the Viet-Minh (1941), and president from 1945 to 1969 of the Democratic Republic of Vietnam (North Vietnam). As the leader of the Vietnamese nationalist movement for nearly three decades, Ho was one of the prime movers of the post-World War II anticolonial movement in Asia and one of the most influential communist leaders of the 20th century.
</Question>
<Choice>Ho Chi Minh</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
31st president of the United States (1929–33). Hoover's reputation as a humanitarian—earned during and after World War I as he rescued millions of Europeans from starvation—faded from public consciousness when his administration proved unable to alleviate widespread joblessness, homelessness, and hunger in his own country during the early years of the Great Depression. (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America.)Hoover was the son of Jesse and Hulda Hoover. His father was a hardworking blacksmith and farm-implement dealer and hi...
</Question>
<Choice>Hoover, Herbert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hungarian naval officer and conservative leader who defeated revolutionary forces in Hungary after World War I and remained the country's head of state until 1944.A member of a noble Protestant family, Horthy entered the Austro-Hungarian naval academy at Fiume (now Rijeka, Croatia) at age 14. Aide-de-camp to the emperor Francis Joseph (1909–14), he distinguished himself as a naval commander in World War I by several times breaking the Allied Adriatic blockade. Promoted to admiral in 1918, he presided over the Austro-Hungarian fleet's transfer to Yugoslavia in October 1918.The following year, a...
</Question>
<Choice>Horthy, Miklós</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician who served as interim president of Mexico in 1920.De la Huerta worked in a variety of jobs in his native state of Sonora before becoming an agitator against the government of President Porfirio Díaz in 1908. He participated in the Mexican Revolution and served as governor of Sonora from 1917 to 1920. Along with his fellow Sonorans Álvaro Obregón and Plutarco Elías Calles, he helped overthrow President Venustiano Carranza in May 1920, and he served as interim president of Mexico from June through November of that year.Serving as minister of finance under Obregón from 1920 to 1923, he...
</Question>
<Choice>Huerta, Adolfo de la</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
dictatorial president of Mexico (Feb. 18, 1913–July 15, 1914), whose regime united disparate revolutionary forces in common opposition to him.Born of Indian parents, Huerta trained at the Chapultepec Military College and eventually rose to the rank of general in the army during the rule of the dictator Porfirio Díaz. Though an admirer of Díaz, Huerta served his successor, the liberal President Francisco Madero, as chief of staff of the army. When part of the army in Mexico City rebelled against Madero in February 1913, Huerta joined forces with the rebels, compelled Madero to resign, and assum...
</Question>
<Choice>Huerta, Victoriano</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prime minister of Australia from 1915 to 1923 and a mainstay of national politics for 50 years.Hughes emigrated to Queensland in 1884. After working for the unionization of maritime workers in Sydney, he was elected to the New South Wales legislature in 1894 as a Labor Party member. He entered the first federal Parliament in 1901 and served as attorney general in the three ministries of Andrew Fisher between 1908 and 1915. He helped establish a national system of defense (1909) and judicial arbitration in labour disputes.Hughes succeeded Fisher as prime minister in 1915, during World War I, an...
</Question>
<Choice>Hughes, William Morris</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
emir of Mecca from 1908 to 1916 and king of Hejaz from 1916 to 1924.?usayn was born into the line of Hashimites to which the Meccan emirate had passed in the early 19th century. He became emir in 1908 and was a leader in the Arab revolt against Ottoman rule during World War I. In October 1916 he proclaimed himself “king of the Arab countries,” though the Allies formally recognized him only as king of the Hejaz. ?usayn was represented at the Versailles peace conference by his third son, Fay?al, but refused to ratify the Versailles Peace Treaty (1919) as a protest against the mandatory regimes i...
</Question>
<Choice>Husayn ibn 'Ali</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chilean president from 1927 to 1931 and from 1952 to 1958. Although by preference Ibáñez was aligned with foreign reactionaries, he made many constructive domestic reforms.After a military career of 30 years, Ibáñez participated in a revolt in September 1924 against the government of Arturo Alessandri Palma. From 1925 to 1927 Ibáñez in effect controlled Chile while serving as minister of war and then as minister of the interior. In 1927 he forced the resignation of President Emiliano Figueroa Larraín and until 1931 held office as chief executive. Backed by the army, he exiled or jailed all opp...
</Question>
<Choice>Ibáñez del Campo, Carlos</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
tribal and Muslim religious leader who formed the modern state of Saudi Arabia and initiated the exploitation of its oil.
</Question>
<Choice>Ibn Sa'ud</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Turkish army officer, statesman, and collaborator with and successor to Mustafa Kemal Atatürk as president of the Turkish Republic. Identified with one-party rule between 1939 and 1946, he later emerged as a champion of democracy.Ismet served on the general staff of the 3rd Army at Edirne and as chief of staff of the army in Yemen. During World War I, he commanded the 4th Army in Syria (1916), and, at the time of the Ottoman surrender (Oct. 30, 1918), he was the undersecretary of war in Constantinople. Later he joined Mustafa Kemal's movement to resist the Allied occupation of Anatolia. In 192...
</Question>
<Choice>Inönü, Ismet</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese politician and prime minister whose assassination marked the end of party participation in the Japanese government in the period preceding World War II.Of samurai origin, Inukai began his career as a reporter. He became minister of education in 1898 and then founded a new political party, the Constitutional National Party (Rikken Kokuminto). In 1913 he headed a popular movement against the autocratic and unpopular government of the former army general Katsura Taro. As a result of Inukai's efforts, Katsura was forced to resign, opening the way for the gradual development of a cabinet s...
</Question>
<Choice>Inukai Tsuyoshi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Argentine statesman who became his country's first president elected by broad popular suffrage. He was driven from office during his second term by a military coup in 1930.Irigoyen became a lawyer, teacher, rancher, and politician and in 1896 took control of the centre-left Radical Civic Union (Unión Cívica Radical; UCR) from its founder, his uncle Leandro N. Alem. His relentless effort to obtain free elections succeeded in winning from the conservative oligarchy the Sáenz Peña Law (1912). Under this provision for the secret ballot, he was elected president. During his term (1916–22) he and hi...
</Question>
<Choice>Irigoyen, Hipólito</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian Muslim politician, founder and first governor-general (1947–48) of Pakistan.
</Question>
<Choice>Jinnah, Mohammed Ali</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
army officer and president (1932–38) of Argentina.After studying at military academies, he spent the years from 1903 until 1930 teaching military science, mathematics, and civil engineering at civilian and military colleges in or near Buenos Aires. He rose to the rank of general and for a brief period after the revolution of 1930 served as commander in chief of the army. Justo held the portfolios of war, agriculture, and public works and climaxed his political career with election to the presidency in November 1931 on a conservative coalition ticket.During the early years of his administration...
</Question>
<Choice>Justo, Agustín Pedro</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hungarian statesman who before World War I desired a reorientation of Austro-Hungarian foreign policy toward friendship with states other than Germany. He also advocated concessions to Hungary's non-Magyar subjects. After the war, as president of the Hungarian Democratic Republic in 1919, Károlyi was nevertheless unable to hold the lands of the former kingdom together and was soon forced into exile.Károlyi was a member of one of the wealthiest and most famous families of the Hungarian aristocracy. Entering the Hungarian parliament as a conservative in 1910, he soon drifted to the left. His pol...
</Question>
<Choice>Károlyi, Mihály, Count</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese prime minister in the mid-1920s whose government and policies were considered the most democratic in Japan before World War II.Kato's first job was with the great Japanese cartel of Mitsubishi, which backed him throughout his political career; he, in turn, watched over its interests. In 1887 he became private secretary to the minister of foreign affairs, Okuma Shigenobu, and subsequently served as director of a bureau in the finance department. After acting as Japanese ambassador to England (1894–99), Kato served as minister of foreign affairs for a few months in 1900 and again in 190...
</Question>
<Choice>Kato Takaaki</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese army officer and statesman who served three times as prime minister of Japan.Katsura fought for the imperial cause in the Meiji Restoration, which in 1868 wrested power from the feudal Tokugawa family and restored it to the emperor. He was later sent to Germany to study military strategy and tactics. He was appointed deputy army minister in 1886 and served in the Sino-Japanese War (1894–95). As a protégé of Yamagata Aritomo—military leader, prime minister, and special adviser to the emperor—he became army minister in 1898 and prime minister in 1901 for the first of three successive te...
</Question>
<Choice>Katsura Taro, Duke</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
moderate socialist revolutionary who served as head of the Russian provisional government from July to October 1917 (Old Style).While studying law at the University of St. Petersburg, Kerensky was attracted to the Narodniki (or populist) revolutionary movement. After graduating (1904), he joined the Socialist Revolutionary Party (c. 1905) and became a prominent lawyer, frequently defending revolutionaries accused of political offenses. In 1912 he was elected to the fourth Duma as a Trudoviki (Labour Group) delegate from Volsk (in Saratov province), and in the next several years he gained a rep...
</Question>
<Choice>Kerensky, Aleksandr Fyodorovich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Southern AfricanTswana (“Bechuana” in older variant orthography) chief of Bechuanaland who allied himself with British colonizers in the area.Khama was converted to Christianity in 1860, and, after more than a decade of dissension between his supporters and those loyal to his father, Sekgoma, he succeeded to the paramount chieftainship of the Ngwato (Mangwato, or Bamangwato) people in 1875. In 1885 Khama III acquiesced happily when Bechuanaland was declared a protectorate of Great Britain. He used British support to define and expand his northern borders in the face of opposition from Lobengul...
</Question>
<Choice>Khama III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Lebanese statesman, president of Lebanon from 1943 to 1952.The son of a prominent Lebanese Christian civil official, Khuri studied law in Paris and there learned to speak French fluently. In 1920 Khuri became secretary-general to the government of Mount Lebanon (the predecessor state of modern-day Lebanon), and he was soon appointed to the newly formed administrative council. He held this position until 1922, when he returned to a private law practice. Under Prime Minister Adib he returned to politics in 1926 as minister of the interior. During the next three years, Khuri himself was prime min...
</Question>
<Choice>Khuri, Bishara al-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prime minister of Canada (1921–26, 1926–30, 1935–48) and leader of the Liberal Party, who helped preserve the unity of the English and French populations of Canada.
</Question>
<Choice>King, W.L. Mackenzie</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese army general and prime minister during the final phase of World War II.Koiso graduated from the Army Academy in 1900 at the top of his class, attended the Army War College, and served on active duty during the Russo-Japanese War. In 1930 he became chief of the Bureau of Military Affairs and in 1932 was appointed vice-minister of war. He later became commander of the 5th division and chief of staff of the Kantogun, the military operation in China. From 1935 to 1938, Koiso, as commander in chief, directed military operations in Korea. During the Hiranuma (1939) and Yonai (1940) cabinets...
</Question>
<Choice>Koiso Kuniaki</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
26th monarch of the Choson (Yi) dynasty and the last to effectively rule Korea.Kojong became king of Korea while still a young boy. During the first years of his reign, power was in the hands of his father, Taewon-gun, who as regent attempted to restore and revitalize the country. When Taewon-gun was kidnapped and taken to China in 1882, power passed to Kojong's queen, Min, who opposed all modernization efforts. She was assassinated by the Japanese in 1895. Two years later, in an effort to save the country, Kojong elevated himself from king to emperor and changed the name of the country from C...
</Question>
<Choice>Kojong</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
political leader and prime minister of Japan (1937–39, 1940–41), who tried unsuccessfully to restrict the power of the military and to keep Japan's war with China from widening into a world conflict.
</Question>
<Choice>Konoe Fumimaro</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman who led the anticolonialist movement in Syria and became the nation's first president.Quwatli entered Syrian politics in the 1930s as a member of the National Bloc, an Arab group that led the opposition to French rule. Quwatli assumed leadership of the movement in 1940. His tolerance for the corruption of his associates helped keep him in power. The National Bloc remained the dominant expression of Syrian nationalism, and, when Syria became independent in 1943, the bloc helped elect Quwatli president. His major concern was to conclude a treaty with France, which had exercised control...
</Question>
<Choice>Kuwatli, Shukri al-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dutch theologian, statesman, and journalist who led the Anti-Revolutionary Party, an orthodox Calvinist group, to a position of political power and served as prime minister of The Netherlands from 1901 to 1905.After serving as a pastor in Beesd, Utrecht, and Amsterdam (1863–74), Kuyper adopted the orthodox Calvinist views of Guillaume Groen van Prinsterer. De Standaard, the newspaper Kuyper founded in 1872, became an organ for Groen's ideas. Elected to the States General (national assembly) in 1874, he became the leader of Groen's political group, expanding it to form the Anti-Revolutionary Pa...
</Question>
<Choice>Kuyper, Abraham</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish socialist leader, prominent during the Second Republic, of which he became prime minister soon after the outbreak of the civil war of 1936–39.Largo Caballero worked in Madrid as a plasterer before joining the Spanish Socialist Workers' Party (Partido Socialista Obrero Español; PSOE) in 1894. He soon became an official in the party's trade union federation, the Unión General de Trabajadores (UGT), and rose to become chief lieutenant of the union's head, Pablo Iglesias. Sentenced to life imprisonment for his part in the general strike of August 1917, he was released on his election to th...
</Question>
<Choice>Largo Caballero, Francisco</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the first French-Canadian prime minister of the Dominion of Canada (1896–1911), noted especially for his attempts to define the role of French Canada in the federal state and to define Canada's relations to Great Britain. He was knighted in 1897.
</Question>
<Choice>Laurier, Sir Wilfrid</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French politician and statesman who led the Vichy government in policies of collaboration with Germany during World War II, for which he was ultimately executed as a traitor to France.A member of the Socialist Party from 1903, Laval became a lawyer in Paris in 1909 and promptly made a name for himself by his defense of trade unionists and leftists. Elected deputy for Aubervilliers in 1914, he urged a negotiated peace to end World War I. Defeated in the 1919 election, he left the Socialist Party in 1920, became mayor of Aubervilliers (1923–44), and was reelected deputy in 1924, leaving the Cham...
</Question>
<Choice>Laval, Pierre</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prime minister of Great Britain from Oct. 23, 1922, to May 20, 1923, the first holder of that office to come from a British overseas possession. He was the leader of the Conservative Party during the periods 1911–21 and 1922–23.The son of a Presbyterian minister of Ulster ancestry, Law from the age of 12 was reared by wealthy cousins in Scotland. Leaving school at age 16, he eventually became a partner in a Glasgow firm of iron merchants. Elected to the House of Commons as a Conservative in 1900, he adhered to the party's imperialist faction led by Joseph Chamberlain, whose illness (from 1906)...
</Question>
<Choice>Law, Bonar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
businessman and politician who, during the first of his two terms as president of Peru (1908–12; 1919–30), settled the country's age-old boundary disputes with Bolivia and Brazil.Leguía was a member of one of the more distinguished families of the Peruvian oligarchy. Before entering politics, he acquired a great deal of experience in business, founding his own insurance company in 1896 and serving on the board of a large British sugar company during the 1890s.He served Peru as minister of finance and premier from 1903 to 1908. After his election as president in 1908, Leguía encouraged economic...
</Question>
<Choice>Leguía y Salcedo, Augusto Bernardino</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
founder of the Russian Communist Party (Bolsheviks), inspirer and leader of the Bolshevik Revolution (1917), and the architect, builder, and first head (1917–24) of the Soviet state. He was the founder of the organization known as Comintern (Communist International) and the posthumous source of “Leninism,” the doctrine codified and conjoined with Marx's works by Lenin's successors to form Marxism-Leninism, which became the Communist worldview.If the Bolshevik Revolution is—as some people have called it—the most significant political event of the 20th century, then Lenin must for good or ill be...
</Question>
<Choice>Lenin, Vladimir Ilich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the Belgians from 1865 to 1909; he led the first European efforts to develop the Congo River basin, making possible the formation of the Congo Free State in 1885, annexed in 1908 as the Belgian Congo (now Congo [Kinshasa]).The eldest son of Leopold I, first king of the Belgians, and his second wife, Marie-Louise of Orléans, Leopold became duke of Brabant in 1846 and served in the Belgian Army. In 1853 he married Maria Henrietta, daughter of the Austrian archduke Joseph, palatine of Hungary, and became king of the Belgians on his father's death in December 1865. Although the domestic af...
</Question>
<Choice>Leopold II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
leader of the Spanish Radical Party who headed four governments during the period of centre-right rule (1933–35) in the Second Republic (1931–39).The son of a sergeant major, Lerroux practiced as a lawyer and worked as a journalist in Barcelona before becoming leader of the Radical Party. In 1901 he was elected to the Spanish Parliament, and in the 1903 elections his party defeated the Catalan nationalists. His republican views led to his exile in 1907, when he fled to Argentina. After his young followers were in 1909 accused of burning convents in Barcelona, he became less extreme, and the Ra...
</Question>
<Choice>Lerroux, Alejandro</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first prime minister of Pakistan (1947–51). Born the son of a landowner, Liaquat was educated at Aligarh, Allahabad, and Exeter College, Oxford. A barrister by profession, like his leader, Mohammed Ali Jinnah, he entered politics in 1923, being elected first to the provincial legislature of the United Provinces and then to the central legislative assembly. He joined the Muslim League and soon became closely associated with Jinnah. By degrees he won first the respect and then the admiration of the Muslim community for his share in the struggle for Pakistan; when independence was won in 1947 and...
</Question>
<Choice>Liaquat Ali Khan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British prime minister (1916–22) who dominated the British political scene in the latter part of World War I. He was raised to the peerage in the year of his death.
</Question>
<Choice>Lloyd George, David</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(Knyaz) Russian social reformer and statesman who was the first head of the Russian provisional government established during the February Revolution (1917).An aristocrat who held a degree in law from the University of Moscow, Lvov worked in the civil service until 1893, when he resigned. He became a member of the Tula zemstvo (local government council), and during the Russo-Japanese War (1904–05) he organized voluntary relief work in the Orient. In 1905 he joined the newly founded liberal Constitutional Democratic (Kadet) Party, was elected to the first Duma (Russian parliament; convened May...
</Question>
<Choice>Lvov, Georgy Yevgenyevich, Prince</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Australian statesman who helped form the United Australia Party in 1931. As prime minister (1931–39), he saw the nation's economic recovery from the Great Depression and increased defense activity.At the age of 17, Lyons became a teacher in the Education Department and was elected a Labor member of the Tasmanian House of Assembly in 1909. As Tasmania's first Labor premier (1923–28), he sponsored bills to encourage industry and to provide welfare benefits for public employees. He was elected to the Australian federal Parliament in 1929 and served as postmaster general and minister for public wo...
</Question>
<Choice>Lyons, Joseph Aloysius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first Labour Party prime minister of Great Britain, in the Labour governments of 1924 and 1929–31 and in the national coalition government of 1931–35.The son of an unmarried maidservant, MacDonald ended his elementary education at the age of 12, but he continued at school for another six years, working as a pupil-teacher.In 1885 he went to work in Bristol, where the activities of the Social Democratic Federation acquainted him with left-wing ideas. Travelling to London the following year, he joined the Fabian Society, was employed in menial office jobs, and worked for a science degree in his s...
</Question>
<Choice>MacDonald, Ramsay</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
hero in the Cuban War of Independence (1895–98) who was later elected president by an overwhelming majority, only to become one of Cuba's most powerful dictators.Leaving the army as a brigadier general after the war, he turned to farming and business but remained active in politics, heading the Liberal Party in 1920. His election to the presidency in 1924 was welcomed by most Cubans, especially the middle class, who thought a sensible businessman would restore order to Cuba's disrupted society. To counteract economic depression caused by declining sugar prices, Machado instituted a massive pro...
</Question>
<Choice>Machado y Morales, Gerardo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish-born explorer, businessman, and politician who was for a short time prime minister of New Zealand (1912) and who later served as High Commissioner in London during World War I.Mackenzie's family had immigrated to New Zealand (1858), where, as a young man, he worked as a surveyor and began his own mercantile business. He served in local government and was elected to Parliament (1887). During these years Mackenzie pursued his interests in the natural history of New Zealand. He crossed from Lake Wakatipu to Martins Bay by the Harris Saddle, explored the Tautuku Forest, and led a party to...
</Question>
<Choice>Mackenzie, Sir Thomas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mexican revolutionary and president of Mexico (1911–13), who successfully ousted the dictator Porfirio Díaz by temporarily unifying various democratic and anti-Díaz forces. He proved incapable of controlling the reactions from both conservatives and revolutionaries that his moderate reforms provoked, however.The son of a wealthy landowning family, Madero attended Mount St. Mary's College in Emmitsburg, Md. (1886–88) and then studied for several years at a business school in Paris and one semester at the University of California at Berkeley. He was short, slender, and pale and became a vegetari...
</Question>
<Choice>Madero, Francisco</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
jurist and official who served three times as prime minister of Egypt.Mahir Pasha, a member of the aristocracy, took a law degree and after three years' practice became a judge in the native courts. In the years before World War I he sided with conservative Egyptian political groups who thought that it was possible to cooperate with the British (who had occupied Egypt in 1882) in bringing economic and social progress to Egypt. He devoted his talents to the service of the king: in 1923 he was appointed director of the royal law school, and in the same year he played an important role in framing...
</Question>
<Choice>Mahir Pasha, 'Ali</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman and politician who formed South Africa's first exclusively Afrikaner government and instituted the policy of apartheid (the enforced segregation of nonwhites from whites).Malan was educated at Victoria College, Stellenbosch, and at the University of Utrecht, Neth., where he received a doctorate in divinity in 1905. He returned to the Cape to enter the ministry of the Dutch Reformed Church. Always a vigorous exponent of Afrikaner aspirations and the use of the Afrikaans language, Malan left the pulpit in 1915 to edit Die Burger, a Cape Town newspaper that supported the National Party,...
</Question>
<Choice>Malan, Daniel F</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman who served as prime minister of Romania (1928–30, 1930, 1932–33) and as head of the National Peasant Party. Maniu was one of the most important Romanian political leaders of the period.Maniu, a native of Transylvania, was elected in 1906 to the Hungarian Parliament, where he joined a small band of Romanian deputies urging equal rights for their minority. During World War I he served in the Austro-Hungarian army, but in the autumn of 1918 he led the movement to separate Transylvania from Hungary and make it a part of Greater Romania. In December 1918 he was elected president of the Tr...
</Question>
<Choice>Maniu, Iuliu</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Finnish military leader and conservative statesman who successfully defended Finland against greatly superior Soviet forces during World War II and served as the country's president (1944–46).Mannerheim was of Swedish ancestry. He entered the Russian army in 1889 as a lieutenant in the cavalry. Finland was then a part of the Russian Empire, and Mannerheim distinguished himself during the Russo-Japanese War (1904–05) and World War I, rising to the rank of lieutenant general and corps commander in the Russian army. After the outbreak of the October (November) Russian Revolution in 1917 he return...
</Question>
<Choice>Mannerheim, Carl Gustaf</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
queen consort (1879–85) of Alfonso XII of Spain whose tact and wisdom as queen regent (1885–1902) for her son Alfonso XIII were instrumental in giving Spain a degree of peace and political stability.María Cristina began her regency, the longest in Spain's history, by entrusting the government to the liberal leader Práxedes Mateo Sagasta and by granting freedom of the press and a generous amnesty to political prisoners. Under her regency the exercise of power was rotated between the conservative Antonio Cánovas del Castillo and the liberal Sagasta. She witnessed the end of the Spanish empire wi...
</Question>
<Choice>María Cristina De Habsburgo-Lorena</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
chief founder and first president (1918–35) of Czechoslovakia.
</Question>
<Choice>Masaryk, Tomáš</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
New Zealand statesman, prime minister (1912–25), lifelong spokesman for agrarian interests, and opponent of left-wing movements. His Reform Party ministries included leadership of the country during World War I.After immigrating to New Zealand in 1870, Massey farmed near Auckland and assumed leadership in farmers' organizations. He entered Parliament in 1894 as a conservative and from 1894 to 1912 was a leader of the conservative opposition to the Liberal ministries. He became prime minister in 1912 and promptly signed legislation enabling freeholders to buy their land at its original value. T...
</Question>
<Choice>Massey, William Ferguson</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman and five-time prime minister of Spain whose vision led him to undertake a series of democratic reforms to prevent revolution and foster a constitutional monarchy. His tolerance and lack of knowledge of human nature, however, tended to obscure his otherwise brilliant political career.Maura was elected to the Cortes (Spanish parliament) of 1881, and in 1890 he became minister for the colonies in the Liberal cabinet of Práxedes Mateo Sagasta. He resigned when his reforms that would have granted autonomy to Cuba failed to pass (1894). Later, as minister of the interior (1902), he conduct...
</Question>
<Choice>Maura y Montaner, Antonio</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
chancellor of Germany, appointed on Oct. 3, 1918, because his humanitarian reputation made the emperor William II think him capable of bringing World War I expeditiously to an end.The son of the grand duke Frederick I's brother Prince William of Baden, Maximilian in 1907 became heir presumptive to the grand duchy because his cousin the grand duke Frederick II (d. 1928) had no children. In the first years of World War I he devoted himself to the Red Cross and to work for the welfare of prisoners of war (on both sides). On Oct. 3, 1918, when Germany was on the verge of collapse, he was appointed...
</Question>
<Choice>Maximilian, Prince Of Baden</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ottoman sultan from 1909 to 1918, whose reign was marked by the absolute rule of the Committee of Union and Progress and by Turkey's defeat in World War I.Having lived in seclusion most of his life, Mehmed Resad became sultan after his brother Abdülhamid II was forced to abdicate. A kind and gentle man, educated in traditional Islamic subjects and Persian literature, he showed a keen interest in Ottoman and Islamic history; nevertheless, he lacked the ability to govern. Attempting to rule as a constitutional monarch, he surrendered all authority to the Committee of Union and Progress, the libe...
</Question>
<Choice>Mehmed V</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the last sultan of the Ottoman Empire, whose forced abdication and exile in 1922 prepared the way for the emergence of the Turkish Republic under the leadership of Mustafa Kemal Atatürk within a year.Clever and perceptive, Mehmed VI became sultan July 4, 1918, and attempted to follow the example of his elder brother Abdülhamid II (reigned 1876–1909) by assuming personal control of the government. After the Armistice of Mudros (Oct. 30, 1918) and the establishment of the Allied military administration in Istanbul on Dec. 8, 1918, the nationalist–liberal Committee of Union and Progress had colla...
</Question>
<Choice>Mehmed VI</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Canadian politician who was Conservative Party leader (1920–26; 1941–42) and prime minister of Canada (1920–21; 1926).Meighen graduated from the University of Toronto in 1896 and was called to the bar in 1903. In 1908 he was elected to Parliament from Portage la Prairie, Manitoba, where he practiced law. A noted debater, he became solicitor general in 1913 and subsequently held cabinet posts in Robert (later Sir Robert) Borden's government. When the Conservatives and some Liberals formed a Union Government in 1917, Meighen became minister of the interior. Meighen worked effectively to implemen...
</Question>
<Choice>Meighen, Arthur</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
emperor of Japan from 1867 to 1912, during whose reign Japan was dramatically transformed from a feudal country into one of the great powers of the modern world.The second son of the emperor Komei, Mutsuhito was declared crown prince in 1860; following the death of his father in 1867, he was raised to the throne. In 1868 his coronation ceremony was carried out, and he took the name Meiji, by which the era of his reign is also known. Meiji's accession to the throne coincided with the end of the Tokugawa shogunate and the restoration to the emperor of supreme executive authority in the country....
</Question>
<Choice>Meiji</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Shewa (or Shoa; 1865–89), and emperor of Ethiopia (1889–1913). One of Ethiopia's greatest rulers, he expanded the empire almost to its present-day borders, repelled an Italian invasion in 1896, and carried out a wide-ranging program of modernization.
</Question>
<Choice>Menilek II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman who served as prime minister of the Cape Colony from 1908 to 1910.In 1849 Merriman moved with his family to Cape Colony. He was educated at the diocesan college, Rondebosch, and at Radley College in England. He returned to the Cape in 1861, engaged in land surveying, and later became a dealer in diamonds and a wine merchant.Merriman's chief interest, however, was politics. He served as a member of the Cape House of Assembly from 1869 to 1910 and as the commissioner of public works in two Cape ministries (1875–78 and 1881–84). He was an outspoken opponent of confederation in his early...
</Question>
<Choice>Merriman, John X.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
general and statesman, dictator of Greece from 1936 to 1941.After active service in the Greco-Turkish war (1897), Metaxas completed his military training in Germany. He distinguished himself on the Greek general staff during the Balkan Wars (1912–13) and was appointed chief of staff in 1913 and promoted to general in 1916. During World War I he unsuccessfully fought to maintain Greek neutrality and opposed the plans of premier Eleuthérios Venizélos for the conquest of western Anatolia, accurately predicting the military catastrophe that ultimately overtook the Greek offensive in Anatolia in 19...
</Question>
<Choice>Metaxas, Ioannis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Romania and, during World War II, a principal leader of the coup d'etat of August 1944, which severed Romania's connection with the Axis powers.After his father—the future king Carol II— had been formally excluded from the royal succession by an act of state (January 1926), Michael was proclaimed king of Romania under a three-member regency on the death of his grandfather, King Ferdinand (July 20, 1927). But upon the return of Carol from exile (June 1930), the regency was dissolved, and Michael was reduced to the rank of crown prince. With Carol's abdication in September 1940, Michael...
</Question>
<Choice>Michael</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German politician and imperial chancellor during World War I, whose government was completely dependent on the military supreme command and lasted only 15 weeks.A Prussian civil servant from 1879, Michaelis taught at the German school of law in Tokyo (1885–89), re-entered the Prussian civil service in 1892, and became undersecretary of state in the Finance Ministry in 1909. During World War I he headed the department for grain supply (from 1915), and in early 1917 was appointed Prussian state commissioner for food supply. After the fall of the government of Theobald von Bethmann Hollweg during...
</Question>
<Choice>Michaelis, Georg</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polish statesman, who tried to establish a democratic, non-Soviet regime in Poland after World War II.Coorganizer and leader of the Peasant Party (1931–39) and a member of the Sejm (Diet), Mikolajczyk fled to London after the German invasion of Poland in 1939. He served as minister of the interior of the Polish government in exile and then became deputy prime minister (1941–43) and prime minister (1943–44).On June 27, 1945, Mikolajczyk returned to Poland and joined the Communist-dominated provisional government as second deputy premier and minister of agriculture and land reform. At the Potsda...
</Question>
<Choice>Mikolajczyk, Stanislaw</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French lawyer and statesman who, as president of the Republic (1920–1924), was noted for his desire to strengthen the power of the president by constitutional revision.Educated for the bar, Millerand was elected to the Chamber of Deputies as a socialist in 1885. He soon became the leader of the socialist left and until 1896 edited their organ, La Petite République. In 1899 he joined René Waldeck-Rousseau's Cabinet of “republican defense” as minister of commerce and applied himself to bettering labour conditions, to upgrading the mercantile marine, and to developing trade, educational resources...
</Question>
<Choice>Millerand, Alexandre</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polish statesman, scholar, and scientist, who, as president of the Polish republic, was a supporter of the dictatorship of Józef Pilsudski.Moscicki was educated as a chemist. He joined the Polish Socialist Party in the early 1890s and was involved in an attempt on the life of the governor-general of Warsaw. Sought by the Russian police for that involvement, Moscicki fled to England (1892), where he met Pilsudski.Returning to the European continent, in 1897 Moscicki began to teach at the Roman Catholic university in Fribourg, Switz. In 1912 he was given the professorship of electrochemistry at...
</Question>
<Choice>Moscicki, Ignacy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
sultan of Morocco (1927–57) who became a focal point of nationalist aspirations, secured Moroccan independence from French colonial rule, and then ruled as king from 1957 to 1961.Mu?ammad was the third son of Sultan Mawlay Yusuf; when his father died in 1927, French authorities chose him to be successor, expecting him to be more compliant than his two older brothers. The first indication of Mu?ammad's nationalist feelings occurred in 1934, when he urged the French to abandon the Berber Dahir legislation of 1930 that had established different legal systems for the two Moroccan ethnic groups, Im...
</Question>
<Choice>Muhammad V</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian prime minister (1922–43) and the first of 20th-century Europe's fascist dictators.
</Question>
<Choice>Mussolini, Benito</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman who, as the leader of the nationalist Wafd party, was a dominant figure in Egyptian politics until the revolution of 1952.A lawyer by profession, Na??as was appointed a judge in the National Court at ?an?a in 1914. Soon after World War I he joined the recently formed Wafd; he was exiled with Sa?d Zaghlul in the early 1920s, and assumed the chairmanship upon Zaghlul's death in 1927. Thus, he embarked upon a career during which he was prime minister of Egypt on five occasions. His first term of office as prime minister began in March 1928. His dismissal in June was occasioned by King F...
</Question>
<Choice>Nahhas Pasha, Mustafa an-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first prime minister of independent India (1947–64), who established parliamentary government and became noted for his “neutralist” policies in foreign affairs. He was also one of the principal leaders of India's independence movement in the 1930s and '40s.
</Question>
<Choice>Nehru, Jawaharlal</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prince (1860–1910) and then king (1910–18) of Montenegro, who transformed his small principality into a sovereign European nation.Heir presumptive to his uncle Danilo II, who was childless, Nicholas came to the throne in August 1860 after Danilo's assassination. Educated abroad in Paris and Trieste, he was throughout his reign faced with the difficult task of popularizing Western ways. A strong prince and an outstanding leader, he fought the Turks in 1862 and again in 1876, when he conducted a brilliant campaign. At the Congress of Berlin (1878), Montenegro was doubled in size, with an outlet...
</Question>
<Choice>Nicholas I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the last Russian emperor (1894–1917), who, with his wife, Alexandra, and their children, was killed by the Bolsheviks after the October Revolution.
</Question>
<Choice>Nicholas II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian statesman who was prime minister for a critical year after World War I.After a career as a journalist and professor of economics, Nitti was elected deputy in 1904. A Left Liberal, he served as minister of agriculture, industry, and commerce in 1911–14 and as minister of the treasury in 1917–19. He succeeded Vittorio Emanuele Orlando, the wartime prime minister, in June 1919, in the midst of foreign and domestic crises involving Italian territorial claims disputed by other Allied countries and the economic and fiscal problems created by the war and demobilization. Nitti's adoption of th...
</Question>
<Choice>Nitti, Francesco Saverio</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Iraqi army officer, statesman, and political leader who maintained close ties with Great Britain and worked for Arab unity.Nuri was commissioned in the Turkish Army in 1909, when Iraq was a province of the Ottoman Empire. During World War I (1914–18) he participated in Ottoman military operations against the British. He was soon captured by the British, however, and in 1916 he joined the Sharifian Arab army led by Amir Fay?al I, which Great Britain was supporting in a revolt against Ottoman rule in the Arab provinces; Nuri distinguished himself in battle. At the war's end Fay?al established a...
</Question>
<Choice>Nuri as-Said</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
soldier, statesman, and reformer who, as president, restored order to Mexico after a decade of political upheavals and civil war that followed the revolution of 1910.Though Obregón had little formal education, he learned a great deal about the needs and desires of poor Mexicans from his work as a farmer and labourer. He did not take part in the revolution (1910–11) that overthrew the dictator Porfirio Díaz, but in 1912 he led a group of volunteers in support of President Francisco Madero against the rebellion led by Pascual Orozco. When Madero was overthrown and assassinated by Victoriano Huer...
</Question>
<Choice>Obregón, Álvaro</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician who twice served as prime minister of Japan (1898; 1914–16). He organized the Rikken Kaishinto (“Progressive Party”) and founded Waseda University.After receiving a conventional education, Okuma turned to Western studies and took the then-unusual step of learning English. Following the Meiji Restoration (1868), which reestablished the formal ruling authority of the emperor, leaders of the Meiji government broadened their base of support by adding representation from Okuma's Saga domain. His ability and courage soon brought him an important role in government, at first specializing i...
</Question>
<Choice>Okuma Shigenobu</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian statesman and prime minister during the concluding years of World War I and head of his country's delegation to the Versailles Peace Conference.Educated at Palermo, Orlando made a name for himself with writings on electoral reform and government administration before being elected to the Chamber of Deputies in 1897. He served as minister of education in 1903–05 and of justice in 1907–09, resuming the same portfolio in 1914. He favoured Italy's entrance into the war (May 1915), and in October 1917, in the crisis following the defeat of Italy's forces at the Battle of Caporetto by the Au...
</Question>
<Choice>Orlando, Vittorio Emanuele</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Finnish statesman and diplomat who, as prime minister (1918, 1944–46) and then president (1946–56) of Finland, cultivated harmonious relations with the Soviet Union in an effort to ensure some measure of independence for Finland.Paasikivi studied law and history at the universities of Stockholm, Uppsala, and Leipzig and from 1902 to 1903 was a lecturer in law at the University of Helsinki. He subsequently turned to financial administration and banking and insurance activities. Paasikivi was a political realist who took the view that small nations could not permanently hope to oppose the power...
</Question>
<Choice>Paasikivi, Juho Kusti</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polish pianist, composer, and statesman, who was prime minister of Poland in 1919.The son of a steward of a Polish landowner, he studied music from 1872 at the Warsaw Conservatory and from 1878 taught piano there. In 1880 he married one of his pupils, Antonina Korsak, who died in childbirth the following year. Encouraged and financed by the actress Helena Modrzejewska (Modjeska), he studied in Vienna from 1884 to 1887 under Theodor Leschetizky, who did much to improve a limited technique. During this period he also taught at the Strasbourg Conservatory. Between 1887 and 1891 he made his first...
</Question>
<Choice>Paderewski, Ignacy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Australian statesman, coleader of the federal government (1923–29) in coalition with Stanley M. Bruce. As head of the Country Party (1920–39), he was a spokesman for the party's goal of rural economic development and was briefly prime minister of Australia in 1939.A physician in New South Wales, Page entered the federal Parliament in 1919. In 1920 he helped found the Country Party (now the National Party), and in the following year he became the party's leader. He formed a coalition with the Nationalist Party to create the Bruce-Page ministry of 1923–29, which was noted for its economic progra...
</Question>
<Choice>Page, Sir Earle</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
soldier and statesman who for eight months in 1926 was dictator of Greece.After service in World War I and the unsuccessful Greek campaign in western Turkey (1921–22), Pangalos was appointed minister of war shortly after the abdication of King Constantine (1922). He directed the military court that condemned those responsible for the rout of Greek forces at Afyon, Turkey, in August 1922 and the later massacre of Greeks in Smyrna (now Izmir, Turkey). In 1923 he was also commander in chief in Thrace. In June 1925 he staged a coup and had himself installed as prime minister, and on Jan. 3, 1926,...
</Question>
<Choice>Pangalos, Theodoros</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
soldier and statesman who late in life organized a political party and became premier (1952–55) of Greece.Papagos, commissioned in 1906, saw his first service in the Balkan Wars (1912–13). He took part in the Greek invasion of Turkey (1919–22), won promotion to the rank of major general (1927), and became corps commander and minister of war (1935); the following year he was named chief of staff. Although at the time of the Italian attack on Greece (October 1940), he conducted, as commander in chief, a passive, basically defensive campaign, he nonetheless succeeded in driving the Italians back...
</Question>
<Choice>Papagos, Alexandros</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German statesman and diplomat who played a leading role in dissolving the Weimar Republic and in helping Adolf Hitler to become German chancellor in 1933.The scion of a wealthy Catholic landowning family, Papen began his career as a professional soldier. At the beginning of World War I, he was military attaché in Washington, but after being implicated in cases of espionage and sabotage, he was recalled in 1915 at the request of the U.S. government. Until the end of the war he served as chief of staff of the 4th Turkish Army in Palestine. Returning after the war to Germany, Papen, a monarchist,...
</Question>
<Choice>Papen, Franz von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Estonian statesman who served as the last president of Estonia (1938–40) before its incorporation into the Soviet Union in 1940.Of peasant stock, Päts was educated in the law but began a career in journalism in 1901, when he founded the Estonian-language newspaper Teataja (“Announcer”), which reflected Päts's socialistic leanings. In 1904 Päts became deputy mayor of Tallinn. During an Estonian rising in connection with the 1905 Russian Revolution, Päts, although he had called for restraint, was sentenced to death and had to flee Estonia. He was not able to return until 1910, at which time he s...
</Question>
<Choice>Päts, Konstantin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
army colonel who became president of Argentina (1946–52, 1952–55, 1973–74) and was founder and leader of the Peronist movement.
</Question>
<Choice>Perón, Juan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French general who was a national hero for his victory at the Battle of Verdun in World War I but was discredited as chief of state of the French government at Vichy in World War II. He died under sentence in a prison fortress.Born into a family of farmers in northern France, Pétain, after attending the local village school and a religious secondary school, was admitted to Saint-Cyr, France's principal military academy. As a young second lieutenant in an Alpine regiment, sharing the rough outdoor life of his men, he came to understand the ordinary soldier. The extraordinary popularity he was l...
</Question>
<Choice>Pétain, Philippe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Serbia from 1903, the first strictly constitutional monarch of his country. In 1918 he became the first king of the Kingdom of Serbs, Croats, and Slovenes (later called Yugoslavia).Born the third son of the reigning prince Alexander Karadjordjevic (1842–58), Peter became heir to the throne on the death of his brother Svetozar (1847). After his father was forced to abdicate (1858), Peter lived in exile for the next 45 years. Educated in France, mainly at military schools such as the prestigious Saint-Cyr, he served as a lieutenant in the French Army during the Franco-German War and was...
</Question>
<Choice>Peter I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the last king of Yugoslavia.The son of Alexander I, who was assassinated during a visit to France on Oct. 9, 1934, Peter became titular king at 11, but the actual rule was in the hands of a regent, his uncle Prince Paul. After Paul was deposed by a coup of officers led by Gen. Dušan Simovic on March 27, 1941, Peter ruled for a few weeks until Axis troops invaded. He then fled into exile in London, where he led an émigré government. In 1944 he married Princess Alexandra of Greece, and, after the Yugoslav monarchy was abolished by Tito in 1945, he settled in the U.S. He wrote A King's Heritage (...
</Question>
<Choice>Peter II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
field marshal and premier of Thailand in 1938–44 and 1948–57, who was associated with the rise of authoritarian military governments in Thailand.He was educated at the royal military academy, and in 1914 he entered the Siamese artillery corps. In 1924–27 he took advanced military training in France, where he became involved with Thai students who were plotting the overthrow of the absolute monarchy. On returning to Bangkok, he served as a major on the army general staff, and in 1928 he received the title by which he was known thereafter, Luang Phibunsongkhram, which he later took as his family...
</Question>
<Choice>Phibunsongkhram, Luang</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polish revolutionary and statesman, the first chief of state (1918–22) of the newly independent Poland established in November 1918. After leading a coup d'état in 1926, he rejected an offer of the presidency but remained politically influential while serving as minister of defense until 1935.
</Question>
<Choice>Pilsudski, Józef</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French statesman who as prime minister in 1912 largely determined the policy that led to France's involvement in World War I, during which he served as president of the Third Republic.The son of an engineer, he was educated at the École Polytechnique. After studying law at the University of Paris, he was admitted to the bar in 1882. Elected a deputy in 1887, he became six years later the youngest minister in the history of the Third Republic, holding the portfolio of education. In 1894 he served as minister of finance and in 1895 again as minister of education. In the Dreyfus Affair he declare...
</Question>
<Choice>Poincaré, Raymond</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
last absolute king of Siam (1925–35), under whose rule the Thai revolution of 1932 instituted the constitutional monarchy. Prajadhipok never expected to succeed to the throne. He was the 32nd and last son of King Chulalongkorn, the youngest of five sons by Queen Saowabha.When King Vajiravudh died in 1925, Prajadhipok had been a likely heir to the throne for less than a year and the certain heir for only two days. He had been prepared for a military career at Eton College and the Royal Military Academy at Woolwich, Eng. Though personally convinced of the necessity of moving toward democratic po...
</Question>
<Choice>Prajadhipok</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first president of the Republic of India (1950–62). A lawyer turned journalist, he was a comrade of Mahatma Gandhi in the earliest noncooperation movements for independence and was also president of the Indian National Congress (1934, 1939, and 1947).Raised in a landowning family of modest means, Prasad was a graduate of the Calcutta Law College. He practiced at the Calcutta High Court and in 1916 transferred to the Patna High Court and founded the Bihar Law Weekly. In 1917 he was recruited by Gandhi to help in a campaign to improve conditions for peasants exploited by British indigo planters...
</Question>
<Choice>Prasad, Rajendra</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
general and statesman who, as dictator of Spain from September 1923 to January 1930, founded an authoritarian and nationalistic regime that attempted to unify the nation around the motto “Country, Religion, Monarchy.” Though it enjoyed success in certain areas, his repressive government failed to create an acceptable political system and succumbed to the widespread discontent that it had engendered.Born into a military family, Primo de Rivera was graduated from the General Military Academy in Toledo in 1888 and served as an officer in Morocco, Cuba, and the Philippines. In 1915 he was named mi...
</Question>
<Choice>Primo de Rivera, Miguel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
last emperor (1908–1911/12) of the Qing (Manchu) dynasty (1644–1911/12) in China and puppet emperor of the Japanese-controlled state of Manchukuo (Chinese: Manzhouguo) from 1934 to 1945.Puyi succeeded to the Manchu throne at the age of three, when his uncle, the Guangxu emperor, died on Nov. 14, 1908. He reigned under a regency for three years, and then on Feb. 12, 1912, in response to the Republican Revolution of the previous year, he was forced to abdicate, ending the 267-year Qing rule of China and the 2,000-year-old imperial system. He was permitted to continue living in the palace in Beij...
</Question>
<Choice>P'u-i</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Filipino statesman, leader of the independence movement, and first president of the Philippine Commonwealth established under U.S. tutelage in 1935.Quezon was the son of a schoolteacher and small landholder of Tagalog descent on the island of Luzon. He cut short his law studies at the University of Santo Tomás in Manila in 1899 to participate in the struggle for independence against the United States, led by Emilio Aguinaldo. After Aguinaldo surrendered in 1901, however, Quezon returned to the university, obtained his degree (1903), and practiced law for a few years. Convinced that the only wa...
</Question>
<Choice>Quezon, Manuel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
political leader and second president of the independent Republic of the Philippines.After obtaining a law degree from the University of the Philippines, near Manila, in 1915, Quirino practiced law until he was elected a member of the Philippine House of Representatives in 1919–25 and a senator in 1925–31. In 1934 he was a member of the Philippine independence mission to Washington, D.C., headed by Manuel Quezon, which secured the passage in Congress of the Tydings–McDuffie Act, setting the date for Philippine independence as July 4, 1946. He was also elected to the convention that drafted a c...
</Question>
<Choice>Quirino, Elpidio</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hungarian Communist ruler of Hungary from 1945 to 1956.An adherent of Social Democracy from his youth, Rákosi returned to Hungary a Communist in 1918, after a period as prisoner of war in Russia. He served as commissar for Socialist production in the short-lived Communist regime of Béla Kun (1919) but, with the triumph of counterrevolution in Hungary, was forced to flee to Moscow. Dispatched in 1924 to reorganize the Hungarian Communist Party, he was arrested by the Hungarian authorities the following year and in 1927 was sentenced to eight and a half years in prison from the date of his arres...
</Question>
<Choice>Rákosi, Mátyás</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman and prime minister of Australia (1904–05) who as premier of New South Wales (1894–99) directed an economic recovery program, maintained free trade, and introduced a tax to break up land monopolies.Reid, whose family had emigrated to Melbourne in 1852, served in the colonial Treasury (1864–78) and began a law practice in Sydney in 1879. Elected to the New South Wales Parliament in 1880, he became minister of public instruction (1883–84) and introduced pioneer bills for technical education and evening university lectures.Becoming premier in 1894, Reid implemented close financial accoun...
</Question>
<Choice>Reid, Sir George Houston</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Social Democratic statesman, chancellor (1918–20, 1945) and president (1945–50) of Austria, who after World War I advocated the Anschluss (union) between Germany and Austria. He played a major role in reestablishing Austrian home rule after the end of the German occupation in 1945.Of peasant stock, Renner studied law at the University of Vienna and became a member of the moderate wing of the Austrian Social Democratic Party. A deputy to the Reichsrat (lower house of parliament) from 1907, Renner became the first chancellor of the new Austrian republic after the collapse of the Habsburg monarch...
</Question>
<Choice>Renner, Karl</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French politician and statesman who, as premier in June 1940, unsuccessfully attempted to save France from German occupation in World War II.Reynaud was a lawyer and served in the army during World War I. Afterward he represented his home district (1919–24) and then a Paris constituency (from 1928) in the Chamber of Deputies and was minister of finance, of colonies, and of justice between 1930 and 1932. Out of office until 1938, he was almost alone in calling on France to resist Nazi Germany and to prepare for combined tank-air warfare, as recommended by Colonel Charles de Gaulle. Appointed mi...
</Question>
<Choice>Reynaud, Paul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Iranian army officer who rose through army ranks to become shah of Iran (1925–41) and began the regeneration of his country.
</Question>
<Choice>Reza Shah Pahlavi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
32nd president of the United States (1933–45). The only president elected to the office four times, Roosevelt led the United States through two of the greatest crises of the 20th century: the Great Depression and World War II. In so doing, he greatly expanded the powers of the federal government through a series of programs and reforms known as the New Deal, and he served as the principal architect of the successful effort to rid the world of German National Socialism and Japanese militarism. (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of A...
</Question>
<Choice>Roosevelt, Franklin D.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
26th president of the United States (1901–09) and writer, naturalist, and soldier. He expanded the powers of the presidency and of the federal government in support of the public interest in conflicts between big business and labour and steered the nation toward an active role in world politics, particularly in Europe and Asia. He won the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1906 for mediating an end to the Russo-Japanese War, and he secured the route and began construction of the Panama Canal (1904–14). (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of A...
</Question>
<Choice>Roosevelt, Theodore</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British prime minister from March 3, 1894, to June 21, 1895; faced with a divided Cabinet and a hostile House of Lords, his ministry achieved little of consequence.His father, Archibald Primrose, son of the 4th earl, died before Archibald was four; as heir to the earldom he therefore bore the title of Lord Dalmeny at Eton. He studied at Christ Church, Oxford, without receiving a degree, and in 1868 he succeeded to the earldom and to large estates in Scotland. Early on, he had taken an interest in politics, leaning toward Liberalism, but he never sat in the House of Commons.At Rosebery's sugges...
</Question>
<Choice>Rosebery, Archibald Philip Primrose, 5th earl of</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French statesman who had some success in balancing the budget during periods of his seven terms as minister of finance and two terms as premier.Having launched the republican journal L'Égalité in 1870, Rouvier, a supporter of Léon Gambetta—one of the founding fathers of the Third Republic—served as deputy in the National Assembly from 1871 to 1902. A financial technician, he served on budget commissions, often as chairman, and as minister for commerce and the colonies (1881–82) and for commerce (1884–85). Resisting pressure from rightists to include General Georges Boulanger in his cabinet, Ro...
</Question>
<Choice>Rouvier, Maurice</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
political leader and first president (1946–48) of the independent Republic of the Philippines.After studying law at the University of the Philippines, near Manila, Roxas began his political career in 1917 as a member of the municipal council of Capiz (renamed Roxas in 1949). He was governor of the province of Capiz in 1919–21 and was then elected to the Philippine House of Representatives, subsequently serving as Speaker of the House and a member of the Council of State. In 1923 he and Manuel Quezon, the president of the Senate, resigned in protest from the Council of State when the U.S. gover...
</Question>
<Choice>Roxas, Manuel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nicaraguan statesman who served as his country's president in 1932–36.Sacasa studied in the United States from 1889 to 1901, earning an M.D. from Columbia University. In 1924 he was elected vice president of Nicaragua as leader of the Liberal Party in a coalition government. The following year a coup d'état installed General Emiliano Chamorro Vargas as president and forced Sacasa into exile. When Chamorro was replaced by Adolfo Díaz in 1926, Sacasa returned to assert his claim to the presidency. In the wake of Sacasa's announcement, Mexico sided with Sacasa; the United States, involved in a di...
</Question>
<Choice>Sacasa, Juan Bautista</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
president of Argentina from 1910 until his death, an aristocratic conservative who wisely responded to popular demand for electoral reform. Universal and compulsory male suffrage from age 18 by secret ballot was established (1912) in Argentina by a statute that he compelled an oligarchical legislature to pass and that has since been known by his name.Sáenz Peña's father, Luis, served as president of Argentina from 1892 to 1895. Roque, who inherited his father's enemies, traveled in Europe before entering politics in the 1870s. He held the office of foreign minister, served as Argentine delegat...
</Question>
<Choice>Sáenz Peña, Roque</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Canadian statesman and jurist who, as Liberal prime minister in 1948–57, helped to maintain Canadian unity and to bring about reforms.Saint Laurent studied at St. Charles College (Sherbrooke) and at Laval University (Quebec). He was called to the bar in 1905 and became one of Canada's leading lawyers, serving two terms as president of the Canadian Bar Association. In 1914 he was appointed professor of law at Laval University. In 1941 he was asked by Prime Minister W.L. Mackenzie King to enter public life.As a member of the Liberal Party, Saint Laurent was elected to the Canadian House of Commo...
</Question>
<Choice>Saint Laurent, Louis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the longest-surviving member of the oligarchy that governed Japan after the Meiji Restoration (1868), which had overthrown the ruling Tokugawa family and formally reestablished the authority of the emperor. As prime minister and elder statesman (genro), he attempted to moderate his country's increasing militarism.Saionji was born into the old court nobility. After studying in France, he returned to Japan in 1881 and founded the Toyo Jiyu Shimbun (“Oriental Free Press”), a newspaper dedicated to popularizing democratic ideas. But journalism was considered a scandalous profession for a court nob...
</Question>
<Choice>Saionji Kimmochi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian statesman who was premier at the beginning of World War I (1914–16).Salandra was educated in law and taught public administration at the University of Rome before entering politics. A member of a wealthy family and a conservative, he rose to become minister of agriculture in 1899 and finance minister in 1906 and again in 1909–10. He became premier in March 1914 and so was confronted with a critical decision on the outbreak of World War I in July. Despite the generation-old Triple Alliance of Germany, Austria-Hungary, and Italy, Salandra chose neutrality, taking for legal ground the fai...
</Question>
<Choice>Salandra, Antonio</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Portuguese economist, who served as prime minister of Portugal for 36 years (1932–68).Salazar, the son of an estate manager at Santa Comba Dão, was educated at the seminary at Viseu and at the University of Coimbra. He graduated from there in law in 1914 and became a professor specializing in economics at Coimbra. He helped form the Catholic Centre Party in 1921 and was elected to the Cortes (parliament), but he resigned after one session and returned to the university. In May 1926, after the army had overthrown Portugal's parliamentary government, Salazar was offered the cabinet post of minis...
</Question>
<Choice>Salazar, António de Oliveira</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French Radical Socialist statesman most noted for his colonial policy and liberal rule as governor-general of Indochina.Sarraut was born into an important Radical family that owned the newspaper Dépêche de Toulouse. Educated at the lycée of Carcassonne and the law faculty of Toulouse, he became a lawyer. As a member of the Chamber of Deputies (1902–24), Sarraut served as undersecretary of state (1906–09), undersecretary of war (1909–10), and minister of education (1914–15), and twice as governor-general of Indochina (1911–14, 1916–19). As governor-general he applied liberal policies, increasin...
</Question>
<Choice>Sarraut, Albert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman who, as New Zealand's first Labour prime minister (1935–40), won public support for his administration's economic recovery and social-welfare programs.After working as a gold miner and a labour organizer in Australia, Savage immigrated to New Zealand in 1907, where he soon became active in the Auckland trade union movement. He joined the Labour Party on its formation in 1916, becoming its deputy leader in 1923 and parliamentary leader in 1933. He greatly contributed to the Labour victory in 1935, when he became prime minister and headed the ministries of external affairs, native affa...
</Question>
<Choice>Savage, Michael Joseph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German Social Democratic politician who, without party or government authorization, on Nov. 9, 1918, made the Weimar Republic a fact by proclaiming it from the balcony of the Reichstag. He later became the republic's first chancellor.A journalist and (from 1903) member of the Reichstag for the Social Democrats, Scheidemann joined the majority of his party in supporting Germany's participation in World War I. Toward the war's end, he was appointed minister without portfolio in the last imperial cabinet (October 1918). Although the Social Democrats had planned to support a constitutional monarch...
</Question>
<Choice>Scheidemann, Philipp</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German army officer, last chancellor of the Weimar Republic, an opponent of Adolf Hitler in 1932–33.Joining the German military in 1900, Schleicher attached himself to the newly created Reichswehr in 1919 and by 1929 was a major general in charge of an office in the Reichswehr ministry. For the next three years, Schleicher—with Wilhelm Groener, minister of defense, Chancellor Heinrich Brüning, and Pres. Paul von Hindenburg—was one of the determining forces in the Weimar Republic. Schleicher came into sharp conflict with Brüning and Hindenburg; his intrigues contributed to Brüning's downfall (M...
</Question>
<Choice>Schleicher, Kurt von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
police official who was twice prime minister of Austria (1921–22 and 1929–30). He established friendly relations with the Czechoslovak republic but was unable to negotiate a union between Austria and Germany.Schober entered the imperial Austrian police service as a young man and became president of police in 1918, a few months before the fall of the Habsburg monarchy at the end of World War I. Upon the proclamation of the Austrian republic in November of that year, he ensured police loyalty to the new government, a decision that probably prevented considerable bloodshed. Schober's administrati...
</Question>
<Choice>Schober, Johann</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Southern African politician who was prime minister of Cape Colony at the outbreak of the South African War (1899–1902); he was the younger brother of author and political activist Olive Schreiner. A moderate politician, he tried to prevent the war and later was a champion of African civil rights.Schreiner became a member of the Cape Colony Parliament in 1893 and was a minister in the government of Cecil Rhodes in 1893 and 1894–96. Elected prime minister in 1898 with the support of the Afrikaner Bond, he first sought a peaceful settlement of differences between the British and the Boers and the...
</Question>
<Choice>Schreiner, William Philip</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman and leader of the Australian Labor Party who as prime minister guided the country through the early years of the Great Depression but was plagued by dissension within his own party.After joining the Labor Party in 1903, Scullin served in Parliament (1910–13) and edited a Labor newspaper, the Echo, during World War I. Elected to Parliament again in 1922, he became leader of the party in 1928 and helped it become stronger than it had been since its split in 1916. When he became prime minister in 1929, he was immediately confronted with the economic depression, compounded by opposition...
</Question>
<Choice>Scullin, James Henry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
New Zealand statesman who as prime minister (1893–1906) led a Liberal Party ministry that sponsored innovating legislation for land settlement, labour protection, and old age pensions.After working in iron foundries in England, Seddon went to Australia in 1863 to work at the Bendigo goldfields in Victoria. He moved to Hokitika, N.Z., in 1866, again for gold mining, and in 1869 he became an advocate for miners in goldfield disputes. His prominence in local politics gained him a seat in Parliament in 1879. Serving as minister of mines and public works in the Liberal ministry of John Ballance (18...
</Question>
<Choice>Seddon, Richard John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first prime minister of Ceylon (1947–52) when the country became independent of Great Britain.Brought up as a devout Buddhist, Senanayake remained in that faith but was educated at the Anglican St. Thomas College in Colombo. After a brief period as a clerk in the surveyor general's office, he turned to rubber planting on his father's estate. Senanayake entered the Legislative Council in 1922 and in 1931 was elected to the State Council and appointed minister for agriculture and lands, a post he was to hold for 15 years. Within two years he had put through the Land Development Ordinance, which...
</Question>
<Choice>Senanayake, D S</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian Nazi leader who was chancellor of Austria during the Anschluss (annexation of Austria by Germany in 1938).Seyss-Inquart served in the Austro-Hungarian army during World War I and was seriously wounded. Returning to Vienna after the war, he became a lawyer there in 1921. He also became a fervent advocate of a political union of Austria with Germany, and he cultivated close ties with the Austrian Nazi Party. A leader of the moderate “legal” faction of the Austrian Nazis, Seyss-Inquart was appointed to the Austrian Staatsrat (federal council of state) in June 1937 in order to bring the N...
</Question>
<Choice>Seyss-Inquart, Arthur</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(Baron) Japanese diplomat, statesman, and prime minister for a brief period after World War II (1945–46). He was so closely identified with the peaceful foreign policy followed by Japan in the 1920s that this policy is usually referred to as Shidehara diplomacy.Shidehara entered the diplomatic service in 1899 and served in Korea, London, Washington, and The Netherlands. As ambassador to the United States in 1919, he argued in vain against U.S. immigration laws discriminating against the Japanese. He was the chief Japanese delegate to the Washington Conference (1921–22), in which the major Paci...
</Question>
<Choice>Shidehara Kijuro, Danshaku</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polish soldier and statesman who led Poland's government in exile during World War II.Born and educated in Austrian Poland, Sikorski served in the Austrian Army. In 1908 he founded a secret Polish military organization, in which Józef Pilsudski was also prominent. During World War I, Sikorski was war commissioner of the Polish Legion, which served with the Austrian Army against Russia. He later distinguished himself in the Polish–Soviet War (1920–21), and in 1921 he was named chief of the Polish general staff.In 1922–23 Sikorski served briefly as prime minister of Poland. In 1924–25, as minist...
</Question>
<Choice>Sikorski, Wladyslaw</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Cambodia from 1904 until his death. He was a figurehead for the French colonial administration, which had secured the protectorate over Cambodia in a treaty signed by Sisowath's half-brother Norodom in 1863.With Norodom, Sisowath received his education under the surveillance of the Thai sovereign at Bangkok because Siam (Thailand), with Vietnam, had long held Cambodia in vassalage and chosen Cambodian sovereigns. Sisowath remained at Bangkok until his father, King Duong, died in 1860. He then went to Oudong, the old Cambodian capital just north of Phnom Penh, to prevent his younger hal...
</Question>
<Choice>Sisowath</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
influential Indonesian nationalist and prime minister who favoured the adoption of Western constitutional democracy for Indonesia.Sjahrir, son of a public prosecutor, received a Dutch education in Sumatra and Java and attended the Law Faculty at the University of Leiden. In The Netherlands he was a member of a socialist student group and secretary of the student group Perhimpunan Indonesia (“Indonesian Union”), which numbered among its members many of Indonesia's future political leaders. He returned to the Dutch East Indies in 1931 and helped establish the Pendidikan Nasional Indonesia, a riv...
</Question>
<Choice>Sjahrir, Sutan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
South African statesman, soldier, and prime minister (1919–24, 1939–48), who sought to promote South Africa as a responsible member of the (British) Commonwealth.
</Question>
<Choice>Smuts, Jan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
family that maintained political control of Nicaragua for 44 years.The founder of the dynasty, Anastasio Somoza García (b. Feb. 1, 1896, San Marcos, Nicaragua—d. Sept. 29, 1956, Ancón, Panama Canal Zone [now Panama]), was the son of a wealthy coffee planter and was educated in Nicaragua and the United States. By marrying the daughter of a prominent Nicaraguan family, he ensured himself a secure political career. He rose quickly through the political ranks to become head of Nicaragua's army, the National Guard, in 1933. With the army at his disposal, he three years later deposed the elected pre...
</Question>
<Choice>Somoza Family</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(Baron) Italian statesman who as foreign minister promoted his country's entrance into World War I. He was also prime minister in 1906 and 1909–10.Having joined the diplomatic service in the 1860s shortly after the formation of a united Italy, Sonnino left it to devote time to political, social, and economic studies of Italian life. These studies led in 1876 to an important work on conditions in Sicily (La Sicilia nel 1876 [1877]) and in 1878 to his founding of a weekly economic review, La Rassegna Settimanale, that he later converted into a political daily. When he was elected deputy in 1880,...
</Question>
<Choice>Sonnino, Sidney, Barone</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
architect of the Finnish constitution and the first president of independent Finland.Joining the Constitutionalist Party, Ståhlberg was elected to the Diet in 1904 and entered the government of the autonomous Grand Duchy of Finland in 1905 but resigned in 1907. From 1908 to 1918 he was professor of administrative law at the University of Helsinki.Consistently democratic in outlook, he was among the first Finnish politicians to call for universal suffrage. His draft of a republican constitution (1917) became the basis of the actual constitution of 1919. In the reshuffling of the political parti...
</Question>
<Choice>Ståhlberg, Kaarlo Juho</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
secretary-general of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union (1922–53) and premier of the Soviet state (1941–53), who for a quarter of a century dictatorially ruled the Soviet Union and transformed it into a major world power.During the quarter of a century preceding his death, the Soviet dictator Joseph Stalin probably exercised greater political power than any other figure in history. Stalin industrialized the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics, forcibly collectivized its agriculture, consolidated his position by intensive police terror, helped to defeat Germany in 1941–45, and extended Sov...
</Question>
<Choice>Stalin, Joseph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
leader of the Agrarian Party in Bulgaria, supporter of the Allied cause during World War I in opposition to his pro-German king Ferdinand, and prime minister of a reformist government after the war (1919–23).After attending an agricultural college in Germany, Stamboliyski turned to journalism, becoming editor of the newly formed Agrarian League's organ in 1902. A lifelong supporter of peasant interests, he entered the National Assembly in 1908 as head of the Bulgarian Agrarian Union (Peasant Party). His recurrent disputes with King Ferdinand finally climaxed in 1915, when Bulgaria prepared to...
</Question>
<Choice>Stamboliyski, Aleksandur</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Danish Social Democratic statesman who as prime minister (1924–26, 1929–42) widened the base of his party by gaining passage of key economic and social welfare legislation.A tobacco worker and trade unionist, Stauning was elected secretary of the Social Democratic Party in 1898 and entered the Folketing (lower house of Parliament) in 1906. After becoming party chairman in 1910, he served from 1916 to 1920 in the Radical-Liberal ministry of Carl Theodor Zahle, which sponsored reforms of the judicial and landholding systems and of local governments.The monetary reforms of Stauning's first admini...
</Question>
<Choice>Stauning, Thorvald</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
conservative statesman who, after the Russian Revolution of 1905, initiated far-reaching agrarian reforms to improve the legal and economic status of the peasantry as well as the general economy and political stability of imperial Russia.Appointed governor of the provinces of Grodno (1902) and Saratov (1903), Stolypin demonstrated his concern for improving the welfare of the peasants as well as his firmness and efficiency in subduing their rebellions. Consequently, he gained the favour of Emperor Nicholas II and was appointed minister of the interior in May 1906. In July he was also named pres...
</Question>
<Choice>Stolypin, Pyotr Arkadyevich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
New Zealand statesman and judge who helped unify the Liberal Party during the late 1870s; as prime minister (1884–87) he worked to expand opportunities for small farmers.A surveyor and an advocate of radical land reform in Lerwick, Stout emigrated to New Zealand in 1863 after hearing of the Otago gold rush. Finding no work as a surveyor, he became a teacher and then a barrister and solicitor in the Supreme Court (1871). Elected to Parliament as a Liberal (1875), he opposed the abolition of provinces, the leading issue of the time, and gained a national reputation. In 1878 he was named attorney...
</Question>
<Choice>Stout, Sir Robert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
chancellor (1923) and foreign minister (1923, 1924–29) of the Weimar Republic, largely responsible for restoring Germany's international status after World War I. With French foreign minister Aristide Briand, he was awarded the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1926 for his policy of reconciliation and negotiation.
</Question>
<Choice>Stresemann, Gustav</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
leader of the Chinese Nationalist Party (Kuomintang [Pinyin: Guomindang]), known as the father of modern China. Influential in overthrowing the Qing (Manchu) dynasty (1911/12), he served as the first provisional president of the Republic of China (1911–12) and later as de facto ruler (1923–25).
</Question>
<Choice>Sun Yat-sen</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the last premier (April–August 1945) of Japan during World War II, who was forced to surrender to the Allies.A veteran of the Sino-Japanese (1894–95) and Russo-Japanese (1904–05) wars, Suzuki was promoted to the rank of admiral in 1923 and became chief of the Naval General Staff two years later. He was appointed grand chamberlain (jijucho) in 1929, but he resigned this post after narrowly surviving the young officers' revolt in 1936.Suzuki became prime minister upon the resignation of Koiso Kuniaki on April 5, 1945, four days after U.S. forces had landed on Okinawa. Though adamant and unyieldi...
</Question>
<Choice>Suzuki Kantaro, Baron</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first chief of state of independent Finland, as prime minister and then as president. He headed the Finnish government during his country's civil war (1918) and in the early 1930s. He was instrumental in suppressing Finland's Communist Party and maintaining a rightist regime.Svinhufvud entered the Finnish Parliament in 1894, while Finland was still part of the Russian Empire. His anti-Russian position earned him exile in Siberia from 1914 to 1917. Having returned at the outbreak of the Russian Revolution of March 1917, he became prime minister of Finland, on November 27. He led the victorious...
</Question>
<Choice>Svinhufvud, Pehr Evind</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Iranian statesman who led the coup d'état of 1921 in which he was made prime minister.Tabataba?i became prominent during World War I as the editor of a pro-British newspaper, Ra?d (“Thunder”). In 1919 he led a quasi-diplomatic mission to negotiate a commercial agreement with the anti-Communist Russian revolutionaries at Baku. On his return to Iran he joined a secret nationalist society, Anjuman-i Fulad (“The Steel Committee”), created a coalition of anticommunist politicians, and masterminded the coup d'état of Feb. 21/22, 1921, that made him prime minister of Iran. Soon after assuming that of...
</Question>
<Choice>Tabataba'i, Sayyid Zia od-Din</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
27th president of the United States (1909–13) and 10th chief justice of the United States (1921–30). As the choice of President Theodore Roosevelt to succeed him and carry on the progressive Republican agenda, Taft as president alienated the progressives—and later Roosevelt—thereby contributing greatly to the split in Republican ranks in 1912, to the formation of the Bull Moose Party (also known as the Progressive Party), and to his humiliating defeat that year in his bid for a second term. (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of Ame...
</Question>
<Choice>Taft, William Howard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(Danshaku) prime minister (1927–29) and author of Japan's aggressive policy toward China in the 1920s.Tanaka distinguished himself in the Russo-Japanese War and as a member of the Japanese army stationed in Manchuria in the early 1900s. Appointed minister of war in 1918, he was one of the most forceful advocates of Japanese involvement in a Siberian expedition against the new Soviet regime in Russia. The civilian leaders of the cabinet finally acquiesced when the United States and other Western countries also sent troops to Russia, but Tanaka, who had dreams of a Japanese empire in Siberia, co...
</Question>
<Choice>Tanaka Giichi, Baron</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(count) Hungarian prime minister who cooperated with Nazi Germany in the early stages of World War II.A member of the Hungarian Parliament from 1905, Teleki, an eminent geographer, was a delegate to the Paris Peace Conference (1919) after World War I. In 1921 he withdrew from party politics, in which he had never greatly believed.After teaching geography at Budapest University, Teleki returned to office as minister of education in May 1938 and became prime minister again on Feb. 15, 1939. As prime minister he dissolved various Fascist parties, although he allowed anti-Semitic laws to stand. Te...
</Question>
<Choice>Teleki, Pál, Gróf</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese soldier and politician who served as Japanese prime minister (1916–18) during World War I.He was born into a family of retainers of the Choshu clan and originally was named Tada Jusaburo. Masatake changed his name when he was adopted into the Terauchi family during his youth. He entered the military at the age of 12 and became a protégé of Yamagata Aritomo, creator of the modern Japanese armed forces. In 1902 Terauchi was made army minister, a position he held for 10 years. In May 1910 he was concurrently appointed resident general of the Japanese colony in Korea, with orders to compl...
</Question>
<Choice>Terauchi Masatake, Count</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Slovak priest and statesman who fought for Slovak autonomy within the Czechoslovak nation during the interwar period and headed the German puppet state of independent Slovakia (1939–45) until he was overthrown by the Red Army and Czechoslovak Partisans at the end of World War II.Becoming a prominent member of Andrej Hlinka's Slovak People's Party after World War I, Tiso was a member of the Czechoslovak government from 1927 to 1929 and succeeded Hlinka as party leader in 1938. On Oct. 6, 1938, he became premier of autonomous Slovakia in the new federal Czechoslovakia, assuming the presidency af...
</Question>
<Choice>Tiso, Jozef</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hungarian statesman who became prime minister of Hungary as well as one of the most prominent defenders of the Austro-Hungarian dualist system of government. He was an opponent of voting franchise reform in Hungary, and he was a loyal supporter of the monarchy's alliance with Germany throughout World War I.Entering the Hungarian Parliament in 1886, Tisza became a leader of the Liberal Party (led by his father, Kálmán Tisza) and a defender of the dual monarchy and of Hungary's large landed interests. He became prime minister in 1903 but was heavily defeated at the polls in 1905. He served as pr...
</Question>
<Choice>Tisza, István, Gróf</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
soldier and statesman who was prime minister of Japan during most of World War II (1941–44) and who was subsequently tried and executed for war crimes.A graduate of the Imperial Military Academy and the Military Staff College, Tojo served briefly as military attaché in Japan's embassy in Berlin after World War I. He was an esteemed administrator and skillful field commander and became noted as a stern disciplinarian. In 1928 he was made commander of the lst Infantry Regiment, which in 1936 participated in the mutiny of the Tokyo garrison. In 1937 he was named chief of staff of the Kwantung Arm...
</Question>
<Choice>Tojo Hideki</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
dictator of the Dominican Republic from 1930 until his assassination in 1961.Trujillo entered the Dominican army in 1918 and was trained by U.S. Marines during the U.S. occupation (1916–24) of the country. He rose from lieutenant to commanding colonel of the national police between 1919 and 1925, becoming a general in 1927. Trujillo seized power in the military revolt against Pres. Horacio Vásquez in 1930. From that time until his assassination 31 years later, Trujillo remained in absolute control of the Dominican Republic through his command of the army, by placing family members in office, a...
</Question>
<Choice>Trujillo, Rafael</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(seeResearcher's Note) 33rd president of the United States (1945–53), who led his nation through the final stages of World War II and through the early years of the Cold War, vigorously opposing Soviet expansionism in Europe and sending U.S. forces to turn back a communist invasion of South Korea. (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America.)
</Question>
<Choice>Truman, Harry S.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman whose 27 years as Liberia's 17th president constituted the longest tenure in that office in the history of Africa's first republic (proclaimed in 1847). He was responsible for numerous reforms and social policies, including enactment of suffrage and property rights for all female residents of 21 or older; authorization of direct participation in government by all tribespeople, who comprise about 80 percent of the population; and the establishment of a nationwide public-school system.A descendant of early American immigrants, mostly liberated slaves, Tubman grew up in poverty and unde...
</Question>
<Choice>Tubman, William V S</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
soldier and dictator who ruled Guatemala for 13 years (1931–44).Ubico received a commission in the Guatemalan army in 1897, distinguished himself in several campaigns, and rose to the rank of colonel. In 1907 he was appointed governor of Alta Verapaz and in 1911 governor of Retalhuleu, where he served with efficiency and honesty. In the following years he was made a brigadier general, a member of the National Assembly, and minister of war (1922–26) under President José María Orellana. In 1931, backed by liberals and progressives, he was elected president of Guatemala, an office he held until 1...
</Question>
<Choice>Ubico, Jorge</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
a leader in the fight for Latvian independence in the early decades of the 20th century. He was the first head of the Latvian Republic in 1918 and again in 1936–40 and was premier in 1918, 1919–21, 1925–26, 1931–32, and 1934–40.Ulmanis studied agronomy in Germany as a young man and afterward worked to improve dairy farming and cattle breeding in Latvia. During the period of upheaval at the time of the Russian Revolution of 1905, he worked to promote freedom from Russia, which had controlled the country for more than a century. The defeat of the revolution forced Ulmanis to seek exile in the Un...
</Question>
<Choice>Ulmanis, Karlis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Siam from 1910 to 1925, noted for his progressive reforms and prolific writings.Vajiravudh was educated at the University of Oxford, where he read history and law; he also received military training at Sandhurst and served briefly with the British Army. Having been named heir apparent in 1895, he returned to Siam in 1903 and succeeded his father, Chulalongkorn, in 1910. Although not comparable to his father as an administrative and political reformer, he promoted numerous social reforms, including a recodification of Siamese law to make monogamy the only legal form of marriage, adoptio...
</Question>
<Choice>Vajiravudh</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
president of Brazil (1930–45, 1951–54), who brought social and economic changes that helped modernize the country. Although denounced by some as an unprincipled dictator, Vargas was revered by his followers as the “Father of the Poor,” for his battle against big business and large landowners. His greatest accomplishment was to guide Brazil as it weathered the far-reaching consequences of the Great Depression and the accompanying polarization between communism and fascism during his long tenure in office.Vargas was born in the state of Rio Grande do Sul, into a family prominent in state politic...
</Question>
<Choice>Vargas, Getúlio</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prime minister of Greece (1910–15, 1917–20, 1924, 1928–32, 1933), the most prominent Greek politician and statesman of the early 20th century. Under his leadership Greece doubled in area and population during the Balkan Wars (1912–13) and also gained territorially and diplomatically after World War I in negotiations with Italy, Bulgaria, and Turkey.
</Question>
<Choice>Venizélos, Eleuthérios</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Italy whose reign brought the end of the Italian monarchy.After a mainly military education, he came suddenly to the throne in 1900 on the assassination of his father, King Umberto I. A tractable constitutional monarch, he accepted a Liberal cabinet and readily acquiesced in Italy's war against Turkey in 1911 and entrance into World War I in 1915.When the strains put on the parliamentary system by the war brought Mussolini to the fore, Victor Emmanuel failed to prevent the Fascist seizure of power, though it apparently lay in his hands to do so merely by signing the decree of martial l...
</Question>
<Choice>Victor Emmanuel III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
New Zealand statesman, prime minister (1906–12, 1928–30), and a key member of the Liberal Party ministries from 1891 to 1906, noted for his financial, social welfare, and postal measures.Ward established a successful grain trade in Invercargill, N.Z., in 1877 and soon became prominent in local politics, gaining a seat in Parliament in 1887. When the Liberal Party took office in 1891 under John Ballance, he became postmaster general and added the post of minister of finance in the succeeding ministry of Richard John Seddon (1893–1906). Ward was responsible for legislation creating state guarant...
</Question>
<Choice>Ward, Sir Joseph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician and the first Labour prime minister of Australia (1904).Educated in New Zealand, Watson moved to Sydney to work as a typographer. He became involved in the labour movement and was elected president of the Sydney Trades and Labour Council and president of the Australia Labour Federation (1893). He was a member of the Legislative Assembly of New South Wales (1894–1901) until he entered federal politics and became the leader of the Labour Party. Although his party did not have a majority in either house, Watson formed the first Commonwealth Labour ministry (1904) but resigned in the sa...
</Question>
<Choice>Watson, John Christian</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first president of the new nation of Israel (1949–52), who was for decades the guiding spirit behind the World Zionist Organization.
</Question>
<Choice>Weizmann, Chaim</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German emperor (kaiser) and king of Prussia from 1888 to the end of World War I in 1918, known for his frequently militaristic manner as well as for his vacillating policies.
</Question>
<Choice>William II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
28th president of the United States (1913–21), an American scholar and statesman best remembered for his legislative accomplishments and his high-minded idealism. Wilson led his country into World War I and became the creator and leading advocate of the League of Nations, for which he was awarded the 1919 Nobel Prize for Peace. During his second term the Nineteenth Amendment to the U.S. Constitution, giving women the right to vote, was passed and ratified. He suffered a paralytic stroke while seeking American public support for the Treaty of Versailles (October 1919), and his incapacity, which...
</Question>
<Choice>Wilson, Woodrow</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polish statesman and leader of the Peasant Party, who was three times prime minister of Poland (1920–21, 1923, 1926).Witos sat during 1908–14 in the Galician Sejm (Diet) of Austria-Poland and in 1911–18 in the Austrian Reichsrat (lower house of parliament). After World War I he was elected to the Sejm of the newly established republic of Poland and soon became the leader of the Peasant Party, then the strongest political group in the Sejm. From July 1920 to September 1921 he served as prime minister of an all-party coalition. In May–December 1923 he headed his second government but was unable...
</Question>
<Choice>Witos, Wincenty</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(Count) Russian minister of finance (1892–1903) and first constitutional prime minister of the Russian Empire (1905–06), who sought to wed firm authoritarian rule to modernization along Western lines.
</Question>
<Choice>Witte, Sergey Yulyevich, Graf</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
one of the leaders in the struggle for Polish independence from Russia in the years before World War I. He later served as the second president of the Polish Republic (1922–26).While a student at the University of Warsaw, Wojciechowski worked for the Polish Socialist movement, which was a major force in the independence effort. He was arrested in 1891, and upon his release a year later he went to Paris and then to London. In England he helped publish the Polish Socialist periodical Przedswit (“The Dawn”) and became friends with Józef Pilsudski. He also studied the cooperative movement, and on...
</Question>
<Choice>Wojciechowski, Stanislaw</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese soldier and statesman who exerted a strong influence in Japan's emergence as a formidable military power at the beginning of the 20th century. He was the first prime minister under the parliamentary regime, serving in 1889–91 and 1898–1900.
</Question>
<Choice>Yamagata Aritomo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese army leader and reformist minister in the twilight of the Qing dynasty (until 1911) and then first president of the Republic of China (1912–16).Yuan was from a landed military family of Xiangcheng in Henan province. In his youth he showed a propensity for pleasure-seeking and excelled in physical activity rather than scholarship, although he was obviously a man of remarkable astuteness. He failed to win even the lowest of the classical-examination degrees but was to have the distinction of being the first Han Chinese to hold a viceroyalty and to become a grand councillor without any ac...
</Question>
<Choice>Yüan Shih-k'ai</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Egyptian statesman and patriot, leader of the Wafd party and of the nationalist movement of 1918–19, which led Britain to give Egypt nominal independence in 1922. He was briefly prime minister in 1924.Zaghlul was from a well-to-do peasant family in Ibyanah in the Nile River delta. He was educated at the Muslim Al-Azhar University in Cairo and at the Egyptian School of Law, then practiced as an advocate and also dabbled in journalism. Becoming a judge in the Court of Appeal in 1892, he married, in 1895, a daughter of Mu??afa Pasha Fahmi, the prime minister of Egypt. In 1906 he was made head of...
</Question>
<Choice>Zaghlul, Sa'd</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
president of Albania from 1925 to 1928 and king from 1928 to 1939. Though able to manipulate Albania's internal affairs to his own advantage, he came to depend heavily on Benito Mussolini's Italy and was eventually ousted by the Italian dictator on the eve of World War II.Siding with Austria during World War I, Zog thereafter became a leader of the reformist Popular Party. He held ministerial posts from 1920 until he was forced into exile in June 1924, but he returned with Yugoslav assistance in December, was elected president on Feb. 1, 1925, and was proclaimed king on Sept. 1, 1928. Zog ende...
</Question>
<Choice>Zog I</Choice>
</item>
</topics>