<topics>
<item>
<Question>
Nigerian military leader, who served as head of state (1993–98).Abacha received his formal military training at Nigerian and British military training colleges. He rose through the ranks in the Nigerian military and by 1983 had achieved the rank of brigadier when he assisted Ibrahim Babangida in overthrowing Shehu Shagari, who had been elected to his second presidential term in 1983. Muhammad Buhari became Nigeria's leader, but just two years later Babangida overthrew Buhari and installed himself as leader with Abacha second in command. Elections were held in 1993 and were won by Moshood Abiol...
</Question>
<Choice>Abacha, Sani</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician and leader of the national independence movement who served as the first president of the Provisional Government of the Algerian Republic.Son of a Muslim official in the Algerian civil service, Abbas received an entirely French education at Philippeville (now Skikda) and Constantine and at the University of Algiers. After two years' service with the French Army, he became a pharmacist at Sétif and was elected first to the municipal council of Sétif and then to the general council in Constantine. Early in his political career, he advocated collaboration with the French, the assimilat...
</Question>
<Choice>Abbas, Ferhat</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Palestinian politician, who served briefly as prime minister of the Palestinian Authority in 2003 and was elected its president in 2005 following the death of Yasir ?Arafat.Abbas, born in the Arab-Jewish town of Zefat, fled with his family to Syria during the 1948 Arab-Israeli war. Despite the family's refugee status, Abbas earned a law degree from the University of Damascus. In the late 1950s Abbas was one of the founders of Fatah, which spearheaded the Palestinian armed struggle and came to dominate the Palestine Liberation Organization (PLO). As head of the PLO's international department in...
</Question>
<Choice>Abbas, Mahmoud</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
regent of Iraq (1939–53) and crown prince to 1958.Son of the Hashimite king ?Ali ibn ?usayn of the Hejaz (northwestern Arabia), who was driven from Arabia by Ibn Sa?ud, ?Abd al-Ilah accompanied his father to Iraq in 1925. Upon King Ghazi's death in 1939, he was appointed regent for his four-year-old nephew, Fay?al II. ?Abd al-Ilah ruled Iraq for 14 turbulent years, loyally serving the throne and supporting the Allies during World War II. In April 1941, faced with an uprising of army officers led by Rashid ?Ali al-Gaylani, who was sympathetic to Germany and Italy, the regent was forced to leave...
</Question>
<Choice>'Abd al-Ilah</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Saudi Arabia from 2005. As crown prince (1982–2005), he had served as the country's de facto ruler following the 1995 stroke of his half brother King Fahd (reigned 1982–2005).?Abd Allah was one of King ?Abd al-?Aziz ibn Sa?ud's 37 sons. For his support of Crown Prince Fay?al (1964–75) during Fay?al's power struggle with King Sa?ud (1953–64), ?Abd Allah was rewarded in 1962 with command of the Saudi National Guard. In 1975 King Khalid (1975–82), Fay?al's successor, appointed him deputy prime minister, and in 1982 King Fahd appointed him crown prince and first deputy prime minister. In 1...
</Question>
<Choice>'Abd Allah</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian scientist and politician, who played a leading role in the development of India's missile and nuclear weapons programs. He was president of India from 2002 to 2007.Kalam earned a degree in aeronautical engineering from the Madras Institute of Technology and in 1958 joined the Defence Research and Development Organisation (DRDO). He soon moved to the Indian Space Research Organisation, where he was project director of the SLV-III, India's first indigenously designed and produced satellite launch vehicle. Rejoining DRDO in 1982, Kalam planned the program that produced a number of successf...
</Question>
<Choice>Abdul Kalam, A.P.J.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first prime minister of independent Malaya (1957–63) and then of Malaysia (1963–70), under whose leadership the newly formed government was stabilized.After studies in England (1920–31), Abdul Rahman returned to Malaya to enter the Kedah civil service. In 1947 he returned to England, was called to the bar in 1949, and was appointed a deputy public prosecutor in the Malayan Federal Legal Department, a post he resigned in 1951 to begin a political career. He became president of the United Malays National Organization (UMNO) and effected the alliance of UMNO with the Malayan Chinese Association (...
</Question>
<Choice>Abdul Rahman Putra Alhaj, Tunku</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Jordan from 1999 and a member of the Hashimite dynasty, considered by pious Muslims to be direct descendants of the Prophet Muhammad (seeAhl al-Bayt).?Abdullah, the eldest son of King ?ussein, served as the crown prince until age three, when unrest in the Middle East prompted ?ussein to name ?Abdullah's adult uncle, Prince ?assan, heir to the throne. ?Abdullah was educated in Great Britain and the United States, and in 1980 he graduated from the Royal Military Academy in Sandhurst, England. He later served in the British Armed Forces as well as in Jordan's Armed Forces in the 41st and...
</Question>
<Choice>Abdullah II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ghanaian army officer, who, after leading a military revolt that overthrew the government of Kofi Busia, became Ghana's chief of state in 1972. In July 1978 he was forced to resign, and the following June he and his successor, Lieut. Gen. F.W.K. Akuffo, were executed after a coup led by young officers, whose Armed Forces Revolutionary Council returned Ghana to civilian rule in September 1979.
</Question>
<Choice>Acheampong, Ignatius Kutu</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first chancellor of the Federal Republic of Germany (West Germany; 1949–63), presiding over its reconstruction after World War II. A Christian Democrat and firmly anticommunist, he supported the North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO) and worked to reconcile Germany with its former enemies, especially France.
</Question>
<Choice>Adenauer, Konrad</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first president of the United Republic of Cameroon, who served from 1960 to 1982. He presided over one of the few successful attempts at supraterritorial African unity: the joining of the southern half of the former British Cameroons with the larger, French-speaking Cameroon.Ahidjo was a Muslim from the northern part of Cameroon and served as a radio operator in the French colonial administration from 1941/42 to 1953. He was elected to the Cameroon territorial assembly in 1947 and reelected in 1952 and 1956. His early political career also included several years in France (1953–56) as the Came...
</Question>
<Choice>Ahidjo, Ahmadou</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman who was president of India from 1974 to 1977.The son of an army doctor from Assam, Ahmed was educated in India and studied history at the University of Cambridge, graduating in 1927. After returning to India, he was elected to the Assam legislature (1935). As Assam's minister of finance and revenue in 1938, he was responsible for some radical taxation measures. On the outbreak of World War II in 1939, the Indian National Congress party had a confrontation with British power, and Ahmed was jailed for a year. Soon after release he was again imprisoned for another three and a half years...
</Question>
<Choice>Ahmed, Fakhruddin Ali</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Finnish politician and noted mediator who was president of Finland (1994–2000). In 2008 he was awarded the Nobel Prize for Peace for his efforts to resolve international conflicts.Ahtisaari graduated from the University of Oulu in 1959 and in the early 1960s worked in Pakistan on an educational project for the Swedish Agency for International Development. He returned to Finland and joined the Foreign Affairs Ministry in 1965; eight years later he was appointed ambassador to Tanzania, a post he held until 1976. Ahtisaari honed his diplomatic skills as the United Nations (UN) commissioner for Na...
</Question>
<Choice>Ahtisaari, Martti</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
emperor of Japan from 1989. As scion of the oldest imperial family in the world, he was, according to tradition, the 125th direct descendant of Jimmu, Japan's legendary first emperor.Akihito was the fifth child and eldest son of Emperor Hirohito and Empress Nagako. During his early years he was reared in the traditional imperial manner, beginning his education at the Peers' School in 1940. He lived outside of Tokyo during the last years of World War II but returned to the Peers' School (from 1949 Gakushuin) after the war. Because of the changes the war had brought to Japanese society, not the...
</Question>
<Choice>Akihito</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
president of Mexico from 1946 to 1952.The son of a village shopkeeper, Alemán studied law and set up practice in Mexico City, specializing in labour cases. Appointed senator from Veracruz, he became governor of the state in 1936. In 1940 he resigned to manage the successful presidential campaign of Manuel Ávila Camacho, who rewarded him with the powerful post of minister of gobernación (“interior”). Alemán became the official candidate for the presidency on the ticket of the Partido Revolucionario Institucional (Revolutionary Institutional Party) in 1946 and easily defeated Ezequiel Padilla. H...
</Question>
<Choice>Alemán, Miguel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
civilian president of Argentina (1983–89), elected after eight years of military rule, and leader of the moderate Radical Civic Union (Spanish: Unión Cívica Radical, or UCR).Alfonsín attended the Liceo Militar (military academy) General San Martin, obtained a law degree from the National University of La Plata (1950), and founded the newspaper El Imparcial in his native town of Chascomús, located about 60 miles (100 km) south of Buenos Aires. After serving for a decade in provincial politics, he was elected to the National Congress (1963) under a UCR president, who later fell victim to a milit...
</Question>
<Choice>Alfonsín, Raúl</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chile's first socialist president.Allende, born into an upper-middle-class family, received his medical degree in 1932 from the University of Chile, where he was a Marxist activist. He participated in the founding (1933) of Chile's Socialist Party. After election to the Chamber of Deputies in 1937, he served (1939–42) as minister of health in the liberal leftist coalition of President Pedro Aguirre Cerda. Allende won the first of his four elections to the Senate in 1945.Allende ran for the presidency for the first time in 1952 but was temporarily expelled from the Socialist Party for accepting...
</Question>
<Choice>Allende, Salvador</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
leftist politician who briefly served as the president of Afghanistan in 1979.Amin was born into a Ghilzay Pashtun family. After graduating from Kabul University, he traveled to the United States for graduate study at Columbia University in New York. Upon returning to Afghanistan, he became a teacher and later the principal of a teacher-training college. He joined the Wikh-e Zalmayan (“Awakened Youth”), a reform-minded brotherhood, and in 1963 became a member of the leftist People's Democratic Party of Afghanistan (PDPA), which was headed by Nur Mohammad Taraki. On April 27, 1978, Amin, who ha...
</Question>
<Choice>Amin, Hafizullah</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
military officer and president (1971–79) of Uganda whose regime was noted for its brutality.A member of the small Kakwa ethnic group of northwestern Uganda, Amin had little formal education and joined the King's African Rifles of the British colonial army in 1946 as an assistant cook. He quickly rose through the ranks, serving in the Allied forces' Burma (Myanmar) campaign during World War II and in the British action against the Mau Mau revolt in Kenya (1952–56). Amin was one of the few Ugandan soldiers elevated to officer rank before Ugandan independence in 1962, and he became closely associ...
</Question>
<Choice>Amin, Idi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Christian Democratic politician who was several times prime minister of Italy in the period from 1972 to 1992. He was one of Italy's most skillful and powerful politicians in the era after World War II.Andreotti took a degree in law at the University of Rome and was president of the Catholic students' federation. In 1942 he became a protégé of Alcide De Gasperi, who would soon organize the Christian Democratic Party. In 1946 Andreotti was elected to the Constituent Assembly that drafted Italy's new constitution, and in 1947 he was elected to the Chamber of Deputies, to which he was reelected r...
</Question>
<Choice>Andreotti, Giulio</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
head of the Soviet Union's KGB (State Security Committee) from 1967 to 1982 and his country's leader as general secretary of the Communist Party's Central Committee from November 1982 until his death 15 months later.The son of a railway worker, Andropov was a telegraph operator, film projectionist, and boatman on the Volga River before attending a technical college and, later, Petrozavodsk University. He became an organizer for the Young Communist League (Komsomol) in the Yaroslav region and joined the Communist Party in 1939. His superiors noticed his abilities, and he was made head of the Ko...
</Question>
<Choice>Andropov, Yury Vladimirovich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
president (1996–2004) of the Palestinian Authority, chairman (1969–2004) of the Palestine Liberation Organization (PLO), and leader of Fatah, the largest of the constituent PLO groups. In 1993 he led the PLO to a peace agreement with the Israeli government. ?Arafat and Yitzhak Rabin and Shimon Peres of Israel were jointly awarded the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1994.?Arafat was one of seven children of a well-to-do merchant whose wife was related to the anti-Zionist grand mufti of Jerusalem, Amin al-?usayni (died 1974). The date and place of ?Arafat's birth are disputed. A birth certificate regis...
</Question>
<Choice>'Arafat, Yasir</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
soldier, politician, and president of Guatemala (1951–54) whose nationalistic economic and social reforms alienated conservative landowners, conservative elements in the army, and the U.S. government and led to his overthrow.The son of a Swiss pharmacist who had emigrated to Guatemala, Arbenz was educated at the National Military Academy of Guatemala. He joined a group of leftist army officers that overthrew the Guatemalan dictator Jorge Ubico in 1944, and in 1949 he was the minister of war in Juan José Arévalo's government. In March 1951 he succeeded to the presidency, supported by the army a...
</Question>
<Choice>Arbenz, Jacobo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
president of Costa Rica (1986–90; 2006– ) and recipient of the Nobel Peace Prize in 1987 for his Central American peace plan.Born into one of the wealthiest coffee-growing families in Costa Rica, Arias studied economics at the University of Costa Rica and earned a Ph.D. in political science from the University of Essex in England. In the 1960s he began working for the moderate socialist National Liberation Party (Partido de Liberación Nacional; PLN), and in 1972 he was appointed minister of planning in the government of President José Figueres Ferrer, a post he held until 1977. He was elected...
</Question>
<Choice>Arias Sánchez, Oscar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
three times president of Panama (June 1940–October 1941, November 1949–May 1951, and Oct. 1–12, 1968) and three times deposed.The younger brother of Harmodio Arias (Panamanian president, 1932–36), Arias was educated at the University of Chicago and Harvard Medical School (to become a surgeon) and was minister of agriculture and public works in the 1930s during the presidency of his brother. During his first term, he forced foreign businessmen to transfer their companies to Panamanian ownership and divested black West Indians in Panama of their citizenship. He sympathized with the Axis powers i...
</Question>
<Choice>Arias, Arnulfo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Iraqi army officer and politician who was president of Iraq from 1963 to 1966.?Arif, the son of a cloth merchant, graduated from military college in 1939 and during his military career trained with British troops in Germany. His rise to power began in 1958 when he, along with General ?Abd al-Karim Qasim, played a prominent role in the overthrow of the Hashimite monarchy, then under Fay?al II. After Qasim was declared president, he named ?Arif deputy prime minister and minister of the interior. In December 1958, however, ?Arif was convicted of attempting to murder Qasim and was condemned to dea...
</Question>
<Choice>'Arif, 'Abd al-Salam</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Haitian politician and Roman Catholic priest of the Salesian order, who was a vocal champion of the poor and disenfranchised. He was president of the country in 1991, 1994–96, and 2001–04.Aristide attended a school in Port-au-Prince run by the Roman Catholic Salesian order, and in 1966 he moved to the Salesian seminary at Cap-Haitien and began to prepare for the priesthood. In 1975 he first aligned himself with the poor and Ti Legliz (“Little Church”), a movement that sprang from liberation theology. The following year he returned to Port-au-Prince to study psychology (B.A., 1979) at the state...
</Question>
<Choice>Aristide, Jean-Bertrand</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
president of Syria (1971–2000) who brought stability to the country and established it as a powerful presence in the Middle East.Born into a poor family of ?Alawites, a minority Islamic sect, Assad joined the Syrian wing of the Ba?th Party in 1946 as a student activist. In 1952 he entered the ?im? Military Academy, graduating three years later as an air force pilot. While exiled to Egypt (1959–61) during Syria's short-lived union with Egypt in the United Arab Republic, Assad and other military officers formed a committee to resurrect the fortunes of the Syrian Ba?th Party. After the Ba?thists...
</Question>
<Choice>Assad, Hafiz al-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
president of Pakistan from 1958 to 1969, whose rule marked a critical period in the modern development of his nation.After studying at Aligarh Muslim University, in Uttar Pradesh, India, and at the British Royal Military College, at Sandhurst, Ayub Khan was commissioned an officer in the Indian army (1928). In World War II he was second-in-command of a regiment in Burma (Myanmar) and commanded a battalion in India. After the 1947 partition of British India he was rapidly promoted in the army of the new Muslim state of Pakistan: from major general (1948) to commander in chief (1951). In additio...
</Question>
<Choice>Ayub Khan, Mohammad</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman and Sudanese prime minister in 1954–56, who was instrumental in achieving his country's independence.Educated at Gordon Memorial College at Khartoum and at the American University of Beirut, al-Azhari became president of the Graduates' General Congress in 1940. At first concerned primarily with educational and social reforms, the congress later opposed British administration of the Sudan and instead supported the Sudan's union with Egypt. In 1943, following a split within the congress, al-Azhari organized the Ashigga? (“Brothers”) party; his opposition to the British proposal for sel...
</Question>
<Choice>Azhari, Isma'il al-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first president of independent Nigeria (1963–66).Azikiwe attended various grammar and high schools in Onitsha, Calabar, and Lagos. He spent almost 10 years (1925–34) studying in the United States, where he attended several schools, including Howard University in Washington, D.C. In 1934 he went to the Gold Coast (now Ghana), where he founded a newspaper and was a mentor to Kwame Nkrumah (first president of Ghana) before returning to Nigeria in 1937. There he founded and edited newspapers and also became directly involved in politics, first with the Nigerian Youth Movement and later (1944) as a...
</Question>
<Choice>Azikiwe, Nnamdi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
lawyer and politician who served as prime minister of Spain from 1996 to 2004.Aznar was born into a politically active, conservative family in Spain. His grandfather was a friend of dictator General Francisco Franco, and both his father and grandfather held government jobs during Franco's regime.In 1975, during Spain's transition to democracy, Aznar received a law degree from the Complutense University of Madrid, and he subsequently worked as a government tax inspector. He became active in the conservative Popular Alliance, and in 1982 he was elected to the Congress of Deputies, the lower hous...
</Question>
<Choice>Aznar, José María</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician who in 1937 became the first Burmese premier under British rule; he later was head of state in the pro-Japanese government during World War II (August 1943–May 1945).Ba Maw was educated at Rangoon College, Calcutta University, the University of Cambridge, and the University of Bordeaux, Fr., where he received a doctorate in 1924. Admitted to the English bar the same year, he first came into prominence as defense lawyer for the Burmese rebel leader Saya San in 1931.During the early 1930s Ba Maw became a prominent opponent of Britain's plan to remove Burma (Myanmar) from the jurisdict...
</Question>
<Choice>Ba Maw</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nigerian military leader, who served as head of state (1985–93).Born in northern Niger state, Babangida received military training in Nigeria, India, Great Britain, and the United States. He rose through the ranks and was known for his courage—he played a major role in suppressing an attempted coup in 1976 when he walked into a rebel-held radio station unarmed.After Murtala Mohammed became the military head of state in 1975, Babangida joined his Supreme Military Council. He played a significant role in the coup that replaced the civilian government of Shehu Shagari with the military regime led...
</Question>
<Choice>Babangida, Ibrahim</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chilean politician, president of Chile (2006– ). She was the first woman president of Chile and the first popularly elected South American woman president whose political career was established independent of her husband.Bachelet's father was a general in Chile's air force, and her mother was an archaeologist. In 1973 her father was arrested for opposing the military coup that brought Augusto Pinochet to power and was tortured for several months before suffering a heart attack and dying in custody in 1974. Michelle Bachelet, then a medical student at the University of Chile, was arrested (alon...
</Question>
<Choice>Bachelet, Michelle</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
president of Iraq from 1968 to 1979.Al-Bakr entered the Iraqi Military Academy in 1938 after spending six years as a primary-school teacher. He was a member of the Ba?th Party and was forced to retire from the Iraqi army for revolutionary activities in 1959. He became prime minister for 10 months following the Ba?th coup of 1963 and replaced Pres. ?Abd al-Ra?man ?Arif in the Ba?th coup of July 17, 1968. Thereafter he governed in concert with the Ba?th leader ?addam ?ussein. His truculent foreign policy effectively isolated him from his Muslim neighbours, and his total opposition to any diploma...
</Question>
<Choice>Bakr, Ahmad Hassan al-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
lawyer, writer, and diplomat who was vice president of the Dominican Republic (1957–60) during the regime of President Hector Trujillo and was president from 1960 to 1962, 1966 to 1978, and from 1986 to 1996.Balaguer earned a law degree from the University of Santo Domingo and a Ph.D. from the University of Paris. Between 1932 and 1957, he held numerous executive and diplomatic posts in the Dominican government under the Trujillo regime. As secretary of education under Hector Trujillo, brother of dictator General Rafael Trujillo, he established free universities and expanded educational and li...
</Question>
<Choice>Balaguer, Joaquín</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nigerian politician, leader in the Northern Peoples Congress (NPC), and the first federal prime minister. A commoner by birth, an unusual origin for a political leader in the NPC, Balewa was both a defender of northern special interests and an advocate of reform and Nigerian unity.Balewa was a teacher by profession and was one of the first Northern Nigerians to be sent to London University Institute of Education (1945). On his return in 1946 he was elected to the House of Assembly of the Northern Region and in 1947 was one of five representatives to the Central Legislative Council in Lagos. He...
</Question>
<Choice>Balewa, Sir Abubakar Tafawa</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French neo-Gaullist politician, prime minister of France from 1993 to 1995.Balladur graduated from the prestigious National School of Administration in 1957 and went to work for the Council of State as a junior official. In 1962 he joined the Office of Radio and Television Broadcasting (ORTF). The head of ORTF recommended him to Prime Minister (later President) Georges Pompidou, and during the 1960s and '70s Balladur was a member of Pompidou's staff. After Pompidou's death in 1974, Balladur worked in industry, becoming chairman of two subsidiaries of the national electric company.From 1984 to...
</Question>
<Choice>Balladur, Édouard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first president of Malawi (formerly Nyasaland) and the principal leader of the Malawi nationalist movement. He governed Malawi from 1963 to 1994, combining totalitarian political controls with conservative economic policies.Banda's birthday was officially given as May 14, 1906, but he was believed to have been born before the turn of the century. He was the son of subsistence farmers and received his earliest education in a mission school. After working in Southern Rhodesia (now Zimbabwe) and South Africa, in 1925 he went to the United States, where he received a B.A. (1931) and a medical degr...
</Question>
<Choice>Banda, Hastings Kamuzu</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman and prime minister of Ceylon (1956–59), whose election marked a significant change in the political history of modern Ceylon.Educated at the University of Oxford, he was called to the bar in 1925. After returning to Ceylon, he entered politics and, in 1931, was elected to the newly formed legislative assembly, the State Council. In 1947, as a prominent member of the governing United National Party (UNP), he was elected to the new House of Representatives and appointed minister of health and local government. He resigned from the government and the Western-oriented UNP in 1951 and was...
</Question>
<Choice>Bandaranaike, S.W.R.D.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
stateswoman who, upon her party's victory in the 1960 Ceylon general election, became the world's first woman prime minister. She left office in 1965 but returned to serve two more terms (1970–77, 1994–2000) as prime minister. The family she founded with her late husband, S.W.R.D. Bandaranaike, rose to great prominence in Sri Lankan politics.Born into a wealthy family, she married the politician S.W.R.D. Bandaranaike in 1940 and began to interest herself in social welfare. After her husband, who became prime minister in 1956, was assassinated in 1959, she was induced by his Sri Lanka Freedom P...
</Question>
<Choice>Bandaranaike, Sirimavo R.D.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Iranian economist and politician who in 1980 was elected the first president of the Islamic Republic of Iran. He was dismissed from office in 1981 after being impeached for incompetence.Bani-Sadr studied religion and economics at the University of Tehran and spent four years at the Institute of Social Research. He was leader of the anti-shah student movement in the early 1960s and was imprisoned twice for political activities. Wounded in the unsuccessful uprising of June 1963, he traveled to France and continued his studies at the Sorbonne in Paris, where he obtained a doctorate and later taug...
</Question>
<Choice>Bani-Sadr, Abolhasan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the last reigning emperor of Vietnam (1926–45).The son of Emperor Khai Dinh, a vassal of the French colonial regime, and a concubine of peasant ancestry, Nguyen Vinh Thuy was educated in France and spent little of his youth in his homeland. He succeeded to the throne in 1926 and assumed the title Bao Dai (“Keeper of Greatness”). He initially sought to reform and modernize Vietnam but was unable to win French cooperation.During World War II the French colonial regime exercised a firm control over Bao Dai until the Japanese coup de force of March 1945, which swept away French administration in I...
</Question>
<Choice>Bao Dai</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
soldier and politician who was the prime minister of Israel from 1999 to 2001.Barak was born in a kibbutz that had been founded by his father, an emigrant from Lithuania, in 1932. Barak was drafted into the Israel Defense Forces in 1959, thus beginning a distinguished military career (he changed his name at this time). He was a commander in battles in the Six-Day War (1967) and the Yom Kippur War (1973) but became especially known as the leader of special forces units that conducted commando raids. These included a group of soldiers (with Benjamin Netanyahu among them) who stormed an airliner...
</Question>
<Choice>Barak, Ehud</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
soldier and political leader who twice ruled Cuba—first in 1933–44 with an efficient government and again in 1952–59 as a dictator, jailing his opponents, using terrorist methods, and making fortunes for himself and his associates.The son of impoverished farmers, Batista worked in a variety of jobs until he joined the army in 1921, starting as a stenographer. He rose to the rank of sergeant and developed a large personal following. In September 1933 he organized the “sergeants' revolt”; it toppled the provisional regime of Carlos Manuel de Céspedes, which had replaced the dictatorial regime of...
</Question>
<Choice>Batista, Fulgencio</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
queen of The Netherlands from 1980.The eldest of four daughters born to Princess (later Queen) Juliana and Bernhard of Lippe-Biesterfeld, Beatrix went into exile with her family when the Germans overran The Netherlands in World War II, and she spent the war years in Britain and Canada. When Juliana ascended the throne in 1948, Princess Beatrix received the title of heiress presumptive. From 1956 to 1961 she attended the State University of Leiden, studying mainly social sciences, law, and history.In 1965 her betrothal to a German diplomat, Claus George Willem Otto Frederik Geert von Amsberg (b...
</Question>
<Choice>Beatrix</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Zionist leader who was prime minister of Israel from 1977 to 1983. Begin was the co-recipient, with Egyptian president Anwar el-Sadat, of the 1978 Nobel Prize for Peace for their achievement of a peace treaty between Israel and Egypt that was formally signed in 1979.Begin received a law degree from the University of Warsaw in 1935. Active in the Zionist movement throughout the 1930s, he became (1938) the leader of the Polish branch of the Betar youth movement, dedicated to the establishment of a Jewish state on both sides of the Jordan River. When the Germans invaded Warsaw in 1939, he escaped...
</Question>
<Choice>Begin, Menachem</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman, architect, and president of Peru (1963–68, 1980–85), known for his efforts at democratic reform and his pro-American stance.Belaúnde, a member of a distinguished aristocratic Peruvian family, studied architecture in the United States and France in 1924–35 and practiced briefly in Mexico before returning in 1936 to Peru, where he became a noted architect and founded the architectural magazine Arquitecto Peruano (“Peruvian Architect”). He served in the Chamber of Deputies (1945–48) while his father, Rafael Belaúnde Diez Canseco, was prime minister. After a military coup in 1948 overth...
</Question>
<Choice>Belaúnde Terry, Fernando</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
army officer and politician who became president of Tunisia in 1987.Ben Ali was trained in France at the military academy of Saint-Cyr and at the artillery school at Châlons-sur-Marne. He also studied engineering in the United States. From 1964 to 1974 he was head of Tunisian military security, a post that brought him into top government circles. In 1974 he began a three-year term as military attaché to the Tunisian embassy in Morocco. He then returned to Tunisia to become head of national security, and in 1980 he became ambassador to Poland. After his return, he was appointed state secretary...
</Question>
<Choice>Ben Ali, Zine al-Abidine</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
principal leader of the Algerian War of Independence against France, the first prime minister (1962–63) and first elected president (1963–65) of the Algerian republic, who steered his country toward a socialist economy.Ben Bella was the son of a farmer and small businessman in Maghnia in the département of Oran. There, he successfully completed his early studies at the French school and continued his education in the neighbouring city of Tlemcen, where he first became aware of racial discrimination and also mingled with the fringes of the nationalist movement.He was conscripted into the French...
</Question>
<Choice>Ben Bella, Ahmed</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Zionist statesman and political leader, the first prime minister (1948–53, 1955–63) and defense minister (1948–53; 1955–63) of Israel. It was Ben-Gurion who, on May 14, 1948, at Tel Aviv, delivered Israel's declaration of independence. His charismatic personality won him the adoration of the masses, and, after his retirement from the government and, later, from the Knesset (the Israeli house of representatives), he was revered as the “Father of the Nation.”Ben-Gurion, born David Gruen, was the son of Victor Gruen, one of the leaders in Plonsk of the “Lovers of Zion,” a movement that was dissem...
</Question>
<Choice>Ben-Gurion, David</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian media tycoon who served three times as prime minister of Italy (1994; 2001–06; 2008– ).After graduating from the University of Milan with a degree in law, Berlusconi became a real-estate developer, amassing a considerable fortune by the 1970s. He created the cable television firm Telemilano in 1974 and four years later mounted the first direct challenge to the national television monopoly. In 1980 he established Canale 5, Italy's first commercial television network, and by the end of the decade Berlusconi-created stations dominated Italian airwaves. Berlusconi also diversified his busi...
</Question>
<Choice>Berlusconi, Silvio</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
left-wing, anticommunist politician who, as president of Venezuela (1945–48; 1959–64), pursued policies of agrarian reform, industrial development, and popular participation in government.While a student at the University of Caracas, Betancourt was jailed (1928) for his activities against the dictatorial regime of Juan Vicente Gómez. Released after a few weeks, he continued to demonstrate against Gómez and was exiled, remaining abroad until 1936. During this period he wrote a book about his experiences and briefly joined the Communist Party in Costa Rica.He returned to Venezuela in 1936 but wa...
</Question>
<Choice>Betancourt, Rómulo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
ninth king of the Chakkri dynasty (1950– ), which has ruled or reigned in Thailand from 1782, Thailand's longest-serving monarch.He was a grandson of King Chulalongkorn and was born while his father, Prince Mahidol of Songkhla, was studying at Harvard University. His older brother, Ananda Mahidol, became king in 1935, but on June 9, 1946, Ananda was found dead in his bed of a gunshot wound. Bhumibol immediately succeeded to the throne following Ananda's mysterious death (the circumstances of which were never explained). He married a distant cousin, Sirikit Kitiyakara, in April 1950 and was for...
</Question>
<Choice>Bhumibol Adulyadej</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pakistani politician who became the first woman leader of a Muslim nation in modern history. She served two terms as prime minister of Pakistan, in 1988–90 and in 1993–96.Bhutto was the daughter of the politician Zulfikar Ali Bhutto, who was the leader of Pakistan from 1971 until 1977. She was educated at Harvard University (B.A., 1973) and subsequently studied philosophy, political science, and economics at the University of Oxford (B.A., 1977).After her father's execution in 1979 during the rule of the military dictator Mohammad Zia-ul-Haq, Bhutto became the titular head of her father's part...
</Question>
<Choice>Bhutto, Benazir</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pakistani statesman, president (1971–73), and prime minister (1973–77), a popular leader who was overthrown and executed by the military.Born into a noble Rajput family that had accepted Islam, Bhutto was the son of a prominent political figure in the Indian colonial government. He was educated in Bombay and at the University of California, Berkeley (B.A., 1950). Bhutto studied law at the University of Oxford and then practiced law and lectured in England. Upon his return to Pakistan (1953), he set up a law practice in Karachi, where he was appointed a member of Pakistan's delegation to the Un...
</Question>
<Choice>Bhutto, Zulfikar Ali</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British Labour Party leader who served as prime minister of the United Kingdom (1997–2007). He was the youngest prime minister since 1812 and the longest-serving Labour prime minister, and his 10-year tenure as prime minister was the second longest continuous period (after Margaret Thatcher's) in more than 150 years.
</Question>
<Choice>Blair, Tony</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
African military leader who was president of the Central African Republic (1966–76) and self-styled emperor of the Central African Empire (1976–79).The son of a village headman, Bokassa attended local mission schools before joining the French army in 1939. He distinguished himself in the French conflict in Indochina, and by 1961 he had achieved the rank of captain. At the request of President David Dacko, Bokassa left the French armed forces to head the army of the newly independent Central African Republic. On Dec. 31, 1965, Bokassa used his position as supreme military commander to overthrow...
</Question>
<Choice>Bokassa, Jean-Bédel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
New Zealand farmer and politician who served as prime minister of New Zealand from 1990 to 1997.Bolger was born to newly arrived Irish Roman Catholic immigrants who had taken up dairy farming in Taranaki province. He left school at age 15 to help his parents on their farm. His first involvement with politics was with a local branch of Federated Farmers. Bolger moved to central North Island in 1963, established a farm of his own, and from that base became vice president of Federated Farmers Waikato (provincial) division and won election to Parliament with the National Party (NP) from 1972. Afte...
</Question>
<Choice>Bolger, James Brendan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
29th sultan of Brunei.Hassanal Bolkiah was the eldest son of Sultan Sir Haji Omar Ali Saifuddin. He was educated privately and later attended the Victoria Institution in Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia, and the Royal Military Academy at Sandhurst, England. In 1961 Sir Omar named him crown prince, and when Sir Omar abdicated six years later, Hassanal Bolkiah became sultan on October 5, 1967, his coronation taking place on August 1, 1968. For the next decade, however, his father remained the power behind the throne. After the death of his mother in 1979, his father withdrew from public affairs, and the s...
</Question>
<Choice>Bolkiah Mu'izzaddin Waddaulah, Haji Hassanal</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Dominican writer, scholar, and politician elected president of the Dominican Republic in 1962 but deposed less than a year later.Bosch, an intellectual, was an early opponent of Rafael Trujillo's dictatorial regime. He went into exile in 1937 and in 1939 founded the leftist Dominican Revolutionary Party (Partido Revolucionario Dominicano; PRD). The PRD was the first well-organized political party of the Dominican Republic and the only one with a constructive program ready to implement after Trujillo's death in 1961. Bosch, a dazzling and charismatic orator, won a landslide victory in the elect...
</Question>
<Choice>Bosch, Juan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prime minister (1978–84) and first state president (1984–89) of South Africa.A native of the Orange Free State, he studied law at the University of Orange Free State at Bloemfontein from 1932 to 1935 but left without graduating. Already active in politics in his teens, he moved to Cape Province at age 20 to become a full-time organizer for the National Party. He was elected to Parliament in the National landslide of 1948. By 1958 he was deputy minister of the interior, and thereafter (1961–80) he was successively minister of commercial development, Coloured affairs, public works, and defense....
</Question>
<Choice>Botha, P. W.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
army officer who became president of Algeria in July 1965 following a coup d'etat.Boukharouba's service to Algeria began in the 1950s, during his country's struggle for independence from France, when, after studying at al-Azhar University in Cairo, he joined the rebel forces and adopted the name Houari Boumedienne. The rebels divided the country into military districts, and Boumedienne commanded the one around Oran. In 1960 he became chief of staff of the National Liberation Front, and he centred his efforts on raising an Algerian army in Morocco and Tunisia, out of reach of the French.After a...
</Question>
<Choice>Boumedienne, Houari</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
architect of Tunisia's independence and first president of Tunisia (1957–87), one of the major voices of moderation and gradualism in the Arab world.
</Question>
<Choice>Bourguiba, Habib</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German statesman, leader of the German Social Democratic Party of Germany (Sozialdemokratische Partei Deutschlands, or SPD) from 1964 to 1987, and chancellor of the Federal Republic of Germany from 1969 to 1974. He was awarded the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1971 for his efforts to achieve reconciliation between West Germany and the countries of the Soviet bloc.Brandt passed his university entrance examination in 1932. A year later, however, when the Nazis came to power, his activities as a young Social Democrat brought him into conflict with the Gestapo, and he was forced to flee the country to...
</Question>
<Choice>Brandt, Willy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Soviet statesman and Communist Party official who was, in effect, the leader of the Soviet Union for 18 years.Having been a land surveyor in the 1920s, Brezhnev became a full member of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union (CPSU) in 1931 and studied at the metallurgical institute in Kamenskoye (now Dniprodzerzhynsk). After graduating (1935), he worked as an engineer and director of a technical school and also held a variety of local party posts; his career flourished under Joseph Stalin's regime, and by 1939 he had become secretary of the regional party committee of Dnepropetrovsk (Dnipropet...
</Question>
<Choice>Brezhnev, Leonid Ilich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician who served three terms as prime minister of Norway in the 1980s and '90s and later was director general of the World Health Organization (WHO; 1998–2003). Trained as a physician, she became identified with public health and environmental issues and with the rights of women.The daughter of a physician and politician, she received an M.D. degree from the University of Oslo in 1963 and a master's degree in public health from Harvard University in 1965. She then worked as a public health officer for the city of Oslo and for Oslo schools. A member of the Labour Party, she was minister of...
</Question>
<Choice>Brundtland, Gro Harlem</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prime minister (taoiseach) of Ireland from December 1994 to May 1997.Bruton was educated at Clongowes Wood College and then studied economics at University College and law at King's Inns in Dublin, qualifying as a barrister in 1970. He joined the Fine Gael party in 1965, and he was elected to the Dáil (lower house of Parliament) for Meath, where he farmed, in 1969. He served as a parliamentary secretary in the government of Liam Cosgrave (1973–77), and when Garret FitzGerald led another Fine Gael–Labour Party coalition into office in 1981, Bruton became minister for finance. His budget imposed...
</Question>
<Choice>Bruton, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nigerian military leader, who served as head of state (1985).Educated largely in Katsina, Buhari took military training in Kaduna as well as Great Britain, India, and the United States. He was involved in the military coup that ousted Yakubu Gowon in 1975 and was appointed military governor of North Eastern state (now Borno) that same year. He was appointed federal commissioner for petroleum resources by General Olusegun Obasanjo, who became military head of state when Gowon's successor, Murtala Mohammed, was assassinated in 1976. By 1977 Buhari had become the military secretary at Supreme Mil...
</Question>
<Choice>Buhari, Muhammad</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician and businessman who was vice president of the United States (1981–89) and the 41st president of the United States (1989–93). As president, Bush assembled a multinational force to compel the withdrawal of Iraq from Kuwait in the Persian Gulf War. (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America.)
</Question>
<Choice>Bush, George</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
43rd president of the United States (2001–09), who led his country's response to the terrorist September 11 attacks in 2001 and initiated the Iraq War in 2003. Narrowly winning the electoral college vote in 2000 over Vice Pres. Al Gore in one of the closest and most controversial elections in American history, George W. Bush became the first person since Benjamin Harrison in 1888 to be elected president despite having lost the nationwide popular vote. Before his election as president, Bush was a businessman and served as governor of Texas (1995–2000). (For a discussion of the history and natur...
</Question>
<Choice>Bush, George W.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Zulu chief, South African politician, and leader of the Inkatha Freedom Party. He was head (1976–94) of the nonindependent KwaZuluBantustan and South Africa's minister of home affairs (1994–2004).Buthelezi descended from a line of important Zulu chiefs. He attended South African Native College (now the University of Fort Hare) and was a member of the Youth League of the African National Congress (ANC). His political activities brought about his expulsion from school, and he completed his degree in history and Bantu administration at the University of Natal. In 1951 he began working in South Af...
</Question>
<Choice>Buthelezi, Mangosuthu G.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
premier of Portugal from September 1968, when he succeeded António de Oliveira Salazar, until the revolution of April 1974.Trained as a lawyer, Caetano served with Salazar (then the finance minister) in 1929 and helped to draft the Constitution of 1933 and other legal documents of the New State. Caetano's scholarly writings on civil law and legal and constitutional history, some of them still in print, influenced generations of the educated elite. He was minister of the colonies (1944–47) and deputy prime minister (1955–58), among other posts, before leaving political life to become rector of...
</Question>
<Choice>Caetano, Marcello José das Neves Alves</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British Labour Party politician, who was prime minister from 1976 to 1979.Callaghan entered the civil service at age 17 as a tax officer. By 1936 he had become a full-time trade-union official. After serving as a lieutenant in naval intelligence during World War II, he entered Parliament in 1945, representing the Welsh constituency of Cardiff South. Between 1947 and 1951 Callaghan held junior posts at the Ministry of Transport and at the Admiralty. When Harold Wilson's Labour government was formed in 1964, Callaghan was named chancellor of the Exchequer. In this capacity he helped secure in 19...
</Question>
<Choice>Callaghan, James Callaghan, Baron</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Canadian politician, who in June 1993 became the first woman to serve as prime minister of Canada. Her tenure was brief, however, lasting only until November.Campbell was educated at the University of British Columbia (B.A., 1969) and at the London School of Economics, where she studied Soviet government. She taught political science for six years before returning to the University of British Columbia to pursue a law degree; upon graduation in 1983 she practiced law in Vancouver for two years before devoting herself full-time to a political career.In Vancouver Campbell served on the city schoo...
</Question>
<Choice>Campbell, Kim</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Sweden from 1973.The only son of King Gustav VI Adolf's eldest son, Prince Gustav Adolf (who died in an air crash in 1947), Carl Gustaf became crown prince in 1950, when his grandfather acceded to the throne. He studied at military cadet schools, at the University of Uppsala, and in France and was commissioned as a naval officer in 1968. He married Silvia Sommerlath in 1976, three years after his accession. The royal couple had three children, Crown Princess Victoria, Prince Carl Philip , and Princess Madeleine.Carl Gustaf's accession occurred when the role of the Swedish monarchy was...
</Question>
<Choice>Carl XVI Gustaf</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
39th president of the United States (1977–81), who served as the nation's chief executive during a time of serious problems at home and abroad. His perceived inability to deal successfully with those problems led to an overwhelming defeat in his bid for reelection. After leaving office he embarked on a career of diplomacy and advocacy, for which he was awarded the Nobel Prize for Peace in 2002. (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America.)The son of Earl Carter, a peanut warehouser who had served in the Georgia state legislature,...
</Question>
<Choice>Carter, Jimmy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
political leader of Cuba (from 1959) who transformed his country into the first communist state in the Western Hemisphere. Castro became a symbol of communist revolution in Latin America. He held the title of premier until 1976 and then began a long tenure as president of the Council of State and the Council of Ministers, handing over provisional power in July 2006 because of health problems and formally relinquishing the presidency in February 2008.Castro was born in southeastern Cuba. His father, Angel Castro y Argiz, an immigrant from Spain, was a fairly prosperous sugarcane farmer in a loc...
</Question>
<Choice>Castro, Fidel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Communist official who was leader of Romania from 1965 until he was overthrown and killed in a revolution in 1989.A member of the Romanian Communist youth movement during the early 1930s, Ceau?escu was imprisoned in 1936 and again in 1940 for his Communist Party activities. In 1939 he married Elena Petrescu (b. Jan. 7, 1919, Oltenia region, Rom.—d. Dec. 25, 1989, near Bucharest), a Communist activist. While in prison, Ceau?escu became a protégé of his cell mate, the Communist leader Gheorghe Gheorghiu-Dej, who would become the undisputed Communist leader of Romania beginning in 1952. Escaping...
</Question>
<Choice>Ceausescu, Nicolae</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
newspaper publisher and politician who served as president of Nicaragua from 1990 to 1997.Chamorro, who was born into a wealthy Nicaraguan family (her father was a cattle rancher), received much of her early education in the U.S. states of Texas and Virginia. In 1950, shortly after the death of her father, she returned to Nicaragua, where she married Pedro Joaquim Chamorro Cardenal, editor of the newspaper La Prensa, which was often critical of the Somoza family dictatorship. The Chamorros were forced into exile in 1957 and lived in Costa Rica for several years before returning to Nicaragua af...
</Question>
<Choice>Chamorro, Violeta Barrios de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
political leader who served as president of Lebanon in 1952–58.Chamoun spent his early political years as a member of a political faction known as the Constitutional Bloc, a predominantly Christian group that emphasized its Arabic heritage in an attempt to establish a rapport with the Muslim groups. By the late 1940s Chamoun had emerged as one of the bloc's most prominent members. When his expectations of succeeding Bishara al-Khuri as president of Lebanon were denied in 1948 by a renewal of Khuri's term, Chamoun began to organize a parliamentary opposition. By the summer of 1952 he had made a...
</Question>
<Choice>Chamoun, Camille</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician and legislator, who served as prime minister of India from November 1990 to June 1991.Shekhar was a leading member of the Socialist Party before he joined the ruling Congress Party in 1964. He was a member of India's upper legislative chamber, the Rajya Sabha, from 1962 to 1967, and he held a seat in the lower chamber, the Lok Sabha, in 1977–79, 1980–84, and from 1989 until he became prime minister. Shekhar split with the leader of the Congress Party, Indira Gandhi, in 1975 and spent time in prison during the national emergency she subsequently declared.In 1977 Shekhar became presid...
</Question>
<Choice>Chandra Shekhar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Venezuelan politician who became president of Venezuela in 1999. Chávez styled himself as the leader of the “Bolivarian Revolution,” a socialist political program for much of Latin America, named after Simón Bolívar, the South American independence hero. Although the focus of the revolution has been subject to change depending on Chavez's goals, its key elements include nationalism, a centralized economy, and a strong military actively engaged in public projects. His ideology became known to many as simply chavismo.
</Question>
<Choice>Chávez, Hugo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
lawyer and politician who served as president of the Republic of China (Taiwan) from 2000 to 2008. He was a prominent leader of the pro-independence movement that sought to establish statehood for Taiwan.Born into a poor farming family, Chen won a scholarship to National Taiwan University and graduated with highest honours from its law department. He entered private practice and soon became one of Taiwan's leading attorneys. His first encounter with politics came when he defended eight protesters opposed to the Nationalist Party (Kuomintang; KMT), the island's ruling party, who had been charge...
</Question>
<Choice>Chen Shui-bian</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
chief political leader of the Soviet Union from February 1984 until his death in 1985.Born to a Russian peasant family in the Yeniseysk region of Siberia, Chernenko joined the Communist Party in 1931. Trained as a party propagandist, he held several administrative posts before becoming head of agitation and propaganda (agitprop) in Moldavia (1948–56), where he was first noticed by Leonid Brezhnev and brought to Moscow to head a similar department for the party's Central Committee (1956–60). When Brezhnev took over the party in 1964, he made Chernenko his chief of staff. Chernenko was a full me...
</Question>
<Choice>Chernenko, Konstantin Ustinovich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
son of Chiang Kai-shek (Jiang Jieshi), and his successor as leader of the Republic of China (Taiwan). His father's death in 1975 was followed by a caretaker presidency until March 21, 1978, when Chiang Ching-kuo (Jiang Jingguo) was formally elected by the National Assembly to a six-year presidential term; he was reelected to a second term in 1984.The son of Chiang Kai-shek and his first wife (whom Chiang Kai-shek subsequently divorced), Chiang Ching-kuo attended primary school in China and was arrested several times during his youth for involvement with revolutionary activities. In 1925 he wen...
</Question>
<Choice>Chiang Ching-kuo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
soldier and statesman, head of the Nationalist government in China from 1928 to 1949, and subsequently head of the Chinese Nationalist government in exile on Taiwan.Chiang was born into a moderately prosperous merchant and farmer family in the coastal province of Chekiang. He prepared for a military career first (1906) at the Paoting Military Academy in North China and subsequently (1907–11) in Japan. From 1909 to 1911 he served in the Japanese army, whose Spartan ideals he admired and adopted. More influential were the youthful compatriots he met in Tokyo; plotting to rid China of the Qing (M...
</Question>
<Choice>Chiang Kai-shek</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French politician, who served as the country's president (1995–2007) and prime minister (1974–76, 1986–88).
</Question>
<Choice>Chirac, Jacques</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Canadian lawyer and Liberal Party politician, who served as prime minister of Canada from 1993 to 2003.The 18th of 19 children of a working-class family, Chrétien studied law at Laval University and was called to the bar in Quebec in 1958. Long interested in politics, he was first elected to the House of Commons in 1963 and was reelected thereafter through 1984. In the successive administrations of Lester B. Pearson and Pierre Elliott Trudeau, Chrétien became a parliamentary secretary to the prime minister in 1965, a minister of state in 1967, and minister of national revenue in 1968. He serve...
</Question>
<Choice>Chrétien, Jean</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Korean soldier and politician who was president of South Korea from 1980 to 1988.Born into a peasant family, Chun entered the Korean Military Academy in 1951. Following his graduation in 1955, he became an infantry officer and in 1958 married Lee Soon Ja, daughter of Brig. Gen. Lee Kyu Dong. Chun commanded a South Korean division in South Vietnam during the Vietnam War and rose rapidly through the ranks. After Park Chung Hee seized power in 1961, Chun served as civil service secretary for the junta (1961–62) and, in 1963, with the nominal restoration of civilian government, as chief of personn...
</Question>
<Choice>Chun Doo Hwan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Turkish economist and politician, who was Turkey's first female prime minister (1993–96).Çiller was born to an affluent family in Istanbul. After graduating from the University of the Bosporus with a degree in economics, she continued her studies in the United States, where she earned graduate degrees from the Universities of New Hampshire and Connecticut and attended Yale University. Çiller returned to Turkey to teach and, at age 36, became the nation's youngest full professor. Together with her husband, she amassed some $60 million through real estate speculation.Çiller joined the ruling Tru...
</Question>
<Choice>Ciller, Tansu</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
New Zealand politician who was prime minister (1999–2008). She was the first woman in New Zealand to hold the office of prime minister immediately following an election.Clark, the oldest of four children of George and Margaret Clark, grew up on a sheep and cattle farm in Te Pahu, west of Hamilton. She left home at age 12 to attend Epsom Girls Grammar School in Auckland. After graduation, she enrolled in the University of Auckland, where she received bachelor's (1971) and master's (1974) degrees in political science and taught from 1973 to 1981.Clark joined the Labour Party in 1971 and during t...
</Question>
<Choice>Clark, Helen</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prime minister of Canada from June 1979 to March 1980, the youngest person ever to win the post.Clark obtained a B.A. in history (1960) and an M.A. in political science (1973) from the University of Alberta and taught political science there from 1965 to 1967. He had been active in politics since 1957 in support of the Progressive Conservative Party; from 1962 to 1965 he was national president of the Progressive Conservative Student Federation. In 1967 he directed the campaign organization that brought Peter Lougheed to power as premier of Alberta, and from 1967 to 1970 he served as executive...
</Question>
<Choice>Clark, Joe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
42nd president of the United States (1993–2001), who oversaw the country's longest peacetime economic expansion. In 1998 he became the second U.S. president to be impeached; he was acquitted by the Senate in 1999. (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America.)
</Question>
<Choice>Clinton, Bill</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Greece from 1964 to 1974.After spending World War II in exile in South Africa, Constantine returned to Greece in 1946. When his father became King Paul I in 1947, Constantine became crown prince; he succeeded to the throne upon his father's death on March 6, 1964. Fearing leftist infiltration of the army, he dismissed Premier Georgios Papandreou in July 1965 and appointed interim premiers until April 21, 1967, when a military coup forestalled the election he was planning for May of that year. He attempted a countercoup from northern Greece on Dec. 13, 1967, but had few sympathizers and...
</Question>
<Choice>Constantine II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prime minister (taoiseach) of Ireland from 1948 to 1951 and from 1954 to 1957.A prosperous lawyer who had served as attorney general, he owed his selection as prime minister to a coalition of several parties (including his own Fine Gael) and prominent independent politicians united in opposition to Eamon De Valera's Fianna Fáil (Republican Party). During his first term as prime minister, he introduced into the Dáil Éireann (Irish Assembly) the Republic of Ireland Act (1948), by which Ireland withdrew from the Commonwealth of Nations. His second government was marked by a sharp increase in acts...
</Question>
<Choice>Costello, John A</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
last president of the Fourth French Republic, from 1954 to 1959.After taking degrees in law and philosophy and pursuing a local political career, Coty was elected to the Chamber of Deputies in 1923. He sat with the left Republicans and specialized in matters of merchant shipping and government reform.In December 1930 Coty served briefly as undersecretary of the interior and then left the Chamber for the Senate. He remained relatively inactive during World War II and returned to the Chamber in 1945. The next year he joined the Robert Schuman government as minister of reconstruction and urban af...
</Question>
<Choice>Coty, René</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian politician who became his nation's first Socialist prime minister (1983–87).Craxi joined the Socialist Youth Movement in his late teens and became a member of the Italian Socialist Party's central committee in 1957. He won a seat on the city council of Milan in 1960, was elected to a seat in the national Chamber of Deputies in 1968, and became a deputy secretary of the Socialist Party in 1970. After the Socialists performed badly in the 1976 general elections, Craxi became the party's general secretary. He proceeded to unite the faction-ridden party, committed it to moderate social and...
</Question>
<Choice>Craxi, Bettino</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
premier of France from May 15, 1991, to April 2, 1992, the first woman in French history to serve as premier.Daughter of a French civil servant, she studied at the School of Higher Commercial Studies, earning a doctorate in demography, and in 1959 married Jacques Cresson, an executive with the automaker Peugeot. She joined the Socialist Party in 1965 and worked vigorously in François Mitterrand's failed presidential campaign of that year. She ran unsuccessfully for a parliamentary seat in 1975 but was subsequently elected mayor of Thuré (1977), member of the European Parliament (1979–81), and...
</Question>
<Choice>Cresson, Edith</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
president of the Central African Republic from 1960 to 1965 and from 1979 to 1981.Dacko, a former teacher, held ministerial posts under Barthélemy Boganda, the prime minister of the autonomous Central African Republic. Claiming a family relationship, Dacko succeeded to the prime ministership in 1959 after Boganda's death. In 1960 the republic gained its full independence, and Dacko became the country's first president. He ruled the Central African Republic as a one-party state and in 1962 easily won the presidential elections. Dacko was unable to improve the country's failing economy, however,...
</Question>
<Choice>Dacko, David</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman who was independent Mauritania's first president (1961–78). He was noted for his progress in unifying his ethnically mixed, dispersed, and partly nomadic people under his authoritarian but enlightened rule.Of aristocratic background, Moktar Ould Daddah was the first Mauritanian to graduate from a university and to become a lawyer. When he returned from Paris in the mid-1950s, he joined the more moderate of two rival parties, the Progressive Mauritanian Union, and in 1957 was elected to the territorial assembly. By 1958 he was president of the Executive Council and the natural choice...
</Question>
<Choice>Daddah, Moktar Ould</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Afghan politician who overthrew the monarchy of Mohammad Zahir Shah in 1973 to establish Afghanistan as a republic. He served as the country's president from 1973 to 1978.Educated in Kabul and France, Daud Khan, a cousin and brother-in-law of Zahir Shah, pursued a career in the military. He rose to command an army corps in 1939 and held the post of minister of defense from 1946 to 1953. As prime minister (1953–63) he instituted educational and social reforms and implemented a pro-Soviet policy. He was also an advocate of Pashtun irredentism, the creation of a greater “Pashtunistan” in Pashtun...
</Question>
<Choice>Daud Khan, Mohammad</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician who as president of South Africa (1989–94) brought the apartheid system of racial segregation to an end and negotiated a transition to majority rule in his country. He and Nelson Mandela jointly received the 1993 Nobel Prize for Peace for their collaboration in efforts to establish nonracial democracy in South Africa.De Klerk was the son of a leading politician. He received a law degree (with honours) from Potchefstroom University in 1958. Soon afterward he began to establish a successful law firm in Vereeniging, becoming active in civic and business affairs there. In 1972 he was el...
</Question>
<Choice>de Klerk, F.W.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Irish politician and patriot, prime minister (1932–48, 1951–54, 1957–59), and president (1959–73) of Ireland. An active revolutionary from 1913, he became president of Sinn Féin in 1918 and founded the Fianna Fáil party in 1926. In 1937 he took the Irish Free State out of the British Commonwealth and made his country a “sovereign” state, renamed Ireland, or Éire. His academic attainments also inspired wide respect; he became chancellor of the National University of Ireland in 1921.
</Question>
<Choice>de Valera, Eamon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician and civil engineer who served seven times as prime minister of Turkey and was president from 1993 to 2000.Born into a peasant family, Demirel graduated in 1948 from the Technical University of Istanbul as an engineer. He entered politics in 1961 and was elected to the National Assembly that same year as a member of the Justice Party (JP), becoming the party's leader in 1964. On October 27, 1965, after the general elections, he became the youngest prime minister in his country's history. As prime minister he improved Turkey's ties with its NATO allies and instituted development progr...
</Question>
<Choice>Demirel, Süleyman</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese communist leader, who was the most powerful figure in the People's Republic of China from the late 1970s until his death in 1997. He abandoned many orthodox communist doctrines and attempted to incorporate elements of the free-enterprise system into the Chinese economy.Deng was the son of a landowner and studied in France (1920–24), where he became active in the communist movement, and in the Soviet Union (1925–26). He then returned to China and later became a leading political and military organizer in the Jiangxi Soviet, an autonomous communist enclave in southwestern China that had...
</Question>
<Choice>Deng Xiaoping</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prime minister of India (1977–79), first leader of sovereign India not to represent the long-ruling Indian National Congress party.The son of a village teacher, Desai was educated at the University of Bombay (now the University of Mumbai) and in 1918 joined the provincial civil service of Bombay as a minor functionary. In 1930 he resigned to join Mohandas Gandhi's civil disobedience movement and spent almost 10 years in British jails during the struggle for independence. During the 1930s and '40s he alternated prison service with ministerial posts in the government of Bombay, rising to the chi...
</Question>
<Choice>Desai, Morarji</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
leader of the Progressive Conservative Party who was prime minister of Canada in 1957–63, following 22 years of uninterrupted Liberal rule.After serving in World War I, Diefenbaker practiced law in Saskatchewan. He was made King's Counsel in 1929. In 1936 he was chosen as leader of the Saskatchewan Conservative Party, serving at that post until 1940, when he was elected to the Canadian House of Commons for the constituency of Lake Centre. His quest for leadership of the Progressive Conservative Party in 1948 was unsuccessful, but he became party leader in 1956.The general election of 1957 brou...
</Question>
<Choice>Diefenbaker, John G</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician who was president of Senegal from 1981 to 2000.Diouf, the son of a postman, was a member of the Serer people and a devout Muslim. He attended the well-known Lycée Faidherbe in Saint-Louis, then capital of Senegal, and the University of Dakar. In 1958 he went to Paris and studied law at the Sorbonne. Shortly after his return home in 1960, Diouf joined the civil service and was appointed to a succession of posts, including regional governor (1961–62), secretary-general to the government (1964–65), and minister of planning and industry (1968–70). On Feb. 28, 1970, Diouf, a member of th...
</Question>
<Choice>Diouf, Abdou</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
soldier and Liberian head of state from 1980 to 1990.Doe, a member of the Krahn (Wee) tribe, enlisted in the army at age 18. He rose through the ranks to become a master sergeant in 1979. Like other indigenous Liberians, Doe resented the privilege and power granted the Americo-Liberians, descendants of the freed American slaves who founded the colony of Liberia in 1822. In April 1980 Doe led an attack by a group of Krahn soldiers on the Liberian executive mansion, killing President William R. Tolbert. Later, 13 prominent Tolbert associates were summarily tried and executed.After the coup Doe a...
</Question>
<Choice>Doe, Samuel K</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician who became president of Angola in 1979.In 1961 dos Santos, a militant nationalist, joined the Movimento Popular de Libertação de Angola (Popular Movement for the Liberation of Angola; MPLA), which supported independence from Portugal. He was chosen by the movement to study in Moscow, where he trained as an engineer, specializing in the problems of the oil industry, an important sector of Angola's economy.After returning to Angola in 1970, dos Santos served as an active fighter with the MPLA's Second Military Front in Cabinda, the oil province of Angola. A frequent representative of...
</Question>
<Choice>dos Santos, José</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British foreign secretary from 1960 to 1963, prime minister from Oct. 19, 1963, to Oct. 16, 1964, and, after the fall of his government, Conservative opposition spokesman in the House of Commons on foreign affairs. He was also foreign secretary from 1970 to 1974.As Lord Dunglass, the courtesy title he held until he succeeded in 1951 to the earldom of Home, he sat in the House of Commons as a Unionist (1931–45, 1950–51). He served as parliamentary private secretary to Prime Minister Neville Chamberlain (1937–39), undersecretary of state for foreign affairs in Winston Churchill's “caretaker” gov...
</Question>
<Choice>Douglas-Home, Sir Alec</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first secretary of the Communist Party of Czechoslovakia (Jan. 5, 1968, to April 17, 1969) whose liberal reforms led to the Soviet invasion and occupation of Czechoslovakia in August 1968.Dubcek received his early education in Kirgiziya (Kyrgyzstan) in Soviet Central Asia, where his father, Stefan Dubcek, a member of the Czechoslovak Communist Party, had settled. The family returned to Czechoslovakia in 1938. During World War II, Dubcek took part in the underground resistance to Nazi occupation and after the war rose steadily in Communist Party ranks, becoming in 1958 chief secretary of the re...
</Question>
<Choice>Dubcek, Alexander</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
president of Haiti whose 14-year regime was of unprecedented duration in that country.Duvalier graduated in 1934 from the University of Haiti School of Medicine, where he served as a hospital staff physician until 1943, when he became prominently active in the U.S.-sponsored anti-yaws campaign.A contributor to the daily Action Nationale (1934), Duvalier was markedly influenced by the mystic scholar Lorimer Denis and became a member of Le Groupe des Griots, a circle of writers who embraced black nationalism and voodoo as the key sources of Haitian culture.A supporter of President Dumarsais Esti...
</Question>
<Choice>Duvalier, François</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
president of Haiti from 1971 to 1986.The only son of François (“Papa Doc”) Duvalier, Jean-Claude succeeded his father as president for life in April 1971, becoming at age 19 the youngest president in the world. Partly because of pressure from the United States to moderate the tyrannical and corrupt practices of his father's regime, Duvalier instituted budgetary and judicial reforms, replaced a few older cabinet members with younger men, released some political prisoners, and eased press censorship, professing a policy of “gradual democratization of institutions.”Nevertheless, no sharp changes...
</Question>
<Choice>Duvalier, Jean-Claude</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Turkish poet, journalist, and politician, who served as prime minister of Turkey in 1974, 1977, 1978–79, and 1999–2002.Ecevit attended the American Robert College in Istanbul and served as an embassy official in London (1946–50). He returned to Ankara as a writer and journalist with the newspapers Halkçi and Ulus, the official organ of the Republican People's Party (RPP), which his father had represented in the National Assembly.Ecevit was elected to the National Assembly as an RPP member for Ankara (1957, 1961) and Zonguldak (1965, 1969), having joined the party council in 1959. He gradually...
</Question>
<Choice>Ecevit, Bülent</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British foreign secretary in 1935–38, 1940–45, and 1951–55 and prime minister from 1955 to 1957.After combat service in World War I, Eden studied Oriental languages (Arabic and Persian) at Christ Church, Oxford. Elected to the House of Commons in 1923, he was appointed undersecretary of state for foreign affairs in 1931, lord privy seal (with special responsibility for international relations) in 1934, and minister for League of Nations affairs (a Cabinet office created for him) in June 1935. He became foreign secretary in December 1935 but resigned in February 1938 to protest Prime Minister N...
</Question>
<Choice>Eden, Anthony</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
34th president of the United States (1953–61), who had been supreme commander of the Allied forces in western Europe during World War II. (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America.)
</Question>
<Choice>Eisenhower, Dwight D.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
queen of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland from February 6, 1952.Elizabeth was the elder daughter of Albert, duke of York, and his wife, Lady Elizabeth Bowes-Lyon. As the child of a younger son of King George V, the young Elizabeth had little prospect of acceding to the throne until her uncle, Edward VIII (afterward duke of Windsor), abdicated in her father's favour on December 11, 1936, at which time her father became King George VI and she became heir presumptive. The princess's education was supervised by her mother, who entrusted her daughters to a governess, Marion...
</Question>
<Choice>Elizabeth II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Turkish politician, who became prime minister of Turkey in 2003.In high school Erdogan became known as a fiery orator in the cause of political Islam. He later played on a professional football (soccer) team and attended Marmara University. During this time he met Necmettin Erbakan, a veteran Islamist politician, and Erdogan became active in parties led by Erbakan, despite a ban in Turkey on religiously based political parties. In 1994 Erdogan was elected mayor of Istanbul on the ticket of the Welfare Party. The election of the first-ever Islamist to the mayoralty shook the secularist establis...
</Question>
<Choice>Erdogan, Recep Tayyip</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
economist and statesman who, as economics minister (1949–63), was the chief architect of West Germany's post-World War II economic recovery. He served as German chancellor from 1963–66.Following World War I, Erhard studied economics, eventually joining an economics research institute. Because he was untainted by Nazi associations, he was entrusted by the postwar Allied occupation authorities with the reconstruction of industry in the Nürnberg-Fürth area. Thereafter he served successively as economics adviser in Middle and Upper Franconia, economics minister for Bavaria (1945–46), director of t...
</Question>
<Choice>Erhard, Ludwig</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prime minister of Israel from 1963 until his death.Eshkol became involved in the Zionist movement while a student in Vilna, Lith. He moved to Palestine in 1914 when it was under Ottoman rule, working there in a number of settlements. He fought as a member of the Jewish Legion on the side of the British forces against the Ottomans. At the end of his service in 1920, Eshkol helped found Deganya Bet, one of the first kibbutzim (collective settlements) in Palestine. Thereafter he worked untiringly for the future Israeli state. He was one of the founders of Histadrut (General Federation of Labour)...
</Question>
<Choice>Eshkol, Levi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
soldier who became president of Togo after a military takeover in January 1967.Eyadéma joined the French army in 1953, served in Indochina, Dahomey, Niger, and Algeria (1953–61), and had attained the rank of sergeant when he returned to Togo in 1962. When President Sylvanus Olympio refused to take 626 Togolese veterans of French wars into Togo's tiny army, a group of them, including Eyadéma, assassinated him in an otherwise almost bloodless military coup (January 1963) and installed a civilian, Nicolas Grunitzky, as president. After an abortive coup by members of the Ewe people of southern Tog...
</Question>
<Choice>Eyadéma, Gnassingbé</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
accountant, politician, and for a short time prime minister of Australia (1941).Fadden was active in local and state government as a young man, and he was a member of Parliament (1936–58) and leader of the Country Party (1941–58). As a member of the cabinet he held the position of minister for air and civil aviation (1940) and of treasurer (1940–41, 1949–58); he also served for five weeks as prime minister upon the resignation of Robert Gordon Menzies (later Sir Robert Menzies). He was knighted in 1951 and retired from politics in 1958.
</Question>
<Choice>Fadden, Sir Arthur William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the Saudi Arabians from 1982 to 2005. As crown prince and as an active administrator, he had been virtual ruler during the preceding reign (1975–82) of his half brother King Khalid.Fahd was the first son of Hassa Sudairi after her remarriage to the founder of the kingdom, Ibn Sa?ud. Court-educated in religion, chivalry, and politics, Fahd was named minister of education in 1953 and established a system of public elementary and secondary education. Later he undertook an earnest program of self-improvement, making up for his lack of formal schooling. In 1962 he was made minister of the i...
</Question>
<Choice>Fahd</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Saudi Arabia from 1964 to 1975, an influential figure of the Arab world who was a critic not only of Israel but of Soviet influence in the Middle East.Fay?al was a son of King Ibn Sa?ud and a brother of King Sa?ud. He was appointed foreign minister and viceroy of Hejaz in 1926 after his father conquered that province, in which lies the holy city of Mecca. In 1934 he led a victorious campaign against Yemen. He represented Saudi Arabia at the United Nations Conference of 1945 and was later ambassador to the UN General Assembly.After Sa?ud's accession in 1953, Fay?al became crown prince a...
</Question>
<Choice>Faysal</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the last king of Iraq, who reigned from 1939 to 1958.Fay?al II, the grandson of Fay?al I and great-grandson of ?usayn ibn ?Ali, former sharif of Mecca and king of the Hejaz, became king of Iraq following the untimely death of his father, King Ghazi. Because Fay?al was only four years old, his maternal uncle ?Abd al-Ilah became regent. In April 1941, when the nationalist prime minister Rashid ?Ali al-Gaylani briefly seized power from ?Abd al-Ilah, Fay?al was smuggled out of the country by his mother, Queen ?Aliyah, and was educated at the Harrow School in England. After the queen's death in 195...
</Question>
<Choice>Faysal II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician who served as president of the Dominican Republic (1996–2000; 2004– ).Fernández lived in New York City beginning in 1962 and attended schools there. He returned to the Dominican Republic in 1971 and in 1978 graduated from the Autonomous University of Santo Domingo with honours in law. He worked as a teacher and journalist and also practiced law before entering politics. The presidential candidate of the Dominican Liberation Party (PLD), he lost the first round of the elections to the mayor of Santo Domingo, José Francisco Peña Gómez, of the Dominican Revolutionary Party. After formi...
</Question>
<Choice>Fernández Reyna, Leonel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
four-star general and president of Brazil from 1979 to 1985.One of the planners of the 1964 coup that established 21 years of military rule, Figueiredo was the last in the succession of five officers chosen by the armed forces to govern Brazil as president in that period. He was an instructor specializing in intelligence in the military's advanced training schools when the coup took place. Promoted to colonel, he was immediately transferred to intelligence operations. His military career culminated with his appointment as chief of the national intelligence service under President Ernesto Geise...
</Question>
<Choice>Figueiredo, João Baptista de Oliveira</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
moderate socialist Costa Rican statesman who served as president of a governing junta in 1948–49 and as constitutional president in 1953–58 and 1970–74.Figueres was educated in universities in Costa Rica and Mexico, and he also studied at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. After returning to Costa Rica, he turned to agriculture, engaging in coffee planting and the production of cabuya (an agave plant from which rope and bags are made). His criticism of the government of Rafael Angel Calderón Guardia in July 1942 forced him into exile in Mexico for two years.When Calderón was defeated b...
</Question>
<Choice>Figueres Ferrer, José</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
teacher, cultural figure, and politician who served as president of Iceland from 1980 to 1996. She was the first woman in the world to be elected head of state in a national election.Finnbogadóttir was born into a wealthy and well-connected family. Her mother chaired Iceland's national nurses association, and her father was a civil engineer. After graduating from Reykjavík College in 1949, Finnbogadóttir attended the University of Grenoble and the Sorbonne in France and the University of Uppsala in Sweden. She also studied in Denmark and at the University of Iceland, where she later taught Fre...
</Question>
<Choice>Finnbogadóttir, Vigdís</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
38th president of the United States (1974–77), who, as 40th vice president, succeeded to the presidency on the resignation of President Richard M. Nixon under the process decreed by the Twenty-fifth Amendment to the Constitution and thereby became the country's only chief executive who was not elected as either president or vice president. His first act upon assuming office was to grant his predecessor “a full, free, and absolute pardon.” (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America.)While Ford was still an infant, his parents wer...
</Question>
<Choice>Ford, Gerald R.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician and, for a short time, prime minister of Australia (1945).Active in state politics as a young man, Forde was a member of the Australian House of Representatives (1922–46) and deputy leader of the Australian Labor Party (1932–46). In the cabinet he served as minister for the army (1941–46), minister for defense (1946), and deputy prime minister to John Curtin (1941–45) and Joseph Benedict Chifley (1945–46). He also served as prime minister for six days, July 6–12, 1945 (the shortest term in Australia's history), after the death of Curtin. He was Australian high commissioner to Canada...
</Question>
<Choice>Forde, Francis Michael</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
businessman and politician who was president of Mexico from 2000 to 2006. His term in office marked the end of 71 years of uninterrupted rule by the Institutional Revolutionary Party (PRI).Fox, the second of nine children, was born to parents of Spanish and Irish descent and raised on a 1,100-acre (445-hectare) ranch in the state of Guanajuato. He earned a degree in business administration from the Ibero-American University in Mexico City and later became a route supervisor for the Mexican unit of the Coca-Cola Company. After a series of promotions, he served as the company's chief executive i...
</Question>
<Choice>Fox, Vicente</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
general and leader of the Nationalist forces that overthrew the Spanish democratic republic in the Spanish Civil War (1936–39); thereafter he was the head of the government of Spain until 1973 and head of state until his death in 1975.
</Question>
<Choice>Franco, Francisco</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Australian politician and leader of the Liberal Party, who served as prime minister of Australia from 1975 to 1983.Fraser attended Magdalen College, Oxford, and was elected a Liberal member of Parliament in 1955. He held cabinet posts in the coalition government of the Liberal and National Country (since 1982 National) parties as minister for the army (1966–68), as minister for education and science (1968–69, 1971–72), and as minister for defense (1969–71).In March 1975 Fraser won the leadership of the Liberal Party, and in November he was named prime minister after the Labor government—which...
</Question>
<Choice>Fraser, Malcolm</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Peruvian politician and president of Peru from 1990 to 2000.Fujimori, the son of Japanese immigrants, earned a degree in agronomic engineering from the National Agrarian University in Lima (1961). He then traveled abroad to pursue graduate studies at the University of Wisconsin and the University of Strasbourg, France. After returning to Peru, he joined the faculty at his alma mater, eventually serving as rector (1984–89). In 1988–89 Fujimori hosted a television show, Concertando (“Getting Together”), which examined environmental and agrarian issues.In 1989, as terrorism and hyperinflation pla...
</Question>
<Choice>Fujimori, Alberto</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician who served as prime minister of India for three consecutive terms (1966–77) and a fourth term (1980–84). She was assassinated by Sikh extremists.She was the only child of Jawaharlal Nehru, the first prime minister of independent India. She attended Visva-Bharati University, West Bengal, and the University of Oxford, and in 1942 she married Feroze Gandhi (died 1960), a fellow member of the Indian National Congress (Congress Party). She was a member of the working committee of the ruling Congress Party from 1955, and in 1959 she was elected to the largely honorary post of party presid...
</Question>
<Choice>Gandhi, Indira</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the leading general secretary of India's Congress (I) Party (from 1981) and prime minister of India (1984–89) after the assassination of his mother, Indira Gandhi. He was himself assassinated in 1991.Rajiv and his younger brother Sanjay (1946–80), the sons of Feroze and Indira Gandhi, were educated at the prestigious Doon School in Dehradun. Rajiv then attended Imperial College, London, and completed an engineering course at the University of Cambridge (1965). After returning to India, he acquired a commercial pilot's license and, beginning in 1968, worked for Indian Airlines.While his brother...
</Question>
<Choice>Gandhi, Rajiv</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
fourth president of the Republic of the Philippines. After graduating from law school in 1923, he became, successively, a schoolteacher, representative in the Philippine Congress, governor of his province (Bohol), and then (1941–53) senator. During the Japanese occupation of the Philippines in World War II, Garcia was active in the resistance movement. He was elected vice president on the ticket of the Nacionalista Party in 1953 and was also minister of foreign affairs (1953–57). He became president of the Philippines in March 1957, upon the death of Pres. Ramon Magsaysay, and was elected to a...
</Question>
<Choice>Garcia, Carlos Polestico</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French soldier, writer, statesman, and architect of France's Fifth Republic.
</Question>
<Choice>Gaulle, Charles de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
army general who was president of Brazil from 1974 to 1979.A career army officer from an immigrant family of German Lutherans, Geisel joined the military coup led by Getúlio Vargas that overthrew the elected government and installed a dictatorship in 1930. Geisel supported Vargas for 15 years, serving in a variety of military and civil administrative posts, but in 1945 he played an important part in overthrowing Vargas's government. Over the course of the next 15 years he held several important offices, including deputy chief of the military staff of the presidency and military representative...
</Question>
<Choice>Geisel, Ernesto</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
longtime head of the Romanian Communist Party, prime minister (1952–55), and president of Romania's State Council (1961–65).Having become a revolutionary after World War I, Gheorghiu-Dej joined the then-outlawed Romanian Communist Party in 1930 and was sentenced to 12 years' hard labour for his role in the Grivi?a railwaymen's strike of 1933. Escaping prison in August 1944, he had established himself as secretary general—i.e., official head—of the party by the time of the antifascist coup of Aug. 23, 1944, which caused Romania to change sides and join the Allies against Germany. He became mini...
</Question>
<Choice>Gheorghiu-Dej, Gheorghe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman, president of India from 1969 to 1974.Giri began his education at Khallikote College, Berhampore, and then went to Dublin to study law. There he became engaged in the Sinn Féin (Irish political party) movement and was expelled from Ireland in 1916. Upon his return to India, he joined the nascent labour movement. He became general secretary and then president of the All-India Railwaymen's Federation and was twice president of the All-India Trade Union Congress, an organization closely linked with the Indian National Congress (Congress Party).When the Congress Party formed a government...
</Question>
<Choice>Giri, Varahagiri Venkata</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French political leader, who served as the third president of the Fifth Republic of France (1974–81).Giscard was the eldest son of a prominent French financier and economist and member of a patrician family. He attended the École Polytechnique (interrupting his schooling in 1944–45 to serve in the French army) and the École Nationale d'Administration in Paris. In the early 1950s he worked in the Finance Ministry.Giscard was elected to the French National Assembly in 1956 and was a delegate to the United Nations General Assembly (1956–58). He served as the secretary of state for finance (1959–6...
</Question>
<Choice>Giscard d'Estaing, Valéry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first secretary of the Central Committee of the Polish Communist Party from 1956 to 1970.Before Gomulka's birth his parents had emigrated to the United States but had returned disillusioned. His father, Jan, was a Socialist and worked in the oil fields. Gomulka completed primary school in 1917 and afterward was trained as a locksmith. At the age of 16 he joined the youth Socialist movement. In 1926 he entered the clandestine Communist Party of Poland and in the same year was first arrested for revolutionary activity.At this time Gomulka became a professional trade union organizer, and in 1930...
</Question>
<Choice>Gomulka, Wladyslaw</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish lawyer and Spanish Socialist Workers' Party (Partido Socialista Obrero Español; PSOE) politician who was prime minister of Spain from 1982 to 1996. During his four terms in office, he consolidated Spain's fledgling democracy, oversaw continued economic growth, and brought Spain into the European Economic Community (EEC; succeeded by the European Union).The son of a livestock handler, González was the only one of five children to attend college. He studied first to be a civil engineer at the University of Sevilla before transferring to its law faculty. He also later studied the law at t...
</Question>
<Choice>González Márquez, Felipe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Soviet official, the general secretary of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union (CPSU) from 1985 to 1991 and president of the Soviet Union in 1990–91. His efforts to democratize his country's political system and decentralize its economy led to the downfall of communism and the breakup of the Soviet Union in 1991. In part because he ended the Soviet Union's postwar domination of eastern Europe, Gorbachev was awarded the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1990.Gorbachev was the son of Russian peasants in Stavropol territory (kray) in southwestern Russia. He joined the Komsomol (Young Communist League)...
</Question>
<Choice>Gorbachev, Mikhail</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman who, as prime minister of Australia (1968–71), maintained his country's military commitment in Vietnam and expanded the role of the federal government in education, science, and taxation.After distinguished service as a pilot in the Royal Australian Air Force in World War II, Gorton was elected to national office in 1949 as a senator for Victoria. He directed a reequipment program as minister of the navy (1958–63) and then served as minister of works (1963–66). He administered the government scientific research program from 1962 to 1968, and in 1966 he was named the first minister fo...
</Question>
<Choice>Gorton, Sir John Grey</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nigerian military leader, who served as head of state (1966–75).From Plateau state in the middle belt of Nigeria, Gowon's father was an early convert to Christianity. Gowon was educated in Zaria and later became a career army officer. He was trained in Ghana and in England at Sandhurst and twice served in the Congo region as part of Nigeria's peacekeeping force there in the early 1960s. After the coup of January 1966, he was appointed chief of staff by Major General Johnson Aguiyi-Ironsi, the new leader. Northern officers staged a countercoup in July 1966, and Gowon emerged as the compromise h...
</Question>
<Choice>Gowon, Yakubu</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Soviet foreign minister (1957–85) and president (1985–88) of the Presidium of the Supreme Soviet of the U.S.S.R. Although never strongly identified with any particular policy or political faction, he served dependably as a skilled emissary and spokesman.Gromyko was born in a Belorussian village, the son of a peasant, and attended an agricultural school in Minsk, studying agricultural economics. After completing postgraduate studies in 1936, he served as senior research associate at the Institute of Economics of the Academy of Sciences and as a university lecturer (1936–39). In the wake of Jose...
</Question>
<Choice>Gromyko, Andrey Andreyevich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the Swedes from 1950 to 1973, the last Swedish monarch to hold real political power after constitutional reforms initiated in 1971.The son of the future king Gustav V and Victoria of Baden, Gustav entered the army in 1902 and by 1932 had risen to the rank of general. His lifelong interest in archaeology began during his studies at the University of Uppsala, and throughout the 1920s he participated in archaeological expeditions in Greece, Italy, and Cyprus. He also excavated and wrote papers on ancient Swedish monuments and was considered an authority on Chinese ceramics, owning one of...
</Question>
<Choice>Gustav VI Adolf</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
emperor of Ethiopia from 1930 to 1974 who sought to modernize his country and who steered it into the mainstream of post-World War II African politics. He brought Ethiopia into the League of Nations and the United Nations and made Addis Ababa the major centre for the Organization of African Unity (now African Union).Tafari was a great-grandson of Sahle Selassie of Shewa (Shoa) and a son of Ras (Prince) Makonnen, a chief adviser to Emperor Menilek II. Educated at home by French missionaries, Tafari at an early age favourably impressed the emperor with his intellectual abilities and was promoted...
</Question>
<Choice>Haile Selassie I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
member of the ruling family of Liechtenstein who became prince (head of state) in 1989.Hans Adam, the eldest son of Prince Francis Joseph II, spent his early youth in the castle of Vaduz with his brothers and his sister but he and his siblings were not isolated from the everyday life of the principality's citizens. He attended primary school in the town, and, as a Boy Scout, he took part in camping and other activities. He received his secondary education at the Schottengymnasium (“Scottish Academy”) in Vienna and in Zuoz, Switzerland. After a brief period as a trainee in a London bank, in the...
</Question>
<Choice>Hans Adam II, prince of Liechtenstein</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese politician, whose election as prime minister in 1996 signaled a return to Liberal Democratic Party (LDP) rule after a brief Socialist regime (1994–95). He left office in 1998 after having failed in his attempts to end a long-lasting economic recession in Japan.The son of a politician, Hashimoto was inspired by his father to take an active role in public life. After receiving a degree from Keio University in 1960, he began his political career in 1963 when he won election to his recently deceased father's seat in the House of Representatives. Hashimoto went on to serve 11 terms as a Li...
</Question>
<Choice>Hashimoto Ryutaro</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Morocco from 1961 to 1999. Hassan was considered by pious Muslims to be a direct descendant of the Prophet Muhammad (Ahl al-Bayt).Hassan, after taking a law degree at Bordeaux, France, was appointed commander of the Royal Armed Forces (1955) and deputy premier (1960) and succeeded to the throne on the death of his father, Mu?ammad V (1961). As king, Hassan tried to democratize the Moroccan political system by introducing a new constitution (1962) that provided for a popularly elected legislature while maintaining a strong executive branch headed by the king. From 1965 to 1970 he exerci...
</Question>
<Choice>Hassan II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
one of Japan's most important post-World War II prime ministers.Hatoyama was born into a wealthy cosmopolitan family; his father was a graduate of Yale University, and his mother was a well-known writer and founder of a women's college. Entering politics, Hatoyama was elected to the lower house of the Japanese Diet (parliament) in 1915 as a member of the dominant Seiyukai Party. He soon became a leading party official and in 1931 was named minister of education. His many Western habits, however, caused him to fall out of favour with the military, which began to dominate the government, and he...
</Question>
<Choice>Hatoyama Ichiro</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
a leader of the Indonesian independence movement who was prime minister (1948–50) and vice president (1950–56) of Indonesia.While he studied in The Netherlands from 1922 to 1932, he was president of the Perhimpunan Indonesia (Indonesian Union), a progressive, nationalist political group founded by overseas Indonesian students. Returning to the Dutch East Indies in 1932, Hatta was arrested for his political activities by the Dutch in 1934 and sent to the infamous concentration camp of Boven Digul in West New Guinea. In 1935 he was exiled to the island of Bandanaira, where he remained until the...
</Question>
<Choice>Hatta, Mohammad</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prime minister of Ireland from 1979 to 1981, from March to December 1982, and from 1987 to 1992.Haughey, the son of an officer in the original Irish Republican Army (IRA), attended University College in Dublin, studying law and accounting. While making a fortune—apparently in real estate—he married (1951) the daughter of Sean Lemass (later to be prime minister) and after several attempts entered the Dáil (lower house of Parliament) in 1957 as a member of the Fianna Fáil party for a constituency in Dublin. He became minister of justice in 1961 and later minister of agriculture and of finance.In...
</Question>
<Choice>Haughey, Charles</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Czech playwright, poet, and political dissident, who, after the fall of communism, was president of Czechoslovakia (1989–92) and of the Czech Republic (1993–2003).Havel was the son of a wealthy restaurateur whose property was confiscated by the communist government of Czechoslovakia in 1948. As the son of bourgeois parents, Havel was denied easy access to education but managed to finish high school and study on the university level. He found work as a stagehand in a Prague theatrical company in 1959 and soon began writing plays with Ivan Vyskocil. By 1968 Havel had progressed to the position o...
</Question>
<Choice>Havel, Václav</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Australian labour leader and prime minister of Australia from 1983 to 1991.After graduating from the University of Western Australia with a degree in law, Hawke spent three years at the University of Oxford as a Rhodes Scholar. He was briefly an economics researcher at the Australian National University in Canberra and in 1958 joined the Australian Council of Trade Unions (ACTU), the umbrella organization of the country's tightly organized labour movement. As president of the ACTU from 1970 to 1980, Hawke proved to be a brilliant trade-union official, getting favourable settlements for the uni...
</Question>
<Choice>Hawke, Robert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Conservative prime minister of Great Britain from 1970 to 1974.Although he was of modest origins, Heath was educated at Oxford, where he was elected president of the University Conservative Association in 1937. In 1938, as chairman of the Federation of University Conservative Associations and president of the Oxford Union, he actively opposed the policy of appeasement toward Nazi Germany pursued by the Conservative prime minister Neville Chamberlain. He served in the army during World War II, worked in the Ministry of Civil Aviation in 1946–47, was editor of the Church Times from January 1948...
</Question>
<Choice>Heath, Sir Edward</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Irish-born Israeli politician, soldier, lawyer, and author. He was an eloquent and passionate spokesman for the Zionist cause and was instrumental in the development of Israel, both as a soldier and as the country's longest-serving president (1983–93).The son of Rabbi Isaac Halevi Herzog, Chaim grew up in Dublin before immigrating with his family to Palestine in 1935. The following year he joined the Haganah, the pre-Israel Jewish defense forces. Herzog later returned to Britain, studying law at the University of London, and served in the British army during World War II. In 1947 he rejoined t...
</Question>
<Choice>Herzog, Chaim</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
emperor of Japan from 1926 until his death in 1989. He was the longest-reigning monarch in Japan's history.Hirohito was born at the Aoyama Palace and was educated at the Peers' School and at the Crown Prince's Institute. Early in life he developed an interest in marine biology, on which he later wrote several books. In 1921 he visited Europe, becoming the first Japanese crown prince to travel abroad. Upon his return he was named prince regent when his father, the emperor Taisho, retired because of mental illness. In 1924 he married the princess Nagako Kuni.Hirohito became emperor of Japan on D...
</Question>
<Choice>Hirohito</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
leader of New Zealand's National Party (1940–57) who, as prime minister (1949–57), suppressed union unrest and relaxed government controls over the economy.After military service in Europe during World War I and subsequent convalescence, Holland became important in business and politics in Christchurch, N.Z. In 1935 he replaced his father, Henry H. Holland, in Parliament and became leader of the National Party opposition in 1940. Holland served briefly (1942) in the war Cabinet but thereafter attacked the Labour-led government for its economic controls and mismanagement. Under him, the Nationa...
</Question>
<Choice>Holland, Sir Sidney</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prime minister of Australia (1966–67) who supported U.S. policies in Vietnam and sponsored the visit to Australia of Lyndon B. Johnson, the first American president-in-office to travel there.As a Melbourne lawyer during the early 1930s, Holt became interested in the United Australia Party, the forerunner of the Liberal Party, and was elected to the federal Parliament in 1935. In 1941 he organized the Department of Labour and National Service for wartime mobilization under Robert Menzies. When Menzies returned to power in 1949, Holt became minister of labour (1949–58) and of immigration (1949–5...
</Question>
<Choice>Holt, Harold</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
communist official who, as first secretary of East Germany's Socialist Unity Party of Germany (Sozialistische Einheitspartei Deutschlands, or SED), was East Germany's leader from 1971 until he fell from power in 1989 in the wake of the democratic reforms sweeping eastern Europe.The son of a miner who was an official of the Communist Party, Honecker joined the Communist Youth Movement at the age of 14 and in 1929 became a full party member. By trade he was a slater. After the Nazis came to power in 1933, he organized illegal activities by young communists in various parts of Germany. He was arr...
</Question>
<Choice>Honecker, Erich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
founder of the reform political party Japan New Party (Nihon Shinto) and prime minister of Japan in 1993–94.Hosokawa's maternal grandfather, Konoe Fumimaro, was prime minister of Japan in 1937–39 and 1940–41. After graduating from Sophia University, Tokyo, Hosokawa joined the staff of the liberal newspaper Asahi Shimbun in 1963. In 1969 he ran for a seat in the lower house of the Japanese parliament. He lost that race, but two years later, with strong support from the ruling Liberal-Democratic Party (LDP), he was elected to the less powerful upper house, where he served for 12 years.Elected go...
</Question>
<Choice>Hosokawa Morihiro</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician and physician who was president of Côte d'Ivoire (Ivory Coast) from independence in 1960 until his death in 1993. Under his rule it became one of the most prosperous nations in sub-Saharan Africa.The son of a wealthy Baule chief, Houphouët-Boigny worked as a rural doctor and pursued a second career as a wealthy planter. He began his political career as a cofounder of the African Agricultural Syndicate, formed by disgruntled African planters (1944) to protect their interests against European settlers. In the first Côte d'Ivoire elections (1945) he was elected a deputy to the French N...
</Question>
<Choice>Houphouët-Boigny, Félix</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Australian politician who was prime minister of Australia (1996–2007) and leader of the Liberal Party (1985–89, 1995–2007).Howard earned a Bachelor of Laws degree from the University of Sydney in 1961 and the following year became a solicitor of the New South Wales Supreme Court. His interests soon turned to politics, and in 1974 he was elected to Parliament as a member of the Liberal Party. Under Prime Minister Malcolm Fraser, he served as minister for business and consumer affairs (1975–77) and as federal treasurer (1977–83). Howard became deputy leader of the Liberal Party in 1982 and advan...
</Question>
<Choice>Howard, John Winston</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the first communist chief of state of Albania. As that country's ruler for 40 years after World War II, he forced its transformation from a semifeudal relic of the Ottoman Empire into an industrialized economy with the most tightly controlled society in Europe.Hoxha, the son of a Muslim cloth merchant, studied at the French lycée at Kor?ë and reportedly also at the American Technical School in Tiranë. In 1930 he went on a state scholarship to the University of Montpellier, France, and then from 1934 to 1936 he was a secretary at the Albanian consulate general in Brussels and studied law at the...
</Question>
<Choice>Hoxha, Enver</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
premier of the People's Republic of China from 1976 to 1980 and chairman of the Chinese Communist Party (CCP) from 1976 to 1981.Hua joined the CCP in 1938. After the Chinese Civil War ended in 1949, he became a local party secretary in Hunan province, the home province of Mao Zedong. He was transferred in 1952 to head the party apparatus in Xiangtan county in Hunan. Hua became vice governor of the province in 1958 and was a strong supporter of Mao in the Great Leap Forward (1958–60). During the Cultural Revolution (1966–76) he received Mao's endorsement against rebel groups in Hunan, and he wa...
</Question>
<Choice>Hua Guofeng</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian statesman, the first Muslim to hold the largely ceremonial position of president of India. His fostering of secularism was criticized by some Muslim activists.Husain responded to the nationalist leader Mahatma Gandhi's appeal to Indian youth to shun state-supported institutions; he helped found the Muslim National University in Aligarh (later moved to New Delhi) and served as its vice-chancellor from 1926 to 1948. At Gandhi's invitation, he also became chairman of the National Committee on Basic Education, established in 1937 to design a Gandhian syllabus for schools.In 1948 Husain beca...
</Question>
<Choice>Husain, Zakir</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Jordan from 1953 to 1999 and a member of the Hashimite dynasty, considered by many Muslims to be among the Ahl al-Bayt (“People of the House,” the direct descendants of the Prophet Muhammad) and the traditional guardians of the holy cities of Mecca and Medina. His reign marked the shaping of the modern kingdom of Jordan, and his policies greatly increased the Jordanian standard of living.Following the July 1951 assassination of ?ussein's grandfather King ?Abdullah in Jerusalem, his father, ?alal, ascended to the throne but was in 1952 declared unfit to rule by parliament owing to menta...
</Question>
<Choice>Hussein</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the first king of Libya when that country gained its independence in 1951.In 1902 Idris succeeded his father as head of the Sanusiyyah, an Islamic tariqa, or brotherhood, centred in Cyrenaica. Because he was a minor, active leadership first passed to his cousin, A?mad al-Sharif. Ruling in his own right after 1916, Idris's first problem was to deal with the Italians, who in 1911 had invaded Libya in an effort to create a North African empire but were unable to extend their authority much beyond the coast. By the peace of Arcoma (1917), Idris secured a cease-fire and, in effect, confirmation of...
</Question>
<Choice>Idris I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prime minister of Japan from July 1960 until October 1964, who was instrumental in Japan's phenomenal economic growth in the years after World War II.Born into a sake brewer's family, he graduated from Kyoto Imperial University law school in 1925 and began his career in the Ministry of Finance. After rising to the position of vice minister of finance, he won a House of Representatives seat in the January 1949 general election and became minister of finance in the government of Yoshida Shigeru. Eventually he and the future prime minister Sato Eisaku became known as leading exponents of the “Yos...
</Question>
<Choice>Ikeda Hayato</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Romanian politician who twice served as president of Romania (1990–96; 2000–04).Iliescu received a degree in business from the Polytechnic Institute of Bucharest and then studied engineering in Moscow. In 1953 he joined the Communist Party, and he held positions of increasing prestige during the following decade. A protégé of Nicolae Ceau?escu, he benefited from his mentor's election as party general secretary in 1965. In 1971, however, he fell out of favour with Ceau?escu, who divested him of all positions except his membership on the Central Committee and launched him on a career of remote a...
</Question>
<Choice>Iliescu, Ion</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Turkish army officer, statesman, and collaborator with and successor to Mustafa Kemal Atatürk as president of the Turkish Republic. Identified with one-party rule between 1939 and 1946, he later emerged as a champion of democracy.Ismet served on the general staff of the 3rd Army at Edirne and as chief of staff of the army in Yemen. During World War I, he commanded the 4th Army in Syria (1916), and, at the time of the Ottoman surrender (Oct. 30, 1918), he was the undersecretary of war in Constantinople. Later he joined Mustafa Kemal's movement to resist the Allied occupation of Anatolia. In 192...
</Question>
<Choice>Inönü, Ismet</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician and union activist who in 1953 became the first popularly elected prime minister of British Guiana (now Guyana). He headed the country's government again from 1957 to 1964 and from 1992 to 1997.The son of a foreman on a sugarcane plantation, Jagan studied dentistry in the United States. When he returned to practice dentistry in British Guiana in 1943, he became active in union and political affairs and was elected to the British Guianan legislature in 1947.In 1950 Jagan and his American-born wife established Guiana's first modern political party, the People's Progressive Party (PPP)...
</Question>
<Choice>Jagan, Cheddi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
army general and communist leader of Poland, chief of state from 1981 to 1989 and president from 1989 to 1990.When World War II broke out, the young Jaruzelski and his family were trapped by the invading Red Army, and he was deported to the Soviet Union. In 1943 he joined the Polish army formed in the Soviet Union and eventually joined the fight against Germany.After the war Jaruzelski graduated from the Polish Higher Infantry School and later from the General Staff Academy. He joined Poland's communist party (renamed the Polish United Workers' Party [PUWP]) in 1948 and steadily rose through t...
</Question>
<Choice>Jaruzelski, Wojciech Witold</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician and veterinarian who was The Gambia's prime minister from 1962 to 1970 and its president from 1970 until he was overthrown in 1994.The son of a Mande trader, Jawara was educated at a Methodist boys' school, studied veterinary medicine at the University of Glasgow in Scotland, and qualified as a veterinary surgeon in 1953. Returning to The Gambia, he became principal veterinary officer of that British colony in 1957. Jawara had become interested in politics, and in 1959 he joined the Protectorate People's Party. He changed its name to the People's Progressive Party and became its lea...
</Question>
<Choice>Jawara, Sir Dawda Kairaba</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
lawyer and public official who served as president of Sri Lanka from 1978 to 1989.The son of a Supreme Court judge, Jayewardene graduated from Ceylon Law College in Colombo in 1932 and practiced as a barrister until 1943. He joined the Ceylon National Congress party and in 1943 won election to the State Council. In 1948, when Ceylon won independence from British rule, Jayewardene became minister of finance in the postindependence government formed by the moderate United National Party (UNP). He became the party's second-ranking leader under D.S. Senanayake and then under his son, Dudley Senana...
</Question>
<Choice>Jayewardene, J.R.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
36th president of the United States (1963–69). A moderate Democrat and vigorous leader in the United States Senate, Johnson was elected vice president in 1960 and acceded to the presidency in 1963 upon the assassination of President John F. Kennedy. During his administration he signed into law the Civil Rights Act (1964), the most comprehensive civil rights legislation since the Reconstruction era, initiated major social service programs, and bore the brunt of national opposition to his vast expansion of American involvement in the Vietnam War. (For a discussion of the history and nature of th...
</Question>
<Choice>Johnson, Lyndon B.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Socialist Party politician who served as prime minister of France (1997–2002) in a cohabitation government with conservative President Jacques Chirac.Born in the Parisian suburb of Meudon, Jospin inherited many of his socialist beliefs from his schoolteacher father. After two years of obligatory military service, in 1963 he entered the École Nationale d'Administration, the training ground for most of France's governing elite. He graduated near the top of his class and joined the foreign ministry. Amid the protests against Gaullist leadership in the late 1960s, Jospin became restless with his p...
</Question>
<Choice>Jospin, Lionel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Spain from Nov. 22, 1975. He acceded to the Spanish throne two days after the death of Francisco Franco. Juan Carlos was instrumental in Spain's peaceful transition to democracy.Juan Carlos was the grandson of the last king, Alfonso XIII, who left Spain in 1931 and died in exile 10 years later, after renouncing his rights in favour of his third son, Juan Carlos Teresa Silverio Alfonso de Borbón y Battenberg, conde de Barcelona (1913–93), popularly known as Don Juan. (Alfonso's eldest son had been killed in an automobile accident, and his second son renounced his rights in 1933 for medi...
</Question>
<Choice>Juan Carlos</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
queen of The Netherlands from 1948 to 1980.Juliana, the only child of Queen Wilhelmina and Prince Henry of Mecklenburg-Schwerin, studied law at the University of Leiden (1927–30) and in 1931 helped form the Nationaal Crisis Comité to foster measures by private enterprise to alleviate the economic depression. She married Prince Bernhard of Lippe-Biesterfeld in 1937 and gave birth to four daughters: Beatrix (1938), Irene (1939), Margriet (1943), and Christina (1947). During World War II, Juliana took refuge in Ottawa while her husband remained with Queen Wilhelmina's government, which had reloca...
</Question>
<Choice>Juliana</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
leader of a rebellion that overthrew President Mobutu Sese Seko of Zaire in May 1997. He subsequently became president and restored the country's former name, Democratic Republic of the Congo.Kabila was born into the Luba tribe in the southern province of Katanga. He studied political philosophy at a French university and attended the University of Dar es Salaam in Tanzania, where he met and formed a friendship with Yoweri Museveni, the future president of Uganda. In 1960 Kabila became a youth leader in a political party allied to Congo's first postindependence prime minister, Patrice Lumumba....
</Question>
<Choice>Kabila, Laurent</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
premier of Hungary (1956–58, 1961–65) and first secretary (1956–88) of Hungary's Communist Party who played a key role in Hungary's transition from the 1956 anti-Soviet government of Imre Nagy to the pro-Soviet regime that followed. Kádár managed to convince the Soviet Union to withdraw its troops and allow Hungary a modicum of internal independence after quelling a popular revolt in his country.Trained as a skilled mechanic, Kádár became a member of the then-illegal Communist Party in 1931 and was arrested several times in the following 12 years. He was admitted to the Central Committee of th...
</Question>
<Choice>Kádár, János</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician and government offical who served as prime minister of Japan in the period 1989–91.The son of a photography studio owner, Kaifu graduated from Waseda University, Tokyo, in 1954. Entering politics, he won election to the House of Representatives as a member of the Liberal-Democratic Party (LDP) in 1960 and was regularly reelected thereafter. He served as deputy chief secretary of Prime Minister Miki Takeo's Cabinet in 1974–76 and then became minister of education (1976–77) under Prime Minister Fukuda Takeo. He held this latter post again in 1985–86 under Prime Minister Nakasone Yasuh...
</Question>
<Choice>Kaifu Toshiki</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek statesman who was prime minister from 1955 to 1963 and again from 1974 to 1980. He then served as president from 1980 to 1985 and from 1990 to 1995. Karamanlis gave Greece competent government and political stability while his conservative economic policies stimulated economic growth. In 1974–75 he successfully restored democracy and constitutional government in Greece after the rule of a military junta there had collapsed.The eldest of seven children of a poor schoolteacher, Karamanlis was able, with the help of local benefactors, to attend secondary school and the University of Athens....
</Question>
<Choice>Karamanlis, Konstantinos</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek politician who served as prime minister of Greece (2004–09).Karamanlis was the nephew of Konstantinos Karamanlis, who, as government minister, prime minister, and president, had shaped Greek politics for nearly half a century. The younger Karamanlis started his political activities in the New Democracy (ND) party, which his uncle had founded in 1974. Although Karamanlis held high positions within the party's youth and student organizations between 1974 and 1979 and served in the navy (1977–79), his political career remained unremarkable as he focused on his studies. He earned a law degre...
</Question>
<Choice>Karamanlis, Kostas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Afghan politician who, backed by the Soviet Union, was president of Afghanistan from 1979 to 1986.The son of a well-connected army general, Karmal became involved in Marxist political activities while a student at Kabul University in the 1950s and was imprisoned for five years as a result. Upon his release, he served in the army and returned to the university for a law degree. In 1965 he was a founding member of the People's Democratic Party of Afghanistan (PDPA) and from 1965 to 1973 served in the National Assembly. When the PDPA split (1967) into the People's (“Khalq”) and the Banner (“Parch...
</Question>
<Choice>Karmal, Babrak</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman and first president of the independent Congo republic from 1960 to 1965, who shortly after independence in 1960 ousted the Congo's first premier, Patrice Lumumba, after the breakdown of order in the country.Educated by Roman Catholic missionaries, Kasavubu became a lay teacher. In 1942 he entered the civil service; he attained the rank of chief clerk, the highest position open to Congolese in the Belgian colonial administration.An early leader in the Congo's independence movement, Kasavubu during the late 1940s held important offices in Congolese cultural societies and alumni associa...
</Question>
<Choice>Kasavubu, Joseph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician who led Zambia to independence in 1964 and served as that country's president until 1991.
</Question>
<Choice>Kaunda, Kenneth</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician who was leader of the Australian Labor Party and prime minister of Australia from December 1991 to March 1996.Growing up in working-class Bankstown, a suburb of Sydney, Keating left school at age 14. He became involved in trade union activity and labour politics and was elected in 1969 to the House of Representatives at age 25. Acquiring a reputation for both pointed political invective and party loyalty, he was chosen by Prime Minister Robert Hawke to be federal treasurer in 1983. Keating became a stellar performer, making his mark with a blend of earthy attacks on his opponents an...
</Question>
<Choice>Keating, Paul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
socialist politician and first president of Mali (1960–68).Keita was trained as a teacher in Dakar and entered politics in his native French Sudan (now Mali). In 1945 he cofounded and became secretary-general of the Sudanese Union. In 1946 the Sudanese Union merged with another anticolonial party, the African Democratic Rally, to form the US-RDA. Keita was briefly imprisoned by the French in 1946. Two years later, however, he won a seat in the territorial assembly of French Sudan, and from 1956 to 1958 he served as a deputy in the French National Assembly, becoming its first African vice presi...
</Question>
<Choice>Keita, Modibo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
35th president of the United States (1961–63), who faced a number of foreign crises, especially in Cuba and Berlin, but managed to secure such achievements as the Nuclear Test-Ban Treaty and the Alliance for Progress. He was assassinated while riding in a motorcade in Dallas. (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America.)
</Question>
<Choice>Kennedy, John F.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
African statesman and nationalist, the first prime minister (1963–64) and then the first president (1964–78) of independent Kenya.
</Question>
<Choice>Kenyatta, Jomo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Saudi Arabia (1975–82), who succeeded his half brother Fay?al as king when Fay?al was assassinated in 1975. A moderate influence in Middle East politics and a relatively retiring man, he left much of the administration of the country to his half brother Prince Fahd, who became his successor.Born in Riyadh when it was a small desert town, Khalid became the closest supporter of his brothers Sa?ud and Fay?al. When he was 14, his father Ibn Sa?ud, founder of the Saudi kingdom, sent him as his representative to the desert tribes to hear their grievances. In 1934 he took part in the Saudi ex...
</Question>
<Choice>Khalid</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Iranian cleric and politician who served as president of Iran (1981–89) and as that country's rahbar, or leader, from 1989. A religious figure of some significance, Khamenei was generally addressed with the honorific ayatollah.Khamenei began his advanced religious studies at Qom under the most prominent Shi?ite scholars of the day, including Ruhollah Khomeini. From 1963 he was actively involved in protests against the monarchy, for which he was imprisoned several times by Iran's security services. Khamenei remained closely associated with the exiled Khomeini during this time and immediately af...
</Question>
<Choice>Khamenei, Ali</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Iranian political leader, who was president of Iran (1997–2005).The son of a well-known religious teacher, Khatami studied at a traditional madrasah (religious school) in the holy city of Qom, where he later taught. However, he also received degrees in philosophy from E?fahan University and the University of Tehran, both secular institutions, a somewhat unusual accomplishment for a member of Iran's Shi?ite clergy. Khatami held the title hojatoleslam, signifying his position as a cleric, and, as a direct descendant of the Prophet Muhammad, he wore a black turban.During the 1960s and '70s Khatam...
</Question>
<Choice>Khatami, Mohammad</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Iranian Shi?ite cleric who led the revolution that overthrew Mohammad Reza Shah Pahlavi in 1979 (seeIranian Revolution) and who was Iran's ultimate political and religious authority for the next 10 years.Khomeini was the grandson and son of mullahs (Shi?ite religious leaders). When he was about five months old, his father was killed on the orders of a local landlord. The young Khomeini was raised by his mother and aunt and then, after their deaths, by his older brother, Mortaza (later known as Ayatollah Pasandideh). He was educated in various Islamic schools, and he settled in the city of Qom...
</Question>
<Choice>Khomeini, Ruhollah</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first secretary of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union (1953–64) and premier of the Soviet Union (1958–64) whose policy of de-Stalinization had widespread repercussions throughout the communist world. In foreign policy he pursued a policy of “peaceful coexistence” with the capitalist West.
</Question>
<Choice>Khrushchev, Nikita Sergeyevich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
conservative politician and chancellor (1966–69) of the Federal Republic of Germany whose “grand coalition” brought the Social Democratic Party (SPD) into the government for the first time since 1930.Kiesinger was educated at Berlin and Tübingen, after which he began to practice law. He joined the Nazi Party after Adolf Hitler's accession to power in 1933 but remained largely inactive in it and refused to join the National Socialist lawyers' guild in 1938. During World War II he served as assistant chief of the radio propaganda department in the foreign ministry. Interned by U.S. forces after...
</Question>
<Choice>Kiesinger, Kurt Georg</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
South Korean politician, who became a prominent opposition leader during the tenure of President Park Chung Hee. He became the first opposition leader to win election to his country's presidency (1998–2003). Kim received the Nobel Prize for Peace in 2000 for his efforts to restore democracy in South Korea and to improve relations with North Korea.Kim was the son of a middle-class farmer, and he graduated from the Mokp'o Commercial High School at the top of his class in 1943. He began working as a clerk in a Japanese-owned shipping company and in 1945 took over the company, eventually becoming...
</Question>
<Choice>Kim Dae Jung</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
communist leader of North Korea from 1948 until his death in 1994. He was the nation's premier from 1948 to 1972, chairman of its dominant Korean Workers (Communist) Party from 1949, and president and head of state from 1972.Kim was the son of parents who fled to Manchuria in 1925 to escape the Japanese rule of Korea. He joined the Korean guerrilla resistance against the Japanese occupation in the 1930s and adopted the name of an earlier legendary Korean guerrilla fighter against the Japanese. Kim was noticed by the Soviet military authorities, who sent him to the Soviet Union for military and...
</Question>
<Choice>Kim Il-sung</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
North Korean politician, son of the former North Korean premier and (communist) Korean Workers' Party (KWP) chairman Kim Il-sung, and successor to his father as ruler of North Korea.The official North Korean version of Kim Jong Il's life, different from the biography documented elsewhere, says that he was born at a guerrilla base camp on Mount Paektu, the highest point on the Korean peninsula; it attributes many precocious abilities to him; and it claims his birth was accompanied by such auspicious signs as the appearance of a double rainbow in the sky. During the Korean War (1950–53) he was p...
</Question>
<Choice>Kim Jong Il</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
South Korean politician, moderate opposition leader, and president from 1993 to 1998.Kim graduated from Seoul National University in 1952 and was first elected to the National Assembly in 1954. A centrist liberal, he was successively reelected until 1979, when he was expelled (on October 9) from the assembly for his opposition to Pres. Park Chung Hee. His expulsion touched off riots and demonstrations. To protest Kim's dismissal, all 66 opposition members of the assembly resigned. After Park's assassination on October 26, it was assumed that Kim would be a contender in the presidential electio...
</Question>
<Choice>Kim Young Sam</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Argentine lawyer and politician, who was president of Argentina from 2003 to 2007.Kirchner studied law at the National University of La Plata, where he was a member of the Peronist Youth organization. In 1975 he married Cristina Fernández, a fellow law student. Following their graduation in 1976, the couple returned to Santa Cruz, where they established a successful law practice in the late 1970s. During the country's military dictatorship (1976–83), Kirchner was briefly imprisoned for his political beliefs. In 1987 he was elected mayor of Río Gallegos, and in 1991 he was elected to the first...
</Question>
<Choice>Kirchner, Néstor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman whose term as prime minister of Japan (1957–60) was marked by a turbulent opposition campaign against a new U.S.–Japan security treaty agreed to by his government.Born Sato Nobusuke, an older brother of future prime minister Sato Eisaku, he was adopted by a paternal uncle bearing the Kishi name. He graduated from the Tokyo Imperial law department (1920) and began a successful civil service career. In 1936 he became a vice minister of the Manchukuo government's industrial department and helped to promote the industrialization of Japanese-occupied Manchuria and China. On his return to...
</Question>
<Choice>Kishi Nobusuke</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
chancellor of West Germany from 1982 to 1990 and of the reunified German nation from 1990 to 1998. He presided over the integration of East Germany into West Germany in 1990 and thus became the first chancellor of a unified Germany since 1945.Kohl grew up in a conservative Roman Catholic family. As a teenager in wartime Germany, he was drafted and sent to basic training, but the war ended before he had to fight. His interest in politics manifested itself early: in 1947 he began working in a Christian Democratic Union (CDU) youth organization in his native town. Kohl earned a doctorate in polit...
</Question>
<Choice>Kohl, Helmut</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
third-generation Japanese politician, who was prime minister of Japan from 2001 to 2006.Both Koizumi's father and grandfather served in the Diet (parliament). He graduated with a degree in economics from Keio University, Tokyo, in 1967 and then attended the London School of Economics. Upon his father's death in 1969, he ran unsuccessfully for the seat, and in 1971 he ran again and was elected. In 1992–93 he was minister of posts and telecommunications and in 1988–89 and 1996–98 minister of health and welfare. He ran unsuccessfully for the presidency of the dominant Liberal-Democratic Party (LD...
</Question>
<Choice>Koizumi Junichiro</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Soviet statesman and premier of the Soviet Union (1964–80). He was a competent and pragmatic economic administrator rather than an ideologue.Kosygin joined the Red Army as a volunteer in 1919 and served in the Russian Civil War. Following the war he received some vocational training, joined the Communist Party (1927), and occupied several positions in the Leningrad (now St. Petersburg) city government and in industry. By 1939 he had been appointed people's commissar for the textile industry as well as a member of the party's Central Committee. In 1940 he became deputy chairman of the Council o...
</Question>
<Choice>Kosygin, Aleksey Nikolayevich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
president of Ukraine from 1991 to 1994. For 30 years a Communist Party functionary, he converted to nationalist politics after the collapse of the Soviet regime. He was the first democratically elected president of Ukraine.In 1958 Kravchuk graduated from the Kiev T.H. Shevchenko State University and joined the Communist Party. He taught political economics in Chernivtsi and began a political career, rising in the 1980s to top posts in the propaganda and ideology departments for Ukraine. He became chairman of the Ukrainian Supreme Soviet in July 1990, and as such he soon became the effective le...
</Question>
<Choice>Kravchuk, Leonid Makarovich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
president of Brazil (1956–61) noted for his ambitious public works, especially the construction of the new capital, Brasília.Kubitschek attended the Diamantina Seminary, worked his way through medical school at the University of Minas Gerais (graduated 1927), and did internships in surgery in Paris, Vienna, and Berlin. He became head of the surgical division of the military Medical Corps of the state of Minas Gerais in 1932 and represented Minas Gerais in the Federal Chamber of Deputies from 1934 to 1937 and 1946 to 1950. As mayor of Belo Horizonte (1940–45) he distinguished himself in city pl...
</Question>
<Choice>Kubitschek, Juscelino</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ukrainian engineer and politician who became prime minister (1992–93) and the second president of independent Ukraine (1994–2005). His administration supported increased privatization, free trade, and closer ties with Russia.After graduating from Dnipropetrovsk State University in 1960, Kuchma embarked on a career as an engineer, serving as Communist Party secretary (1972–82) for his company in Dnipropetrovsk. During those years he also retained a top-secret post as a technical manager in Baikonur, Kazakhstan, the centre of the Soviet space program. From 1986 to 1992, he served as the general...
</Question>
<Choice>Kuchma, Leonid</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
member of a prominent Sri Lankan political family, who was the first woman to serve as the country's president (1994–2005).Chandrika Bandaranaike was the daughter of two former prime ministers. Her father was S.W.R.D. Bandaranaike, founder of the socialist Sri Lanka Freedom Party and prime minister from 1956 until his assassination in 1959. Her mother was Sirimavo Bandaranaike, who took control of the party upon his death and who served as prime minister from 1960 to 1965 and from 1970 to 1977. Their daughter was educated at the Universities of Paris and London, where she studied political sci...
</Question>
<Choice>Kumaratunga, Chandrika Bandaranaike</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polish politician, who served as president of Poland from 1995 to 2005.Kwasniewski attended the University of Gdansk, where he studied economics and was chairman of the socialist student group. A leader in the student activist movement, he served as chair of the University Council of the Socialist Union of Polish Students (1976–77). In 1977 he joined the governing communist Polish United Workers' Party (PUWP) and moved to Warsaw to edit two of the party's youth newspapers—the weekly Itd (1981–84; “Etc.”) and the daily Sztandar Mlodych (1984–85; “Standard of Youth”).Kwasniewski steadily rose th...
</Question>
<Choice>Kwasniewski, Aleksander</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chilean economist and politician who served as president of Chile (2000–06).Lagos earned a law degree from the University of Chile in 1960 and then attended Duke University in Durham, North Carolina, U.S., where he received a Ph.D. in economics in 1966. Lagos returned to Chile and served as director of the University of Chile's School of Political and Administrative Sciences and was subsequently appointed Chile's ambassador to the Soviet Union by Salvador Allende, Chile's first socialist president. In 1973, however, shortly after the appointment, Allende was overthrown in a military coup led b...
</Question>
<Choice>Lagos, Ricardo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Australian statesman and Labor premier of New South Wales (1925–27, 1930–32) whose defiance of Australia's Labor prime minister James Henry Scullin's economic policies contributed to Scullin's defeat in 1931 and to the decline of the Labor Party from national power.After entering the New South Wales Parliament in 1913, Lang rose to party secretary and state treasurer (1920–22), becoming premier and treasurer in 1925. During his first ministry he developed Australia's first child endowment plan and sponsored a widows' pension bill. He led the Labor parliamentary opposition (1927–30) and was ele...
</Question>
<Choice>Lang, Jack</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
New Zealand lawyer and politician, who was prime minister of New Zealand (1984–89).Strongly influenced by his father, a physician noted for his socialist views, Lange grew up in a working-class suburb of Auckland. After receiving a law degree from the University of Auckland, he chose to provide low-cost legal aid to the poor rather than pursue a more lucrative practice. At age 25 he moved to London for a year, during which time he was greatly influenced by the preaching of a Methodist minister in a mission for the poor. After returning to Auckland, Lange continued to practice law and in 1977 w...
</Question>
<Choice>Lange, David</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician and lawyer who was prime minister of Singapore from 1959 to 1990. During his long rule, Singapore became the most prosperous nation in Southeast Asia.Lee was born into a wealthy Chinese family that had been established in Singapore since the 19th century. His first language was English; only upon entering politics did he acquire a command of Chinese as well as Malay and Tamil. After attending school in Singapore, Lee entered the University of Cambridge, England. There he headed the honours list; he also became a socialist. In 1950 he was admitted to the English bar. Instead of pract...
</Question>
<Choice>Lee Kuan Yew</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Irish patriot, politician, and prime minister from 1959 to 1966.As early as the age of 16, Lemass became a freedom fighter in the streets of Dublin, engaging in the Easter Rising (April 1916) and other hostilities and landing in jail again and again; his brother Noel died as a revolutionary. After establishment of the Irish Free State, he joined Eamon De Valera and the other holdouts, becoming a member of the headquarters staff of the Irish Republican Army in 1922 and sharing in the founding of the new party, Fianna Fáil, in 1926. After De Valera rose to the premiership in 1932, Lemass held po...
</Question>
<Choice>Lemass, Sean F</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the Belgians whose actions as commander in chief of the Belgian Army during the German conquest of Belgium (1940) in World War II aroused opposition to his rule, eventually leading to his abdication in 1951.The son of Albert I and his consort Elisabeth of Bavaria, Leopold served as a private soldier during the final campaign of World War I. On Nov. 10, 1926, he married Princess Astrid of Sweden (died August 1935); their children were Joséphine-Charlotte, Baudouin, and Albert. Leopold became king of the Belgians following his father's death on Feb. 17, 1934. Favouring an independent for...
</Question>
<Choice>Leopold III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Canadian public official who was premier of Quebec during the period of reform in the early 1960s.Lesage received a law degree in 1934 from Laval University, Quebec, and in 1939–44 served as a crown attorney. In 1945 he was elected to the federal House of Commons—to serve as parliamentary assistant to leading members of the cabinet and also as a delegate to the United Nations. In 1953 he was appointed minister of resources and development in the federal government. In 1958 he was elected leader of the provincial Quebec Liberal Party, after which he resigned his national portfolio and Commons s...
</Question>
<Choice>Lesage, Jean</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
premier of the French-speaking Canadian province of Quebec (1976–85) and a leading advocate of sovereignty for that province.Lévesque went to school in Gaspésie and afterward to Laval University, Quebec. Already a part-time journalist while still a student, he broke off his law studies to serve in Europe (1944–45) as a reporter and correspondent attached to the U.S. forces. Back in Quebec after the war, he joined the international service of the Canadian Broadcasting Corporation in 1946, became a war correspondent in Korea in 1952, and from 1956 to 1959 was commentator on a popular TV news pro...
</Question>
<Choice>Lévesque, René</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
chairman of the People's Republic of China (1959–68) and chief theoretician for the Chinese Communist Party (CCP), who was considered the heir apparent to Mao Zedong until he was purged in the late 1960s. Liu was active in the Chinese labour movement from its inception, and he was influential in formulating party and, later, governmental strategy. He played an important role in Chinese foreign affairs after the communists had gained control of the country.
</Question>
<Choice>Liu Shaoqi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
soldier and politician whose overthrow of Prince Norodom Sihanouk (1970) involved Cambodia in the Indochina war and ended in the takeover (1975) of the country by the communist Khmer Rouge.Lon Nol entered the French colonial service in 1937 and became a magistrate, then a provincial governor and head of the national police (1951). He joined the army in 1952 and fought against intruding Vietnamese communist guerrillas in Cambodia as an area commander. After again serving as a provincial governor, he became Cambodian army chief of staff (1955) and commander in chief (1960) under the country's le...
</Question>
<Choice>Lon Nol</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mexican lawyer, economist, and writer, who was president of Mexico from 1976 to 1982.López Portillo attended the National Autonomous University of Mexico and the University of Chile. He then practiced law and later was professor of law, political science, and public administration at the National University of Mexico before beginning his political career. He held various administrative positions under Presidents Gustavo Díaz Ordaz and Luis Echeverría before becoming minister of finance in 1971. In this position he modernized tax-collection procedures, pursued tax evaders, and reduced public sp...
</Question>
<Choice>López Portillo, José</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Belarusian politician who espoused communist principles and who became president of the country in 1994.Lukashenka graduated from the Mogilyov Teaching Institute and the Belarusian Agricultural Academy. In the mid-1970s he was an instructor in political affairs, and he spent five years in the army. He subsequently held minor posts in the Komsomol (communist youth organization) and in local party organizations. From 1982 through 1990 he held management and party posts at collective and state farms and at a construction materials combine. He was elected to the parliament of the Belorussian S.S.R...
</Question>
<Choice>Lukashenka, Alyaksandr Hrygorevich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Brazilian politician who served as president of Brazil from 2003.Born in Pernambuco state to sharecropping parents, Luiz Inácio da Silva (“Lula” was a nickname that he later added to his legal name) worked as a shoe-shine boy, street vendor, and factory worker to help supplement the family income. During the recession that followed the military coup of 1964 in Brazil, he found employment with the Villares Metalworks in São Bernardo do Campo, an industrial suburb of São Paulo. At Villares he joined the Metalworkers' Union, and in 1972 he left the factory to work for the union full-time, heading...
</Question>
<Choice>Lula da Silva, Luiz Inácio</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
African nationalist leader, the first prime minister of the Democratic Republic of the Congo (June–September 1960). Forced out of office during a political crisis, he was assassinated a short time later.Lumumba was born in the village of Onalua in Kasai province, Belgian Congo. He was a member of the small Batetela ethnic group, a fact that became significant in his later political life. His two principal rivals, Moise Tshombe, who led the breakaway of the Katanga province, and Joseph Kasavubu, who later became the Congo's president, both came from large, powerful ethnic groups from which they...
</Question>
<Choice>Lumumba, Patrice</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Zulu chief, teacher and religious leader, and president of the African National Congress (1952–60) in South Africa. He was the first African to be awarded a Nobel Prize for Peace (1960), in recognition of his nonviolent struggle against racial discrimination.Albert John Mvumbi (Zulu: “Continuous Rain”) Luthuli was born in Rhodesia, where his father, John Bunyan Luthuli, a missionary interpreter, had gone from Zululand. After his father's death, the 10-year-old Albert returned to South Africa and learned Zulu traditions and duties in the household of his uncle, the chief of Groutville, a commun...
</Question>
<Choice>Luthuli, Albert John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Irish politician who was prime minister of Ireland from 1966 to 1973 and from 1977 to 1979.Lynch studied law and entered the civil service (Department of Justice) in 1936. He eventually decided on an active legal career, was called to the bar (1945), resigned from the civil service, and practiced on the Cork circuit. He entered politics as a member of the opposition in 1948 and worked closely with Eamon De Valera. After his party, Fianna Fáil, came to power in 1951, he was a parliamentary secretary in 1951–54, minister for the Gaeltacht (Gaelic-speaking districts) in 1957, minister for educati...
</Question>
<Choice>Lynch, Jack</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
reformist president of the Philippines from 1961 to 1965.After receiving his law degree, Macapagal was admitted to the bar in 1936. During World War II he practiced law in Manila and aided the anti-Japanese resistance. After the war he worked in a law firm and in 1948 served as second secretary to the Philippine Embassy in Washington, D.C. The following year he was elected to a seat in the Philippine House of Representatives, serving until 1956. During this time he was Philippine representative to the United Nations General Assembly three times. From 1957 to 1961 Macapagal was a member of the...
</Question>
<Choice>Macapagal, Diosdado</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British politician who was prime minister from January 1957 to October 1963.The son of an American-born mother and the grandson of a founder of the London publishing house of Macmillan &amp; Co., he was educated at Balliol College, Oxford. He distinguished himself in combat during World War I and entered politics after the war. He sat in the House of Commons from 1924 to 1929 and from 1931 to 1964. When Winston Churchill formed his World War II coalition government (May 1940), Macmillan, who had bitterly condemned British “appeasement” of Nazi Germany in the late 1930s, was appointed parliamen...
</Question>
<Choice>Macmillan, Harold</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
president of the Philippines (1953–57), best known for successfully defeating the communist-led Hukbalahap (Huk) movement.The son of an artisan, Magsaysay was a schoolteacher in the provincial town of Iba on the island of Luzon. Though most Philippine political leaders were of Spanish descent, Magsaysay was of Malay stock, like most of the common people. Working his way through José Rizal College near Manila, he obtained a commercial degree in 1933 and became general manager of a Manila transportation company. After serving as a guerrilla leader on Luzon during World War II, he was appointed m...
</Question>
<Choice>Magsaysay, Ramon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Malaysian politician, who served as prime minister of Malaysia from 1981 to 2003, overseeing his country's transition to an industrialized nation.Mahathir, the son of a schoolmaster, was educated at Sultan Abdul Hamid College and the University of Malaya in Singapore, where he studied medicine. After graduating in 1953, he worked as a government medical officer until 1957 and then entered private practice. He was first elected to parliament in 1964 as a member of the United Malays National Organization (UMNO), the dominant party within the ruling governmental coalition. In 1969, however, Mahat...
</Question>
<Choice>Mahathir bin Mohamad</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British politician and public official who was prime minister of the United Kingdom from 1990 to 1997.The son of a former circus performer and vaudeville manager, Major left school at age 16 to help support his family. He worked as a bank accountant for some years and eventually tried to enter politics, twice standing unsuccessfully for Parliament in 1974. He gained a seat in the House of Commons during the Conservative Party landslide of 1979, and his subsequent rise through that party's ranks was rapid, owing in part to the interested patronage of high party officials from Prime Minister Mar...
</Question>
<Choice>Major, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
archbishop and primate of the Orthodox Church of Cyprus. He was a leader in the struggle for enosis (union) with Greece during the postwar British occupation, and, from 1959 until his death in 1977, he was the president of independent Cyprus.Mouskos, the son of a poor shepherd, studied in Cyprus and at the University of Athens and later at the School of Theology of Boston University. He was ordained in 1946, became bishop of Kition (Larnaca) in 1948, and on October 18, 1950, was made archbishop.During that time Makarios became identified with the movement for enosis, the archbishop of Cyprus h...
</Question>
<Choice>Makarios III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prominent Soviet statesman and Communist Party official, a close collaborator of Joseph Stalin, and the prime minister (March 1953–February 1955) after Stalin's death.Having entered the Red Army (1919) during the civil war that followed the 1917 October Revolution, Malenkov joined the Communist Party in 1920 and rose swiftly through the ranks. He became closely associated with Stalin and was deeply involved in the great party purge of the late 1930s. Named a candidate member of the Politburo in 1941, he served during World War II on the State Defense Committee, the small group that directed th...
</Question>
<Choice>Malenkov, Georgy Maksimilianovich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
black nationalist and first black president of South Africa (1994–99). His negotiations in the early 1990s with South African Pres. F.W. de Klerk helped end the country's apartheid system of racial segregation and ushered in a peaceful transition to majority rule. Mandela and de Klerk were jointly awarded the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1993 for their efforts.
</Question>
<Choice>Mandela, Nelson</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jamaican politician who served three terms as prime minister of Jamaica (1972–80 and 1989–92) and was a powerful champion of Third World issues.He was the son of noted sculptor Edna Swithenbank Manley and national hero Norman Manley, the cofounder of the People's National Party (PNP) and Jamaica's chief minister (1955–59) and premier (1959–62). Following service in the Royal Canadian Air Force during World War II, he attended the London School of Economics, where he studied with socialist Harold Laski. After working as a freelance journalist in London, Manley returned to Jamaica in 1951 and we...
</Question>
<Choice>Manley, Michael</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
principal Chinese Marxist theorist, soldier, and statesman who led his nation's communist revolution. Leader of the Chinese Communist Party from 1935, he was chairman (chief of state) of the People's Republic of China from 1949 to 1959 and chairman of the party until his death.When China emerged from a half century of revolution as the world's most populous nation and launched itself on a path of economic development and social change, Mao Zedong occupied a critical place in the story of the country's resurgence. To be sure, he did not play a dominant role throughout the whole struggle. In the...
</Question>
<Choice>Mao Zedong</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Philippine lawyer and politician who, as head of state from 1966 to 1986, established an authoritarian regime in the Philippines that came under criticism for corruption and for its suppression of democratic processes.Marcos attended school in Manila and studied law in the late 1930s at the University of the Philippines, near that city. Tried for the assassination in 1933 of a political opponent of his politician father, Marcos was found guilty in November 1939. But he argued his case on appeal to the Philippine Supreme Court and won acquittal a year later. He became a trial lawyer in Manila....
</Question>
<Choice>Marcos, Ferdinand E.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Canadian politician and prime minister of Canada (2003–06).Martin's father, Paul Joseph Martin, served as a minister in four Liberal governments and was a leading architect of Canada's post-World War II social policy. The younger Martin attended the University of Toronto, graduating from its law school in 1964, and was called to the bar in 1966. He did not practice law, however, and instead joined Canada Steamship Lines, a Montreal firm. He built the domestic-freight carrier into a strong multinational company and in 1981 purchased it.Though he had been on the fringe of the Liberal Party, Mart...
</Question>
<Choice>Martin, Paul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polish journalist and Solidarity official who in 1989 became the first non-communist premier of an eastern European country since the late 1940s.After graduating in law from the University of Warsaw, Mazowiecki entered journalism and became prominent among Poland's liberal young Roman Catholic intellectuals in the mid-1950s. In 1958 Mazowiecki cofounded the independent Catholic monthly journal Wiez (“Link”), which he edited until 1981. From 1961 to 1971 he was a member of the Sejm, Poland's legislative assembly. In the 1970s he forged links with the Workers' Defense Committee, which protected...
</Question>
<Choice>Mazowiecki, Tadeusz</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
farmer, politician, and prime minister of Australia from Dec. 19, 1967, to Jan. 10, 1968.A member of the House of Representatives (1934–71), McEwen served in several ministerial posts during World War II, including deputy prime minister (1958–71), and was acting prime minister for three weeks upon the death of Prime Minister Harold Holt in 1967. McEwen was knighted in 1971.
</Question>
<Choice>McEwen, Sir John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Australian politician and lawyer who was prime minister of Australia from March 1971 to December 1972.He was educated at the University of Sydney, where he earned a degree in law. After practicing as a solicitor in Sydney he enlisted in the Australian Army in 1939 and rose to the rank of major. He served in the House of Representatives for Lowe (New South Wales) from 1949 to 1982. He held various ministerial posts in Liberal governments throughout the 1950s and '60s and headed the Treasury (1966–69) and the Ministry of Foreign Affairs (1969–71). After having served as deputy leader of the Libe...
</Question>
<Choice>McMahon, Sir William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
a founder and fourth prime minister (1969–74) of the State of Israel.In 1906 Goldie Mabovitch's family emigrated to Milwaukee, Wis., where she attended the Milwaukee Normal School (now University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee) and later became a leader in the Milwaukee Labor Zionist Party. In 1921 she and her husband, Morris Myerson, emigrated to Palestine and joined the Mer?avya kibbutz. She became the kibbutz's representative to the Histadrut (General Federation of Labour), the secretary of that organization's Women's Labour Council (1928–32), and a member of its executive committee (1934 until Wor...
</Question>
<Choice>Meir, Golda</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French socialist statesman and premier (June 1954–February 1955) whose negotiations ended French involvement in the Indochina War. He was distinguished for his efforts to invigorate the Fourth Republic and the Radical Party.Born into a Jewish family, Mendès-France became a lawyer and was a Radical–Socialist deputy for the Eure département from 1932 to 1940. He was undersecretary of state for finance under Léon Blum from March to June 1938. After serving in the air force in World War II and being imprisoned by the Vichy government, he escaped in June 1941, reached London in February 1942, and j...
</Question>
<Choice>Mendès-France, Pierre</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician and lawyer, who served as president of Argentina (1989–99)—the first Peronist to be elected president of Argentina since Juan Perón in 1973.Menem, the son of Syrian immigrants, was born into the Muslim faith but converted to Roman Catholicism, the official religion of Argentina, to achieve his political aspirations. He joined the Peronist (Justicialist Party) movement in 1956 and was briefly imprisoned that year after participating in a revolt aimed at restoring Juan Perón (who had been ousted from power) to the presidency. After obtaining a law degree from the National University o...
</Question>
<Choice>Menem, Carlos</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ethiopian army officer and head of state (1974–91), who helped overthrow the centuries-old monarchy and attempted to mold Ethiopia into a communist state.Mengistu received officer training at Holeta and additional training in the United States. Rising to the rank of major, he became one of a group of junior officers and enlisted men who, discontented with their lack of patronage and promotion within the military, plotted rebellion against the government of Emperor Haile Selassie I. In June 1974 Mengistu was made chairman of the Armed Forces Coordinating Committee (known as the Dergue), a commi...
</Question>
<Choice>Mengistu Haile Mariam</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman who, as prime minister of Australia (1939–41, 1949–66), strengthened military ties with the United States and fostered industrial growth and immigration from Europe.Menzies gave up a highly successful law practice in Victoria to serve in the state legislature (1929–34). He entered the federal Parliament in 1934, serving as attorney general (1934–39) under Joseph Lyons; and in 1939, as leader of the United Australia Party, he became prime minister. Pressure from various quarters forced his resignation in 1941, after he had initiated Australia's mobilization for World War II. Organizin...
</Question>
<Choice>Menzies, Sir Robert Gordon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Estonian scholar and political leader, who was president of Estonia from 1992 to 2001.His father, Georg Meri, was a man of letters who served newly independent Estonia as a diplomat between World Wars I and II, and consequently Lennart was educated in Berlin, London, and Paris. After the Soviet Union annexed Estonia in 1940, Georg Meri was sent to a labour camp in Moscow and the rest of the family to Siberia. In 1946 the family was reunited in Estonia, which had become a Soviet republic. Lennart Meri received a degree in history and languages from Tartu University in 1953, and he spent much of...
</Question>
<Choice>Meri, Lennart</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician, prime minister of Japan from December 1974 to December 1976.The son of a Shikoku landowner, Miki attended Meiji University in Tokyo, as well as American universities, earned a law degree in 1937, and was elected to the Diet a few months later. He publicly opposed the war against the United States, and thus his political career, unlike those of many others, was not interrupted or destroyed by the postwar American occupation. At various times of his life he occupied 10 Cabinet posts, including the Ministry of International Trade and Industry and the Foreign Ministry (1966–68).In the...
</Question>
<Choice>Miki Takeo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician and administrator, who, as Serbia's party leader and president (1989–97), pursued Serbian nationalist policies that contributed to the breakup of the socialist Yugoslav federation. He subsequently embroiled Serbia in a series of conflicts with the successor Balkan states. From 1997 to 2000 he served as president of the Federal Republic of Yugoslavia.Miloševic was born in Serbia of Montenegrin parents and joined the Communist Party of Yugoslavia (from 1963 the League of Communists of Yugoslavia [LCY]) when he was 18 years old. He graduated from the University of Belgrade with a law d...
</Question>
<Choice>Miloševic, Slobodan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician who served two terms (1981–95) as president of France, leading his country to closer political and economic integration with western Europe. The first socialist to hold the office, Mitterrand abandoned leftist economic policies early in his presidency and generally ruled as a pragmatic centrist.The son of a stationmaster, Mitterrand studied law and political science in Paris. On the outbreak of World War II, he enlisted in the infantry and in June 1940 was wounded and captured by the Germans. After escaping from a prison camp in late 1941, he worked with the collaborationist Vichy g...
</Question>
<Choice>Mitterrand, François</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prime minister of Japan from 1991 to 1993.Born into a family of politicians, Miyazawa graduated in law from Tokyo Imperial University in 1941 and soon secured a civilian position in the finance ministry (1942–52). In 1953 he was elected to the Diet (parliament) and in 1962 secured his first cabinet position, as director general of the Economic Planning Agency. Subsequently Miyazawa served as minister of international trade and industry (1970–71), of foreign affairs (1974–76), and of finance (1986–88). He also acted as cabinet secretary in the early 1980s and, briefly, as deputy prime minister...
</Question>
<Choice>Miyazawa Kiichi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
president of Zaire (now the Democratic Republic of the Congo), who seized power in a 1965 coup and ruled for some 32 years before being ousted in a rebellion in 1997.Mobutu was educated in missionary schools and began his career in 1949 in the Belgian Congolese army, the Force Publique, rising from a clerk to a sergeant major, the highest rank then open to Africans. While still in the army, Mobutu contributed articles to newspapers in Léopoldville (now Kinshasa). After his discharge in 1956 he became a reporter for the daily L'Avenir (“The Future”) and later editor of the weekly Actualités Afr...
</Question>
<Choice>Mobutu Sese Seko</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Kenyan politician, who held the office of president (1978–2002).Moi was educated at mission and government schools. He became a teacher at age 21 and in the early 1960s, as Kenya began to move toward independence (1963), was appointed minister of education in the transitional government. Although he had originally been cofounder and chairman of the Kenya African Democratic Union, a party composed of minority peoples, he joined the Kikuyu-dominated Kenya African National Union (KANU) in 1964. That same year Moi was appointed minister of home affairs.Named vice president in 1967, Moi became pres...
</Question>
<Choice>Moi, Daniel arap</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Bolivian labour leader who served as president of Bolivia (2006– ). A member of the Aymara indigenous group, Morales was Bolivia's first Indian president.Born in a mining village in Bolivia's western Oruro department, Morales herded llamas when he was a boy. After attending high school and serving in the Bolivian military, he emigrated with his family to the Chapare region in eastern Bolivia, where the family farmed. Among the crops they grew was coca, which is used in the production of cocaine but is also a traditional crop in the region.In the early 1980s Morales became active in the regiona...
</Question>
<Choice>Morales, Evo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese politician who was prime minister in 2000–01 during a period of economic downturn.Both Mori's father and grandfather had been mayor of Neagari. He received a degree in commerce from Waseda University, Tokyo, in 1959. He became secretary to a member of the Diet (parliament) in 1962, and in 1969 he was elected as an independent to the House of Representatives, after which he joined the Liberal-Democratic Party (LDP). He held a number of powerful positions in the government and the party. In 1983–84 he served as minister of education and in 1992–93 minister of international trade and ind...
</Question>
<Choice>Mori Yoshiro</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
law professor, Italian statesman, and leader of the Christian Democratic Party, who served five times as premier of Italy (1963–64, 1964–66, 1966–68, 1974–76, and 1976). In 1978 he was kidnapped and subsequently murdered by left-wing terrorists.A professor of law at the University of Bari, Moro published several books on legal subjects and served as president of the Federazione Universitaria Cattolica Italiana (Federation of Italian University Catholics; 1939–42) and the Movimento Laureati Cattolici (Movement of Catholic Graduates; 1945–46). After World War II he was elected a deputy to the Co...
</Question>
<Choice>Moro, Aldo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Iranian political leader who nationalized the huge British oil holdings in Iran and, as premier in 1951–53, almost succeeded in deposing the shah.The son of an Iranian public official, Mosaddeq grew up as a member of Iran's ruling elite. He received a Doctor of Law degree from the University of Lausanne in Switzerland and then returned to Iran in 1914 and was appointed governor-general of the important Fars province. He remained in the government following the rise to power of Reza Khan in 1921 and served as minister of finance and then briefly as minister of foreign affairs. Mosaddeq was elec...
</Question>
<Choice>Mosaddeq, Mohammad</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Panamanian politician, who was Panama's first woman president (1999–2004).Moscoso was born to a poor family in a rural town. After graduating from high school, she worked as a secretary and in the early 1960s met Arnulfo Arias, a former president of Panama. She began working on his political campaigns, and on October 1, 1968, he was reelected. When he was deposed nine days later by General Omar Torrijos, Moscoso joined Arias in exile in Miami, Florida. There she studied interior design, and in 1969 the two were married. After Arias's death in 1988, she returned to Panama and in the early 1990s...
</Question>
<Choice>Moscoso, Mireya</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
president of Egypt from October 1981.Born in the Nile River delta, Mubarak graduated from the Egyptian military academy at Cairo (1949) and the air academy at Bilbays (1950), receiving advanced flight and bomber training in the Soviet Union. He held command positions in the Egyptian air force and from 1966 to 1969 was director of the air academy. In 1972 President Anwar el-Sadat appointed Mubarak chief commander of the air force, and in this capacity he was credited with the successful performance of the Egyptian air force in the opening days of the war with Israel in October 1973. He was prom...
</Question>
<Choice>Mubarak, Hosni</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the first prime minister (1980–87) of the reconstituted state of Zimbabwe, formerly Rhodesia. A black nationalist of Marxist persuasion, he eventually established one-party rule in his country, becoming executive president of Zimbabwe in 1987.
</Question>
<Choice>Mugabe, Robert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Canadian politician, leader of the Progressive Conservative Party of Canada (1983–93), and prime minister of Canada from 1984 to 1993.Born the son of an electrician in a paper-and-pulp town northeast of Quebec city, Mulroney grew up bilingual in English and French and received a B.A. (1959) from Saint Francis Xavier University, Antigonish, N.S., and a law degree (1962) from Laval University, Quebec city. In 1965 he began practicing law in Montreal, becoming a labour specialist. In 1974 he gained local celebrity as a member of the Cliche Commission investigating crime in Quebec's construction i...
</Question>
<Choice>Mulroney, Brian</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician who in 1994–96 was the first Socialist prime minister of Japan since 1948.One of 11 children born to a fisherman, Murayama graduated from Meiji University in Tokyo in 1946 and then returned to Oita, where he became an activist in the local fishermen's union. Most of his subsequent political career was spent in relative obscurity. He won election to the Oita city assembly in 1955 and moved up to a seat in the Oita prefectural assembly in 1963. He was elected to the lower house of the Diet (parliament) in 1972 as a member of the Japan Socialist Party (JSP) and was successively reelect...
</Question>
<Choice>Murayama Tomiichi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician who became president of Uganda in 1986.Museveni was born to cattle farmers and attended missionary schools. While studying political science and economics at the University of Dar es Salaam, Tanzania (B.A., 1970), he became chairman of a leftist student group allied with African liberation movements. When Idi Amin came to power in Uganda in 1971, Museveni returned to Tanzania in exile. There he founded the Front for National Salvation, which helped overthrow Amin in 1979. Museveni held posts in transitional governments and in 1980 ran for president of Uganda. When the elections, wid...
</Question>
<Choice>Museveni, Yoweri Kaguta</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Egyptian army officer and statesman who played a prominent role in the revolutionary overthrow of King Farouk I in 1952.A professional soldier, Naguib distinguished himself during the Egyptian defeat at the hands of Israel (1948) and won the respect of the Free Officers, a nationalist military group led by Gamal Abdel Nasser. In 1952 the Free Officers helped Naguib win election as president of the officers club in opposition to a man backed by King Farouk. The Free Officers engineered a coup that overthrew Farouk that July, and they saw Naguib as the man to represent their new regime to the pu...
</Question>
<Choice>Naguib, Muhammad</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hungarian statesman, independent Communist, and premier of the 1956 revolutionary government whose attempt to establish Hungary's independence from the Soviet Union cost him his life.Born to a peasant family, Nagy was apprenticed as a locksmith before being drafted in World War I. Captured by the Russians, he joined the Communists and fought in the Red Army. In 1929 he went to live in Moscow, where, as a member of the Institute for Agrarian Sciences, he remained until late 1944. He returned again to Hungary under Soviet occupation and helped establish the postwar government, holding several mi...
</Question>
<Choice>Nagy, Imre</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Afghan military official who was president of Afghanistan from 1986 to 1992.The son of a prominent Pashtun family, Najibullah began studying medicine at Kabul University in 1964 and received his degree in 1975, but he never practiced medicine. He joined the Banner (“Parcham”) faction of the People's Democratic Party of Afghanistan (PDPA) in 1965, and he was twice imprisoned for political activities. In 1978 the PDPA staged a successful coup, but the People's (“Khalq”) faction soon gained supremacy over the Banner faction. Najibullah was named ambassador to Iran in 1978 but was fired within mon...
</Question>
<Choice>Najibullah, Mohammad</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian politician and diplomat, who was the president of India from 1997 to 2002. He was the first member of the country's lowest social caste, the group traditionally considered to be untouchable, to occupy the office.Despite his family's poverty and social status, Narayanan's intellect won him a government-sponsored scholarship. After graduating from the University of Travancore (now the University of Kerala), he worked as a journalist for the Hindu (1944–45) and the Times of India (1945). He soon won another scholarship and left India to attend the London School of Economics, where he recei...
</Question>
<Choice>Narayanan, Kocheril Raman</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
New Zealand statesman who was prime minister in 1957–60 and who earlier, as finance minister during the Great Depression and through World War II, guided the Labour Party's economic recovery program and then directed the government's wartime controls.While continuing his self-education, Nash worked as a costing clerk around Birmingham and became a wholesale confectionery merchant in 1907. He emigrated to New Zealand in 1909, soon joining the Labour Party, and from 1919 to 1960 he was a member of the party's executive. He entered Parliament in 1929 and became the first Labour minister of financ...
</Question>
<Choice>Nash, Sir Walter</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
army officer, prime minister (1954–56), and then president (1956–70) of Egypt, who became a controversial leader of the Arab world, creating the short-lived United Arab Republic (1958–61), twice fighting wars with Israel (1956, 1967), and engaging in such inter-Arab policies as mediating the Jordanian civil war (1970).
</Question>
<Choice>Nasser, Gamal Abdel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Burmese general who was the leader of Burma (Myanmar) from 1962 to 1988.Ne Win studied at University College, Rangoon (Yangon), from 1929 to 1931, and in the mid-1930s he became involved in the struggle for Burmese independence from the British. During World War II, after the Japanese invasion of Burma, he was one of the Thirty Comrades who, in 1941, went to Hainan to receive military training from the Japanese. Ne Win was an officer in the Japanese-sponsored Burma National Army from 1943 to 1945, but, becoming disillusioned with the Japanese, he helped organize the underground resistance. Aft...
</Question>
<Choice>Ne Win, U</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Israeli politician and diplomat, who twice served as his country's prime minister (1996–99 and 2009– ).In 1963 Netanyahu, the son of the historian Benzion Netanyahu, moved with his family to Philadelphia in the United States. After enlisting in the Israeli military in 1967, he became a soldier in the elite special operations unit Sayeret Matcal and was on the team that rescued a hijacked jet plane at the Tel Aviv airport in 1972. He later studied at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (M.B.A., 1976), taking time out to fight in the Yom Kippur War in Israel in 1973. After his brother Jona...
</Question>
<Choice>Netanyahu, Benjamin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
poet, physician, and first president of the People's Republic of Angola.Neto first became known in 1948, when he published a volume of poems in Luanda and joined a national cultural movement that was aimed at “rediscovering” indigenous Angolan culture (similar to the Negritude movement of the French-speaking African countries). His first of many arrests for political activities came shortly thereafter in Lisbon, where he had gone to study medicine.Neto returned home as a doctor in 1959 but was arrested in the presence of his patients in June 1960 because of his militant opposition to the colon...
</Question>
<Choice>Neto, Agostinho</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Vietnamese political leader who served as president, with dictatorial powers, of South Vietnam from 1955 until his assassination.Diem was born into one of Vietnam's noble families. His ancestors in the 17th century had been among the first Vietnamese converts to Roman Catholicism. He was on friendly terms with the Vietnamese imperial family in his youth, and in 1933 he served as the emperor Bao Dai's minister of the interior, but he resigned that same year in frustration at French unwillingness to countenance his legislative reforms. Relinquishing his titles and decorations, he spent the next...
</Question>
<Choice>Ngo Dinh Diem</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
president of the Republic of Vietnam (South Vietnam) from 1967 until the republic fell to the forces of North Vietnam in 1975.The son of a small landowner, Thieu joined the communist-oriented Viet Minh in 1945 but later fought for the French colonial regime against the Viet Minh. In 1954 he was put in charge of the Vietnamese National Military Academy and, after 1956, continued to serve under the regime of Ngo Dinh Diem in South Vietnam. Thieu played an important part in a successful coup against Diem in 1963. In 1965 he became chief of state in a military government headed by Premier Nguyen C...
</Question>
<Choice>Nguyen Van Thieu</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
37th president of the United States (1969–74), who, faced with almost certain impeachment for his role in the Watergate Scandal, became the first American president to resign from office. He was also vice president (1953–61) under Pres. Dwight D. Eisenhower. (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America.)
</Question>
<Choice>Nixon, Richard M.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ghanaian nationalist leader who led the Gold Coast's drive for independence from Britain and presided over its emergence as the new nation of Ghana. He headed the country from independence in 1957 until he was overthrown by a coup in 1966.
</Question>
<Choice>Nkrumah, Kwame</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
twice king of Cambodia (1941–55 and 1993–2004), who also served as prime minister, head of state, and president. He attempted to steer a neutral course for Cambodia in its civil and foreign wars of the late 20th century.Sihanouk was, on his mother's side, the grandson of King Monivong (reigned 1927–41), whom he succeeded to the throne at age 18. At the time Cambodia was a French protectorate, and Sihanouk wielded little power. However, near the end of World War II, the occupying Japanese encouraged the young king to declare Cambodia's independence from France. When French military forces moved...
</Question>
<Choice>Norodom Sihanouk</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Czech communist leader of a Stalinist faction who was deposed in the reform movement of 1968.Trained as a locksmith, Novotný became a member of the Communist Party in 1921. He was arrested during the German occupation of Czechoslovakia in 1938 and placed in Mauthasen concentration camp (1941–45). In 1946 he was elected to the party's Central Committee, and in February 1948 he took a leading role in the Stalinist communist takeover of the Czech government. He was admitted to the Politburo in 1951 and became first secretary of the Communist Party in 1953. After the death of Antonín Zápotocký (No...
</Question>
<Choice>Novotný, Antonín</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Burmese independence leader and prime minister of Myanmar (formerly Burma) from 1948 to 1958 and from 1960 to 1962.U Nu was educated at the University of Rangoon (Yangon), from which he received his B.A. degree in 1929. For some years headmaster of the National High School in Pantanaw, he returned to the university in 1934 to study law, becoming president of the Student Union of Rangoon and joining student political movements. His expulsion and that of the young leader Aung San from the university in 1936 resulted in a student strike. One of the first confrontations between young Burmese natio...
</Question>
<Choice>Nu, U</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first president of independent Namibia (1990–2005).Nujoma was born to a peasant family in the remote Ongandjera region of Owambo (Ovamboland) and spent his early years tending the family's few cattle and goats. His primary education began at night school, and he left school at age 16 to become a railway dining-car steward. After a fellow worker was sent home without compensation following a serious injury, Nujoma tried to form a trade union for railway men but was discharged. He subsequently worked as a clerk and a store assistant.In the late 1950s he helped found the Ovamboland People's Organ...
</Question>
<Choice>Nujoma, Sam</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first prime minister of independent Tanganyika (1961), who became the first president of the new state of Tanzania (1964). Nyerere was also the major force behind the Organization of African Unity (OAU; now the African Union).Nyerere was a son of the chief of the small Zanaki ethnic group. He was educated at Tabora Secondary School and Makerere College in Kampala, Uganda. A convert to Roman Catholicism, he taught in several Roman Catholic schools before going to Edinburgh University. He was the first Tanganyikan to study at a British university. He graduated with an M.A. in history and economi...
</Question>
<Choice>Nyerere, Julius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
44th president of the United States (2009– ) and the first African American to hold the office. Before winning the presidency, Obama represented Illinois in the U.S. Senate (2005–08). He was the third African American to be elected to that body since the end of Reconstruction (1877). In 2009 he was awarded the Nobel Peace Prize “for his extraordinary efforts to strengthen international diplomacy and cooperation between peoples.” (On the eve of Obama's inauguration, journalist David Mendell, author of Britannica's biography of Obama and of the book Obama: From Promise to Power, answered a few q...
</Question>
<Choice>Obama, Barack</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nigerian general, politician, and diplomat, who was the first military leader in Africa to hand over power to civilian rule. He served as ruler of Nigeria (1976–79) and as president (1999–2007).Obasanjo attended Baptist Boys' High School and later worked as a teacher. Unable to afford college, he joined the army in 1958 and received officer training in England. Obasanjo rose quickly through the army ranks, and during the Biafra conflict (1967–70) he headed a commando division that was stationed at the Biafran front in southeastern Nigeria. The Biafran forces surrendered to him in January 1970....
</Question>
<Choice>Obasanjo, Olusegun</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician who was prime minister (1962–70) and twice president (1966–71, 1980–85) of Uganda. He led his country to independence in 1962, but his two terms in office (both of which were ended by military coups) were consumed by struggles between Uganda's northern and southern ethnic groups.Obote was born the third of nine children in a farming family in north-central Uganda. He first attended Busoga College in Mwiri and then Makerere College in Kampala from 1948 to 1949, but he was expelled from the latter for his political activities before he could graduate. The British colonial government p...
</Question>
<Choice>Obote, Milton</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese politician who was prime minister from July 1998 to April 2000 and is credited with reversing Japan's economic downturn.Obuchi received a degree in English literature from Waseda University, Tokyo, in 1962. The following year, he won the seat his father had held in the House of Representatives, becoming the youngest person ever elected to the Diet (parliament). Although he was often said to be bland and undistinguished, his political career was successful. In 1973 he was appointed deputy director general in the prime minister's office and in 1987 chief cabinet secretary. As he rose th...
</Question>
<Choice>Obuchi Keizo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Israeli politician who served as mayor of Jerusalem (1993–2003) and as prime minister of Israel (2006–09).Olmert's parents were members of the Irgun Zvai Leumi, a militant Jewish group that fought for the establishment of Israel. In the mid-1950s and early '60s, Olmert's father, Mordechai, served in Israel's Knesset (parliament) as a member of the Herut Party, a political outgrowth of the Irgun and a precursor of the Likud.Olmert attended the Hebrew University of Jerusalem, where he received both bachelor's (1968) and law (1973) degrees. In 1973 he became Israel's youngest Knesset member, elec...
</Question>
<Choice>Olmert, Ehud</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
nationalist politician and first president of Togo who was the first presidential victim of a wave of military coups that occurred in Africa in the 1960s.A leader of the Committee of Togolese Unity after World War II, Olympio was elected president of the first territorial assembly in 1946 and by 1947 was in open (though nonviolent) conflict with Togoland's French colonial administration. One of his main early concerns was to unite the Ewe people, who were divided by the boundaries of British and French Togoland. His hopes were dashed in 1956, however, when British Togoland voted by plebiscite...
</Question>
<Choice>Olympio, Sylvanus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nicaraguan guerrilla leader, member of the Sandinista junta that took power in 1979, and the elected president of Nicaragua from November 1984 to April 1990 and again from January 2007.Son of a veteran of the peasant army of César Augusto Sandino, Ortega moved with his family to Managua in the mid-1950s. He briefly attended the Central American University in Managua, then in 1963 he went underground and became a member of the Sandinista National Liberation Front (FSLN). By 1967 he was in charge of the FSLN's urban resistance campaign against the ruling Somoza family.In the fall of 1967 Ortega...
</Question>
<Choice>Ortega, Daniel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Turkish politician, prime minister from 1983 to 1989 and president from 1989 to 1993.Özal studied electrical engineering at Istanbul Technical University, where he met the future prime minister Süleyman Demirel. Özal became an under secretary at the Turkish State Planning Organization (1967–71), and during the 1970s he worked as an economist for the World Bank. In 1979 he became an adviser to Demirel's government. When the military overthrew Demirel in 1980, Özal was asked to stay on as deputy prime minister. He implemented a program of economic reforms, including the lifting of exchange contr...
</Question>
<Choice>Özal, Turgut</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prime minister of Sweden (1969–76, 1982–86), prominent leader of the Swedish Social Democratic Workers' Party (Sveriges Socialdemokratiska Arbetar Partiet), Sweden's oldest continuing party. He became Sweden's best-known international politician.Born into a wealthy Stockholm family, Palme studied at Kenyon College, Ohio, U.S. (B.A., 1948), and obtained a law degree from Stockholm University in 1951. An active member of the Social Democrats from the early 1950s, Palme became Prime Minister Tage Erlander's personal secretary in 1953 and entered the Swedish Parliament in 1958. Palme joined the So...
</Question>
<Choice>Palme, Olof</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician and educator who was prime minister of Greece from 1981 to 1989 and from 1993 to 1996.The son of Georgios Papandreou, he attended the American College in Athens (Modern Greek: Athína) and studied law at the University of Athens. A Trotskyite, he was imprisoned briefly by the dictator Ioannis Metaxas and, when freed, fled to the United States, where he received a Ph.D. (1943) from Harvard University and obtained U.S. citizenship (1944). After serving in the U.S. Navy, he taught at Harvard, the University of Minnesota, and the University of California, Berkeley (1955–63). When his fat...
</Question>
<Choice>Papandreou, Andreas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek liberal politician who served three terms as prime minister of his country and who established a political dynasty that spanned three generations.Papandreou studied at the University of Athens (L.L.D., 1911) and in Germany. He began his political career in 1915, served as governor of the Aegean Islands (1917–20), and was minister of education (1929–33) in the liberal antimonarchist government of Eleuthérios Venizélos. He broke away from the left wing of the Liberal Party and in 1935 founded the Democratic Socialist Party. During the dictatorship of Ioannis Metaxas, he was in exile, and h...
</Question>
<Choice>Papandreou, Georgios</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
South Korean general and politician, president of the Republic of Korea (South Korea) from 1963 to his death. His 18-year rule brought about enormous economic expansion, though at the cost of civil liberties and political freedom.Born into an impoverished rural family, Park graduated (1937) with top honours from Taegu (Daegu) Normal School, after which he taught primary school. After attending a Japanese military academy, Park served as a second lieutenant in the Japanese army during World War II and became an officer in the Korean army when Korea was freed from Japanese rule after the war. He...
</Question>
<Choice>Park Chung Hee</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician, diplomat, and prime minister of Canada (1963–68), who was prominent as a mediator in international disputes. He was awarded the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1957.Pearson served in World War I (1914–18) and lectured in history at the University of Toronto (1924–28), after studying there and at the University of Oxford. He joined the Canadian foreign service in 1928 and became first secretary in the Department of External Affairs. He served on two royal commissions (1931) and as counselor of the Canadian high commissioner's office in London (1935).Recalled to Canada in 1941, Pearson then...
</Question>
<Choice>Pearson, Lester B.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polish-born Israeli statesman, who served as prime minister of Israel (1984–86 and 1995–96) and leader of the Israel Labour Party (1977–92, 1995–97, and 2003–05). In 1993, in his role as Israeli foreign minister, Peres helped negotiate a peace accord with Yasir ?Arafat, chairman of the Palestine Liberation Organization (PLO), for which they, along with Israeli Prime Minister Yitzhak Rabin, were jointly awarded the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1994.Peres immigrated with his family to Palestine in 1934. In 1947 he joined the Haganah movement, a Zionist military organization, under the direction of D...
</Question>
<Choice>Peres, Shimon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
president of Venezuela from 1974 to 1979 and from 1989 to 1993.Pérez began his political life as a member of the liberal political party Democratic Action, led by Rómulo Betancourt. When Betancourt took power as president of the junta that overthrew President Isaías Medina Angarita in 1945, Pérez followed as his secretary. A right-wing coup drove Pérez and other party leaders into exile until 1958, when the dictatorship of Marcos Pérez Jiménez was overthrown. Pérez then served in several important government and party posts. With Betancourt's support, Pérez easily won the 1973 presidential ele...
</Question>
<Choice>Pérez, Carlos Andrés</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
president of Argentina 1974–76, third wife of President Juan Perón.She was born to a lower-middle-class family, acquired the name Isabel (her saint's name) on her Roman Catholic confirmation, and adopted the name when she became a dancer. She met Perón in either 1955 or 1956 and, giving up her career in show business, became his personal secretary, accompanying him in exile to Madrid, where they were married in 1961. She visited Argentina several times in the 1960s and early '70s, building support for Perón. When Perón finally returned to Argentina to run for president in 1973, Isabel was chos...
</Question>
<Choice>Perón, Isabel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
army colonel who became president of Argentina (1946–52, 1952–55, 1973–74) and was founder and leader of the Peronist movement.
</Question>
<Choice>Perón, Juan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Bahamian politician who, as prime minister (1967–92), guided the Bahamas to independence in 1973 and was considered the country's founding father.Pindling studied at the Bahamas Government High School (1943–46) and at King's College, University of London (1948–52), from which he received a law degree. He was called to the British bar in 1953 and soon after returned home to practice law. Later that year he helped found the Progressive Liberal Party (PLP), which represented the interests of the black community in the Bahamas. He became party treasurer and was chosen parliamentary leader soon aft...
</Question>
<Choice>Pindling, Sir Lynden Oscar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
leader of the military junta that overthrew the socialist government of President Salvador Allende of Chile on Sept. 11, 1973, and head of Chile's military government (1974–90).Pinochet, a graduate of the military academy in Santiago (1936), was a career military officer who was appointed army commander in chief by President Allende 18 days before the coup, which he planned and led. Pinochet was named head of the victorious junta's governing council, and he moved to crush Chile's liberal opposition; in its first three years, the regime arrested approximately 130,000, many of whom were tortured...
</Question>
<Choice>Pinochet, Augusto</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Soviet statesman and Communist Party official.As a youth, Podgorny served as secretary in his district's Komsomol committee. He attended the Kiev Technological Institute for the Food Industry, graduating in 1931 and subsequently working in engineering jobs in the sugar industry. Podgorny's first government appointment came in 1939, as deputy people's commissar of the food-processing industry in the Ukraine; he was promoted in 1940 to deputy commissar of the Soviet food-processing industry. His first important Communist Party appointment was as first secretary of the Kharkov regional party comm...
</Question>
<Choice>Podgorny, Nikolay</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Khmer political leader whose totalitarian regime (1975–79) imposed severe hardships on the Cambodian people. His radical communist government forced the mass evacuations of cities, killed or displaced millions of people, and left a legacy of brutality and impoverishment.The son of a landowning farmer, Saloth Sar was sent at age 5 or 6 to live with an older brother in Phnom Penh, where he was educated. A mediocre student, he failed the entrance examinations for high school and so instead studied carpentry for a year at a technical school in Phnom Penh. In 1949 he went to Paris on a scholarship...
</Question>
<Choice>Pol Pot</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French statesman, bank director, and teacher who was premier of the Fifth French Republic from 1962 to 1968 and president from 1969 until his death.The son of a schoolteacher, Pompidou graduated from the École Normale Supérieure and then taught school in Marseilles and Paris. During World War II he fought as a lieutenant and won the Croix de Guerre. In late 1944 he was introduced to Charles de Gaulle, who was then head of the provisional French government. At this time Pompidou was a complete stranger to politics, but he soon proved adept at interpreting and presenting de Gaulle's policies. Po...
</Question>
<Choice>Pompidou, Georges</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mexican political leader and diplomat who was provisional president of Mexico from Dec. 1, 1928, after the assassination of President-elect Alvaro Obregón, to Feb. 5, 1930.From late 1914 Portes Gil worked for the revolutionary movement led by Venustiano Carranza, but he supported Alvaro Obregón against Carranza in the presidential elections of 1920. After Obregón was elected president for the first time, Portes Gil became provisional governor of Tamaulipas. He also was governor of that state from 1925 to 1928, during the presidency of Plutarco Elías Calles. As provisional president of Mexico h...
</Question>
<Choice>Portes Gil, Emilio</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Thai political leader who was one of the instigators of the June 1932 constitutional revolution and was made prime minister in 1946.After studies at the Royal Law School, Pridi won a government scholarship to study law in France; he earned a doctorate in law from Paris in 1927. While in Paris he was strongly influenced by French socialism, and, with other students, including Luang Phibunsongkhram, he began plotting the overthrow of the Thai absolute monarchy. On return to Thailand the conspirators intensified their efforts, and on June 24, 1932, they carried out a bloodless coup d'état that fo...
</Question>
<Choice>Pridi Phanomyong</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian politician who was twice prime minister of Italy (1996–98; 2006–08) and who served as president of the European Commission (1999–2004).Prodi graduated from Catholic University in Milan in 1961 and did postdoctoral work at the London School of Economics. After serving as a professor of economics at the University of Bologna, he entered government as minister of industry in 1978. In 1996, after two productive stints as chairman of the Institute for Industrial Reconstruction (1982–89 and 1993–94), he ran for prime minister. Prodi, taking advantage of Italian electoral reform, built a cent...
</Question>
<Choice>Prodi, Romano</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian intelligence officer and politician who served as president (1999–2008) of Russia; he also was the country's prime minister in 1999 and again from 2008.Putin studied law at Leningrad State University, where his tutor was Anatoly Sobchak, later one of the leading reform politicians of the perestroika period. Putin served 15 years as a foreign intelligence officer for the KGB (Committee for State Security), including six years in Dresden, East Germany (now Germany). In 1990 he retired from active KGB service with the rank of lieutenant colonel and returned to Russia to become prorector o...
</Question>
<Choice>Putin, Vladimir</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
sultan of Oman.Qaboos, a member of Oman's Al Bu Sa?id dynasty, was educated at Bury Saint Edmunds, Suffolk, England, and at Sandhurst, the Royal Military Academy, in Berkshire. He was called home in 1965 by his father, Sa?id ibn Taymur, who kept his son a virtual prisoner for six years while maintaining his subjects in a state of relative underdevelopment despite the country's growing oil revenues.In 1970 Qaboos took over the palace in a coup with British support and exiled his father. He immediately undertook a range of ambitious modernization projects, including constructing roads, hospitals...
</Question>
<Choice>Qaboos bin Said</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
de facto leader of Libya from 1969 and a controversial Arab statesman.The son of an itinerant Bedouin farmer, Qaddafi was born in a tent in the Libyan desert. He proved a talented student and graduated from the University of Libya in 1963. A devout Muslim and ardent Arab nationalist, Qaddafi early began plotting to overthrow the Libyan monarchy of King Idris I. He graduated from the Libyan military academy in 1965 and thereafter rose steadily through the ranks, all the while continuing to plan a coup with the help of his fellow army officers. On Sept. 1, 1969, Qaddafi seized control of the gov...
</Question>
<Choice>Qaddafi, Muammar al-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
army officer who overthrew the Iraqi monarchy in 1958 and became head of the newly formed Republic of Iraq.Qasim attended the Iraqi military academy and advanced steadily through the ranks until by 1955 he had become a high-ranking officer. Like many Iraqis, he disliked the socially conservative and pro-Western policies of the monarchy. By 1957 Qasim had assumed leadership of the several opposition groups that had formed in the army. On July 14, 1958, Qasim and his followers used troop movements planned by the government as an opportunity to seize military control of Baghdad and overthrow the...
</Question>
<Choice>Qasim, 'Abd al-Karim</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Israeli statesman and soldier who, as prime minister of Israel (1974–77, 1992–95), led his country toward peace with its Palestinian and Arab neighbours. He was chief of staff of Israel's armed forces during the Six-Day War (June 1967). Along with Shimon Peres, his foreign minister, and Palestine Liberation Organization (PLO) chairman Yasir ?Arafat, Rabin received the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1994.Rabin graduated from Kadourie Agricultural School in Kfar Tabor and in 1941 joined the Palmach, the Jewish Defense Forces' commando unit. He participated in actions against the Vichy French in Syria...
</Question>
<Choice>Rabin, Yitzhak</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
scholar and statesman who was president of India from 1962 to 1967. He served as professor of philosophy at Mysore (1918–21) and Calcutta (1921–31; 1937–41) universities and as vice chancellor of Andhra University (1931–36). He was professor of Eastern religions and ethics at the University of Oxford in England (1936–52) and vice chancellor of Benares Hindu University (1939–48) in India. From 1953 to 1962 he was chancellor of the University of Delhi.Radhakrishnan led the Indian delegation to the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization (UNESCO; 1946–52) and was elected...
</Question>
<Choice>Radhakrishnan, Sarvepalli</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Iranian cleric and politician, who was president of Iran from 1989 to 1997.Rafsanjani was the son of a prosperous farmer in the town of Rafsanjan, in the Kerman region of Iran. He moved to the Shi?ite holy city of Qom in 1948 to pursue his religious studies, and in 1958 he became a disciple of Ruhollah Khomeini. Rafsanjani became a hojatoleslam (from the Arabic ?ujjat al-Islam: “proof of Islam”), the second highest Shi?ite Muslim rank (after that of ayatollah). Like Khomeini, he opposed Shah Mohammad Reza Pahlavi's modernization program, and when Khomeini was exiled from Iran in 1962, Rafsanja...
</Question>
<Choice>Rafsanjani, Hashemi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Bengali leader who became the first prime minister (1972–75) and later the president (1975) of Bangladesh.Mujib, the son of a middle-class landowner, studied law and political science at the Universities of Calcutta and Dacca (now Dhaka). Although jailed briefly as a teenager for agitating for Indian independence, he began his formal political career in 1949 as a cofounder of the Awami League. The league advocated political autonomy for East Pakistan, the detached eastern part of Pakistan. Mujib's arrest in the late 1960s incited mob violence that eroded the Pakistani president's authority in...
</Question>
<Choice>Rahman, Mujibur</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
31st hereditary ruler of the principality of Monaco (1949–2005). He was the son of Prince Pierre, count de Polignac, and Princess Charlotte de Monaco, daughter of Louis II, prince de Monaco. Rainier became a Grimaldi (i.e., received his mother's family name) in accord with a sovereign ordinance of March 18, 1920.Rainier was educated in England and Switzerland and at the University of Montpellier in France. In 1944, during World War II, he served in the French army, and after the war he studied at the University of Paris. His mother having renounced her rights to succession in 1944, Rainier suc...
</Question>
<Choice>Rainier III, prince de Monaco</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Iranian politician who was prime minister of the Islamic Republic of Iran from 1980 to 1981.Born into poverty, Raja?i enlisted in the Iranian Air Force at age 16 and later earned a teacher's diploma from Tehran's Teachers' College. In 1960 he joined the Iranian Liberation Movement and was arrested three times by the government of Mohammad Reza Shah Pahlavi for his political activities. He became a member of the Central Committee of the Association of Islamic Teachers, and following the 1979 Iranian Revolution, he headed the Ministry of Education.Noted for his persistence and determination, Raj...
</Question>
<Choice>Raja'i, Mohammad Ali</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
military leader and politician who was president of the Philippines from 1992 to 1998. He was generally regarded as one of the most effective presidents in that nation's history.Ramos was educated at the U.S. Military Academy at West Point, N.Y., and at the University of Illinois, U.S. He then entered the Philippine army, serving in Korea and Vietnam. In 1972 President Ferdinand Marcos (who was Ramos' second cousin) appointed him chief of the Philippine Constabulary, and when Marcos imposed martial law later that year Ramos was responsible for enforcing it; the Constabulary arrested thousands...
</Question>
<Choice>Ramos, Fidel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
leader of the Congress (I) Party and prime minister of India from 1991 to 1996.Rao studied at Osmania University in Hyderabad and at Bombay and Nagpur universities, eventually receiving a law degree from the latter institution. He entered politics as a Congress Party activist working for independence from Britain. He served in the Andhra Pradesh legislative assembly from 1957 to 1977, supporting Indira Gandhi in her split from the Congress Party organization in 1969. He held various ministerial positions in the Andhra Pradesh government from 1962 to 1973, including that of chief minister, or g...
</Question>
<Choice>Rao, P.V. Narasimha</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
military and political leader in Ghana who twice (1979, 1981) overthrew the government and seized power. His second period of rule (1981–2001) afforded Ghana political stability and competent economic management.Rawlings was the son of a Scottish father and a Ghanaian mother. He was educated at Achimoto College and the military academy at Teshie. He was commissioned a second lieutenant in the Ghanaian Air Force in 1969 and became a flight lieutenant and expert pilot, skilled in aerobatics. In June 1979 Rawlings and other junior officers led a successful military coup with the purported aim of...
</Question>
<Choice>Rawlings, Jerry J.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
40th president of the United States (1981–89), noted for his conservative Republicanism, his fervent anticommunism, and his appealing personal style, characterized by a jaunty affability and folksy charm. The only movie actor ever to become president, he had a remarkable skill as an orator that earned him the title “the Great Communicator.” His policies have been credited with contributing to the demise of Soviet communism. (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America.)
</Question>
<Choice>Reagan, Ronald W.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prime minister (taoiseach) of Ireland from February 1992 to December 1994.Reynolds was educated at Summerhill College in County Sligo and worked for a shipping firm before succeeding at a variety of entrepreneurial ventures, including promoting dances and owning ballrooms, a pet-food factory, and newspapers. In 1974 he was elected to the Longford County Council as a member of Fianna Fáil. He entered the Dáil (lower house of Parliament) in 1977 as a member for Counties Longford and Westmeath and became minister for posts and telegraphs in the Fianna Fáil government of Charles Haughey (1979–81)....
</Question>
<Choice>Reynolds, Albert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first president of the Republic of Korea (South Korea).Rhee completed a traditional classical Confucian education and then entered a Methodist school, where he learned English. He became an ardent nationalist and, ultimately, a Christian. In 1896 he joined with other young Korean leaders to form the Independence Club, a group dedicated to asserting Korean independence from Japan. When right-wing elements destroyed the club in 1898, Rhee was arrested and imprisoned until 1904. On his release he went to the United States, where in 1910 he received a Ph.D. from Princeton University, becoming the...
</Question>
<Choice>Rhee, Syngman</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
South Korean politician and lawyer, president of South Korea from 2003 to 2008.Born into a poor family, Roh worked as a night watchman in high school and later served in the military (1968–71). Although he did not attend college, he was able to pass the bar exam in 1975. He was appointed a judge in 1977 and later became a highly respected human rights lawyer, defending student protestors accused of being pro-communist.In the late 1980s, Roh entered politics at the invitation of then-opposition leader Kim Young Sam. Roh won a seat in the National Assembly in 1988 and gained notice for criticizi...
</Question>
<Choice>Roh Moo Hyun</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Korean military officer and politician who, as president of South Korea (1988–93), instituted democratic reforms.While a high-school student in Taegu (Daegu), Roh became friends with a fellow student, Chun Doo Hwan. Following the outbreak of the Korean War (1950–53), Roh joined the South Korean army and with Chun attended the Korean Military Academy, where they both graduated in 1955. Roh rose steadily through the ranks thereafter, becoming a general by 1979.In October 1979 Pres. Park Chung Hee was assassinated, and in December Chun and some fellow officers launched a coup against the civilian...
</Question>
<Choice>Roh Tae Woo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
member of the ruling ?aba? family of Kuwait and emir (1977–2006).Sheikh Jabir was the third son of Sheikh A?mad al-Jabir al-?aba?, who ruled Kuwait from 1921 to 1950. Beginning in the late 1940s he held a number of important public positions, including ministries in the government overseeing financial and economic affairs. When Iraq claimed sovereignty over newly independent Kuwait in 1961, he led a delegation to the Arab League to negotiate a settlement. He became prime minister in November 1965, and the following year he was formally designated crown prince and heir apparent to his cousin Sh...
</Question>
<Choice>Sabah, Sheikh Jabir al-Ahmad al-Jabir as-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Egyptian army officer and politician who was president of Egypt from 1970 until his assassination in 1981. He initiated serious peace negotiations with Israel, an achievement for which he shared the 1978 Nobel Prize for Peace with Israeli Prime Minister Menachem Begin. Under their leadership, Egypt and Israel made peace with each other in 1979.Sadat graduated from the Cairo Military Academy in 1938. During World War II he plotted to expel the British from Egypt with the help of the Germans. The British arrested and imprisoned him in 1942, but he escaped two years later. In 1946 Sadat was arres...
</Question>
<Choice>Sadat, Anwar el-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
president of Iraq (1979–2003), whose brutal rule was marked by costly and unsuccessful wars against neighbouring countries.
</Question>
<Choice>Saddam Hussein</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Canadian statesman and jurist who, as Liberal prime minister in 1948–57, helped to maintain Canadian unity and to bring about reforms.Saint Laurent studied at St. Charles College (Sherbrooke) and at Laval University (Quebec). He was called to the bar in 1905 and became one of Canada's leading lawyers, serving two terms as president of the Canadian Bar Association. In 1914 he was appointed professor of law at Laval University. In 1941 he was asked by Prime Minister W.L. Mackenzie King to enter public life.As a member of the Liberal Party, Saint Laurent was elected to the Canadian House of Commo...
</Question>
<Choice>Saint Laurent, Louis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Yemeni military officer who led a coup against the government of North Yemen in 1962 and who became president in 1978; in 1990 he became president of a reunified Yemen.?ali? attended the local Qur?anic school and joined the army at age 16. Four years later, on Sept. 26, 1962, he led a military coup that replaced the imamate of North Yemen with a civilian government (seeYemen: Two Yemeni states). Continuing to advance in his military career, he helped to bring Ibrahim al-?amdi to power in a 1974 coup, but the assassination of ?amdi in 1977 and of his successor in the following year threw the co...
</Question>
<Choice>Salih, 'Ali 'Abd Allah</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
economist and government official who was president of Mexico from 1988 to 1994.The son of a Mexican senator, Salinas joined the Institutional Revolutionary Party (PRI) at age 18 and studied economics at the National Autonomous University of Mexico and at Harvard University, earning a Ph.D in 1978. From 1971 on he held successively more important economic-affairs posts in the government and was supported in his rise by Miguel de la Madrid, who had been one of his professors at the National Autonomous University. When Madrid became president of Mexico in 1982, he made Salinas his minister of pl...
</Question>
<Choice>Salinas de Gortari, Carlos</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
field marshal and premier in a military government of Thailand from 1958 to 1963.Sarit studied at the Chula Chom Klao military academy in Bangkok, graduating in 1929 and subsequently serving as an army officer. He supported the military dictator Phibunsongkhram in his coup d'etat in 1947 and served until 1957 in that regime as minister of defense and commander of the army. In 1957, with some popular support, he removed Phibun, allowing the establishment of a civilian “caretaker” government. In October 1958, however, he seized power in another coup d'etat and proclaimed an “interim constitution...
</Question>
<Choice>Sarit Thanarat</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prime minister of Japan between 1964 and 1972, who presided over Japan's post-World War II reemergence as a major world power. For his policies on nuclear weapons, which led to Japan's signing of the Treaty on the Non-proliferation of Nuclear Weapons, he was awarded (with cowinner Sean MacBride) the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1974.After graduating with a degree in law from Tokyo Imperial University (now University of Tokyo) in 1924, Sato joined the Ministry of Railways, becoming the chief of its bureau of control in 1941 and vice-minister for transportation in 1948. That same year he joined the...
</Question>
<Choice>Sato Eisaku</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Social Democratic politician and publisher of the influential weekly Die Zeit who was chancellor of West Germany from 1974 to 1982.The son of a half-Jewish teacher, Schmidt served in the Wehrmacht (German Army) during World War II, serving in an armoured division on the Eastern Front and later in the Ardennes offensive and earning an Iron Cross. After the war he joined the Social Democratic Party, studied economics at the University of Hamburg, and then served in the economics and transport sector of the Hamburg municipal government (1949–53). He was elected to the Bundestag (1953–61), returne...
</Question>
<Choice>Schmidt, Helmut</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German politician, chancellor of Germany from 1998 to 2005.Having practiced law in Hannover, Schröder was elected to the Bundestag (lower house of parliament) in 1980 and served there until 1986, when he lost an election for premier of the state of Lower Saxony. He led the Social Democratic Party (SPD) opposition in the state parliament until he was elected to the premiership in 1990. The SPD joined with the Greens, a left-leaning environmentalist party, in a “Red-Green” coalition government until 1994, when the SPD won a clear majority. Schröder's strong showing in the March 1998 state electi...
</Question>
<Choice>Schröder, Gerhard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French statesman who founded the European Coal and Steel Community and worked for economic and political unity leading to an eventual establishment of a “United States of Europe.”Schuman, a member of the French National Assembly from 1919, was arrested by the German Gestapo in September 1940 after the German occupation of France. He escaped in 1942 and worked in the Résistance until France was liberated (1944). A founder of the Popular Republican Movement (Mouvement Républicain Populaire; MRP), he served as minister of finance (July–November 1946), premier (November 1947–July 1948 and August–S...
</Question>
<Choice>Schuman, Robert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian statesman and chancellor who struggled to prevent the Nazi takeover of Austria (March 1938).As an Innsbruck lawyer of monarchist political sympathies attached to the Christian Social Party, he was elected to the federal Nationalrat (lower house of parliament) in 1927. Later, in the government of Engelbert Dollfuss (1932–34) he was first appointed minister of justice (1932), then minister of education (1933); and after Dollfuss' assassination (1934), he was named federal chancellor. He eliminated the threats to his government posed by the Heimwehr, a national paramilitary defense force...
</Question>
<Choice>Schuschnigg, Kurt von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nigerian politician, president of Nigeria from 1979 to 1983.Shagari's great-grandfather founded the village from which the family took its name. Shagari was educated at Kaduna College and taught school briefly. As one of the few northerners to show an interest in national politics, he ran for office in 1954 and was elected to the federal House of Representatives. Thereafter he held several posts and was a member of every administration after Nigeria's independence in 1960. After a military coup led by Major General Johnson Aguiyi-Ironsi in 1966 ended civilian government, he retired to his home...
</Question>
<Choice>Shagari, Shehu</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polish-born Zionist leader and prime minister of Israel in 1983–84 and 1986–90 (in alliance with Shimon Peres of the Labour Party) and in 1990–92.Shamir joined the Beitar Zionist youth movement as a young man and studied law in Warsaw. He emigrated to Palestine in 1935 and enrolled at the Hebrew University in Jerusalem. There he joined the Irgun Zvai Leumi (IZL) underground movement; and in 1940, following a policy split in the IZL, he joined the Israel Freedom Fighters (IFF), a terrorist group later known as the Stern Gang (after its founder, Abraham Stern).Following the death of Stern, Shami...
</Question>
<Choice>Shamir, Yitzhak</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Israeli Zionist leader and politician who was prime minister of Israel from 1953 to 1955.Born in Ukraine, Moshe in 1906 immigrated with his family to Palestine, which was then part of the Ottoman Empire. Sharett studied law in Constantinople (later Istanbul) and during World War I was an interpreter in the Ottoman army. He later attended the London School of Economics (1922–24), during which time he became involved in the Zionist movement. After returning to Palestine, Sharett in 1933 became head of the political department of the Jewish Agency, an organization that encouraged Jews to settle i...
</Question>
<Choice>Sharett, Moshe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian lawyer and politician who was president of India from 1992 to 1997.Sharma pursued his higher education at Agra and Lucknow universities. After earning a doctorate in law at the University of Cambridge, he attended Lincoln's Inn in London and Harvard University. In 1940 he began his legal practice in Lucknow and soon after joined the Indian National Congress. Sharma's involvement in the national movement for independence led to his arrest, and he was imprisoned for eight months.After 1947 Sharma became active in independent India's political setup and held numerous political offices at t...
</Question>
<Choice>Sharma, Shankar Dayal</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Israeli general and politician, whose public life was marked by brilliant but controversial military achievements and political policies. One of the chief participants in the Arab-Israeli wars, he was elected prime minister of Israel in 2001, a position he held until he was incapacitated by a stroke in 2006.Sharon received military training early in life, becoming part of a Jewish defense force that protected kibbutzim (collective-farming settlements) from raids by Bedouin and neighbouring Arab villagers. During the Israeli war of independence in 1948–49, he led one of the crack units, and aft...
</Question>
<Choice>Sharon, Ariel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian statesman, prime minister of India (1964–66) after Jawaharlal Nehru.A member of Mahatma Gandhi's noncooperation movement against British government in India, he was imprisoned for a short time (1921). Upon release he studied in the Kashi Vidyapitha, a nationalist university, where he graduated with the title of shastri (“learned in the scriptures”). He then returned to politics as a follower of Gandhi, was imprisoned several more times, and attained influential positions in the Congress Party of the state of the United Provinces, now Uttar Pradesh state.Shastri was elected to the legisl...
</Question>
<Choice>Shastri, Lal Bahadur</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Georgian politician, who was foreign minister of the Soviet Union (1985–90, 1991) and head of state of Georgia (1992–2003).The son of a Georgian teacher, Shevardnadze became a Komsomol (Young Communist League) member and rose steadily in the hierarchy, becoming first secretary of Georgia's Komsomol Central Committee (1957–61). While in charge of the Georgian police (1965–72), he gained prominence in the regular party apparatus in Tbilisi, the capital, becoming first secretary of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of Georgia in 1972.Shevardnadze became a member of the Central Committe...
</Question>
<Choice>Shevardnadze, Eduard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
New Zealand politician who was New Zealand's first female prime minister (1997–99).After graduating from Christchurch Teachers' College in 1972, Robson married Burton Shipley, a farmer, and began teaching at a primary school. Active in the community, she joined the National Party (NP) in 1975. Shipley held numerous positions in the NP, and in 1987 she was elected to Parliament. In October 1990 the NP's leader, James Bolger, became prime minister, and later that year he named Shipley minister of social welfare (1990–93) and minister of women's affairs (1990–96). She attracted criticism for her...
</Question>
<Choice>Shipley, Jennifer</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
legal scholar and politician who served as prime minister of Greece from 1996 to 2004.Simitis was the son of George Simitis, an attorney and prominent leftist politician; both his parents were active in the Resistance during World War II. He received a bachelor's degree and a doctor of jurisprudence degree (1959) from the Philipps University of Marburg in West Germany and also studied at the London School of Economics and Political Science (1961–63). After a military junta took power in Greece in 1967, Simitis participated in clandestine political activities directed against the regime. In ord...
</Question>
<Choice>Simitis, Konstantinos</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian politician who served briefly as prime minister (1979–80).Singh became a lawyer and in 1929 joined the Indian National Congress movement. He was jailed several times in the struggle for Indian independence. He served in the United Provinces (now Uttar Pradesh) state assembly from 1937 on and was chief minister of Uttar Pradesh in 1967–68 and 1970. In 1977 he allied his peasant- and agricultural-based Indian Revolutionary Party with the Janata Party of Morarji Desai and subsequently served as minister of home affairs (1977–78) and deputy prime minister (1979) in Desai's coalition governm...
</Question>
<Choice>Singh, Charan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian economist and politician, who became prime minister of India in 2004. A Sikh, he was the first non-Hindu to occupy the office.Singh attended Punjab University and the University of Cambridge in Great Britain. He later earned a doctorate in economics from the University of Oxford. In the 1970s he was named to a series of economic advisory posts with the Indian government and became a frequent consultant to prime ministers. Singh also worked at the Reserve Bank of India, serving as director (1976–80) and governor (1982–85). When he was named finance minister in 1991, the country was on th...
</Question>
<Choice>Singh, Manmohan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician and government official who was prime minister of India in 1989–90.Singh studied at Allahabad and Pune (Poona) universities and became a member of the Legislative Assembly of his home state of Uttar Pradesh in 1969 as a member of the Congress Party. He won election to the Lok Sabha (lower house of Parliament) in 1971 and was appointed a deputy minister of commerce by Prime Minister Indira Gandhi in 1974. He was minister of commerce in 1976–77, and, when Indira Gandhi returned to power in 1980, he served as chief minister (governor) of Uttar Pradesh until 1982 and resumed his post as...
</Question>
<Choice>Singh, V P</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian politician who was the first Sikh to serve as president of India (1982–87). He was an impotent bystander in 1984 when government troops stormed the Golden Temple in Amritsar, the Sikhs' holiest shrine, in an effort to apprehend militants who were demanding independence for the state of Punjab.When he was barely 15 years old, Singh became active in the politics of the Akali Dal, a Sikh organization that opposed British rule. He pursued traditional studies in Sikh holy books and earned the title Giani (“Learned Man”) for his scholarly mastery of the scriptures. In 1938 he established the...
</Question>
<Choice>Singh, Zail</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first native-born prime minister of the British colony of Southern Rhodesia (now Zimbabwe) and ardent advocate of white rule, who in 1965 declared Rhodesia's independence and its subsequent withdrawal from the British Commonwealth.Smith attended local schools and entered Rhodes University in Grahamstown, S.Af. He interrupted his studies in 1939 to join the Royal Air Force, and, as a fighter pilot in World War II, he was shot down twice. After completing his work at the university, Smith was elected to the Southern Rhodesian Assembly in 1948. He joined the governing Federal Party when the Feder...
</Question>
<Choice>Smith, Ian</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Socialist politician and lawyer, who became president of Portugal in 1986 as the country's first elected civilian head of state in 60 years, holding the post until 1996.His father, João Lopes Soares (d. 1970), had been a liberal republican, often jailed or exiled during the dictatorship of António Oliveira Salazar. The young Soares studied at the University of Lisbon and at the Faculty of Law, Sorbonne, Paris, becoming a student activist and thereafter taking up a law practice defending political dissidents. By the time that the army-imposed right-wing dictatorship fell in 1974, Soares had bee...
</Question>
<Choice>Soares, Mário</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the Swazi from 1921 and of the Kingdom of Swaziland from 1967 to 1982.His father, King Ngwane V, died when Sobhuza was an infant, and a queen regent ruled during his minority, while he was being educated in Swaziland and at the Lovedale Institute in Cape province, S.Af. He finally was installed as constitutional ruler of the Swazi on Dec. 22, 1921. At the time, Swaziland was one of Great Britain's High Commission territories in southern Africa.In 1967–68 Swaziland achieved independence from Great Britain, with a limited monarchy and an elected legislature. Less than five years later (i...
</Question>
<Choice>Sobhuza II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
family that maintained political control of Nicaragua for 44 years.The founder of the dynasty, Anastasio Somoza García (b. Feb. 1, 1896, San Marcos, Nicaragua—d. Sept. 29, 1956, Ancón, Panama Canal Zone [now Panama]), was the son of a wealthy coffee planter and was educated in Nicaragua and the United States. By marrying the daughter of a prominent Nicaraguan family, he ensured himself a secure political career. He rose quickly through the political ranks to become head of Nicaragua's army, the National Guard, in 1933. With the army at his disposal, he three years later deposed the elected pre...
</Question>
<Choice>Somoza Family</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
leader of the revolutionary Pathet Lao movement and first president of Communist-governed Laos.Souphanouvong, half brother of the Lao premier Souvanna Phouma, was born a prince, a son of Viceroy Boun Khong of Luang Prabang. He was trained in civil engineering in France, and, under the French Indochina administration, he built bridges and roads in Vietnam (1938–45). After World War II he opposed the reimposition of French rule in Laos and joined the nationalist provisional government in Vientiane as defense minister. After a period as foreign minister of the Free Lao government-in-exile in Bang...
</Question>
<Choice>Souphanouvong</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
premier of Laos known for having sought, throughout several terms in office, to maintain Laotian neutrality in Southeast Asian affairs.Souvanna was the nephew of King Sisavangvong of Laos. He studied architectural engineering in France and then entered the Public Works Service of French Indochina on returning to his country in 1931. When his uncle welcomed the return of French rule after the defeat of the Japanese, who had occupied Laos at the end of World War II, Souvanna and his half brother Souphanouvong joined the Lao Issara (Free Laos) movement and its provisional Vientiane government (19...
</Question>
<Choice>Souvanna Phouma</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sierra Leonean prime minister (1967 and 1968–71) and president (1971–85) who survived in office despite attempted coups, a burdensome national debt, and almost continual charges of gross mismanagement and governmental corruption.Stevens was a police officer, mine worker, and railway station master before founding the United Mineworkers Union (1943). He studied industrial relations at Ruskin College, Oxford (1947–48), and represented the Sierra Leone People's Party in the Protectorate Assembly, becoming minister of lands, mines, and labour (1952). After serving as deputy leader of the breakaway...
</Question>
<Choice>Stevens, Siaka</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
military leader, who became president of Paraguay after leading an army coup in 1954. One of Latin America's longest-serving rulers, he was overthrown in 1989.Stroessner, the son of a German immigrant, attended the Military College in Asunción and was commissioned in the Paraguayan army in 1932. He rose through the ranks to become general and in 1951 was made commander in chief of the armed forces. In 1954 he deposed President Federico Chávez and later assumed the presidency after an election in which he was the sole candidate for the office.Stroessner attempted to placate the rural poor and u...
</Question>
<Choice>Stroessner, Alfredo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first woman prime minister of Poland (1992–93).The daughter of a pharmacist, Suchocka specialized in constitutional law at the University of Adam Mickiewicz in Poznan, from which she graduated in 1968. She lectured in law there and at the Catholic University of Lublin. In 1980 she joined the Sejm (parliament) as a member of the Democratic Party, which was then affiliated with the Communist Party. In 1981 she opposed the imposition of martial law; after voting against the 1984 law banning Solidarity, she was expelled from the Democratic Party.In both 1989 and 1991 she was elected to the post-Co...
</Question>
<Choice>Suchocka, Hanna</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
army officer and political leader who was president of Indonesia from 1967 to 1998. His three decades of uninterrupted rule gave Indonesia much-needed political stability and sustained economic growth, but his authoritarian regime finally fell victim to an economic downturn and its own internal corruption.Like many Javanese, Suharto used only his given name, without a surname. The son of a minor official and trader in Yogyakarta, he aspired from his youth to a career in the military. After graduating from high school and working briefly as a bank clerk, he joined the Dutch colonial army and th...
</Question>
<Choice>Suharto</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
leader of the Indonesian independence movement and Indonesia's first president (1949–66), who suppressed the country's original parliamentary system in favour of an authoritarian “Guided Democracy” and who attempted to balance the Communists against the army leaders. He was deposed in 1966 by the army under Suharto.
</Question>
<Choice>Sukarno</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indonesian politician who was the fifth president of Indonesia (2001–04).The daughter of Sukarno, the first president of Indonesia, Megawati studied psychology and agriculture in college but did not take a degree. In 1987 she entered politics and was elected to the People's Consultative Assembly (national parliament), becoming head of the Indonesian Democratic Party (Partai Demokrasi Indonesia; PDI) in 1993. She grew to be a threat to Indonesian president Suharto (who had replaced Sukarno in 1967), and in June 1996 the government engineered her removal as head of the PDI, thereby disqualifying...
</Question>
<Choice>Sukarnoputri, Megawati</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prime minister of Japan (1980–82), who worked closely with the United States and other Western countries.The son of a fisherman, Suzuki attended the former Imperial Fisheries Institute and joined the Japan Fisheries Association. At the second postwar general election, in 1947, Suzuki won a seat in the lower house of the Diet (parliament) as a socialist. Two years later he switched to the conservative Liberal Party, forerunner of the Liberal-Democratic Party (LDP), and he won reelection 12 times, during which period he held several cabinet posts. His abilities as a mediator brought him the chai...
</Question>
<Choice>Suzuki Zenko</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
president of Czechoslovakia (1968–75) who achieved great popularity by resisting the Soviet Union's demands during and after its invasion of August 1968. He was also a national hero of two world wars.Deserting from the Austro-Hungarian army during World War I, Svoboda fought in the Czechoslovak legion in Russia. After the war he rose in the ranks of the Czechoslovak army. He was in charge of a battalion at the time of the Munich crisis (1938), which resulted in the occupation by Germany of large parts of Czechoslovakia. After the German seizure in March 1939 of what was left of his country, Sv...
</Question>
<Choice>Svoboda, Ludvík</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prime minister of Japan from November 1987 to June 1989, at which time he resigned because of his involvement in an influence-peddling scandal. A behind-the-scenes power broker, he continued to shape and control the country's government after leaving office.Takeshita, the son of a sake brewer, graduated from Waseda University, Tokyo, in 1947, after which he taught high school for four years. He served seven years on the Shimane prefectural council before being elected to the lower house of the Diet (parliament) in 1958; it was the first of 11 consecutive terms. His first ministerial post was a...
</Question>
<Choice>Takeshita Noboru</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician who was prime minister of Japan from 1972 to 1974 and who subsequently became the central figure in a major political scandal.Tanaka was the only son of a bankrupt cattle dealer. He dropped out of school at the age of 15 and soon opened his own construction firm, the Tanaka Civil Engineering Company. His business prospered during World War II, largely because of military contracts, and he became one of the richest men in Japan. Entering politics, he was elected to a seat in the lower house of the Diet (parliament) in 1947 and rose rapidly through the ranks of the powerful Liberal-De...
</Question>
<Choice>Tanaka Kakuei</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Afghan politician who was president and prime minister of Afghanistan from 1978 to 1979.Born into a rural Pashtun family, Taraki attended night school while working as a clerk in Bombay, India, where he learned English. In the late 1940s he worked in the press department of the Afghan government and in 1953 was appointed attaché at the Afghan embassy in Washington, D.C. On returning to Kabul he opened a business that translated materials for foreign organizations, and his clientele included the U.S. embassy. When Mohammad Zahir Shah introduced a more flexible home and foreign policy in 1963, T...
</Question>
<Choice>Taraki, Nur Mohammad</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Liberian politician and guerrilla leader, who served as Liberia's president from 1997 until he was forced into exile in 2003. He was widely held responsible for the country's devastating civil war during the 1990s.Taylor was the son of a judge, a member of the elite in Liberia descended from the freed American slaves who colonized the region in the early 19th century. He attended college in the United States, where in 1977 he received a degree in economics from Bentley College in Waltham, Massachusetts. He then became the director of Liberia's General Services Administration under President Sa...
</Question>
<Choice>Taylor, Charles Ghankay</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British Conservative Party politician and prime minister (1979–90), Europe's first woman prime minister. The only British prime minister in the 20th century to win three consecutive terms and, at the time of her resignation, Britain's longest continuously serving prime minister since 1827, she accelerated the evolution of the British economy from statism to liberalism and became, by personality as much as achievement, the most renowned British political leader since Winston Churchill.
</Question>
<Choice>Thatcher, Margaret</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
dictator-like leader of Panama (1968–78), who negotiated the Panama Canal treaties with the United States, leading to Panama's eventual assumption of control of the canal.Educated at a military school in El Salvador, Torrijos also studied military-related subjects in the United States and Venezuela. In 1952 he was commissioned second lieutenant in the National Guard of Panama (Guardia Nacional; the country's only military force), becoming lieutenant colonel (1966), colonel (1968), and brigadier general (1969). In October 1968 he participated in a coup by the National Guard that overthrew Presi...
</Question>
<Choice>Torrijos, Omar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first president of the Republic of Guinea (1958–84) and a leading African politician.Although his parents were poor and uneducated, Touré claimed to be the grandson of Samory, a military leader who resisted French rule at the end of the 19th century, long after many other Africans had surrendered. Reared as a Muslim, Touré attended a French technical school at Conakry, from which he was expelled after one year for leading a food riot (1936). In 1940 Touré was hired as a clerk by a business firm, the Niger Français, and the following year took an administrative assignment in the postal service....
</Question>
<Choice>Touré, Sékou</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Liberal politician and prime minister of Canada (1968–79; 1980–84). His terms in office were marked by the establishment of diplomatic relations with China (1970) and improved relations with France, the defeat of the French separatist movement, constitutional independence from the British Parliament, and the formation of a new Canadian constitution with the principal additions of a bill of rights and an amending formula.Trudeau grew up in a family of French and Scots-French descent, in the affluent Montreal suburb of Outremont. He studied at Jean-de-Brébeuf, an elite Jesuit preparatory school,...
</Question>
<Choice>Trudeau, Pierre Elliott</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(seeResearcher's Note) 33rd president of the United States (1945–53), who led his nation through the final stages of World War II and through the early years of the Cold War, vigorously opposing Soviet expansionism in Europe and sending U.S. forces to turn back a communist invasion of South Korea. (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America.)
</Question>
<Choice>Truman, Harry S.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician, president of the secessionist African state of Katanga, and premier of the united Congo Republic (now the Democratic Republic of the Congo) who took advantage of an armed mutiny to announce the secession of mineral-rich Katanga province in July 1960. With covert military and technical assistance from Belgium and the aid of a white mercenary force, Tshombe maintained his independent Republic of Katanga for three years in the face of combined United Nations and Congolese efforts to end the secession of the province. Often accused of being a pawn of foreign commercial interests, Tshom...
</Question>
<Choice>Tshombe, Moise</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman whose 27 years as Liberia's 17th president constituted the longest tenure in that office in the history of Africa's first republic (proclaimed in 1847). He was responsible for numerous reforms and social policies, including enactment of suffrage and property rights for all female residents of 21 or older; authorization of direct participation in government by all tribespeople, who comprise about 80 percent of the population; and the establishment of a nationwide public-school system.A descendant of early American immigrants, mostly liberated slaves, Tubman grew up in poverty and unde...
</Question>
<Choice>Tubman, William V S</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Croat politician who led the country to independence from Yugoslavia in 1991 and who was president until his death.Having joined the Partisans in 1941, Tudjman launched a military career in the Yugoslav army, rose quickly in rank, and in 1960 became one of its youngest generals. The following year he left military service and became the director of the Institute for the History of the Workers' Movement. He received a doctorate in history from the University of Zagreb in 1965.Tudjman was outspoken on nationalist issues, including the charge that Yugoslav authorities had inflated the crimes comm...
</Question>
<Choice>Tudjman, Franjo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
president of Colombia from 1978 to 1982, a centrist liberal who proved unable to end his country's continuing social unrest.Born into a middle-class family descended from Lebanese immigrants, Turbay was educated at the National Commercial School in Bogotá and the University College of Botero. He served in the House of Representatives from 1943 to 1953 and became a leader of the Liberal Party. He was appointed minister of mines and energy in 1957 and became minister of foreign affairs in 1958 under President Alberto Lleras Camargo.Turbay was elected to two successive terms in the Senate (1962–6...
</Question>
<Choice>Turbay Ayala, Julio César</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Canadian lawyer and politician who in June 1984 succeeded Pierre Elliott Trudeau as head of the Liberal Party and prime minister of Canada. In general elections of September of the same year, his party was routed by the Progressive-Conservatives under Brian Mulroney.Turner's family immigrated to Canada in 1932, and Turner gained his early education in Ottawa. After graduating in political science from the University of British Columbia (A.B., 1949), he studied for a year in Paris and attended the University of Oxford as a Rhodes scholar, receiving a degree in law in 1952 and a master's degree...
</Question>
<Choice>Turner, John Napier</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German Communist leader and head of the post-World War II German Democratic Republic, or East Germany.Ulbricht, a cabinetmaker by trade, joined the Social Democratic Party (SPD) in 1912 and during World War I served on the Eastern Front, deserting twice. After the war he entered the new Communist Party of Germany (KPD). A bureaucrat and organizer, he was elected to the party's central committee in 1923. With the rise of Joseph Stalin, Ulbricht became instrumental in Bolshevizing the German party and organizing it on a cell basis. He became a member of the Reichstag (parliament) in 1928 and led...
</Question>
<Choice>Ulbricht, Walter</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prince of Savoy and briefly king of Italy in 1946 until he was forced to abdicate after a republican form of government was approved in a general referendum.The son of King Victor Emmanuel III, Umberto graduated from the Royal Military Academy in Turin. He became a general in 1931 and commanded an armoured division in World War II. On Mussolini's recommendation he was made marshal in October 1942. After the Allies took Rome, his father appointed him lieutenant general of the realm (June 2, 1944) and abdicated in his favour on May 9, 1946. Although Umberto campaigned to rally the monarchist for...
</Question>
<Choice>Umberto II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician who served as prime minister of Japan for 68 days (June 2–Aug. 9, 1989).The son of a wealthy brewer, Uno attended the Kobe University of Commerce, served in the army in World War II, and was first elected to the House of Representatives in 1960. He served in various ministerial posts before the Liberal-Democratic Party chose him to be prime minister. He was chosen largely by default, he being one of the few politicians without links to the influence-peddling and bribery scandals that brought down the ministry of his predecessor, Takeshita Noboru. Ironically, Uno was soon compelled t...
</Question>
<Choice>Uno Sosuke</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
leader of the pro-Hindu Bharatiya Janata Party (BJP) and twice prime minister of India (1996; 1998–2004).Vajpayee was first elected to Parliament in 1957 as a member of the Bharatiya Jana Sangh (BJS), a forerunner of the BJP. In 1977 the BJS joined three other parties to form the Janata Party, which led a government that lasted until July 1979. As foreign minister in the Janata government, Vajpayee earned a reputation for improving relations with Pakistan and China. In 1980, following a split in the Janata Party, Vajpayee helped the BJS to reorganize itself as the BJP. In 1992 he was one of th...
</Question>
<Choice>Vajpayee, Atal Bihari</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
lawyer, major political figure in Ecuador from the 1930s to the '70s, and five times president of Ecuador.Velasco Ibarra was born into a wealthy family and educated in Quito and Paris. He held various public posts before being elected president as the Conservative Party's candidate in 1933, assuming office in 1934. His economic-development plans, which included the proposed division of large landed estates, failed to win the support of Congress, and he responded by assuming dictatorial powers, imprisoning opposition leaders, and censoring the press. He was deposed in 1935 by army leaders after...
</Question>
<Choice>Velasco Ibarra, José María</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian politician, government official, and lawyer who was president of India from 1987 to 1992.Venkataraman studied law at the University of Madras and began his legal practice in 1935. He became involved in India's independence struggle and was consequently jailed by the British (1942–44). After his release he continued to practice law and helped draft India's constitution, which was adopted in 1950. Venkataraman was elected to independent India's Provisional Parliament in 1950 as a member of the Indian National Congress party. He subsequently was a member of the Lok Sabha (the lower house o...
</Question>
<Choice>Venkataraman, Ramaswamy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
South African professor, editor, and statesman who as prime minister (1958–66) rigorously developed and applied the policy of apartheid, or separation of the races.When Verwoerd was three months old, his family migrated to South Africa. A brilliant scholar at the University of Stellenbosch, he was appointed professor of applied psychology there in 1927. In 1933 he changed to the chair of sociology and social work.Verwoerd became prominent in politics in 1937, when he was appointed editor of the new Nationalist daily, Die Transvaler, in Johannesburg. He held that post until the National Party w...
</Question>
<Choice>Verwoerd, Hendrik Frensch</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
far right Nationalist politician who served as prime minister (1966–78) and president (1978–79) of South Africa. He was forced to resign from the presidency because of a political scandal.Vorster was the 13th child of a wealthy Afrikaner sheep farmer. He studied at the University of Stellenbosch, where he gained attention as a Nationalist student leader. In 1938 Vorster left the university to act as registrar to the judge-president at the Cape, and the next year he practiced law at Port Elizabeth. During World War II, Vorster helped to found the anti-British Ossewa Brandwag (Ox-Wagon Guard) an...
</Question>
<Choice>Vorster, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Austrian diplomat and statesman who served two terms as the fourth secretary-general of the United Nations (UN), from 1972 to 1981. He was the elected president of Austria from 1986 to 1992.Waldheim's father, a Czech by ethnic origin, changed his name from Waclawik to Waldheim. Kurt Waldheim served in the Austrian army as a volunteer (1936–37) before he began to study for a diplomatic career. He was soon conscripted into the German army, however, and served on the Russian front until 1941, when he was wounded. Waldheim's later claims that he spent the rest of World War II studying law at the U...
</Question>
<Choice>Waldheim, Kurt</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
labour activist who helped form and led (1980–90) communist Poland's first independent trade union, Solidarity. The charismatic leader of millions of Polish workers, he went on to become the president of Poland (1990–95). He received the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1983.Walesa, the son of a carpenter, received only primary and vocational education and in 1967 began work as an electrician at the huge Lenin Shipyard in Gdansk. He witnessed the 1970 food riots in Gdansk in which police killed a number of demonstrators. When new protests against Poland's communist government erupted in 1976, Walesa e...
</Question>
<Choice>Walesa, Lech</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Australian politician and lawyer whose unsuccessful premiership (1972–75) of his country ended when he was dismissed by the governor-general.Whitlam was born in Kew, a suburb of Melbourne. His father, Fred Whitlam, was a public servant who served as Commonwealth crown solicitor. Whitlam earned a bachelor's degree from the University of Sydney in 1938. During World War II he served overseas as a navigator in the Royal Australian Air Force, reaching the rank of flight lieutenant. After the war he completed his studies at the university (LL.B., 1946) and became a barrister in 1947. He was a membe...
</Question>
<Choice>Whitlam, Gough</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Labour Party politician who was prime minister of the United Kingdom from 1964 to 1970 and from 1974 to 1976.The son of an industrial chemist, Wilson was educated at the University of Oxford, where, as a fellow of University College (1938–39), he collaborated with Sir William (afterward 1st Baron) Beveridge on work that led to Beveridge's epochal report (1942) advocating social insurance and other welfare measures. On the outbreak of World War II, Wilson was drafted into the civil service. As director of economics and statistics (1943–44) at the Ministry of Fuel and Power, he produced a study...
</Question>
<Choice>Wilson, Harold, Baron Wilson Of Rievaulx</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
president of Pakistan (1969–71), a professional soldier who became commander in chief of the Pakistani armed forces in 1966.Yahya was born to a family that was descended from the elite soldier class of Nader Shah, the Persian ruler who conquered Delhi in the 18th century. He was educated at Punjab University and later graduated first in his class from the Indian Military Academy at Dehra Dun. He served in Italy and the Middle East during World War II and, after the partition of India in 1947, organized the Pakistani Staff College.After serving in the war with India over the Kashmir region, he...
</Question>
<Choice>Yahya Khan, Agha Mohammad</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian politician, who became president of Russia in 1990. In 1991 he became the first popularly elected leader in the country's history, guiding Russia through a stormy decade of political and economic retrenching until his resignation on the eve of 2000.Yeltsin attended the Urals Polytechnic Institute and worked at various construction projects in the Sverdlovsk oblast from 1955 to 1968, joining the Communist Party in 1961. In 1968 he began full-time work in the party and in 1976 became first secretary of the Sverdlovsk oblast party committee. Thereafter he came to know Mikhail Gorbachev, t...
</Question>
<Choice>Yeltsin, Boris</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese political leader who served several terms as prime minister of Japan during most of the critical transition period after World War II, when Allied troops occupied the country and Japan was attempting to build new democratic institutions.After graduating in law from Tokyo Imperial University in 1906, Yoshida entered the Foreign Ministry. In 1928 he was appointed minister to Sweden, Norway, and Denmark and then vice foreign minister (1928–30). In 1936 the army vetoed his appointment as foreign minister, and he was instead made ambassador to Great Britain, serving until 1939. During Worl...
</Question>
<Choice>Yoshida Shigeru</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Afghanistan from 1933 to 1973, who provided an era of stable government to his country.The sons of Mo?ammad Nader Shah, Zahir and his brothers reasserted central government control during a period of anarchy and banditry in the late 1920s. Zahir Shah came to the throne at the age of 19, after the assassination of his father in November 1933, having previously served as a cabinet minister. For a number of years Zahir Shah remained in the background while his relatives ran the government, but he asserted his power through the constitution of 1964, which established a constitutional monar...
</Question>
<Choice>Zahir Shah, Mohammad</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish politician, who became prime minister of Spain in 2004.Zapatero was the son of a lawyer and the grandson of a Republican army officer executed by Gen. Francisco Franco's forces during the Spanish Civil War. He attended the University of León and became a member of the university's law faculty after graduating in 1982. In 1986 Zapatero, who had joined the Spanish Socialist Workers' Party (Partido Socialista Obrero Español; PSOE) in 1979, was elected to the national parliament, becoming its youngest member. Two years later he was made general secretary of the PSOE's León provincial feder...
</Question>
<Choice>Zapatero, José Luis Rodríguez</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
president of Mexico from 1994 to 2000.Reared in a working-class family in Mexicali, Mexico, just south of the California border, Zedillo returned to his native Mexico City in 1965 to study at the National Polytechnic Institute. In 1971 he joined the Institutional Revolutionary Party (PRI), the dominant political party in Mexico since 1929. Zedillo also studied in the United States, receiving his doctorate in economics from Yale University in 1981. He then worked for Mexico's central bank and at the Ministry of Programming and Budget, becoming secretary in 1988. As such, he successfully control...
</Question>
<Choice>Zedillo, Ernesto</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
premier of China (1980–87) and general secretary of the Chinese Communist Party (1987–89).Born into a landlord family in Henan province, Zhao joined the Young Communist League in 1932 and became a member of the Chinese Communist Party (CCP) in 1938. He served in local party organizations in northern China during the Sino-Japanese War (1937–45). After the establishment of the People's Republic in 1949, he was moved to Guangdong province in the south, where he became provincial first party secretary in 1965. Purged in 1967 during the Cultural Revolution, he was later rehabilitated and sent as fi...
</Question>
<Choice>Zhao Ziyang</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first secretary of the ruling Bulgarian Communist Party's Central Committee (1954–89) and president of Bulgaria (1971–89). His 35 years as Bulgaria's ruler made him the longest-serving leader in any of the Soviet-bloc nations of eastern Europe.The son of poor peasants, Zhivkov rose in the Communist Party and during World War II helped organize the resistance movement known as the People's Liberation Insurgent Army. After the war and the institution of a Soviet-sponsored communist government in Bulgaria, Zhivkov held increasingly important posts, including the command of the People's Militia, w...
</Question>
<Choice>Zhivkov, Todor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
leading figure in the Chinese Communist Party (CCP) and premier (1949–76) and foreign minister (1949–58) of the People's Republic of China, who played a major role in the Chinese Revolution and later in the conduct of China's foreign relations. He was an important member of the CCP from its beginnings in 1921 and became one of the great negotiators of the 20th century and a master of policy implementation, with infinite capacity for details. He survived internecine purges, always managing to retain his position in the party leadership. Renowned for his charm and subtlety, Zhou was described as...
</Question>
<Choice>Zhou Enlai</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese politician who was a leading economic reformer in the Chinese Communist Party (CCP). He was premier of China from 1998 to 2003.Zhu joined the CCP in 1949. Following his graduation (1951) from Tsinghua (Qinghua) University in Beijing with a degree in electrical engineering, he began work as a deputy division chief with the state planning commission. Though twice exiled to rural northwestern China because of his criticism of Mao Zedong's economic policies, he eventually earned the favour of paramount leader Deng Xiaoping and by 1987 had been appointed deputy party secretary of Shanghai....
</Question>
<Choice>Zhu Rongji</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician who served as prime minister of Bangladesh in 1991–96 and 2001–06. The first woman to serve as prime minister of Bangladesh, she governed during a period of natural disasters, economic distress, and civil unrest.Khaleda was the third of five children born to Taiyaba and Iskandar Majumdar, a businessman. In 1960 she passed the government matriculation exam and later attended Surendranath College in Dinajpur. In 1959 she married Zia ur-Rahman, a leader in the fight for the independence of Bangladesh, then part of Pakistan. During the struggle in 1971 she was kept under house arrest, t...
</Question>
<Choice>Zia, Begum Khaleda</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pakistani chief of Army staff, chief martial-law administrator, and president of Pakistan (1978–88).Zia was commissioned in 1945 from the Royal Indian Military Academy in Dehra Dun and served with the British armoured forces in Southeast Asia at the end of World War II. After 19 years spent in various staff and command appointments he was made an instructor at the Command and Staff College in Quetta. He successively commanded a regiment, brigade, division, and a corps during the period 1966–72. A major general from 1972, he was president of the military courts that tried several Army and Air F...
</Question>
<Choice>Zia-ul-Haq, Mohammad</Choice>
</item>
</topics>