<topics>
<item>
<Question>
fifth caliph (685–705) of the Umayyad Arab dynasty centred in Damascus. He reorganized and strengthened governmental administration and, throughout the empire, adopted Arabic as the language of administration.
</Question>
<Choice>'Abd al-Malik</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first caliph and greatest ruler of the Umayyad Arab Muslim dynasty of Spain. He reigned as hereditary emir (“prince”) of Córdoba from October 912 and took the title of caliph in 929.
</Question>
<Choice>'Abd al-Rahman III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
member of the Umayyad ruling family of Syria who founded an Umayyad dynasty in Spain.When the ?Abbasids overthrew the Umayyad caliphate in 750 CE and sought to kill as many members of the Umayyad family as possible, ?Abd al-Ra?man fled, eventually reaching Spain. The Iberian Peninsula had for some time been occupied by Muslim Arab forces, and he recognized political opportunity for himself in the rivalries of the Qays and Yaman, the dominant Arab factions there. By shifting alliances and using mercenary support, he placed himself in a position of power, attacking and defeating the governor of...
</Question>
<Choice>'Abd ar-Rahman I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Islamic caliph (reigned 749–754), first of the ?Abbasid dynasty, which was to rule over eastern Islam for approximately the next 500 years. The ?Abbasids were descended from an uncle of Mu?ammad and were cousins to the ruling Umayyad dynasty. The Umayyads were weakened by decadence and an unclear line of succession, and they enjoyed little popular support, prompting the ?Abbasids to declare open revolt in 747. When Abu al-?Abbas assumed the caliphate in 749, he began a campaign of extermination against the Umayyads, the ?Alids, other ?Abbasid leaders who had become too popular, and all other c...
</Question>
<Choice>Abu al-'Abbas as-Saffah</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Muhammad's closest companion and adviser, who succeeded to the Prophet's political and administrative functions, thereby initiating the office of the caliphate.Of a minor clan of the ruling merchant tribe of Quraysh at Mecca, Abu Bakr purportedly was the first male convert to Islam, but this view is doubted by a majority of Muslim historians. Abu Bakr's prominence in the early Muslim community was clearly marked by Muhammad's marriage to his young daughter ?A?ishah and again by Muhammad's choosing Abu Bakr as his companion on the journey to Medina (the Hijrah [Hegira], 622). In Medina he was M...
</Question>
<Choice>Abu Bakr</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
consort of the Western emperor Otto I and, later, regent for her grandson Otto III; one of the most influential women of 10th-century Europe, she helped strengthen the German church while subordinating it to imperial power.The daughter of Rudolf II (d. 937), king of Burgundy, and Bertha of Swabia, Adelaide was married (947) to Lothar, who succeeded his father, Hugh of Arles, as king of Italy in the same year. After Lothar died (950), Berengar of Ivrea, his old rival, seized the Italian throne and imprisoned Adelaide (April 951) at Garda. After her escape four months later, she asked the German...
</Question>
<Choice>Adelaide, Saint</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Wessex (from 855/856), the son of Aethelwulf, with whom he led the West Saxons to victory against the Danes at Aclea (851). He reportedly rebelled against his father either before (855) or on the latter's return from Rome in 856 and deprived him of Wessex, which he ruled until his death. On his father's death in 858 he married his stepmother, Judith.
</Question>
<Choice>Aethelbald</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the West Saxons, or Wessex, who succeeded to the subkingdom of Kent during the lifetime of his father Aethelwulf and retained it until the death of his elder brother Aethelbald in 860, when he became sole king of Wessex and Kent, the younger brothers Aethelred and Alfred renouncing their claim. He ruled these kingdoms for five years. His reign was marked by two serious attacks from the Danes, who destroyed Winchester in 860, in spite of the resistance of the ealdormen Osric and Aethelwulf. In 865 the Danes ravaged Kent.
</Question>
<Choice>Aethelberht</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Kent (560–616) who issued the first extant code of Anglo-Saxon laws. Reflecting some continental influence, the code established the legal position of the clergy and instituted many secular regulations. Aethelberht's marriage to Bertha (or Berhta), daughter of Charibert, king of Paris, and a Christian, may account for the tolerant reception that he accorded Augustine and other missionaries dispatched to Kent by Pope Gregory I the Great in 597. Aethelberht gave them a dwelling at Canterbury and later may have accepted Christianity himself; he did not force it on his subjects. According...
</Question>
<Choice>Aethelberht I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Bernicia (from 592/593) and of Deira, which together formed Northumbria.Aethelfrith was the son of Aethelric and grandson of Ida, king of Bernicia, and his reign marks the true beginning of the continuous history of a united Northumbria and, indeed, of England. He married Acha, daughter of Aelle, king of Deira, whom his father succeeded in 588 or 590, expelling Aelle's son Edwin.In 604 Aethelfrith repelled the attack of Aidan, king of the Dalriada Scots, at Degsastan, defeating him with great loss. The appearance of Hering, son of Aethelfrith's predecessor, on the side of the invaders...
</Question>
<Choice>Aethelfrith</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Wessex and of Kent (865/866–871), son of Aethelwulf of Wessex.By his father's will he should have succeeded to Wessex on the death of his eldest brother Aethelbald (d. 860). He seems, however, to have stood aside in favour of his brother Aethelberht, king of Kent, to whose joint kingdoms he succeeded in 865 or 866. Aethelred's reign was one long struggle against the Danes. In the year of his succession a large Danish force landed in East Anglia, and in the year 868 Aethelred and his brother Alfred went to help Burgred of Mercia against this host, but the Mercians soon made peace with t...
</Question>
<Choice>Aethelred I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Anglo-Saxon king in England, the father of King Alfred the Great. As ruler of the West Saxons from 839 to 856, he allied his kingdom of Wessex with Mercia and thereby withstood invasions by Danish Vikings.The son of the great West Saxon king Egbert (ruled 802–839), Aethelwulf ascended the throne four years after the Danes had begun large-scale raids on the English coast. In 851 he scored a major victory over a large Danish army at a place called Aclea in Surrey. Aethelwulf then married his daughter to the Mercian king Burgred (853), and in 856 he himself married Judith, the daughter of Charles...
</Question>
<Choice>Aethelwulf</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the Scottish kingdom of Dalriada. He was the son of Gabran, king of Dalriada.Aidan was inaugurated as king at Iona by St. Columba. He refused to allow his kingdom to remain dependent on the Irish Dalriada; but, coming into collision with his southern neighbours, he led a large force against Aethelfrith, king of the Northumbrians, and was defeated at Degsastan, probably in Liddesdale.
</Question>
<Choice>Aidan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Wessex (871–899), a Saxon kingdom in southwestern England. He prevented England from falling to the Danes and promoted learning and literacy. Compilation of the Anglo-Saxon Chronicle began during his reign, c. 890.When he was born, it must have seemed unlikely that Alfred would become king, since he had four older brothers; he said that he never desired royal power. Perhaps a scholar's life would have contented him. His mother early aroused his interest in English poetry, and from his boyhood he also hankered after Latin learning, possibly stimulated by visits to Rome in 853 and 855. I...
</Question>
<Choice>Alfred</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
cousin and son-in-law of Muhammad, the Prophet of Islam, and fourth of the “rightly guided” (rashidun) caliphs, as the first four successors of Muhammad are called. Reigning from 656 to 661, he was the first imam (leader) of Shi?ism in all its forms. The question of his right to the caliphate (the political-religious structure comprising the community of Muslims and its territories that emerged after the death of Muhammad) resulted in the only major split in Islam, into the Sunni and Shi?ite branches.
</Question>
<Choice>'Ali</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
daughter of Theodoric the Great, Ostrogothic king of Italy, and regent (526) and queen (534) of the Ostrogoths (526–534).When her husband died, Amalasuntha was left with a son, Athalaric, and a daughter. At Theodoric's death, in 526, Athalaric was 10 years old, and the highly educated Amalasuntha assumed the regency. Her pro-Byzantine policy, her patronage of literature and the arts, and her desire to educate her son in the Roman style were vigorously opposed by a large segment of the Ostrogoth nobility. Hence, she moved even closer to the Byzantine emperor, arranging with Justinian that if sh...
</Question>
<Choice>Amalasuntha</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
sixth caliph of the ?Abbasid dynasty.As the son of Harun ar-Rashid, the fifth caliph, and Zubayda, a niece of al-Man?ur, the second caliph, al-Amin took precedence in the succession over his elder half brother, al-Ma?mun, whose mother was a Persian slave. In 809, al-Amin succeeded to the caliphate, and al-Ma?mun was vested with the administration of the eastern Khorasan region. Relations between the brothers soon broke down, and in 810 al-Amin declared his own son as his direct heir. Open hostilities began in 811, and by 812 al-Amin was besieged in Baghdad, the defense of which lasted more tha...
</Question>
<Choice>Amin, al-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese general of Iranian and Turkish descent who, as leader of a rebellion in AD 755, proclaimed himself emperor and unsuccessfully attempted to found a dynasty to replace the Tang dynasty (618–907). Despite its failure, the rebellion precipitated far-reaching social and economic change.
</Question>
<Choice>An Lu-shan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor from 491 who perfected the empire's monetary system, increased its treasury, and proved himself an able administrator of domestic and foreign affairs. His heretical monophysite religious policies, however, caused periodic rebellions.After serving as an administrator in the department of finance and as a personal bodyguard to the emperor Zeno, Anastasius was chosen at the age of 61 to be emperor by his predecessor's widow, Ariadne, who married him shortly thereafter. He began his rule by abolishing the sale of offices, reforming taxation, and refusing rewards to informers.Amon...
</Question>
<Choice>Anastasius I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(d. 721), Byzantine emperor from 713 to 715.He was chosen to take the throne after an army coup deposed Philippicus, whose secretary he had been. Anastasius reversed the ecclesiastical policies of Philippicus and tried to reform the army before he, too, was deposed. Assuring Pope Constantine of his orthodoxy, Anastasius withdrew Philippicus' monothelite decrees, which had imposed the heretical doctrine of a single will of Christ. Militarily, he fortified Constantinople, selected the island of Rhodes as a Byzantine naval base, and sent the Isaurian Leo, the future emperor Leo III, to defend Syr...
</Question>
<Choice>Anastasius II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
leader of the nomadic Mongol-speaking Khitan tribes who occupied the northern border of China.Elected to a three-year term as great khan of the Khitans, Abaoji refused to resign at the end of his term but made himself king of the Khitan nation. After the collapse in 907 of Tang rule in China, Abaoji made himself emperor and by 916 had set up a Chinese-style dynasty, with his son as heir apparent. He organized his followers into fighting units known as ordos (similar to what Westerners later called a horde) and then joined 12 ordos into an administrative district.In 926, in return for aiding th...
</Question>
<Choice>A-pao-chi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
duke of Carinthia who deposed his uncle, the Holy Roman emperor Charles III the Fat, and became king of Germany, later briefly wearing the crown of the emperor.Arnulf was the illegitimate son of Charles the Fat's eldest brother, Carloman, who was king of Bavaria. Arnulf inherited the march of Carinthia from his father but was excluded from the succession to the kingdom on Carloman's death. Arnulf maintained and consolidated his frontiers, though in constant tension with the Moravian kingdom of Svatopluk. In November 887, at Frankfurt, the East Frankish magnates revolted against the incompetent...
</Question>
<Choice>Arnulf</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first West Saxon king to have effective rule over the whole of England.On the death of his father, Edward the Elder, in 924, Athelstan was elected king of Wessex and Mercia, where he had been brought up by his aunt, Aethelflaed, Lady of the Mercians. Crowned king of the whole country at Kingston on Sept. 4, 925, he proceeded to establish boundaries and rule firmly. He annexed the Viking kingdom of York in 927. His dominion was significantly challenged in 937 when Constantine of the Scots, Owain of Strathclyde, and Olaf Guthfrithson, claimant of the kingdom of York, joined forces and invaded En...
</Question>
<Choice>Athelstan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
caliph under whom the Fa?imid empire attained its greatest extent.The first of the Fa?imids to begin his reign in Egypt, where the caliphate was later centred, al-?Aziz succeeded his father, al-Mu?izz, in 975. He was ambitious to expand his domains at the expense of the Byzantine Empire and of the rival ?Abbasid caliphate, and for most of his reign he was involved in military and political ventures in northern Syria, where he and the Byzantine emperor Basil II at length reached a stalemate. Al-?Aziz, who had a Christian wife, was known for his favourable attitude toward Christians and Jews, an...
</Question>
<Choice>'Aziz, al-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sasanian king (reigned 590–591). A general and head of the house of Mihran at Rayy (near modern Tehran), he performed, in gaining the throne, a feat exceptional for one not of Sasanian royal blood.Prominent as master of the household in the Byzantine wars of the Sasanian king Hormizd IV, Bahram later received the supreme command in Khorasan and was able to repel a Turkish invasion. Following a defeat by the Romans in 589, however, he was harshly treated by Hormizd. Bahram, with the support of his army, rebelled; in the ensuing disorder, Hormizd was assassinated, and Khosrow II, his successor,...
</Question>
<Choice>Bahram VI Chubin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor (867–886), who founded the Macedonian dynasty and formulated the Greek legal code that later became known as the Basilica.Basil came of a peasant family that had settled in Macedonia, perhaps of Armenian origin. He was a handsome and physically powerful man who gained employment in influential official circles in Constantinople and was fortunate enough to attract the imperial eye of the reigning emperor, Michael III. After rapid promotion he became chief equerry, then chamberlain, and finally, in 866, co-emperor with Michael. Quick to sense opposition, he forestalled the Empe...
</Question>
<Choice>Basil I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
son of Eberhard, Frankish margrave of Friuli, king of Italy from 888 (as Berengar I), and Holy Roman emperor from 915. He was the founder of a line of princes of the 9th–11th century who in popular Italian histories are ranked incorrectly as national kings. Through his mother Gisela he was a grandson of the Carolingian emperor Louis I the Pious.After the fall of the emperor Charles III the Fat, Berengar, margrave since c. 874, was elected king of Italy in 888 at Pavia. He acknowledged the overlordship of the East Frankish king Arnulf, and from early 889 he was confined to northeastern Italy by...
</Question>
<Choice>Berengar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
grandson of Berengar I and king of Italy from 950 to 952.Berengar was important in the career of the German king and Holy Roman emperor Otto I the Great. For several months in 951 he held captive Adelaide, the daughter and widow of kings of Italy; she escaped and married Otto, who assumed the title of king of the Lombards and made Berengar his vassal. Later (from 960) Berengar and his son Adalbert attacked Pope John XII, on whose appeal Otto marched into Rome and was crowned emperor (962). John's subsequent negotiations with Berengar caused Otto to depose the pope and imprison Berengar in Germ...
</Question>
<Choice>Berengar II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
khagan, or great khan, of Mongolia from 716 until his death. His name literally translates as “Wise Emperor.”Bilge assumed leadership of the T'u-chüeh, a tribe of Turks in control of southern Central Asia, when his brother instigated a palace coup against the old ruler. When the T'ang emperor Hsüan Tsung refused his offer of an alliance, Bilge decimated the Chinese army, forcing them to sue for peace in 721. Bilge is even better known, however, for advising his successors that the power of the T'u-chüeh came from their nomadic life and that to settle in agricultural communities on the Chinese...
</Question>
<Choice>Bilge</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Premyslid prince of Bohemia from 929, who established the basis of the medieval Czech state.After instigating the murder of his elder brother, Prince Wenceslas I (St. Wenceslas), Boleslav became ruler of Bohemia. He made Prague the effective administrative centre of his domain, promoted the spread of Christianity, and added the territories of Moravia, Slovakia, and Silesia to his domain. After being attacked by the Holy Roman emperor Otto I (950), he was forced to recognize the German king as his suzerain. His feudal ties remained largely formal, however, and Bohemia was able to retain its aut...
</Question>
<Choice>Boleslav I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prince of Bohemia (967 [or 973]–999), the son and successor of Boleslav I. He successfully continued his father's work by further consolidating the supremacy of the Czechs over the other Bohemian tribes and by founding monasteries, nunneries, and capitular churches.Boleslav II secured the establishment of the bishopric of Prague in 973, under the metropolitan authority of the archbishops of Mainz. He treacherously but completely destroyed the Slavnikovci, the only princely rivals of the Premyslid dynasty in Bohemia, in 995. He was usually loyal to his suzerains, the Holy Roman emperors Otto I,...
</Question>
<Choice>Boleslav II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
khan of Bulgaria (852–889), whose long reign witnessed the conversion of the Bulgarians to Christianity, the founding of an autocephalous Bulgarian church, and the advent of Slavonic literature and establishment of the first centres of Slav-Bulgarian scholarship and education. Boris' active domestic and foreign diplomacy was of great importance in the formation of a united Bulgarian ethnic community, and it left lasting traces on Bulgaria's subsequent development.When Boris inherited the throne from his father, Bulgaria's territorial, military, and political potential had made it one of the la...
</Question>
<Choice>Boris I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of lower Burgundy, or Provence, from 877.The son of Buvin (or Beuves), Count of Ardennes, Boso was given the governance of Lombardy (876) by his brother-in-law Charles II the Bald, king of the West Franks (France), and received the title of duke. During the minorities of the West Frankish kings Louis III and Carloman, he convoked the bishops of Provence and had them proclaim him their king (Oct. 15, 879). Boso thereafter proceeded to expand his domains. The territory over which he usurped royal authority included not only Provence but many lands to the north, as far as Autun—an enlarged B...
</Question>
<Choice>Boso</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
queen of the Frankish kingdom of Austrasia, daughter of the Visigothic king Athanagild, and one of the most forceful figures of the Merovingian Age.In 567 Brunhild married Sigebert I, king of Austrasia, changing her religion from Arianism to Roman Catholicism. In the same year, her sister Galswintha married Sigebert's half brother Chilperic I, king of the western part of the Frankish territory, but in 567 or 568, at the instigation of his concubine Fredegund, Chilperic had Galswintha murdered. Prompted by Brunhild, Sigebert then exacted Galswintha's marriage settlement (Bordeaux, Limoges, Quer...
</Question>
<Choice>Brunhild</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
archbishop of Cologne and coregent of the Holy Roman Empire.The youngest son of King Henry I the Fowler of Germany and St. Matilda, and brother of Emperor Otto I the Great, Bruno was educated at the cathedral school of Utrecht and the court school of Otto. Proficient in Latin and Greek, he was a patron of learning. As chancellor from 940, he prepared his brother's official papers and after ordination to the priesthood accompanied him to Italy in 951. Already abbot of Lorsch and Corvey, where he restored monastic observance, he was elected to the see of Cologne in 953 and soon was named duke of...
</Question>
<Choice>Bruno the Great, Saint</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British king of Gwynedd (in present north Wales) who, with the Mercian king Penda, invaded Northumbria in 632 or 633, killed the Northumbrian king Edwin in battle in Hatfield Chase (south of York), and devastated the region. A year later Cadwallon was defeated and slain by Oswald, who became king of Northumbria, ending one of the greatest Welsh threats to the Anglo-Saxon kingdoms.
</Question>
<Choice>Cadwallon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
second son of Louis II and king of France or the West Franks (882–884). On Louis II's death (879) Carloman was associated with his brother Louis III as king of the West Franks, but both, as the children of a first marriage that had been unacceptable to their grandfather Charles the Bald, had difficulty in obtaining recognition. On Louis's death (882) Carloman became sole ruler. He died while hunting.
</Question>
<Choice>Carloman (king of France)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the younger brother of Charlemagne, with whom, at the instance of their father, Pippin III the Short, he was anointed king of the Franks in 754 by Pope Stephen II (or III) in the abbey of Saint-Denis. Carloman inherited the eastern part of Pippin's lands (768). He favoured alliance with the Lombards and married Gerberga, a daughter of their king, Desiderius. When Carloman died, Charlemagne annexed his territory and became sole ruler of the Frankish empire.
</Question>
<Choice>Carloman (king of the Franks)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the West Saxons, or Wessex (from 643), son of Cynegils. Though his father became a Christian, Cenwalh himself long remained a pagan. Soon after his succession he discarded his wife, sister of King Penda of Mercia, who retaliated by making war and driving Cenwalh into exile (645–648). While in exile in East Anglia he was baptized and, on his return to the throne in Wessex (648), built St. Peter's in Winchester. Throughout much of his reign, he fended off his enemies, the Welsh and the Mercians. The Mercians seized the Isle of Wight, southern Hampshire, and all the West Saxon lands north...
</Question>
<Choice>Cenwalh</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
founder of the West Saxon kingdom, or Wessex. All the sovereigns of England except Canute, Hardecanute, the two Harolds, and William the Conqueror are said to be descended from him. A Continental ealdorman who in 495 landed in Hampshire, Cerdic was attacked at once by the Britons. Nothing more is heard of him until 508, when he defeated the Britons with great slaughter. Strengthened by fresh arrivals of Saxons, he gained another victory in 519 at Certicesford, a spot which has been identified with the modern Charford, and in this year took the title of king. Turning westward, Cerdic appears to...
</Question>
<Choice>Cerdic</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the Franks (768–814), king of the Lombards (774–814), and emperor (800–814).
</Question>
<Choice>Charlemagne</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of France (i.e., Francia Occidentalis, the West Frankish kingdom) from 843 to 877 and Western emperor from 875 to 877. (He is reckoned as Charles II both of the Holy Roman Empire and of France.)Son of the emperor Louis I the Pious and his second wife, Judith, Charles was the unwitting cause of violent discord when, in 829, he was granted lands by his father; Louis's action precipitated a series of civil wars, lasting until 838, in which the three sons of his first marriage, Lothair I, Louis II the German, and Pippin I, strove to maintain or to increase the rights that they had been guaran...
</Question>
<Choice>Charles II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of France (893–922), whose authority came to be accepted by Lorraine and who settled the Northmen in Normandy but who became the first Carolingian ruler of the western kingdom to lose his crown.The posthumous son of Louis II the Stammerer by a marriage of contested legitimacy, Charles was passed over for the throne on the death of his half-brother, Carloman, in 884 or that of his cousin, Charles the Fat, in 888. On Jan. 28, 893, however, he was crowned king by Fulk, archbishop of Reims, as a rival to King Eudes (Odo); and, although he renounced his rights after civil war in 897, the death...
</Question>
<Choice>Charles III (king of France)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Frankish king and emperor, whose fall in 887 marked the final disintegration of the empire of Charlemagne. (Although he controlled France briefly, he is usually not reckoned among the kings of France).The youngest son of Louis the German and great-grandson of Charlemagne, Charles became king of Swabia on his father's death in 876; in 879, on the resignation of his sick brother Carloman (died 880), he took over the kingdom of Italy. He was crowned emperor by Pope John VIII in 881. Saxony fell to Charles on the death of his brother Louis the Younger (882), and Charles became king of all the East...
</Question>
<Choice>Charles III (Holy Roman emperor)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Merovingian king of Paris from 511, who helped to incorporate Burgundy into the Frankish realm.Childebert was a son of Clovis I and Clotilda. He received lands in northwestern France, stretching from the Somme down to Brittany, in the partition of his father's kingdom in 511; to these he added part of the kingdom of Orléans in the 520s (by the murder of his brother Chlodomer's young heirs), part of the kingdom of Burgundy in 534 (by conquest, with his brother Chlotar I), and Provence in 536 (by treaty from the Ostrogoths). After a campaign in 531 against the Visigoths, who still held the coast...
</Question>
<Choice>Childebert I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Merovingian king of the eastern Frankish kingdom of Austrasia and later also king of Burgundy.Still very young on the death of his father, Sigebert I, in 575, Childebert was dominated by his mother, Brunhild, who was hostile to his uncle, King Chilperic of Soissons. The intervention in 575 of a second uncle, Guntram of Burgundy, to protect Childebert's southern lands against Chilperic was followed two years later by Guntram's adoption of his young nephew as his heir. The Austrasian–Burgundian alliance was briefly broken in 581, when Chilperic too adopted Childebert, but Guntram bought off Chil...
</Question>
<Choice>Childebert II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the last Merovingian king.Effective power in France had long been wielded by the Carolingian mayors of the palace, but the revolt that followed the death of Charles Martel in 741 made it wise for his sons Carloman and Pippin III the Short, in 743, to place Childeric III, a Merovingian of questionable legitimacy, on the Frankish throne, which had been vacant since 737, so that they could dissemble their authority behind his name. Carloman entered a monastery in 747, and, when Pippin felt sufficiently secure to have himself elected king of the Franks (751), Childeric was deposed, tonsured, and c...
</Question>
<Choice>Childeric III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Merovingian king of Soissons whom Gregory of Tours, a contemporary, called the Nero and the Herod of his age.Son of Chlotar I by Aregund, Chilperic shared with his three half brothers (sons of Ingund, Aregund's sister) in the partition that followed their father's death in 561, receiving the poorest region, the kingdom of Soissons. To this was added, however, the best part of Charibert's lands on the latter's death in 567 or 568, so that Chilperic's kingdom corresponded in large part to that later known as Neustria. In 568 he repudiated his wives in order to marry Galswintha, sister of the Vis...
</Question>
<Choice>Chilperic I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Merovingian king of Soissons from 511 and of the whole Frankish kingdom from 558, who played an important part in the extension of Frankish hegemony.The youngest of Clovis I's sons, Chlotar shared in the partition of his father's kingdom in 511, receiving the old heartlands of the Salian Franks in modern northern France and Belgium. After the death of his brother, Clodomir, in 524, he murdered his nephews and shared the kingdom of Orléans with his two remaining brothers, Childebert I and Theodoric I. The deaths without heirs of the latter's grandson, Theodebald, in 555 and of Childebert in 558...
</Question>
<Choice>Chlotar I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Merovingian king of Neustria and sole ruler of the Franks from 613.An infant when his father, Chilperic I, was assassinated in 584, he was assured the succession by the power of his mother, Fredegund, and by the protection of his uncle, Guntram, king of Burgundy. Fighting off an attack by his cousin Childebert II of Austrasia-Burgundy in 592, Chlotar himself seized territory from Childebert's young successors, Theodebert II and Theodoric II, in 596 but lost much of his realm to them in 599 or 600. In 613, however, when both were dead, Austrasian hostility toward Brunhild, great-grandmother of...
</Question>
<Choice>Chlotar II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chinese general who usurped the throne of the last emperor of the Tang dynasty (618–907) and proclaimed himself the first emperor of the Hou (Later) Liang dynasty (907–923).Originally, Zhu Wen was a follower of the great Tang rebel Huang Chao (d. 884), but at an opportune time he surrendered his forces to government troops and was rewarded with the governorship of the strategic region around Kaifeng, in central China. After the defeat of Huang Chao, there ensued a struggle for control of North China between Zhu Wen and the Turkish general Li Keyong (d. 908), who had defeated Huang Chao. Zhu We...
</Question>
<Choice>Chu Wen</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Merovingian king of Orléans from 511.The eldest son of Clovis I by Clotilda, Chlodomer shared in the fourfold partition of his father's kingdom in 511, receiving lands in western and central France; his was the only one of the four kingdoms to form a single geographical unit on both sides of the Loire River. In 523, with his two full brothers, Chlotar I and Childebert I, as allies, he attacked his eastern neighbours, the Burgundians; their king, Sigismund, was captured and put to death together with his family. In the following year, Chlodomer resumed the attack, this time with his half-brothe...
</Question>
<Choice>Clodomir</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German king from 911 to 918 and member of the powerful Franconian dynasty known as the Conradines.Duke of Franconia, Conrad was elected German king on Nov. 10, 911, at Forchheim, after the death of Louis the Child, the last of the East Frankish Carolingians. It is not clear whether Conrad was supported by all the German nobles east of the Rhine or only by the Franks and Saxons. Between the East and West Frankish kingdoms, the Lotharingian nobles turned to the West Frankish Carolingian, Charles III. In 913 Conrad married Kunigunde, a member of the Alaholfing family of Swabia. His reign was a bi...
</Question>
<Choice>Conrad I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine (Eastern Roman) emperor whose reign saw the loss of Byzantium's southern and eastern provinces to the Arabs.The son of the emperor Constantine III, Constans came to the throne in September 641, at age 11, after his father's death; during his minority the regency was under the control of the Senate of Constantinople. The Muslim Arabs seized Egypt from Byzantium in the second year of his reign and invaded Armenia in 647. In 655 he fought the naval battle of Phoenix (modern Finike, Turkey) off the coast of Asia Minor; his fleet was routed, and he escaped death only through the heroism o...
</Question>
<Choice>Constans II Pogonatus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
one of the greatest of early Scottish kings, his long reign (900–943) being proof of his power during a period of dynastic conflicts and foreign invasions.During the first part of his reign the kingdom was still beset by the Norsemen. In his third year they wasted Dunkeld and all of Alba. They were repulsed, however, in Strathearn the following year. In his eighth year Rognwald, the Danish king of Dublin, with earls Ottir and Oswle Crakaban, ravaged Dunblane. Six years later the same leaders were defeated on the Tyne by Constantine in a battle whose site and incidents are told in conflicting s...
</Question>
<Choice>Constantine II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the Scots (995–997), who succeeded to the crown after the murder of his cousin, Kenneth II, son of Malcolm I. After a brief reign of two years he was himself killed, perhaps by an illegitimate son (named Kenneth) of Malcolm I or by his successor, Kenneth III.
</Question>
<Choice>Constantine III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor from 668 to 685. He was the eldest son of Constans II and became coemperor with him in 654.Constantine withstood a four-year Arab siege of Constantinople (674–678), greatly enhancing Byzantine prestige and indeed marking a turning point in European history. In the Balkans, however, he could not prevent the Bulgars from crossing the Danube River and establishing their kingdom in the area where their name still survives. He had to recognize their kingdom and pay them annual tribute. Constantine summoned the sixth ecumenical Council of Constantinople (680–681), which condemned M...
</Question>
<Choice>Constantine IV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor from 741 to 775, son of Leo III the Isaurian.Constantine was made coruler of the empire with his father in 720. Most of his life before and after his accession as sole ruler was spent in largely successful military campaigns against Arabs and Bulgars who threatened the empire. Because the empire's resources were thus engaged, the Lombards were able to take the exarchate of Ravenna in Italy (751), thus ending Byzantine influence in north and central Italy and indirectly fostering the historic alliance between the papacy and the Franks. Constantine was a strong Iconoclast (one...
</Question>
<Choice>Constantine V Copronymus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor from 780 to 797, grandson of Constantine V.At 10 years of age Constantine succeeded his father, Leo IV, under the guardianship of his mother, Irene. It was during her regency that the seventh ecumenical Council of Nicaea (787) reestablished the veneration of icons. When Constantine came of age, Irene attempted to retain supreme power; but in 790 the army proclaimed Constantine VI as sole ruler, and she was arrested. Constantine foolishly pardoned her in 792 and again accepted her as coruler. In 796 Constantine roused public opinion by divorcing his wife in order to marry his...
</Question>
<Choice>Constantine VI</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor from 913 to 959. His writings are one of the best sources of information on the Byzantine Empire and neighbouring areas. His De administrando imperio treated the Slavic and Turkic peoples, and the De ceremoniis aulae Byzantinae, his longest book, described the elaborate ceremonies that made the Byzantine emperors priestly symbols of the state.Constantine's surname, Porphyrogenitus (that is, born in the Purple Chamber of the Imperial Palace in Constantinople, as befitted legitimate children of reigning emperors), pointedly answers the doubts expressed about the legitimacy of h...
</Question>
<Choice>Constantine VII Porphyrogenitus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the West Saxons, or Wessex (611–643), in England and the first to be converted to Christianity.With his son Cwichelm (d. 636), Cynegils defeated the advancing Britons at Bampton in Oxfordshire in 614, and Cwichelm sought to arrest the growing power of the Northumbrian king Eadwine by procuring his assassination. The attempt, however, failed, and in 626 the West Saxons were defeated in battle and forced to own Eadwine's supremacy.Cynegils' next struggle was with Penda of Mercia at Cirencester in 628. There again he was defeated in battle, and he was quite probably compelled to surrender...
</Question>
<Choice>Cynegils</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the West Saxons, or Wessex (757–786), in England who succeeded to the throne following the deposition of Sigebert. Cynewulf was constantly at war with the Welsh. In 779 Offa of Mercia defeated him and took Bensington. In 785 he was surprised and killed, with all his thanes present, at Marten, in modern Wiltshire (Merantune), by Cyneheard, the brother of the deposed Sigebert.
</Question>
<Choice>Cynewulf</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the last Frankish king of the Merovingian dynasty to rule a realm united in more than name only.The son of Chlotar II, Dagobert became king of Austrasia in 623 and of the entire Frankish realm in 629. Dagobert secured his realm by making a friendship treaty with the Byzantine emperor Heraclius, defeating the Gascons and Bretons, and campaigning against the Slavs on his eastern frontier. In 631 he sent an army to Spain to help the Visigothic usurper Swinthila (Svintila). He moved his capital from Austrasia to Paris, a central location from which the kingdom could be governed more effectively. H...
</Question>
<Choice>Dagobert I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
60th emperor of Japan. He was unsuccessful in continuing his father's policy of limiting the power of the important Fujiwara family, which dominated the Japanese government from 857 to 1160.The son of the emperor Uda, he ascended the throne in 897 and assumed the reign name Daigo; Uda, however, continued to hold power as the retired emperor. Like his father, Daigo attempted to rule without appointing a Fujiwara to the post of kampaku, or chancellor, the office through which commands could be issued on behalf of the emperor. He kept the post vacant and continued his father's policy of relying o...
</Question>
<Choice>Daigo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the English from 946 to 955, who brought Northumbria permanently under English rule. Eadred was the son of the West Saxon king Edward the Elder (ruled 899–924) and Eadgifu, the half brother of King Athelstan (ruled 924–939), and the brother of King Edmund I (ruled 939–946). Upon Eadred's accession to power, the Northumbrians acknowledged his overlordship, but they soon proclaimed as their king Erik Bloodax, son of the Norwegian ruler Harald I Fairhair. In revenge Eadred ravaged all of Northumbria (948). The Northumbrians submitted to Eadred, but in 949 they accepted another Norse king,...
</Question>
<Choice>Eadred</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the Mercians and Northumbrians from 957 who became king of the West Saxons, or Wessex, in 959 and is reckoned as king of all England from that year. He was efficient and tolerant of local customs, and his reign was peaceful. He was most important as a patron of the English monastic revival.The younger son of Edmund I, king of the English, Edgar was made king of the Mercians and Northumbrians in place of Eadwig, his brother, who was deposed. On Eadwig's death (Oct. 1, 959), Edgar succeeded to the West Saxon throne. His ecclesiastical policy was also that of St. Dunstan, whom Edgar recal...
</Question>
<Choice>Edgar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the English (939–946), who recaptured areas of northern England that had been occupied by the Vikings.He was the son of the West Saxon king Edward the Elder (reigned 899–924) and Eadgifu and the half brother of King Athelstan (reigned 924–939), under whom the political unification of England had been accomplished. On Athelstan's death (939), Olaf Guthfrithson, the Norse king of Dublin, occupied Northumbria and raided the Midlands.Edmund recovered the Midlands after Olaf died in 942, and in 944 he regained Northumbria, driving out the Norse kings Olaf Sihtricson and Raegnald. He capture...
</Question>
<Choice>Edmund I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Anglo-Saxon king in England, the son of Alfred the Great. As ruler of the West Saxons, or Wessex, from 899 to 924, Edward extended his authority over almost all of England by conquering areas that previously had been held by Danish invaders.Edward ascended the throne upon his father's death in October 899, and in a battle in 902 his forces killed a rival claimant, Aethelwald, who had allied with the Danes. After defeating the Northumbrian Danes at Tettenhall, he set out in August 912 to subdue the Danes of the eastern Midlands and East Anglia. From 910 to 916 he constructed a series of fortifi...
</Question>
<Choice>Edward (Anglo-Saxon king)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of England from 975 to 978. His reign was marked by a reaction against the promonastic policies of his father and predecessor, King Edgar (reigned 959–975). Upon Edgar's death a faction sought to win the throne for his younger son, Ethelred, but Edward was quickly elected king. He evidently played little part in the antimonastic reaction, which was led by Aelfhere, ealdorman of Mercia. Edward was assassinated while visiting Ethelred in Corfe. Although Ethelred succeeded to the throne, it is not known whether he and his mother Aelfthryth (Edward's stepmother) had a hand in the murder of hi...
</Question>
<Choice>Edward (king of England)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Anglo-Saxon king of Northumbria from 616 to 633. He was the most powerful English ruler of his day and the first Christian king of Northumbria.The son of King Aelle of Deira, one of the two Northumbrian kingdoms, Edwin fled into exile when Aethelric, king of Bernicia, seized power in Deira in 588 or 590. In 616 King Raedwald of East Anglia defeated and killed Aethelric's son Aethelfrith and installed Edwin on the Northumbrian throne. Edwin conquered part of Wales and was recognized as overlord by all the other English rulers except the king of Kent.Edwin's conversion to Christianity resulted f...
</Question>
<Choice>Edwin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the West Saxons from 802 to 839, who formed around Wessex a kingdom so powerful that it eventually achieved the political unification of England (mid-10th century).The son of Ealhmund, king in Kent in 784 and 786, Egbert was a member of a family that had formerly held the West Saxon kingship. In 789 Egbert was driven into exile on the European continent by the West Saxon king Beorhtric and his ally, the powerful Mercian king Offa (d. 796). Nevertheless, Egbert succeeded to Beorhtric's throne in 802. He immediately removed Wessex from the Mercian confederation and consolidated his power...
</Question>
<Choice>Egbert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Norway (c. 930–935) and later king of Northumberland (948, 952–954). On the death of his father, Harald I Fairhair, first king of united Norway, Erik attempted to make himself sole king of Norway, defeating and slaying two of his brothers to whom vassal kingdoms had been assigned by their father; but his tyranny fostered the reaction that had set in against the strong rule of Harald. Another son, Haakon, who had been brought up in England, was invited to Norway by dissident nobles and succeeded in ejecting Erik.Much later Erik turned up in Northumbria, once a Viking stronghold but at t...
</Question>
<Choice>Erik I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
count of Paris and the first king of the West Franks (France) who was not of Merovingian or Carolingian blood.The son of Robert the Strong, from whom all the Capetian kings of France descended, Eudes successfully defended Paris against the besieging Vikings (or Normans) in 885–886 and gained election as king as a result. Internal opposition meant that his position was never secure, however, and between 893 and 897 he had to fight off the challenge of the future Charles III the Simple, who was supported by Archbishop Fulk of Reims and Count Baldwin II of Flanders. Although Eudes won a victory o...
</Question>
<Choice>Eudes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japanese regent, creator (in 880) of the post of kampaku, or chancellor, through which he acted as regent for four adult emperors until his death. This post allowed the Fujiwara family to dominate the Japanese government for more than three centuries.Mototsune's uncle, and father through adoption, Yoshifusa, had acted as regent for the child emperor Seiwa, who ascended the throne in 858. Succeeding Yoshifusa as head of the Fujiwara family in 872, Mototsune assumed the post of regent when another minor, Yozei, succeeded to the throne four years later. In order to further increase his power, Mot...
</Question>
<Choice>Fujiwara Mototsune</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
imperial courtier under whom the Fujiwara family began its three-century-long domination of the Japanese imperial government.By the middle of the 9th century the Fujiwara clan had become powerful at court, mainly because of the consistent choice of its women as imperial consorts. In 857 Yoshifusa was appointed to the influential post of great minister of state (dajo daijin), a position the court had left vacant for several generations. The following year Yoshifusa had his nine-year-old grandson placed on the throne and had himself assigned as regent (sessho), the first instance in Japan in whi...
</Question>
<Choice>Fujiwara Yoshifusa</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Merovingian king of Burgundy who strove to maintain a balance of power among his warring relations.Guntram received the kingdom of Orleans, including Burgundy in the quadripartite division of the lands of his father, Chlotar I, which took place on the king's death in 561, and added further territory when his brother, Charibert of Paris, died in 567 or 568. Well endowed with the political skills of prudence and duplicity, he strove to prevent either of his two remaining brothers, Chilperic I and Sigebert I, from gaining too great a power, allying now with the one, now with the other. After the...
</Question>
<Choice>Guntram</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
leader of a major Danish invasion of Anglo-Saxon England who waged war against the West Saxon king Alfred the Great (reigned 871–899) and later made himself king of East Anglia (reigned 880–890).Guthrum went to England in the great Danish invasion of 865, and in mid-January 878 he attacked Alfred's kingdom of Wessex. Although all Wessex was overrun, a successful counterattack by Alfred in May brought Guthrum to terms. While negotiations were in progress, Guthrum allowed himself to be baptized under the name Aethelstan, with Alfred as his godfather. The treaty was signed at Aller in present-day...
</Question>
<Choice>Guthrum</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
duke of Spoleto, who was claimant to the throne of the Holy Roman Empire in the chaotic end of the Carolingian era.His father, Guy I, duke of Spoleto, had come to Italy in the entourage of Lothar I and had successfully expanded his family's power in central and southern Italy. Eventually succeeding to the duchy, Guy II failed in his bid for the throne of the West Franks in 888, despite the support of Archbishop Fulk of Reims. He was successful, however, in defeating Berengar, king of Italy (889), and in forcing the pope to crown him as the first non-Carolingian Holy Roman emperor in 891. He is...
</Question>
<Choice>Guy II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Norwegian king and one of the most eminent Scandinavian rulers of his time. He fostered the growth of governmental institutions but failed in his attempt to Christianize the lesser Norwegian chieftains.Haakon, the youngest son of Harald I Fairhair, was brought up at the court of the English king Athelstan. At the age of 15, after his father died, he returned to Norway and deposed his half brother Erik Bloodax (reigned c. 930–935), who had earned his name by murdering seven of his eight half brothers.Haakon had been reared as a Christian in England, and he brought English missionaries to Norway...
</Question>
<Choice>Haakon I Adalsteinsfostre</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
fourth caliph of the ?Abbasid dynasty (reigned 785–786).Al-Hadi's persecution of the ?Alids, representatives of the Shi?ite sect of Islam, precipitated revolts in Medina, Egypt, and Iraq, all of which were put down brutally. Throughout his short reign, he struggled with the question of succession, attempting to annul the rights of his brother, Harun ar-Rashid, who was later to become one of the most famous rulers of the ?Abbasid dynasty. At the time of al-Hadi's death, which may have been a murder, ar-Rashid was imprisoned and then later was released to assume the caliphate.
</Question>
<Choice>Hadi, al-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Denmark from c. 958? to c. 985, credited with the first unification of the country.He was the son of Gorm the Old, the first significant figure in a new royal line centred at Jelling (North Jutland). Harald completed the country's unification begun by his father, converted the Danes to Christianity, and conquered Norway. After Harald's Baptism (c. 960) his father's pagan tomb was transformed into a Christian place of worship with a church between two great mounds; and the newly appointed Jutland bishops, under the Archbishop of Hamburg, organized the country's conversion. The Trellebor...
</Question>
<Choice>Harald I (king of Denmark)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the first king to claim sovereignty over all Norway. One of the greatest of the 9th-century Scandinavian warrior chiefs, he gained effective control of Norway's western coastal districts but probably had only nominal authority in the other parts of Norway.The son of Halvdan the Black, ruler of part of southeastern Norway and a scion of the Yngling dynasty, the ancient royal house of Sweden, Harald succeeded his father at the age of 10. His first conquest came with the suppression of a revolt in the Uplands region. A pact with Haakon, earl of Lade, enabled him to pursue conquest of the western...
</Question>
<Choice>Harald I (king of Norway)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
fifth caliph of the ?Abbasid dynasty (786–809), who ruled Islam at the zenith of its empire with a luxury in Baghdad memorialized in The Thousand and One Nights (The Arabian Nights Entertainment).
</Question>
<Choice>Harun ar-Rashid</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
a grandson of the Prophet Muhammad (the founder of Islam), the elder son of Muhammad's daughter Fa?imah. He belongs to the group of the five most holy persons of Shi?ah, those over whom Muhammad spread his cloak while calling them “The People of the House.” After his father, ?Ali, he was considered by many of his contemporaries to be the rightful heir to Muhammad's position of leadership.As a child, ?asan lived with Muhammad for seven years, and after the latter's death in 632 he was politically inactive until the end of the reign of the caliph ?Uthman ibn ?Affan (the caliph was the titular le...
</Question>
<Choice>Hasan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German king and founder of the Saxon dynasty (918–1024) who strengthened the East Frankish, or German, army, encouraged the growth of towns, brought Lotharingia (Lorraine) back under German control (925), and secured German borders against pagan incursions.The son of Otto the Illustrious, the Liudolfing duke of Saxony, Henry became duke at his father's death (912). His first marriage, to Hatheburg, daughter of Erwin, count of Merseburg, was declared invalid because she had become a nun after her first husband's death. He married Matilda, daughter of Dietrich, count of Westphalia, in 909; their...
</Question>
<Choice>Henry I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Eastern Roman emperor (610–641) who reorganized and strengthened the imperial administration and the imperial armies but who, nevertheless, lost Syria, Palestine, Egypt, and Byzantine Mesopotamia to the Arab Muslims.Heraclius was born in eastern Anatolia. His father, probably of Armenian descent, was governor of the Roman province of Africa when an appeal came from Constantinople to save the Eastern Roman Empire from the terror and incompetence of the emperor Phocas. The Governor equipped an expeditionary force and put his devout son, the blond and gray-eyed Heraclius, in command of it.In Octo...
</Question>
<Choice>Heraclius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Visigothic prince, son of Leovigild of Spain.Brought up in the Arian heresy, Hermenegild married (579) a daughter of Sigebert I of Austrasia, Ingund, a zealous orthodox Catholic. Given a separate command at his father's siege of Byzantine-held Sevilla (Seville), he was converted through the efforts of his wife and of the bishop of Sevilla, St. Leander, and almost immediately rebelled against his father. He was aided initially by the Byzantines, but Leovigild succeeded in buying them off, and Hermenegild was captured and beheaded. Most contemporary writers suggested that Hermenegild was execute...
</Question>
<Choice>Hermenegild, Saint</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the Sasanian empire (reigned 578/579–590); he was the son and successor of Khosrow I.According to one ancient source, Hormizd protected the common people while maintaining severe discipline in his army and court. When the priests demanded a persecution of the Christians, he refused on the grounds that the throne and government could be safe only with the goodwill of both religions. From his father, Hormizd inherited wars against the Byzantine Empire and the Turks. Though negotiations for peace had begun with the Byzantine emperor Maurice, Hormizd declined to cede any of his father's co...
</Question>
<Choice>Hormizd IV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
temple name (miaohao) of the seventh emperor of the Tang dynasty (618–907) of China, which during his reign (712–756) achieved its greatest prosperity and power.Li Longji was the third son of the Ruizong emperor, who was himself a son of the empress Wuhou. Li Longji was born during a period when actual power was entirely in the hands of Wuhou, although his father was nominal emperor. Enfeoffed as prince of Chu in 687, Li Longji was reenfeoffed as prince of Linzi in 693 after Wuhou's usurpation of the throne under her own name in 690. Toward the end of her reign he was appointed to several cere...
</Question>
<Choice>Hsüan Tsung</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of France from 987 to 996, and the first of a direct line of 14 Capetian kings of that country. The Capetian dynasty derived its name from his nickname (Latin capa, “cape”).Hugh was the eldest son of Hugh the Great, duke of the Franks. On his father's death in 956, Hugh Capet inherited vast estates in the regions of Paris and Orléans, extending in some places south of the Loire River. He thus became one of the most powerful vassals in the kingdom and a serious danger to the Carolingian king, Lothar. Hugh married Adelaide, daughter of William III, duke of Aquitaine, in 970, but his efforts...
</Question>
<Choice>Hugh Capet</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
chieftain called in the prologues to the Welsh lawbooks “king of all Wales.” This epithet was indeed appropriate for Hywel, particularly during the last years of his reign.Hywel became ruler of Seisyllwg (roughly the area of Dyfed and the Towy Valley) jointly with his brother Clydog after the death of their father, Cadell (c. 910), but after Clydog's death in 920 he ruled alone. Sovereignty over Dyfed in southwest Wales came to him through his wife, Elen, daughter of Llywarch ap Hyfaidd (died 904), the last king of its dynasty; he acquired Gwynedd, in northwest Wales, and probably Powis, in no...
</Question>
<Choice>Hywel Dda</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
ruler of the Khmer kingdom of Angkor (Cambodia) from 877 to about 890.Indravarman probably usurped the throne from his cousin Jayavarman III. During his reign a large reservoir was constructed at the capital city of Hariharalaya (near modern Phumi Rôluos). The lake was the first part of a vast system of reservoirs, canals, and irrigation channels eventually built to control the river system of the region and to permit the cultivation of rice on lands that would otherwise have remained unproductive. This vast irrigation system later enabled the Khmers at Angkor to maintain a densely populated a...
</Question>
<Choice>Indravarman I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Anglo-Saxon king of the West Saxons, or Wessex, from 688 to 726. One of the most powerful West Saxon rulers before Alfred the Great, Ine was the first West Saxon king to issue a code of laws, which are an important source for the structure of early English society.Ine succeeded to the throne upon the retirement of King Caedwalla, and in 694 he forced the men of Kent to pay compensation for slaying Caedwalla's brother Mul. In 710 Nunna, the king of the South Saxons, or Sussex, lent Ine aid against the Cornish Britons, but in 722 and 725 Ine took up arms against the South Saxons, who were harbou...
</Question>
<Choice>Ine</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
founder of the Khmer, or Cambodian, empire and outstanding member of the series of rulers of the Angkor period (802–1431). Among Jayavarman II's accomplishments were the deification of the Cambodian monarchy, the establishment of the devaraja cult as the official state religion, and the reunification of the old kingdom of Chenla, which he expanded and formed into the Khmer empire.Possibly of Khmer descent, Jayavarman II came from Java, where he had been in captivity or exile, to succeed to the throne as Java's vassal around 800. An unwilling puppet, he defied the Javanese and asserted Khmer in...
</Question>
<Choice>Jayavarman II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor (969–976) whose extension of Byzantine influence into the Balkans and Syria and maintenance of domestic tranquillity assured the prestige and stability of the empire for his immediate successors.Descended from an aristocratic Armenian family, John was related through his mother to the general, and later emperor, Nicephorus II Phocas. He entered the imperial army and fought with Nicephorus against the Arabs in Cilicia and Syria. Having helped Nicephorus gain the throne, he was rewarded with the supreme command of Byzantine forces in the East. His ambition for the throne later...
</Question>
<Choice>John I Tzimisces</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
temple name (miaohao) of the sixth emperor of the Tang dynasty of China. He was placed on the throne by his mother, the future empress Wuhou, in 684, before she decided to set him aside and rule the country herself in 690. This was the first such usurpation in Chinese history. Although Ruizong had been made Wuhou's heir, his brother Zhongzong, under the domination of a clique of court officials, succeeded to the throne in 705, after a palace coup overthrew the empress. A further coup led by Ruizong's son put Ruizong back on the throne in 710. He ruled for two years before abdicating to his son...
</Question>
<Choice>Jui-tsung</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor (from 518) who was a champion of Christian orthodoxy; he was the uncle and predecessor of the great emperor Justinian.Born of Illyrian peasant stock, Justin was a swineherd in his youth. At about the age of 20 he went to Constantinople, where he entered the palace guard and rose to be a patrician. Under the Byzantine emperor Anastasius I he became commander of the palace guard, with the title of count.On the death of Anastasius in July 518, Justin secured the throne. Unlike his predecessor, he supported orthodoxy, and in 518–519 he was instrumental in ending the Acacian schis...
</Question>
<Choice>Justin I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor (from 565) whose attempts to maintain the integrity of the Byzantine Empire against the encroachments of the Avars, Persians, and Lombards were frustrated by disastrous military reverses.A nephew and close adviser of the Byzantine emperor Justinian I, Justin II became emperor in November 565 following his uncle's death. He began his reign on a note of resolution and common sense; he paid state debts, remitted overdue taxes, and reduced expenditures.In the early part of his reign, Justin allowed a measure of toleration to the dissident monophysite Christians. Initially, he hop...
</Question>
<Choice>Justin II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor (527–565), noted for his administrative reorganization of the imperial government and for his sponsorship of a codification of laws known as the Codex Justinianus (534).
</Question>
<Choice>Justinian I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
last Byzantine emperor of the Heraclian dynasty. Although possessed of a despotic temperament and capable of acts of cruelty, Justinian was in many ways an able ruler, who recovered for the empire areas of Macedonia that had previously been conquered by Slavic tribesmen.On the death of his father, Constantine IV, in September 685, Justinian II became emperor at the age of 16. At the beginning of his reign he made a treaty with the Arabs whereby they paid increased tribute and agreed to joint sovereignty over Cyprus, Armenia, and Georgia. In 688/689 he led a successful expedition into Slav-occu...
</Question>
<Choice>Justinian II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ethiopian slave who, as vizier under the Ikshidid dynasty, was de facto ruler of Egypt from 946 to 966 and de jure ruler from then until his death.Kafur was originally a slave belonging to the founder of the Ikshidid dynasty, Mu?ammad ibn ?ughj. Mu?ammad recognized Kafur's talent, made him tutor to his children, and promoted him to an officer. Kafur showed outstanding military abilities in the campaigns he conducted in Syria and the Hejaz. On his deathbed Mu?ammad appointed Kafur guardian of one of his two sons, and thus Kafur became the real ruler of Egypt during the reign of Unujur (946–961)...
</Question>
<Choice>Kafur, Abu al-Misk</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
50th emperor of Japan, who established the Japanese capital at Heian-kyo, where it remained until 1868. His accomplishments laid the basis for the Heian period (794–1185).Enthroned in 781 as the emperor Kammu, he was one of the strongest rulers Japan had known for several centuries. When he assumed office, the Buddhist religious leaders, because of their immunity to taxation and their political ambitions, had grown so strong that they threatened the stability of the government. Kammu issued an edict that limited the construction of new Buddhist buildings, the entrance of people into monasterie...
</Question>
<Choice>Kammu</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
temple name (miaohao) of the founder and first emperor (618–626) of the Tang dynasty (618–907).Although Gaozu claimed to be of Chinese descent, his family was intermarried with nomadic tribes of North China. As an official of the Sui dynasty (581–618), Li Yuan was expected to suppress peasant revolts and prevent incursions of Turkish nomads into North China. With the Sui dynasty about to disintegrate, Li Yuan—urged on by Li Shimin (later the emperor Taizong), his ambitious second son—rose in rebellion in 617. Aided by Turkish allies, Li Yuan captured the capital at Chang'an. The next year, he...
</Question>
<Choice>Kao-tsu</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
temple name (miaohao) of the third emperor of the Tang dynasty and husband of the empress Wuhou. During his 34-year reign (649–683) he expanded the Tang empire into Korea.In 649 Gaozong succeeded his father, the Taizong emperor. He continued his father's foreign campaigns, conquering the Korean peninsula and making Korea a vassal state in 668. In domestic affairs he ended the lavish expenditure on palace construction carried out by his father. But he proved to be a weak ruler and in his later years was dominated by his consort, Wu Zhao (the future empress Wuhou), a former concubine of his fath...
</Question>
<Choice>Kao-tsung</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the Sasanian empire of Persia (reigned 488–496 and 498/499–531). He was a son of Firuz and succeeded Firuz' brother Balash as ruler.Time spent in youth as a hostage in the hands of the Hephthalites after their first defeat of his father gave Kavadh valuable military experience and connections, which he later turned to good use. After the deposition of his uncle Balash in AD 488, he was called to the throne. At first he was largely dependent on the feudal chief Zarmihr (elsewhere called Sokhra), but when he contrived to eliminate this over-powerful protector, the hostility of the nobles...
</Question>
<Choice>Kavadh I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first king of the united Scots of Dalriada and the Picts and so of Scotland north of a line between the Forth and Clyde rivers.Of his father, Alpin, little is known, though tradition credits him with a signal victory over the Picts by whom he was killed three months later (c. 834). Kenneth succeeded him in Dalriada and ruled in Pictavia also, ruling for 16 years. The period is obscure. The gradual union of the two kingdoms from 843 doubtless owes much to intermarriage. By the Pictish marriage custom, inheritance passed through the female. Nevertheless, Kenneth probably made some conquests amon...
</Question>
<Choice>Kenneth I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the united Picts and Scots (from 971), son of Malcolm I.He began his reign by ravaging the Britons, probably as an act of vengeance, but his name is also included among a group of northern and western kings said to have made submission to the Anglo-Saxon king Edgar in 973, perhaps at Chester; and the chronicler Roger of Wendover (Flores Historiarum, under the year 975) states that shortly afterward Kenneth received from Edgar all the land called Lothian (i.e., between the Tweed and the Forth rivers). This is the first mention of the River Tweed as the recognized border between England...
</Question>
<Choice>Kenneth II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Persian king who ruled the Sasanian empire from 531 to 579 and was remembered as a great reformer and patron of the arts and scholarship.
</Question>
<Choice>Khosrow I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
late Sasanian king of Persia (reigned 590–628), under whom the empire achieved its greatest expansion. Defeated at last in a war with the Byzantines, he was deposed in a palace revolution and executed.
</Question>
<Choice>Khosrow II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the last empress to rule Japan until the 17th century; she twice occupied the throne (749–758; 764–770). There had been a number of female rulers before Koken, but the power achieved by the Buddhist monk Dokyo during her second reign caused the Council of Ministers to preclude female succession to the throne thereafter.Koken was the daughter of the emperor Shomu; she ascended the throne in August 749, as the empress Koken, when her father abdicated. Nine years later she abdicated in favour of Prince Oi, who ruled as Emperor Junnin. In 761 she met Dokyo when he was lecturing at the imperial pal...
</Question>
<Choice>Koken</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
khan of the Bulgars (802–814) who briefly threatened the security of the Byzantine Empire. His able, energetic rule brought law and order to Bulgaria and developed the rudiments of state organization.With the defeat of the Avars by Charlemagne in 805, Krum was able to extend greatly the power of the Pannonian Bulgars. His early offensives against the Byzantines were repulsed, and in the spring of 811 his own capital at Pliska was destroyed. On July 26, 811, however, his army crushed the Byzantines, killed the emperor Nicephorus I, and opened the way for further victories. Krum besieged Constan...
</Question>
<Choice>Krum</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor (717–741), who founded the Isaurian, or Syrian, dynasty, successfully resisted Arab invasions, and engendered a century of conflict within the empire by banning the use of religious images (icons).
</Question>
<Choice>Leo III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor responsible for inaugurating the second Iconoclastic period in the Byzantine Empire.When Bardanes Turcus and Nicephorus I were fighting over the Byzantine throne in 803, Leo, son of the patrician Bardas, at first served Bardanes but later sided with Nicephorus. Leo distinguished himself as a general under Nicephorus I and Michael I and became strategos (“general”) of the Anatolikon district of the empire. He took part in the campaign of 813 against the Bulgars, but, when Michael unwisely refused the peace terms they offered, the Asian troops under Leo deserted at the Battle o...
</Question>
<Choice>Leo V</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine coemperor from 870 and emperor from 886 to 912, whose imperial laws, written in Greek, became the legal code of the Byzantine Empire.Leo was the son of Basil I the Macedonian, who had begun the codification, and his second wife, Eudocia Ingerina. Made coemperor in 870, Leo succeeded to the throne on his father's death. His foreign policy was directed mainly against the Arabs and the Bulgars. The able commander Nicephorus Phocas the Elder was recalled from his successful campaigns against the Lombards in south Italy to assist in the Balkans. After this Byzantium met with reverses in t...
</Question>
<Choice>Leo VI</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the last Arian ruler in Visigothic Spain, who did much to restore the extent and power of the Visigothic kingdom.Brother of King Athanagild (d. 567), Leovigild succeeded (568) to that part of the Visigothic kingdom that lay south of the Pyrenees. Another brother, Liuva, ruled in Septimania, but after his death (572) Leovigild became sole king. Throughout his reign he was constantly at war. He took (569) Leon and Zamora from the Suebi in the northwest and Córdoba (571–572) from the Greeks in the south. One of Leovigild's sons, Hermenegild, married Ingund, daughter of Brunhild and of the Frankis...
</Question>
<Choice>Leovigild</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Carolingian king of France from 954 to 986, the eldest son of Louis IV. He was elected king without opposition after his father's death but was dominated first by Hugh the Great and then, from 956 to 965, by his uncle, Bruno, archbishop of Cologne, whose support was invaluable but who used his influence also in the interests of Otto I, his brother, the German king, and of Hugh Capet and the other sons of Hugh the Great, Bruno's nephews.After Bruno's death, Lothar's position deteriorated. Although his relations with Hugh Capet were generally good, he had only a tiny domain and was much distract...
</Question>
<Choice>Lothar (king of France)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Frankish king of the area known as Lotharingia whose attempts to have his marriage dissolved so that he could marry his mistress caused much controversy and led to a bitter struggle between himself and Pope Nicholas I.Lothar was the second son of the Frankish emperor Lothar I, ruler of the middle portion of the former empire of Charlemagne. Upon the death of Lothar I in 855, his realm was divided among his three sons, young Lothar receiving the area west of the Rhine from the North Sea to the Alps, which became known as Lotharingia (Lotharii regnum, or Lothar's kingdom, the modern Lorraine). W...
</Question>
<Choice>Lothar (king of Lotharingia)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Frankish emperor, whose attempt to gain sole rule over the Frankish territories was checked by his brothers.The eldest son of the emperor Louis I the Pious and a grandson of Charlemagne, Lothar was made king in Bavaria after Louis succeeded Charlemagne in 814, and in 817 he was made joint emperor. Under the Ordinatio imperii, a decree issued by Louis in 817 to provide for the unity of the empire after his death, Lothar's younger brothers, Pippin and Louis (later called the German), were to receive their own kingdoms, Aquitaine and Bavaria, but were to remain under the general suzerainty of Lot...
</Question>
<Choice>Lothar I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Carolingianruler of the Franks who succeeded his father, Charlemagne, as emperor in 814 and whose 26-year reign (the longest of any medieval emperor until Henry IV [1056–1106]) was a central and controversial stage in the Carolingian experiment to fashion a new European society. Commonly called Louis the Pious, he was known to his contemporaries by the Latin names Hludovicus or Chlodovicus, which echo the Latin name of Clovis (c. 466–511), the illustrious founder of the Merovingian dynasty. Louis was appointed king of Aquitaine in 781 and was already a seasoned 35-year-old politician and milit...
</Question>
<Choice>Louis I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Francia Occidentalis (the West Frankish kingdom) from 877 until his death.Louis, the son of King Charles II the Bald, was made king of Aquitaine under his father's tutelage in 867. Charles became emperor in 875 and two years later left Louis as regent while he defended Italy for Pope John VIII. Louis was elected king of the West Franks in December 877. At a council at Troyes in 878, the Pope attempted to force Louis to take up the role of defender of the papacy, but Louis refused. Louis and his cousin Louis the Younger, ruler of the East Frankish kingdom, agreed to maintain the divisio...
</Question>
<Choice>Louis II (king of France)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the East Franks, who ruled lands from which the German state later evolved.The third son of the Carolingian emperor Louis I the Pious, Louis the German was assigned Bavaria at the partition of the empire in 817. Entrusted with the government of Bavaria in 825, he began his rule the following year. Louis took part in the revolts against his father (830–833) and joined his half-brother, Charles the Bald, in opposing the claim of his brother, Lothar I, to imperial suzerainty over the whole empire after their father's death in 840. By the Treaty of Verdun (August 843), Charles, Lothar I, a...
</Question>
<Choice>Louis II (king of the East Franks)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Frankish emperor (850–875) who, as ruler of Italy, was instrumental in checking the Arab invasion of the peninsula.The eldest son of the Frankish emperor Lothar I, who ruled the “middle realm” of what had once been Charlemagne's empire, Louis took over the administration of Italy on his father's behalf in 844 and was crowned king of the Lombards in Rome on June 15 of that year. In April 850 he was crowned emperor. When his father divided his realm in September 855, Italy was allotted to Louis. After Lothar's death a few weeks later, Louis was sole emperor, a dignity which at that time implied...
</Question>
<Choice>Louis II (emperor of Franks)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Provence and, from 901 to 905, Frankish emperor whose short-lived tenure marked the failure to restore the Carolingian dynasty to power in Italy.Louis was a son of Boso, king of Provence, and Irmingard, daughter of the Frankish emperor Louis II, the last of the elder male line of the Carolingian dynasty. The emperor Charles III the Fat took Louis under his protection on Boso's death in 887, and, although Charles was deposed that same year, Louis was recognized as king of Provence in 890. In 900 Louis was called to Italy by a group of nobles who were opposed to the rule of the Italian k...
</Question>
<Choice>Louis III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of France from 936 to 954 who spent most of his reign struggling against his powerful vassal Hugh the Great.When Louis's father, Charles III the Simple, was imprisoned in 923, his mother, Eadgifu, daughter of the Anglo-Saxon king Edward the Elder, took Louis to England. He was recalled to France in 936 and crowned on June 19 at Laon by Artand, archbishop of Reims, who became Louis's chief supporter against Hugh the Great. Louis proved not to be the puppet monarch that Hugh had anticipated; he even moved from Paris to Laon to avoid Hugh's influence. In 939 he married Gerberga, the sister o...
</Question>
<Choice>Louis IV (king of France)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
East Frankish king, the last of the East Frankish Carolingians. During his reign the country was ravaged by frequent Magyar raids, and local magnates (the ancestors of the later ducal dynasties) brought Bavaria, Franconia, Swabia, and Saxony under their sway.The only son of the East Frankish king Arnulf, Louis was declared heir to the kingdom in 897 and, after Arnulf's death (899), was crowned king in 900. Later that year a party of Lotharingians, after defeating their king, Zwentibold (Louis's half brother), in an uprising, acknowledged Louis as their sovereign.Although in theory the boy king...
</Question>
<Choice>Louis IV (king of the East Franks)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
seventh ?Abbasid caliph (813–833), known for his attempts to end sectarian rivalry in Islam and to impose upon his subjects a rationalist Muslim creed.
</Question>
<Choice>Ma'mun, al-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the Picts and Scots (Alba).Malcolm succeeded to the crown when his cousin Constantine II entered a monastery (943). He annexed Moray to the kingdom for the first time. After driving the Danes from York, the English king Edmund turned Cumbria over to Malcolm, apparently as a fief or seal of alliance. Later, when Norsemen again invaded the land, the Scots sent raids against the English, and in 954 the West Saxon king Eadred reunited the northern counties to his dominions. Malcolm was slain the same year during a rebellion in Moray.
</Question>
<Choice>Malcolm I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the chief minister and virtual ruler of the Umayyad caliphate of Córdoba for 24 years (978–1002).Man?ur was descended from a member of the Arab army that conquered Spain. He began his career as a professional letter writer, becoming the protégé (and supposedly the lover) of the mother of the young caliph Hisham II (first reign 976–1009). In 978, with the aid of his father-in-law, General Ghalib, he overthrew and succeeded the vizier (chief minister). By giving African territories local independence under Umayyad suzerainty, Man?ur reduced the drain on government resources. He replaced Slavs in...
</Question>
<Choice>Mansur, Abu 'Amir al-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the second caliph of the ?Abbasid dynasty (754–775), generally regarded as the real founder of the ?Abbasid caliphate. He established the capital city at Baghdad (762–763).Al-Man?ur was born at al-?umaymah, the home of the ?Abbasid family after their emigration from the Hejaz in 687–688. His father, Mu?ammad, was a great-grandson of ?Abbas; his mother was a Berber slave.Shortly before the overthrow of the Umayyads, the first dynasty of caliphs, by an army of rebels from Khorasan, many of whom were influenced by propaganda spread by the ?Abbasids, the last Umayyad caliph, Marwan II, arrested th...
</Question>
<Choice>Mansur, al-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first of the Marwanid caliphs of the Umayyad dynasty (reigned 684–685).A governor of Medina and the Hejaz under the caliph Mu?awiya I, where he showed unusual vigour, Marwan I was an old man in poor health when he ascended the throne himself in 684. He died of illness less than a year later. His short reign was a period of continuous battle between various factions for the caliphate. Marwan I was able to arrange the succession of his son ?Abd al-Malik by eliminating all other contenders for the caliphate. He strengthened the foundations of the Umayyad house and concentrated more power in the h...
</Question>
<Choice>Marwan I ibn al-Hakam</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
last of the Umayyad caliphs (reigned 744–750). He was killed while fleeing the forces of Abu al-?Abbas as-Saffa?, the first caliph of the ?Abbasid dynasty.The grandson of Marwan I, Marwan II was governor of Armenia and other territories for 12 years, gaining military experience which later led him to reorganize the Islamic army. In place of a clumsy system of divisions based on tribal loyalties, Marwan II created smaller, more mobile divisions of paid troops under professional commanders. Ascending to the throne in 744, he completed the reconquest of Syria by 746. However, the ?Abbasid rebelli...
</Question>
<Choice>Marwan II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
outstanding general and emperor (582–602) who helped transform the shattered late Roman Empire into a new and well-organized medieval Byzantine Empire.Maurice first entered the government as a notary but in 578 was made commander of the imperial forces in the East. Distinguished by his successes against the Persians, he was selected by the emperor Tiberius II as his successor. On Aug. 5, 582, he was made emperor and betrothed to Tiberius' daughter Constantina. He was crowned on August 13, the day preceding Tiberius' death.In the East, Maurice led his armies against Persia, reaching a satisfact...
</Question>
<Choice>Maurice</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor from 811 to 813.The son-in-law of the emperor Nicephorus I, Michael was proclaimed emperor by a coup d'etat, despite the claims of Nicephorus's son Stauracius, who had been mortally wounded in Bulgaria. Under the influence of the abbot and theologian Theodore Studites, Michael supported the proponents of the use of religious images, or icons. He recognized Charlemagne's title of emperor (Western, Holy Roman) in return for the cession to Byzantium of Venice and other cities on the Adriatic. He also ended Nicephorus's policies of fiscal austerity.When in 812 Krum, the Bulgarian...
</Question>
<Choice>Michael I Rhangabe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor and founder of the Amorian dynasty who attempted to moderate the Iconoclastic controversy that divided 9th-century Byzantium.Rising from humble origins, Michael became a military commander. He was a comrade-in-arms of Leo the Armenian, who later became Emperor Leo V (813). When, in 803, Bardanes Turcus and Nicephorus I were fighting over the imperial throne, Leo and Michael at first supported Bardanes but later deserted him and joined the cause of Nicephorus. Years later, after Leo had ascended the throne, Michael incurred the suspicion of his former friend and was imprisoned...
</Question>
<Choice>Michael II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor—last of the Amorian, or Phrygian, dynasty—whose reign was marked by the restoration of the use of icons in the Byzantine Church, and by successful campaigns against the Arabs and Slavs.Michael became a child emperor (Jan. 20, 842) upon the death of his father, Theophilus. A council of regency was set up, in which the dowager empress, Theodora, and her chief minister, Theoctistus, were the leading figures. The following year the use of icons was restored but with a conciliatory ecclesiastical policy toward the Iconoclasts. Also beginning in 843, campaigns undertaken against th...
</Question>
<Choice>Michael III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Piast prince or duke of Poland (from c. 963), who brought Poland into Christendom and expanded the state to the Baltic Sea.Mieszko accepted Christianity from Rome in 966 in order to resist forced conversion by the Germans and the incorporation of Poland into the Holy Roman Empire—the fate of Bohemia. Mieszko expanded the Polish state southward into Galicia at the expense of Bohemia and northward to the Baltic Sea through the incorporation of Pomerania. At the height of his power, Mieszko subordinated his kingdom to the papacy (990–991) in order to guarantee its ecclesiastical independence from...
</Question>
<Choice>Mieszko I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
early Islamic leader and founder of the great Umayyad dynasty of caliphs. He fought against the fourth caliph, ?Ali (Muhammad's son-in-law), seized Egypt, and assumed the caliphate after ?Ali's assassination in 661. He restored unity to the Muslim empire and made Damascus its capital. He reigned from 661 to 680.
</Question>
<Choice>Mu'awiyah I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the most powerful of the Fa?imid caliphs, whose armies conquered Egypt and who made the newly founded Al-Qahirah, or Cairo, his capital in 972–973.He was about 22 years of age when he succeeded his father, al-Mansur, in 953 with the title of al-Mu?izz. His authority was acknowledged over the greater part of the region now comprising Morocco, Algeria, and Tunisia, and he soon took the island of Sicily. In the years 958–959 he sent his general Jawhar westward to reduce Fès and other places where the authority of the Fa?imid caliph had been repudiated; after a successful expedition Jawhar advance...
</Question>
<Choice>Mu'izz, al-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
one of the greatest of the ?Abbasid caliphs (reigned 892–902), known especially for his ruthless skill in dealing with competing provincial dynasties, sects, and factions.The son of al-Muwaffaq, al-Mu?ta?id was coregent, with al-Mu?tamid, in his father's last years. He became caliph on al-Mu?tamid's death in 892, having forced him to disinherit his own son. As caliph, al-Mu?ta?id reorganized the administration and reformed finances. He concluded a peace with the ?ulunids by marrying their caliph's daughter and dealt cruelly with many other factional dynasties that had appeared, including the D...
</Question>
<Choice>Mu'tadid, al-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
eighth ?Abbasid caliph, a younger son of Harun ar-Rashid.Succeeding his brother al-Ma?mun in 833, al-Mu?ta?im was the first caliph to employ the Turkish mercenaries who later came to dominate the ?Abbasid dynasty. In 837 he crushed a revolt of Persian schismatics led by the rebel Babak, who was cooperating with the Greeks. After the Byzantine emperor Theophilus had laid waste the Muslim town of Ziba?ra (known to the Byzantines as Sozopetra), al-Mu?ta?im invaded Asia Minor, defeated Theophilus, and destroyed the fortresses of Ancyra (Ankara) and Amorium (August 838).
</Question>
<Choice>Mu'tasim, al-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor from 802 who late in his reign alienated his subjects with his extremely heavy taxation and frequent confiscations of property.Nicephorus became a high financial official under the empress Irene, and, when a revolution deposed Irene in 802, he was proclaimed emperor. In the following year he crushed a rebellion by Bardanes Turcus, a rival candidate for the throne, and in 808 he put down a similar revolt led by Arsaber.When Nicephorus withheld the tribute that Irene had agreed to pay the Baghdad caliph Harun ar-Rashid, war followed, and Arab forces defeated the Byzantine emper...
</Question>
<Choice>Nicephorus I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor (963–969), whose military achievements against the Muslim Arabs contributed to the resurgence of Byzantine power in the 10th century.
</Question>
<Choice>Nicephorus II Phocas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
one of the most powerful kings in early Anglo-Saxon England. As ruler of Mercia from 757 to 796, Offa brought southern England to the highest level of political unification it had yet achieved in the Anglo-Saxon period (5th–11th century AD). He also formed ties with rulers on the European continent.A member of an ancient Mercian ruling family, Offa seized power in the civil war that followed the murder of his cousin, King Aethelbald (reigned 716–757). By ruthlessly suppressing resistance from several small kingdoms in and around Mercia, he created a single state covering most of England south...
</Question>
<Choice>Offa</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Viking king of Norway (995–c. 1000), much celebrated in Scandinavian literature, who made the first effective effort to Christianize Norway.Olaf, the great-grandson of the Norwegian king Harald I Fairhair and the son of Tryggvi Olafsson, a chieftain in southeastern Norway, was born soon after his father was killed by the Norwegian ruler Harald II Graycloak. According to legend, Olaf fled with his mother, Astrid, to the court of St. Vladimir, grand prince of Kiev and of all Russia, and was trained as a Viking warrior. In 991 he joined in the Viking attacks on England, which were resumed with th...
</Question>
<Choice>Olaf I Tryggvason</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
semilegendary Viking (Varangian) leader who became prince of Kiev and is considered to be the founder of the Kievan Rus state.According to The Russian Primary Chronicle of the 12th century, Oleg, after succeeding his kinsman Rurik as ruler of Novgorod (c. 879), went down the Dnieper River with his Varangian retinue and seized control of Smolensk and Kiev (882), which he subsequently made his capital. Extending his authority east and west of the Volkhov–Dnieper waterway, he united the local Slavic and Finnish tribes under his rule and became the undisputed ruler of the Kievan–Novgorodian state....
</Question>
<Choice>Oleg</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
princess who was the first recorded female ruler in Russia and the first member of the ruling family of Kiev to adopt Christianity. She was canonized as the first Russian saint of the Orthodox Church.Olga was the widow of Igor I, prince of Kiev, who was assassinated (945) by his subjects while attempting to extort excessive tribute. Because Igor's son Svyatoslav was still a minor, Olga became regent of the grand principality of Kiev from 945 to 964. She soon had Igor's murderers scalded to death and hundreds of their followers killed. Olga became the first of the princely Kievans to adopt Orth...
</Question>
<Choice>Olga, Saint</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Anglo-Saxon king of Northumbria from 633 to 642 who introduced Celtic Christian missionaries to his kingdom and gained ascendancy over most of England.Oswald's father, King Aethelfrith (d. 616), had ruled the two ancient Northumbrian kingdoms of Bernicia and Deira. Expelled from Northumbria upon the accession of his uncle Edwin in 616, Oswald and his brother Oswiu took refuge in Iona in the Hebrides, where they were converted to Christianity.Edwin was killed fighting King Cadwallon of Gwynedd (in northern Wales) and Penda of Mercia in 633, but the next year Oswald defeated and killed Cadwallon...
</Question>
<Choice>Oswald, Saint</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Anglo-Saxon king of Northumbria from 655 to 670.Oswiu's father, King Aethelfrith (d. 616), had ruled the two ancient Northumbrian kingdoms of Bernicia and Deira, but after the death of Oswiu's brother, King Oswald, in 642, Northumbria was again divided, Oswiu assuming control of Bernicia. For 13 years he was subordinate to King Penda of Mercia. Finally, in 655 Penda invaded Bernicia and was killed by Oswiu's forces in the Battle of the Winwaed near Leeds in modern West Yorkshire. Oswiu then reunited Northumbria and became overlord of southern England. He annexed northern Mercia but gave southe...
</Question>
<Choice>Oswiu</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
duke of Saxony (as Otto II, 936–961), German king (from 936), and Holy Roman emperor (962–973), who consolidated the German Reich by his suppression of rebellious vassals and his decisive victory over the Hungarians. His use of the church as a stabilizing influence created a secure empire and stimulated a cultural renaissance.
</Question>
<Choice>Otto I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German king from 961 and Holy Roman emperor from 967, sole ruler from 973, son of Otto I and his second wife, Adelaide.Otto, a cultivated man, continued his father's policies of promoting a strong monarchy in Germany and of extending the influence of his house in Italy. In 961 he was crowned co-regent king of Italy and Germany with his father and was made co-regent emperor in 967. On April 14, 972, he married the Byzantine princess Theophano. At his father's death in 973 he was accepted without opposition as successor, although revolts in the duchy of Bavaria and in Lorraine occupied the early...
</Question>
<Choice>Otto II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German king and Holy Roman emperor who planned to recreate the glory and power of the ancient Roman Empire in a universal Christian state governed from Rome, in which the pope would be subordinate to the emperor in religious as well as in secular affairs.Son of the Holy Roman emperor Otto II and Empress Theophano, Otto III was elected German king in June 983 and crowned at Aachen in December, shortly after his father's death. But the child king was seized by Henry II the Quarrelsome, the deposed duke of Bavaria, in an attempt to secure the regency, if not the throne, for himself. In May 984, h...
</Question>
<Choice>Otto III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
founder of the Christian kingdom of Asturias in northern Spain, which survived through the period of Moorish hegemony to become the spearhead of the Christian Reconquista in the later Middle Ages.Pelayo's historical personality is overshadowed by his legend. As far as can be ascertained, he was a page, or possibly a member of the royal bodyguard, of the Visigothic king Roderick, and he may have been of royal blood. He survived the defeat (711) of the Visigoths by the Moors at the Battle of Guadalete near Medina Sidonia and reached his native Asturias, where he led a revolt of Asturians and Vis...
</Question>
<Choice>Pelayo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Anglo-Saxon king of Mercia from about 632 until 655, who made Mercia one of the most powerful kingdoms in England and temporarily delayed the rise of Northumbria.In 628 Penda defeated a West Saxon people known as the Hwicce at the Battle of Cirencester (in present-day Gloucestershire) and annexed their territory. He and King Cadwallon of Gwynedd (in northern Wales) invaded Northumbria in 632 and defeated and killed the Northumbrian king Edwin. That victory carried Penda into the Mercian kingship, but in 633 he was forced to recognize Northumbrian overlordship. Penda did not recover his indepen...
</Question>
<Choice>Penda</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
centurion of modest origin, probably from Thrace, who became the late Roman, or Byzantine, emperor in 602.Following an army rebellion against the emperor Maurice in 602, Phocas was sent to Constantinople as spokesman. There he took advantage of revolts in the capital to get himself chosen emperor in place of Maurice, who, together with his son, was executed. Phocas enjoyed good relations with Rome, his recognition of the primacy of the pope in matters of religion winning him praise from Pope Gregory I. Having made peace with the Avars (604) by agreeing to pay them an increased annual tribute,...
</Question>
<Choice>Phocas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Carolingian king of Aquitaine.The son of Pippin I of Aquitaine (d. 838), he was forced to fight for his inheritance. He gained the throne about 845 after defeating King Charles II the Bald, who had received authority over Aquitaine from Louis the Pious. War soon broke out again, however, and Charles slowly advanced through Aquitaine. Pippin took refuge with Sancho, duke of the Gascons, but in 852 was handed over to Charles, tonsured, and relegated to a monastery. Escaping in 854, he renewed the struggle, but in 859 the Aquitanians began to abandon him. Thereafter on the defensive and a wandere...
</Question>
<Choice>Pippin II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the first king of the Frankish Carolingian dynasty and the father of Charlemagne. A son of Charles Martel, Pippin became sole de facto ruler of the Franks in 747 and then, on the deposition of Childeric III in 751, king of the Franks. He was the first Frankish king to be anointed—first by St. Boniface and later (754) by Pope Stephen II.
</Question>
<Choice>Pippin III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Leon and Asturias in Christian Spain from 931 to 951. The second son of King Ordoño II, he became king on the abdication of his elder brother, Alfonso IV. Ramiro was an exceptional general who scored several major victories (e.g., the Battle of Simancas, 939) over the caliphate of Córdoba in Muslim Spain. In 944 he negotiated a five-year truce with the caliph ?Abd ar-Ra?man III. He failed, however, to suppress the Castilian separatist movement led by Fernán González, the first count of unified Castile, a region that eventually came to dominate Spain militarily, politically, and linguis...
</Question>
<Choice>Ramiro II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
younger son of Robert the Strong of Neustria and briefly king of France (922–923), or West Francia. His decisive victory over the Northmen at Chartres (911) led to a treaty settling one group of these fierce warriors in Normandy.Robert faithfully served his older brother, King Eudes, during Eudes's reign (888–898), as margrave. Though on Eudes's death he became one of the most powerful Frankish lords, inheriting all the family lands between the Seine and the Loire rivers, he swore fealty with other magnates to the new king, the Carolingian Charles III the Simple. From 911 onward, his role beca...
</Question>
<Choice>Robert I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the last Visigothic king of Spain, who died in the Muslim invasion.Roderick's predecessor, King Witiza, died in 710, leaving two young sons, for whom Witiza's widow and family tried to secure the succession. But a faction of the Visigothic nobles elected Roderick and drove the Witizans from Toledo. Roderick seems to have been dux (duke) or military commander of one of the provinces, perhaps Baetica. He faced a revolt of the Basques and was never recognized in every region of Spain. Meanwhile, Witiza's family had made contact with the Muslims. From North Africa the Muslims sent over a raiding p...
</Question>
<Choice>Roderick</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor who shared the imperial throne with his son-in-law Constantine VII and exercised all real power from 920 to 944. Romanus was admiral of the Byzantine fleet on the Danube when, hearing of the defeat of the army at Achelous (917), he resolved to sail for Constantinople. Soon after the marriage of his daughter Helena to Constantine he was crowned colleague of his son-in-law. His reign was terminated by his own sons, Stephen and Constantine, who in 944 compelled him to become a monk.
</Question>
<Choice>Romanus I Lecapenus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor from 959 to 963. The son of Constantine VII Porphyrogenitus, Romanus was a politically incapable ruler who left affairs of state to the eunuch Joseph Bringas and military affairs to Nicephorus Phocas; Nicephorus became emperor after Romanus' death with the help of Romanus' widow, Theophano.
</Question>
<Choice>Romanus II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Burgundy (912–937) who ruled Italy for nearly four years (923–926) during the chaotic period at the end of the Carolingian era.The son of Rudolf I, founder of the kingdom of Jurane (Upper) Burgundy (i.e., the part of Burgundy north of Provence), and a descendant of the Welf (Guelf) family, Rudolf II was offered the throne of Italy by Italian nobles disaffected with their king, Berengar of Friuli. Crowned at Pavia in 922, Rudolf fought and defeated Berengar near Piacenza. After Berengar's murder (924), Rudolf ruled both Jurane Burgundy and Italy, residing alternately in the two kingdoms...
</Question>
<Choice>Rudolf II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
tsar of western Bulgaria, or Macedonia, from 997; his realm was the successor of the first Bulgarian empire.Samuel began his effective rule in the 980s in western Bulgaria. (His state initially corresponded with the geographic region of Macedonia, and some Macedonian scholars have argued that this state was distinctly Macedonian; other scholars dismiss this characterization of early Macedonian ethnic awareness. SeeResearcher's Note: Macedonia: the provenance of the name.) Samuel then conquered independent Serbia and further extended his power into northern Bulgaria, Albania, and northern Greec...
</Question>
<Choice>Samuel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
45th emperor of Japan, who devoted huge sums of money to the creation of magnificent Buddhist temples and artifacts throughout the realm; during his reign Buddhism virtually became the official state religion.He ascended the throne in 724, taking the reign name Shomu. In 729 his consort, a member of the powerful Fujiwara family, was declared empress, shattering the precedent that all empress consorts had to be princesses of the blood. Shomu and his wife were both devout Buddhists, and he attempted to create a Buddhist structure throughout the country that would parallel the existing nationwide...
</Question>
<Choice>Shomu</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
influential regent of Japan and author of some of the greatest contributions to Japanese historiography, constitutional government, and ethics.Shotoku was a member of the powerful Soga family and was the second son of the short-reigned emperor Yomei. When political maneuvering brought his aunt to the throne, Shotoku became crown prince and regent in 593. He remained in that position until his death. One of his first acts was to resume sending envoys to China, a practice that had been discontinued since the 5th century, thus opening up avenues for cultural, economic, and political exchange. He...
</Question>
<Choice>Shotoku, Taishi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Frankish king of the Merovingian dynasty, son of Chlotar I and Ingund; he successfully pursued a civil war against his half brother, Chilperic I.When Chlotar I died in 561, his kingdom was divided, in accordance with Frankish custom, among his four sons; Sigebert became king of the northeastern portion, known as Austrasia, as well as of portions of Aquitaine and Provence, to which he added further territory on the death of his brother, Charibert I, in 567 or 568. Incursions by the Avars, a fierce nomadic tribe, compelled him twice to repel their attacks (562 and c. 568). About 566 he married B...
</Question>
<Choice>Sigebert I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
tsar of the first Bulgarian empire (925–927), a warlike sovereign who nevertheless made his court a cultural centre.Educated in Constantinople (now Istanbul), Simeon succeeded his father, Boris I, in 893 after the short intervening reign (889–893) of his dissolute elder brother, Vladimir.His dominant ambition, which was to himself ascend the imperial throne of Byzantium—an aspiration afterward shared by many Bulgarian tsars—led Simeon to embark on many wars with the Byzantine Empire (894, 896, 913, 917, 923). He never took Constantinople, although it was more than once at his mercy; but he too...
</Question>
<Choice>Simeon I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Tibetan king (crowned 629) who extended his dominion to include Nepal and parts of India and China and whose reign marked the beginning of recorded history in Tibet. He commissioned a court scholar to create the Tibetan written language using an Indo-European model for the script. Because two of his wives, a Nepalese and a Chinese princess, were Buddhists, he is credited by lama historians with introducing Buddhism into Tibet. To house the famous image of the Gautama Buddha brought to Tibet by his Nepalese bride, he built in Lhasa, the capital, the Tsuglagkhang, or Gtsug-lag-khang (Jokhang), T...
</Question>
<Choice>Srong-brtsan-sgam-po</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
grand prince of Kiev from 945 and the greatest of the Varangian princes of early Russo-Ukrainian history.He was the son of Grand Prince Igor, who was himself probably the grandson of Rurik, prince of Novgorod. Svyatoslav was the last non-Christian ruler of the Kievan state. After coming of age he began a series of bold military expeditions, leaving his mother, Olga, to manage the internal affairs of the Kievan state until her death in 969.The Russian Primary Chronicle (Povest vremennykh let) says that Svyatoslav “sent messengers to the other lands announcing his intention to attack them.” Betw...
</Question>
<Choice>Svyatoslav I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Denmark (c. 987–1014), a leading Viking warrior and the father of Canute I the Great, king of Denmark and England. Sweyn formed an imposing Danish North Sea empire, establishing control in Norway in 1000 and conquering England in 1013, shortly before his death.The son of the Danish king Harald Bluetooth (Blåtand), Sweyn rebelled in 987 against his father, who fled to Wendland (in Germany). Sweyn began feuding with Olaf I after the latter's accession to the Norwegian throne in 995, and he allied with the Swedish king Olaf Skötkonung and with the Norwegian Erik, the earl of Lade. The thr...
</Question>
<Choice>Sweyn I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
temple name (miaohao) of the Chinese emperor (reigned 960–976), military leader, and statesman who founded the Song dynasty (960–1279). He began the reunification of China, a project largely completed by his younger brother and successor, the Taizong emperor.
</Question>
<Choice>T'ai-tsu</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
temple name (miaohao) of the second emperor (reigned 626–649) of the Tang dynasty (618–907) of China.Li Shimin was the second son of the dynastic founder, the Gaozu emperor. Traditional historians have portrayed him as the driving force behind his father's uprising against the doomed Sui dynasty in 617, but powerful evidence shows that his was a minor role. In the initial campaign to take the Sui capital, he and his elder brother, Li Jiancheng, were both Tang commanders. Li Shimin distinguished himself as a general and strategist and was largely responsible for the conquest of the eastern capi...
</Question>
<Choice>T'ai-tsung</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
38th emperor of Japan, from 668 to 672, and the ruler who freed the Japanese court from the domination of the Soga family. Tenji implemented a series of reforms that strengthened the central government in accord with the Chinese model and restored power to the emperor.The Soga family had begun to dominate the Imperial family in the late 6th century AD, and by 645 it appeared that Iruka, the son of the head of the Soga clan, would attempt to usurp the throne for himself. Nakano Oe, then an Imperial prince, conspired with Nakatomi Kamatari, the head of the powerful Nakatomi family, to murder Iru...
</Question>
<Choice>Tenji</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Merovingian king of Reims who succeeded his father, Theodoric I, in late 533 and greatly expanded the area under Frankish hegemony.A proven soldier before he came to the throne, Theodebert exploited the war in Italy between Byzantium and the Ostrogoths to gain extensive territory in the Alpine regions and the northeast of the peninsula, though most of this was lost after his death. With expansion also in the east, Theodebert claimed control of peoples from the Baltic to beyond the Danube. By minting gold coins bearing his, rather than the Byzantine emperor's, effigy and name, Theodebert assert...
</Question>
<Choice>Theodebert I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Merovingian king of Austrasia.Theodebert succeeded his father, Childebert II, on the throne of Austrasia in 595 while his brother, Theodoric II, mounted that of Burgundy. Their grandmother Brunhild exercised at first a joint regency over both kingdoms, but in 599 the Austrasian aristocracy confined her power to Burgundy. After early cooperation against their cousin, Chlotar II of Neustria—whom they defeated at Dormelles (near Montereau) in 600—and against the Basques (602), the brothers fell out. When Chlotar attacked Burgundy in 605, Austrasia stood aloof, and in 610 Theodebert seized Theodor...
</Question>
<Choice>Theodebert II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine empress, wife of the emperor Justinian I (reigned 527–565), probably the most powerful woman in Byzantine history. Her intelligence and political acumen made her Justinian's most trusted adviser and enabled her to use the power and influence of her office to promote religious and social policies that favoured her interests.Little is known of Theodora's early life, but a combination of the official version with that found in the highly coloured Secret History of Procopius of Caesarea probably provides the best explanation. Her father was a bear keeper at the Hippodrome (circus) in Con...
</Question>
<Choice>Theodora</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the Ostrogoths (from 471), who invaded Italy in 488 and completed the conquest of virtually the entire peninsula and Sicily by 493, making himself king of Italy (493–526) and establishing his capital at Ravenna. In German and Icelandic legend, he is the prototype of Dietrich von Bern (q.v.).
</Question>
<Choice>Theodoric</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Merovingian king of Reims from 511. Theodoric was the eldest son of Clovis I, but born of an unknown woman, unlike the other sons, whose mother was Clotilda. An able soldier, he played an important part in his father's campaigns against the Visigoths. On Clovis's death in 511 a fourfold division of his kingdom took place, each of his sons receiving some territories north of the Loire River and some to its south. No doubt as the most experienced of the four, Theodoric received those northern lands (the future Austrasia) most exposed to attack and the largest share overall; their axis was the Rh...
</Question>
<Choice>Theodoric I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
younger son of the Merovingian Childebert II; he succeeded his father as king of Burgundy in 595, at first under his grandmother Brunhild's regency and later under her influence. Cooperation with his brother, Theodebert II of Austrasia, was followed by discord, and in 612 Theodoric, supported by Brunhild, overthrew his brother. He died shortly afterward, and Brunhild then attempted to install his young son, Sigebert II, as successor. Her efforts failed, however, and she fell in a rebellion led by Chlotar II, who then reunified Frankish lands under his authority.
</Question>
<Choice>Theodoric II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Merovingian ruler who succeeded his brother Chlotar III as king of Neustria and Burgundy in 673, at the instigation of Ebroin, the Neustrian mayor of the palace. He was soon deposed by another brother, Childeric II, was restored in 675, then was momentarily deposed again in favour of a certain Clovis (allegedly Chlotar III's son), but recovered his throne in 676 and finally (679) also became king of Austrasia. A puppet pure and simple, he then had to watch his subjects fight one another until the final victory of Pippin II and the Austrasians at the Battle of Tertry in 687.
</Question>
<Choice>Theodoric III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor from 715 to 717. He was an obscure tax collector of southwestern Asia Minor who against his will was proclaimed emperor by the troops of the Opsikion theme rebelling against Anastasius II. His supporters successfully captured Constantinople, and Anastasius was deposed and entered a monastery. Theodosius was quite unsuited to imperial office and in 717 was forced to abdicate by the able commander of the Anatolikon troops, Leo III the Isaurian, and ended his life in a monastery at Ephesus.
</Question>
<Choice>Theodosius III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Eastern Roman emperor (829–842), principal promoter of the 9th-century Byzantine renascence of learning, and the last advocate of the Eastern heresy of Iconoclasm (the destruction of religious images) in a reign beset by Arab invasions.The son of the emperor Michael II, of the Phrygian dynasty traditionally favourable to Iconoclasm, Theophilus was liberally educated by the Byzantine scholar and ardent Iconoclast John Philoponus. He was also much influenced by the learned court of the early 9th-century caliph of Baghdad Harun ar-Rashid.Theophilus was crowned as co-emperor in 820 and shortly the...
</Question>
<Choice>Theophilus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Byzantine emperor from 578 who succeeded in defending the empire against the Persians to the east but suffered reverses in conflicts with the Avars and the Slavs to the north and west.Tiberius served in campaigns against the Avars in the Balkans under Justin II. About the year 574, Justin became subject to fits of insanity; the empress Sophia and Tiberius then took over control of the government. Justin adopted Tiberius as his son, named him Caesar on Dec. 7, 574, and crowned him emperor (Sept. 26, 578). Justin died soon after (October 4), leaving Tiberius sole ruler.Meanwhile, in 578, Byzanti...
</Question>
<Choice>Tiberius II Constantinus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ostrogoth king who recovered most of central and southern Italy, which had been conquered by the Eastern Roman Empire in 540.A relative of Theudis, king of the Visigoths, Totila was chosen king by Gothic chiefs in the autumn of 541 after King Witigis had been carried off prisoner to Constantinople. Totila proved himself both as a general and as a political leader, winning the support of the lower classes by freeing slaves and distributing land to the peasants. By 543, fighting on land and sea, he had retaken the bulk of the lost territory. Rome held out, and Totila appealed fruitlessly to the...
</Question>
<Choice>Totila</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
59th emperor of Japan, from 887 to 897.The son of the emperor Koko, Uda was one of the few rulers during this period whose mother was not a member of the Fujiwara family, which, partly through intermarriage with the imperial line, dominated Japan from 859 to 1160. During the first part of Uda's reign, Mototsune, the head of the Fujiwara house, occupied the post of kampaku, or chief councillor, through which he could issue commands on behalf of the emperor. After Mototsune's death in 891, Uda kept the post vacant, selecting his advisers from members of minor Japanese noble families.In 897 Uda a...
</Question>
<Choice>Uda</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the second Muslim caliph (from 634), under whom Arab armies conquered Mesopotamia and Syria and began the conquest of Iran and Egypt.A member of the clan of ?Adi of the Meccan tribe of Quraysh (Koreish), ?Umar at first opposed Mu?ammad but, about 615, became a Muslim. By 622, when he went to Medina with Mu?ammad and the other Meccan Muslims, he had become one of Mu?ammad's chief advisers, closely associated with Abu Bakr. His position in the state was marked by Mu?ammad's marriage to his daughter Hafsa in 625. On Mu?ammad's death in 632 ?Umar was largely responsible for reconciling the Medinan...
</Question>
<Choice>'Umar I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
pious and respected caliph who attempted to preserve the integrity of the Muslim Umayyad caliphate (661–750) by emphasizing religion and a return to the original principles of the Islamic faith.His father, ?Abd al-?Aziz, was a governor of Egypt, and through his mother he was a descendant of ?Umar I (second caliph, 634–644). He received a traditional education in Medina and won fame for his piety and learning. In February or March 706, ?Umar was appointed governor of the Hejaz. During his tenure of office, he initiated policies that later characterized his reign, particularly his creation of a...
</Question>
<Choice>'Umar II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
third caliph to rule after the death of the Prophet. He centralized the administration of the caliphate and established an official version of the Qur?an. ?Uthman is critically important in Islamic history because his death marked the beginning of open religious and political conflicts within the Islamic community (see fitnah).?Uthman was born into the rich and powerful Umayyad clan of Mecca, and he became a wealthy merchant. When Mu?ammad began preaching in Mecca c. 615, he soon aroused the hostility of the Umayyads, but about five years later ?Uthman accepted Mu?ammad and thus became the fir...
</Question>
<Choice>'Uthman ibn 'Affan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
grand prince of Kiev (Kyiv) and first Christian ruler in Kievan Rus, whose military conquests consolidated the provinces of Kiev and Novgorod into a single state, and whose Byzantine baptism determined the course of Christianity in the region.Vladimir was the son of the Norman-Rus prince Svyatoslav of Kiev by one of his courtesans and was a member of the Rurik lineage dominant from the 10th to the 13th century. He was made prince of Novgorod in 970. On the death of his father in 972, he was forced to flee to Scandinavia, where he enlisted help from an uncle and overcame Yaropolk, another son o...
</Question>
<Choice>Vladimir I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
sixth caliph (reigned 705–715) of the Umayyad Arab dynasty, who is best known for the mosques constructed during his reign.Al-Walid, the eldest son of the caliph ?Abd al-Malik ibn Marwan, was fervently orthodox in his religious views, and he had a great interest in architecture. As caliph, he confiscated the Christian Basilica of St. John the Baptist in Damascus and had the Great Mosque (Umayyad Mosque) erected on the site. He also had mosques built at Medina and Jerusalem. During al-Walid's reign, areas in Central Asia, in coastal northern Africa, and in Spain were conquered and brought under...
</Question>
<Choice>Walid, al-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prince of Bohemia, martyr, and patron saint of Czechoslovakia.Wencelas was raised a Christian by his grandmother St. Ludmila, but his ambitious mother, Drahomíra (Dragomir), a pagan, had her murdered and acted as regent herself, until Wenceslas came of age in 924 or 925. Her court intrigues and the wishes of the people to end the conflicts between Christian and non-Christian factions in Bohemia led Wenceslas to take the reins of government. As duke he was pious, reportedly taking the vow of virginity, and encouraged the work of German missionary priests in the Christianization of Bohemia. His...
</Question>
<Choice>Wenceslas I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
posthumous name (shi) of the emperor (reigned 581–604) who reunified and reorganized China after 300 years of instability, founding the Sui dynasty (581–618). He conquered southern China, which long had been divided into numerous small kingdoms, and he broke the power of the Turks in the northern part of the country.
</Question>
<Choice>Wen-ti</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ostrogoth soldier who became king of Italy and led his people in an unsuccessful last-ditch struggle against the Eastern Roman Empire.Witigis was elected king in the autumn of 536 to replace Theodahad, who had been deposed and killed as the Byzantine general Belisarius advanced on Rome. Leaving a small garrison to defend Rome, Witigis massed his forces in Ravenna, where he married Matasuntha, granddaughter of King Theodoric, to strengthen the legality of his own position. In Witigis' absence, Pope Silverius turned Rome over to Belisarius.In March 537 Witigis returned to besiege Rome, cutting t...
</Question>
<Choice>Witigis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
posthumous name (shi) of the woman who rose from concubinage to become empress of China during the Tang dynasty (618–907). She ruled effectively for many years, the last 15 (690–705) in her own name. During her reign, Tang rule was consolidated, and the empire was unified.Wu Zhao entered the palace of the Tang emperor Taizong (ruled 626–649) in 638, at the age of 14, as a junior concubine. By that time, the Tang dynasty had recently reunited China, largely through the efforts of Taizong. Little is known of Wu's life as a concubine of Taizong, but, on his death in 649, she is traditionally said...
</Question>
<Choice>Wu Hou</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
posthumous name (shi) of the founder and first emperor (502–549) of the Nan (Southern) Liang dynasty (502–557), which briefly held sway over South China. A great patron of Buddhism, he helped establish that religion in the south of China.Wudi was a relative of the emperor of the Nan Qi dynasty (479–502), one of the Six Dynasties that existed in South China in the turbulent period between the Han (206 BC–AD 220) and Tang (618–907) dynasties. He led a successful revolt against the Nan Qi after his elder brother was put to death by the emperor. He proclaimed himself first emperor of the Liang dyn...
</Question>
<Choice>Wu-ti</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
posthumous name (shi) of the second and penultimate emperor (604–617/618) of the Sui dynasty (581–618). Under the Yangdi emperor canals were built and great palaces erected.He acceded to the throne in 604, and it is generally agreed that he did so after assassinating his father (the Wendi emperor) and his elder brother. Embarking on a costly program of construction and conquest, in 608 he built a great canal between the rice-producing areas in the south and the Beijing area in the north. Yangdi extended this transportation system in 610, beginning the Grand Canal network that was later used to...
</Question>
<Choice>Yang Ti</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the last king of the Sasanian dynasty (reigned 632–651), the son of Shahryar and a grandson of Khosrow II.A mere child when he was placed on the throne, Yazdegerd never actually exercised power. In his first year the Arab invasion began, and in 636/637 the Battle of al-Qadisiyah on one of the Euphrates canals decided the fate of the empire. His capital, Ctesiphon, was occupied by the Arabs, and Yazdegerd fled into Media, where his generals unsuccessfully attempted to organize resistance. After the Battle of Nahavand (642), in which Sasanian forces were badly defeated, Yazdegerd sought refuge i...
</Question>
<Choice>Yazdegerd III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
second Umayyad caliph (680–683), particularly noted for his suppression of a rebellion led by ?usayn, the son of ?Ali. The death of ?usayn at the Battle of Karbala? (680) made him a martyr and made permanent a division in Islam between the party of ?Ali (the Shi?ites) and the majority Sunnis.As a young man, Yazid commanded the Arab army that his father, Mu?awiyah, sent to lay siege to Constantinople. Soon afterward he became caliph, but many of those whom his father had kept in check rebelled against him.Although presented in many sources as a dissolute ruler, Yazid energetically tried to cont...
</Question>
<Choice>Yazid I</Choice>
</item>
</topics>