<topics>
<item>
<Question>
Palestinian guerrilla leader (b. 1948/49?, near Haifa?, Palestine/Israel?—d. March 8/9, 2004, near Baghdad, Iraq), was best known as the mastermind behind the 1985 hijacking of the Italian cruise ship Achille Lauro, during which a wheelchair-bound American Jewish man, Leon Klinghoffer, was shot and pushed into the sea; this act brought worldwide condemnation, and Abbas was sentenced in absentia to life in prison in Italy. Abbas grew up in a Palestinian refugee camp in Syria and, under the nom de guerre Abu Abbas, became a rising star in Ahmad Jibril's Popular Front for the Liberation of Palest...
</Question>
<Choice>Abbas, Abu</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
black American pastor and civil-rights leader who was Martin Luther King's chief aide and closest associate during the Civil Rights Movement of the 1950s and '60s.The son of a successful farmer, Abernathy was ordained as a Baptist minister in 1948 and graduated with a B.S. degree from Alabama State University in 1950. His interest then shifted from mathematics to sociology, and he earned an M.A. degree in the latter from Atlanta University in 1951. That same year he became pastor of the First Baptist Church in Montgomery, Ala., and he met King a few years later when the latter became pastor of...
</Question>
<Choice>Abernathy, Ralph David</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Arabic“Father of the Struggle”militant leader of the Fatah Revolutionary Council, more commonly known as the Ab? Ni??l Organization (ANO), or Ab? Ni??l Group, a Palestinian organization that engaged in numerous acts of terrorism beginning in the mid-1970s.Ab? Ni??l and his family fled Palestine after the 1948 war following the creation of the state of Israel, and for the next 20 years he lived in Jordan and Saudi Arabia. In the late 1960s he joined Y?sir ?Araf?t's guerrilla group, Fatah, a component of the Palestine Liberation Organization (PLO), which had as its aim wresting Palestine from Is...
</Question>
<Choice>Abu Nidal</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American first lady (1797–1801), the wife of John Adams, second president of the United States, and mother of John Quincy Adams, sixth president of the United States. She was a prolific letter writer whose correspondence gives an intimate and vivid portrayal of life in the young republic.Born to William Smith, a Congregational minister, and Elizabeth Quincy Smith, Abigail was the second of four children. Educated entirely at home, she read widely in her father's large library, and the constant flow of interesting, intelligent, and well-educated guests at the Smith home turned her into a learne...
</Question>
<Choice>Adams, Abigail</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American professional boxer and social activist. Ali was the first fighter to win the world heavyweight championship on three separate occasions; he successfully defended this title 19 times.Cassius Marcellus Clay, Jr., grew up in the American South in a time of segregated public facilities. His father, Cassius Marcellus Clay, Sr., supported a wife and two sons by painting billboards and signs. His mother, Odessa Grady Clay, worked as a household domestic.When Clay was 12 years old, he took up boxing under the tutelage of Louisville policeman Joe Martin. After advancing through the amateur ran...
</Question>
<Choice>Ali, Muhammad</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
leader of the Harijans (untouchables or low-caste Hindus) and law minister of the government of India (1947–51).Born of an untouchable Mahar family of western India, he was as a boy humiliated by his high-caste schoolfellows. His father was an officer in the Indian Army. Awarded a scholarship by the Gaekwar (the ruler) of Baroda (now Vadodara), he studied at universities in the United States, Britain, and Germany. He entered the Baroda Public Service at the Gaekwar's request, but, again ill-treated by his high-caste colleagues, he turned to legal practice and teaching. He soon established his...
</Question>
<Choice>Ambedkar, Bhimrao Ramji</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American poet whose several volumes of autobiography explore the themes of economic, racial, and sexual oppression.Although born in St. Louis, Angelou spent much of her childhood in the care of her paternal grandmother in rural Stamps, Arkansas. Raped at the age of eight by her mother's boyfriend, she went through an extended period of muteness. This early life is the focus of Angelou's first autobiographical work, I Know Why the Caged Bird Sings (1970). Subsequent volumes of autobiography include Gather Together in My Name (1974), Singin' and Swingin' and Gettin' Merry Like Christmas (1976),...
</Question>
<Choice>Angelou, Maya</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
hero and principal leader of armed Jewish resistance in the Warsaw ghetto during World War II.Anielewicz was born into a working-class family and attended a Hebrew academic secondary school. As a boy he joined Betar, a Zionist youth organization that among other things advocated self-defense for Jews. By 1940 he had gone to Warsaw and become active in a pro-Soviet group of young Zionists, Hashomer Hatzair. When Germany invaded Poland, he escaped to Vilna (now Vilnius), which the Soviet Union had annexed with Lithuania. He eventually made his way back to the Warsaw ghetto, where he set up an un...
</Question>
<Choice>Anielewicz, Mordecai</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
pioneer crusader for the woman suffrage movement in the United States and president (1892–1900) of the National American Woman Suffrage Association. Her work helped pave the way for the Nineteenth Amendment (1920) to the Constitution, giving women the right to vote.Anthony was reared in the Quaker tradition in a home pervaded by a tone of independence and moral zeal. She was a precocious child and learned to read and write at the age of three. After the family moved from Massachusetts to Battensville, New York, in 1826, she attended a district school, then a school set up by her father, and fi...
</Question>
<Choice>Anthony, Susan B.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Myanmar opposition leader, daughter of Aung San (a martyred national hero of independent Burma) and Khin Kyi (a prominent Burmese diplomat), and winner in 1991 of the Nobel Prize for Peace.Aung San Suu Kyi was two years old when her father, then the de facto prime minister of what would shortly become independent Burma, was assassinated. She attended schools in Burma until 1960, when her mother was appointed ambassador to India. After further study in India, she attended the University of Oxford, where she met her future husband. She had two children and lived a rather quiet life until 1988, w...
</Question>
<Choice>Aung San Suu Kyi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
founder of the Black Consciousness Movement in South Africa. His death from injuries suffered while in police custody made him an international martyr for South African black nationalism.After being expelled from high school for political activism, Biko enrolled in and graduated (1966) from St. Francis College, a liberal boarding school in Natal, and then entered the University of Natal Medical School. There he became involved in the multiracial National Union of South African Students (NUSAS), a moderate organization that had long espoused the rights of blacks. He soon grew disenchanted with...
</Question>
<Choice>Biko, Stephen</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
On May 20, 2002, Irish rock singer and songwriter Bono and U.S. Secretary of the Treasury Paul O'Neill embarked on an 11-day economic mission to Africa, visiting Ghana, South Africa, Uganda, and Ethiopia. Although the pairing might seem unlikely, Bono had for many years been a strong advocate of aid to less-developed countries and had gained considerable knowledge on the subject. The men were not in harmony on the best use of aid money in Africa, however. O'Neill favoured investments in African enterprises, while Bono preferred debt relief and aid given directly to organizations and individual...
</Question>
<Choice>Bono</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
militant American abolitionist whose raid on the federal arsenal at Harpers Ferry, Virginia (now in West Virginia), in 1859 made him a martyr to the antislavery cause and was instrumental in heightening sectional animosities that led to the American Civil War (1861–65).Moving about restlessly through Ohio, Pennsylvania, Massachusetts, and New York, Brown was barely able to support his large family in any of several vocations at which he tried his hand: tanner, sheep drover, wool merchant, farmer, and land speculator. Though he was white, in 1849 Brown settled with his family in a black communi...
</Question>
<Choice>Brown, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
West-Indian-born civil-rights activist, leader of black nationalism in the United States in the 1960s and originator of its rallying slogan, “black power.”Carmichael immigrated to New York City in 1952, attended high school in the Bronx, and enrolled at Howard University in 1960. There he joined the Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (SNCC) and the Nonviolent Action Group. In 1961 Carmichael was one of several Freedom Riders who traveled through the South challenging segregation laws in interstate transportation. For his participation he was arrested and jailed for about 50 days in Jack...
</Question>
<Choice>Carmichael, Stokely</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
organizer of migrant American farmworkers and founder of the National Farm Workers Association (NFWA) in 1962.Chavez, who was a farm labourer himself, grew up in a migrant farm-labour family of Mexican American descent. He lived in a succession of migrant camps and attended school sporadically. After two years in the U.S. Navy during World War II, Chavez returned to migrant farmwork in Arizona and California. His initial training as an organizer was provided by the Community Services Organization (CSO) in California, a creation of Saul Alinsky's Industrial Areas Foundation. In 1958 Chavez beca...
</Question>
<Choice>Chavez, Cesar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
lawyer whose work as defense counsel in many dramatic criminal trials earned him a place in American legal history. He was also well-known as a public speaker, debater, and miscellaneous writer.Darrow attended law school for only one year before being admitted to the Ohio bar in 1878. He moved to Chicago in 1887 and immediately took part in attempts to free the anarchists charged with murder in the Haymarket Riot (May 4, 1886). Through his friendship with Judge John Peter Altgeld, afterward governor of Illinois, Darrow was appointed Chicago city corporation counsel in 1890, and then he became...
</Question>
<Choice>Darrow, Clarence</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
African American who was one of the most eminent human-rights leaders of the 19th century. His oratorical and literary brilliance thrust him into the forefront of the U.S. abolition movement, and he became the first black citizen to hold high rank in the U.S. government.Separated as an infant from his slave mother (he never knew his white father), Frederick lived with his grandmother on a Maryland plantation until, at age eight, his owner sent him to Baltimore to live as a house servant with the family of Hugh Auld, whose wife defied state law by teaching the boy to read. Auld, however, declar...
</Question>
<Choice>Douglass, Frederick</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American sociologist, the most important black protest leader in the United States during the first half of the 20th century. He shared in the creation of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP) in 1909 and edited The Crisis, its magazine, from 1910 to 1934. Late in life he became identified with communist causes.
</Question>
<Choice>Du Bois, W.E.B.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Iranian lawyer, writer, and teacher, who received the Nobel Prize for Peace in 2003 for her efforts to promote democracy and human rights, especially those of women and children in Iran. She was the first Muslim woman and the first Iranian to receive the award.Ebadi was born into an educated Iranian family; her father was an author and a lecturer in commercial law. When she was an infant, her family moved to Tehr?n. Ebadi attended Anoshiravn Dadgar and Reza Shah Kabir schools before earning a law degree, in only three and a half years, from the University of Tehr?n (1969). That same year she t...
</Question>
<Choice>Ebadi, Shirin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American black civil-rights activist, whose murder received national attention and made him a martyr to the cause of the civil rights movement.Evers served in the U.S. Army in Europe during World War II. Afterward he and his elder brother, Charles Evers, both graduated from Alcorn Agricultural and Mechanical College (now Alcorn State University, Lorman, Miss.) in 1950. They settled in Philadelphia, Miss., and engaged in various business pursuits—Medgar was an insurance salesman, and Charles operated a restaurant, a gas station, and other enterprises—and at the same time began organizing local...
</Question>
<Choice>Evers, Medgar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American civil rights activist who, as a leader of the Congress of Racial Equality (CORE), helped shape the civil rights movement through his nonviolent activism and organizing of sit-ins and Freedom Rides, which broadened popular support for passage of the Civil Rights and Voting Rights acts in the mid-1960s.Farmer was educated at Wiley College in Marshall, Texas (1938), and at Howard University in Washington, D.C. (1941), where his father taught divinity. A conscientious objector on religious grounds, he received a military deferral in World War II, and he joined the pacifist Fellowship of R...
</Question>
<Choice>Farmer, James</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sikh religious leader who became the foremost campaigner for Sikh rights in post-independence India.Fateh Singh spent most of his early career in social and educational activities around Sri Gang?nagar in R?jasth?n, western India. In the 1940s he, Tara Singh, and other Sikh leaders joined the Quit India movement, a confederation of Indians determined to force Great Britain to give up India. India gained its independence in 1947, and by 1955 Fateh Singh and Tara Singh were advocating the establishment of Punjabi Suba, a Punjabi-speaking autonomous state in India in which Sikh religious, cultura...
</Question>
<Choice>Fateh Singh, Sant</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
leader of the Indian nationalist movement against British rule, considered to be the father of his country. He is internationally esteemed for his doctrine of nonviolent protest to achieve political and social progress.Gandhi was the youngest child of his father's fourth wife. His father, Karamchand Gandhi, who was the dewan (chief minister) of Porbandar, the capital of a small principality in Gujarat in western India under British suzerainty, did not have much in the way of a formal education. He was, however, an able administrator who knew how to steer his way between the capricious princes,...
</Question>
<Choice>Gandhi, Mohandas Karamchand</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American journalistic crusader who published a newspaper, The Liberator (1831–65), and helped lead the successful abolitionist campaign against slavery in the United States.Garrison was the son of an itinerant seaman who subsequently deserted his family. The son grew up in an atmosphere of declining New England Federalism and lively Christian benevolence—twin sources of the abolition movement, which he joined at age 25. As editor of the National Philanthropist (Boston) in 1828 and the Journal of the Times (Bennington, Vermont) in 1828–29, he served his apprenticeship in the moral reform cause....
</Question>
<Choice>Garrison, William Lloyd</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian businessman, philanthropist, and vigilant fighter for the rights of his Jewish co-religionists in the teeth of persecution by the Russian government. His father was the philanthropist Joseph Günzburg. His son David became a prominent Orientalist and bibliophile.For a time, Horace Günzburg ran the banking firm that his father had founded, but he closed it during a financial crisis, even though it was solvent. In 1863, along with his father, he founded the Society for the Promotion of Culture Among the Jews of Russia, a highly successful organization that disseminated Jewish culture in t...
</Question>
<Choice>Günzburg, Horace, Baron</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jewish philanthropist, banker, and financier who contributed much to the industrialization of 19th-century Russia and who successfully fought some of the discriminatory measures against Jews in Russia. His son Horace carried on his philanthropic work, and his grandson David was a well-known Orientalist and bibliophile.After an early career as a contractor for the government, he founded a banking firm in 1859 in St. Petersburg. Along with other wealthy Russian Jewish families, he also financed the building of much of Russia's railroad network. He was created a baron in the early 1870s.Günzburg...
</Question>
<Choice>Günzburg, Joseph, Baron</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
militant Palestinian and leader of the Popular Front for the Liberation of Palestine (PFLP).?abash was forced to flee Palestine in 1948, after the State of Israel was established there, and earned a medical degree at the American University of Beirut. In the early 1950s he was active in the “Youth of Vengeance” group, which advocated violent attacks on traditional Arab governments. ?abash founded the militant PFLP after his goal to liberate Palestine through Arab unity proved unrealistic following the Arab defeat by Israel in the Six-Day War of 1967 (seeArab-Israeli wars). Under the leadership...
</Question>
<Choice>Habash, George</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Czech playwright, poet, and political dissident, who, after the fall of communism, was president of Czechoslovakia (1989–92) and of the Czech Republic (1993–2003).Havel was the son of a wealthy restaurateur whose property was confiscated by the communist government of Czechoslovakia in 1948. As the son of bourgeois parents, Havel was denied easy access to education but managed to finish high school and study on the university level. He found work as a stagehand in a Prague theatrical company in 1959 and soon began writing plays with Ivan Vysko?il. By 1968 Havel had progressed to the position o...
</Question>
<Choice>Havel, Václav</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
founder of the political form of Zionism, a movement to establish a Jewish homeland. His pamphlet The Jewish State (1896) proposed that the Jewish question was a political question to be settled by a world council of nations. He organized a world congress of Zionists that met in Basel, Switz., in August 1897 and became first president of the World Zionist Organization, established by the congress. Although Herzl died more than 40 years before the establishment of the State of Israel, he was an indefatigable organizer, propagandist, and diplomat who had much to do with making Zionism into a pol...
</Question>
<Choice>Herzl, Theodor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish-born American songwriter and organizer for the Industrial Workers of the World (IWW); his execution for an alleged robbery-murder made him a martyr and folk hero in the radical American labour movement.Born into a conservative Lutheran family, all of whom were amateur musicians, Hill left Sweden for the United States in 1902. He drifted around the country, from job to job, and in 1910 joined the San Pedro (Calif.) local of the Industrial Workers of the World, soon becoming its secretary. The following year his first and most famous folksong, “The Preacher and the Slave,” appeared in th...
</Question>
<Choice>Hill, Joe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American lawyer and educator instrumental in laying the legal groundwork that led to U.S. Supreme Court rulings outlawing racial segregation in public schools.Houston graduated as one of six valedictorians from Amherst College (B.A., 1915). After teaching for two years at Howard University in Washington, D.C., he enlisted in the U.S. Army and was commissioned a second lieutenant in field artillery and served in France and Germany during World War I.Following his discharge in 1919, Houston enrolled at Harvard Law School (LL.B., 1922; D.J.S., 1923), where he was the first black editor of the Har...
</Question>
<Choice>Houston, Charles Hamilton</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American labour leader and activist whose work on behalf of migrant farmworkers led to the establishment of the United Farm Workers of America.When Huerta was a child she moved to Stockton, California, with her mother and siblings after her parents' divorce. She remained in touch with her father, Juan Fernández, and took pride in his personal and professional development from coal miner to migrant labourer to union activist to an elected representative in the New Mexico state legislature to college graduate. Unlike most Hispanic women of her era, she went on to college, after graduating from S...
</Question>
<Choice>Huerta, Dolores</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Zionist leader, journalist, orator, and man of letters who founded the militant Zionist Revisionist movement that played an important role in the establishment of the State of Israel.Jabotinsky began his career in 1898 as a foreign correspondent, but his popularity as a journalist led to his recall to Odessa in 1901 as an editorial writer. By 1903 Jabotinsky began to expound Zionist views for the restoration and creation of a Jewish national state in Palestine both in his writings and in his oratory, of which he was a master. During the next decade, he continued to work as a journalist while t...
</Question>
<Choice>Jabotinsky, Vladimir</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American civil rights leader, Baptist minister, and politician whose bids for the U.S. presidency (in the Democratic Party's nomination races in 1983–84 and 1987–88) were the most successful by an African American until 2008, when Barack Obama captured the Democratic presidential nomination. Jackson's life and career have been marked by both accomplishment and controversy.Jesse adopted the name of his stepfather, Charles Jackson, at about age 15. A good student in high school, Jesse was elected class president and later attended the University of Illinois (1959–60) on a football scholarship. H...
</Question>
<Choice>Jackson, Jesse</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American civil rights activist, who was the wife of Martin Luther King, Jr.Coretta Scott graduated from Antioch College in Yellow Springs, Ohio, and in 1951 enrolled at the New England Conservatory of Music in Boston. While working toward a degree in voice, she met Martin Luther King, Jr., then a graduate theology student at Boston University. They were married in 1953 and had four children.After both had completed their studies, the Kings moved to Montgomery, Alabama, where Martin Luther King had accepted a position as pastor of the Dexter Avenue Baptist Church. Coretta Scott King joined her...
</Question>
<Choice>King, Coretta Scott</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Baptist minister and social activist who led the civil rights movement in the United States from the mid-1950s until his death by assassination in 1968. His leadership was fundamental to that movement's success in ending the legal segregation of African Americans in the South and other parts of the United States. King rose to national prominence as head of the Southern Christian Leadership Conference, which promoted nonviolent tactics, such as the massive March on Washington (1963), to achieve civil rights. He was awarded the Nobel Peace Prize in 1964.
</Question>
<Choice>King, Martin Luther, Jr.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian writer and politician, outspoken in his advocacy of a militant anti-British nationalism in the Indian National Congress (Congress Party) and as a leader of the Hindu supremacy movement.After studying law at the Government College in Lahore, Lajpat Rai practiced at Hissar and Lahore, where he helped to establish the nationalistic Dayananda Anglo-Vedic School and became a follower of Dayananda Sarasvati, the founder of the conservative Hindu society Arya Samaj (“Society of Aryans”). After joining the Congress Party and taking part in political agitation in the Punjab, Lajpat Rai was depor...
</Question>
<Choice>Lajpat Rai, Lala</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Kenyan politician and environmental activist who was awarded the 2004 Nobel Prize for Peace, becoming the first black African woman to win a Nobel Prize. Her work was often considered both unwelcome and subversive in her own country, where her outspokenness constituted stepping far outside traditional gender roles.Maathai was educated in the United States at Mount St. Scholastica College (now Benedictine College; B.S. in biology, 1964) and at the University of Pittsburgh (M.S., 1966). In 1971 she received a Ph.D. at the University of Nairobi, effectively becoming the first woman in either East...
</Question>
<Choice>Maathai, Wangari</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
African American leader and prominent figure in the Nation of Islam, who articulated concepts of race pride and black nationalism in the early 1960s. After his assassination, the widespread distribution of his life story—The Autobiography of Malcolm X (1965)—made him an ideological hero, especially among black youth.
</Question>
<Choice>Malcolm X</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
black nationalist and first black president of South Africa (1994–99). His negotiations in the early 1990s with South African Pres. F.W. de Klerk helped end the country's apartheid system of racial segregation and ushered in a peaceful transition to majority rule. Mandela and de Klerk were jointly awarded the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1993 for their efforts.
</Question>
<Choice>Mandela, Nelson</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Native American leader and activist, the first woman chief of a major tribe.Mankiller was of Cherokee, Dutch, and Irish descent; the name Mankiller derives from the high military rank achieved by a Cherokee ancestor. She grew up on Mankiller Flats, the farm granted to her grandfather as part of a government settlement after the forced relocation of his tribe. After the failure of the farm, the family moved to California. During the 1960s Mankiller studied sociology and got a job as a social worker. In 1969 she became active in the Native American Rights movement. She moved back to Oklahoma to...
</Question>
<Choice>Mankiller, Wilma Pearl</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
lawyer, civil rights activist, and associate justice of the Supreme Court of the United States (1967–91), the first African American member of the Supreme Court. As an attorney, he successfully argued before the U.S. Supreme Court the case of BrownBoard of Education of Topeka (1954), which declared unconstitutional racial segregation in American public schools.Marshall was the son of William Canfield Marshall, a railroad porter and a steward at an all-white country club, and Norma Williams Marshall, an elementary school teacher. He graduated with honours from Lincoln University (Pennsylvania)...
</Question>
<Choice>Marshall, Thurgood</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Guatemalan Indian-rights activist, who was awarded the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1992.Menchú, of the Quiché Maya group, spent her childhood helping with her family's agricultural work; she also likely worked on coffee plantations. As a young woman, she became an activist in the local women's rights movement and joined with the Catholic church to advocate for social reform. The activism of Menchú and her family led to persecution by Guatemala's military government. When a guerrilla organization became active in their region, her father, a leader of a peasant organization opposed to the governmen...
</Question>
<Choice>Menchú, Rigoberta</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American civil rights activist who gained national renown at a key juncture in the civil rights movement in 1962, when he became the first African American student at the University of Mississippi. State officials, initially refusing a U.S. Supreme Court order to integrate the school, blocked Meredith's entrance, but, following large campus riots that left two people dead, Meredith was admitted to the university under the protection of federal marshals.Meredith served in the U.S. Air Force (1951–60) before attending an all-black school, Jackson State College (1960–62). His repeated application...
</Question>
<Choice>Meredith, James</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American politician and gay-rights activist.After graduating from the New York State College for Teachers in Albany (1951), Milk served in the U.S. Navy during the Korean War and was discharged in 1955 (Milk later said that he was dishonourably discharged due to his homosexuality, but military records do not support this claim). He held several jobs before becoming a financial analyst in New York. In 1972 he moved to San Francisco, where he opened a camera store and soon gained a following as a leader in the gay community. His popularity grew when he challenged the city's gay leadership, which...
</Question>
<Choice>Milk, Harvey</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
political activist, feminist, poet-writer, and the first Indian woman to be president of the Indian National Congress and to be appointed an Indian state governor. She was sometimes called “the Nightingale of India.”Sarojini was the eldest daughter of Aghorenath Chattopadhyay, a Bengali Brahman who was principal of the Nizam's College, Hyderabad. She entered the University of Madras at the age of 12 and studied (1895–98) at King's College, London, and later at Girton College, Cambridge.After some experience in the suffragist campaign in England, she was drawn to India's Congress movement and t...
</Question>
<Choice>Naidu, Sarojini</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
militant champion of woman suffrage whose 40-year campaign achieved complete success in the year of her death, when British women obtained full equality in the voting franchise. Her daughter Christabel Harriette (afterward Dame Christabel) Pankhurst (1880–1958) also was prominent in the woman suffrage movement.In 1879 Emmeline Goulden married Richard Marsden Pankhurst, lawyer, friend of John Stuart Mill, and author of the first woman suffrage bill in Great Britain (late 1860s) and of the Married Women's Property acts (1870, 1882). Ten years later she founded the Women's Franchise League, which...
</Question>
<Choice>Pankhurst, Emmeline</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
African American civil rights activist whose refusal to relinquish her seat on a public bus to a white man precipitated the 1955–56 Montgomery bus boycott in Alabama, which is recognized as the spark that ignited the U.S. civil rights movement.In 1932 she married Raymond Parks, who encouraged her to return to high school and earn a diploma. She later made her living as a seamstress. In 1943 Parks became a member of the Montgomery chapter of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP), and she served as its secretary until 1956. On December 1, 1955, she was arrested f...
</Question>
<Choice>Parks, Rosa</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American woman suffrage leader who introduced the first equal rights amendment campaign in the United States.Paul was reared in a Quaker home. She graduated from Swarthmore College (1905) and pursued postgraduate studies at the New York School of Social Work. She then went to England to do settlement work (1906–09), and during her stay there she was jailed three times for suffragist agitation. She also continued to do postgraduate work at the Universities of Birmingham and London and received degrees from the University of Pennsylvania (M.A., 1907, in absentia; Ph.D., 1912). Returning to the U...
</Question>
<Choice>Paul, Alice</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian politician and spokesman for the untouchables, a low-caste Hindu social class in India.Ram was born into an untouchable family and was among the first of his caste to receive a higher education. He attended Benaras Hindu University and the University of Calcutta (B.Sc., 1931), becoming a member of Mohandas K. Gandhi's Indian National Congress party in 1931. He played a role in the founding (1935) of the All-India Depressed Classes League, an organization dedicated to attaining equality for untouchables. During the late 1930s he also was elected to a position in the Bihar government and...
</Question>
<Choice>Ram, Jagjivan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
East Timorese political activist who, along with Bishop Carlos F.X. Belo, received the 1996 Nobel Prize for Peace for their efforts to bring peace and independence to East Timor, a former Portuguese possession that was under Indonesian control from 1975 to 1999. Ramos-Horta became prime minister of East Timor in 2006 and president in 2007.Ramos-Horta's mother was a native Timorese, and his father was a Portuguese national who was deported to East Timor for participating in a revolt against the dictator António Salazar. After studying law in the United States, Ramos-Horta returned to East Timor...
</Question>
<Choice>Ramos-Horta, José</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American first lady (1933–45), the wife of Franklin D. Roosevelt, 32nd president of the United States, and a United Nations diplomat and humanitarian. She was, in her time, one of the world's most widely admired and powerful women.Eleanor was the daughter of Elliott Roosevelt and Anna Hall Roosevelt and the niece of Theodore Roosevelt, 26th president of the United States. She grew up in a wealthy family that attached great value to community service. Both her parents died before she was 10, and she and her surviving brother (another brother died when she was 9) were raised by relatives. The de...
</Question>
<Choice>Roosevelt, Eleanor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian religious, social, and educational reformer who challenged traditional Hindu culture and indicated the lines of progress for Indian society under British rule. He is sometimes called the father of modern India.
</Question>
<Choice>Roy, Ram Mohun</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Soviet nuclear theoretical physicist, an outspoken advocate of human rights, civil liberties, and reform in the Soviet Union as well as rapprochement with noncommunist nations. In 1975 he was awarded the Nobel Prize for Peace.Sakharov was born into the Russian intelligentsia. His father, Dmitry Sakharov, taught physics at several Moscow schools and institutes and wrote popular scientific works and textbooks. A man of principle, he had an enormous effect on his son. His mother, Ekaterina, remained at home and took care of the family. Andrey Sakharov was tutored at home for several years and ent...
</Question>
<Choice>Sakharov, Andrey Dmitriyevich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American leader in the women's rights movement who in 1848 formulated the first organized demand for woman suffrage in the United States.Elizabeth Cady received a superior education at home, at the Johnstown Academy, and at Emma Willard's Troy Female Seminary, from which she graduated in 1832. While studying law in the office of her father, Daniel Cady, a U.S. congressman and later a New York Supreme Court judge, she learned of the discriminatory laws under which women lived and determined to win equal rights for her sex. In 1840 she married Henry Brewster Stanton, a lawyer and abolitionist (s...
</Question>
<Choice>Stanton, Elizabeth Cady</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American social activist who was cofounder and first president of the National Association of Colored Women. She was an early civil rights advocate, an educator, an author, and a lecturer on woman suffrage and rights for African Americans.Mary Church was the daughter of Robert Reed Church and Louisa Ayers Church, both former slaves prominent in the growing black community of Memphis, Tennessee. Both parents owned small, successful businesses, and they provided “Mollie” and her brother with advantages that few other African American children of her time enjoyed. She received a bachelor's degree...
</Question>
<Choice>Terrell, Mary Eliza Church</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
African American evangelist and reformer who applied her religious fervour to the abolitionist and women's rights movements.Isabella was the daughter of slaves and spent her childhood as an abused chattel of several masters. Her first language was Dutch. Between 1810 and 1827 she bore at least five children to a fellow slave named Thomas. Just before New York state abolished slavery in 1827, she found refuge with Isaac Van Wagener, who set her free. With the help of Quaker friends, she waged a court battle in which she recovered her small son, who had been sold illegally into slavery in the So...
</Question>
<Choice>Truth, Sojourner</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American bondwoman who escaped from slavery in the South to become a leading abolitionist before the American Civil War. She led hundreds of bondsmen to freedom in the North along the route of the Underground Railroad—an elaborate secret network of safe houses organized for that purpose.Born a slave, Araminta Ross later adopted her mother's first name, Harriet. From early childhood she worked variously as a maid, a nurse, a field hand, a cook, and a woodcutter. About 1844 she married John Tubman, a free black.In 1849, on the strength of rumours that she was about to be sold, Tubman fled to Phi...
</Question>
<Choice>Tubman, Harriet</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
South African Anglican cleric who in 1984 received the Nobel Prize for Peace for his role in the opposition to apartheid in South Africa.Tutu was born of Xhosa and Tswana parents and was educated in South African mission schools at which his father taught. Though he wanted a medical career, Tutu was unable to afford training and instead became a schoolteacher in 1955. He resigned his post in 1957. He then attended St. Peter's Theological College in Johannesburg and was ordained an Anglican priest in 1961. In 1962 he moved to London, where in 1966 he obtained an M.A. from King's College, London...
</Question>
<Choice>Tutu, Desmond</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
labour activist who helped form and led (1980–90) communist Poland's first independent trade union, Solidarity. The charismatic leader of millions of Polish workers, he went on to become the president of Poland (1990–95). He received the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1983.Wa??sa, the son of a carpenter, received only primary and vocational education and in 1967 began work as an electrician at the huge Lenin Shipyard in Gda?sk. He witnessed the 1970 food riots in Gda?sk in which police killed a number of demonstrators. When new protests against Poland's communist government erupted in 1976, Wa??sa e...
</Question>
<Choice>Walesa, Lech</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Australian Aboriginal writer and political activist, considered the first of the modern-day Aboriginal protest writers. Her first volume of poetry, We Are Going (1964), is the first book by an Aboriginal woman to be published.Raised on Stradbroke Island (Minjerribah), off Moreton Bay, Queensland, where many of the ancient Aboriginal customs were still practiced, the child baptized as Kathleen Ruska was a member of the Noonuccal tribe. Her formal education ended with primary school; at age 13 she entered domestic service in Brisbane. At age 16 she was rejected for nurse's training because of he...
</Question>
<Choice>Walker, Kath</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
African American journalist who led an antilynching crusade in the United States in the 1890s.Ida Wells was the daughter of slaves. She was educated at Rust University, a freedmen's school in her native Holly Springs, Mississippi, and at age 14 began teaching in a country school. She continued to teach after moving to Memphis, Tennessee, in 1884 and attended Fisk University in Nashville during several summer sessions. In 1887 the Tennessee Supreme Court, reversing a Circuit Court decision, ruled against Wells in a suit she had brought against the Chesapeake &amp; Ohio Railroad for having been...
</Question>
<Choice>Wells-Barnett, Ida Bell</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
black American civil-rights leader who served as the executive director (1955–77) of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP). He was often referred to as the senior statesman of the U.S. Civil Rights Movement.After graduation from the University of Minnesota, Minneapolis (1923), Wilkins became a reporter and later managing editor of the Kansas City Call, a newspaper serving the black community. Joining the staff of the NAACP in 1931, he edited its official publication, The Crisis, between 1934 and 1949 and simultaneously directed the NAACP antidiscrimination prog...
</Question>
<Choice>Wilkins, Roy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Northern Irish peace activist who, with Máiread Maguire and Ciaran McKeown, founded the Peace People, a grassroots movement dedicated to ending the sectarian strife in Northern Ireland. For her work, Williams shared with Maguire the 1976 Nobel Prize for Peace.Williams, an office worker and wife and mother, took little part in public life until August 1976, when she witnessed an incident that moved her to speak out. An Irish Republican Army terrorist was shot by British troops while fleeing in a car, and the car went out of control and struck several people, killing three children. Williams imm...
</Question>
<Choice>Williams, Betty</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American activist who helped found the International Campaign to Ban Landmines (ICBL). In 1997 she and the campaign were named corecipients of the Nobel Prize for Peace.In 1984 Williams received a master's degree from Johns Hopkins School of Advanced International Studies in Washington, D.C. She was a co-coordinator of the Nicaragua-Honduras Education Project (1984–86) and deputy director of Medical Aid for El Salvador (1986–92). In October 1992, with the cooperation of six international organizations, she coordinated the launch of the ICBL with the mission of abolishing the use of antipersonn...
</Question>
<Choice>Williams, Jody</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English writer and passionate advocate of educational and social equality for women.The daughter of a farmer, Wollstonecraft taught school and worked as a governess, experiences that inspired her views in Thoughts on the Education of Daughters (1787). In 1788 she began working as a translator for the London publisher James Johnson, who published several of her works, including the novel Mary: A Fiction (1788). Her mature work on woman's place in society is A Vindication of the Rights of Woman (1792), which calls for women and men to be educated equally.In 1792 Wollstonecraft left England to ob...
</Question>
<Choice>Wollstonecraft, Mary</Choice>
</item>
</topics>