<topics>
<item>
<Question>
(1404–72). Humanist, architect, and principal initiator of Renaissance art theory, the Italian Leon Battista Alberti is considered a typical example of the Renaissance “universal man.” He belonged to a wealthy merchant-banker family of Florence and at the age of 10 or 11 was sent to boarding school in Padua. There Alberti was given a classical...
</Question>
<Choice>Alberti, Leon Battista</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
The school of design, architecture, and applied arts known as the Bauhaus was founded in Weimar, Germany, in 1919. It was based in Weimar until 1925, Dessau through 1932, and Berlin in its final months in 1933.
</Question>
<Choice>Bauhaus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1598–1680). Perhaps the greatest sculptor of the 17th century and one of its outstanding architects, Gian Lorenzo Bernini created the baroque style of sculpture. He developed it to such an extent and it became so admired and popular that it continued for at least two more generations in various parts of Europe, and 18th-century Italian sculpture...
</Question>
<Choice>Bernini, Gian Lorenzo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1599–1667). The Italian architect Francesco Borromini believed that space must be controlled totally. This is illustrated in his works by walls that are broken by niches, in dynamic forms that produce wavelike effects, and in external turrets that seem to add movement. Planning in terms of brick, stucco, and travertine and creating effects...
</Question>
<Choice>Borromini, Francesco</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1444–1514). In the last years of his life, Donato Bramante introduced what came to be known as the High Renaissance style in architecture. In later generations the Italian-born Bramante was recognized as the first to understand the principles of ancient architecture and reshape its classical forms to meet the needs of his own time. His style was...
</Question>
<Choice>Bramante, Donato</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1377–1446). “A man of great genius,” as his tomb inscription states, Filippo Brunelleschi is known as the originator of the Renaissance architectural style. He created new forms from classical Roman, Tuscan, and Italian late Gothic models with some Byzantine influences evident. He was trained as a goldsmith, acquired great skill as a sculptor...
</Question>
<Choice>Brunelleschi, Filippo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Early in the Middle Ages when Latin was still the language of religious and political life in western Europe, a Christian church that contained the official “seat” or throne (cathedra) of a bishop was known as the ecclesia cathedralis, or “church of the throne.” As time went on ecclesia cathedralis was shortened into “cathedral,” the modern word...
</Question>
<Choice>cathedral</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1887–1965). A revolutionary influence in modern architecture and urban planning, Le Corbusier was also a painter, sculptor, and writer. His was a classic definition of architecture: “the conscious, correct, and magnificent interplay of volumes assembled under light.”
</Question>
<Choice>Le Corbusier</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1475–1564). Sculptor, painter, architect, and poet Michelangelo was the greatest artist in a time of greatness. He lived during the Italian Renaissance, a period known for its creative activity. Civilization made huge strides in science and invention, in literature, and in politics. In art, the age's great achievement, Michelangelo led all...
</Question>
<Choice>Michelangelo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1886–1969). One of the most influential architects of the 20th century, Ludwig Mies van der Rohe epitomized the International Style that emerged in the late 1920s. His rectilinear forms, crafted in elegant simplicity, are the result of his two famous axioms: “Less is more” and “God is in the details.” He was also a noted designer of furniture...
</Question>
<Choice>Mies van der Rohe, Ludwig</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1508–80). One of the most influential figures in the history of Western architecture was Andrea Palladio. He was considered the best architect of 16th-century Italy. He is known for his palaces, villas, and churches as well as for his treatise ‘The Four Books of Architecture', published in 1570. In all of his work Palladio combined the finest...
</Question>
<Choice>Palladio, Andrea</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1632–1723). Having one of the greatest minds of his age, Christopher Wren could have become famous in any one of several fields. He had become a professor of astronomy before he was 30. It was more by accident than intention that he became England's greatest architect.
</Question>
<Choice>Wren, Christopher</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(1867–1959). Considered the most influential architect of his time, Frank Lloyd Wright designed about 1,000 structures. He described his “organic architecture” as one that “proceeds, persists, creates, according to the nature of man and his circumstances as they both change.” As a pioneer whose ideas were well ahead of his time, Wright had to...
</Question>
<Choice>Wright, Frank Lloyd</Choice>
</item>
</topics>