<topics>
<item>
<Question>
American professional baseball player who, during 23 seasons in the major leagues (1954–76), surpassed batting records set by some of the greatest hitters in the game, including Babe Ruth, Ty Cobb, and Stan Musial.Aaron, a right-hander, began his professional career in 1952, playing shortstop for a few months with the Indianapolis Clowns of the Negro American League. His contract was bought by the Boston Braves of the National League, who assigned him to minor league teams. In 1954 he moved up to the majors, playing mostly as an outfielder for the Braves (who had moved to Milwaukee, Wisconsin,...
</Question>
<Choice>Aaron, Hank</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American professional boxer and social activist. Ali was the first fighter to win the world heavyweight championship on three separate occasions; he successfully defended this title 19 times.Cassius Marcellus Clay, Jr., grew up in the American South in a time of segregated public facilities. His father, Cassius Marcellus Clay, Sr., supported a wife and two sons by painting billboards and signs. His mother, Odessa Grady Clay, worked as a household domestic.When Clay was 12 years old, he took up boxing under the tutelage of Louisville policeman Joe Martin. After advancing through the amateur ran...
</Question>
<Choice>Ali, Muhammad</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American baseball player and manager who played professionally for 27 years and was still in his team's regular lineup at the age of 46. He batted .300 or better for 23 seasons and was the most famous player of the 19th century.Anson played in the National Association, the first professional baseball league, with the Forest City team of Rockford, Illinois, in 1871 and with the Philadelphia Athletics (1872–75). He is believed to have batted .352 during those five years. In 1876, when the Chicago National Association team—the White Stockings, later known as the Cubs—switched to the newly formed...
</Question>
<Choice>Anson, Cap</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American cyclist, who is the only rider to have won seven Tour de France titles (1999–2005).Armstrong entered sports at a young age, excelling in both swimming and cycling, and, by the time he was a teenager, he was competing in triathlons and swimming competitions. Before his high-school graduation the junior national team of the U.S. Cycling Federation had recruited him. Armstrong competed in Moscow at the Junior World Championships and in 1990 won the U.S. Amateur Championships. In 1992 he turned professional when he joined the Motorola team, and one year later he became the second youngest...
</Question>
<Choice>Armstrong, Lance</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English neurologist who was the first athlete to run a mile in less than four minutes.While a student at the University of Oxford and at St. Mary's Hospital Medical School, London, Bannister won British (1951, 1953–54) and Empire (1954) championships in the mile run and the European title (1954) in the 1,500-metre event. He broke the four-minute barrier with a time of 3 min 59.4 s in a dual meet at Oxford on May 6, 1954. Breaking the world record (4 min 1.3 s), held for nine years by Gunder Hägg of Sweden, was almost incidental to his successful defiance of the “psychological” barrier, the gen...
</Question>
<Choice>Bannister, Sir Roger</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American professional baseball player, a great all-around player who broke the major league home run records for both a career (with his 756th home run, in 2007) and a single season (with 73 home runs in 2001). SeeResearcher's Note: Baseball's problematic single-season home run record.Bonds was born into a baseball family. His father, Bobby Bonds, was an outfielder for the San Francisco Giants. His cousin was baseball great Reggie Jackson. His godfather was the legendary Willie Mays, who was a teammate of Bobby Bonds. Barry Bonds excelled at baseball from early childhood. The San Francisco Gia...
</Question>
<Choice>Bonds, Barry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish tennis player who was one of the finest competitors of the modern era. He was the first man to win the Wimbledon singles championship five successive times (1976–80) since Laurie Doherty (1902–06). He won the French Open men's singles championship an unprecedented four times in a row and six times in all (1974–75, 1978–81).Borg learned to play tennis at a very early age, and, by the time he was 13, he was beating Sweden's top junior players. Noted for his powerful serve and two-handed backhand, Borg joined the professional circuit at age 14 and went on to win the Italian Open at 17 and...
</Question>
<Choice>Borg, Björn</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
professional basketball player, considered to be one of the greatest offensive players in the history of the game. More than 7 feet (2.1 metres) tall, Chamberlain was an outstanding centre. During his 1961–62 season he became the first player to score more than 4,000 points in a National Basketball Association (NBA) season, with 4,029, averaging 50.4 points per game.As a teenager, Chamberlain was sought after by more than 100 colleges and universities after his play at Overbrook High School in Philadelphia. He played two years (1956–58) at the University of Kansas, after which he joined the Ha...
</Question>
<Choice>Chamberlain, Wilt</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
professional baseball player, considered one of the greatest offensive players in baseball history and generally regarded as the fiercest competitor in the game.During his 24-season career in the American League, Cobb set the record for runs scored of 2,245, a test that was not surpassed until 2001 by Rickey Henderson. Cobb's mark of 892 stolen bases was surpassed only in 1979 by Lou Brock (and in 1991 it was Henderson who beat Brock's record for stolen bases as well). Finally, Cobb's lifetime batting average of .366 was unequaled through the 20th century. (It should be noted that there is dis...
</Question>
<Choice>Cobb, Ty</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British athlete, who won four Olympic medals and set eight world records in middle-distance running. His great rivalry with fellow Briton Steve Ovett dominated middle-distance racing for much of the 1980s.Coe studied economics and social history at Loughborough University and won his first major race in 1977, an 800-metre event at the European indoor championships in San Sebastián, Spain. He first ran against Ovett in Prague in 1978 in an 800-metre race that neither won. The next year in Oslo, Norway, Coe set his first world records, in 800-metre and one-mile races. At the 1980 Olympic Games i...
</Question>
<Choice>Coe, Sebastian</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American professional tennis player who was one of the leading competitors in the 1970s and early '80s and was known for his intensity and aggressive play. During his career he won 109 singles championships and was ranked number one in the world for 160 consecutive weeks.The left-handed Connors learned to play tennis from his mother at an early age, and when he was eight years old he competed in the U.S. boys' championship. A former student at the University of California at Los Angeles, he joined team tennis in 1972.In 1974 he won three of the grand slam tournaments (U.S. Open, Australian Ope...
</Question>
<Choice>Connors, Jimmy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
outstanding American tennis player who dominated the sport in the mid- and late 1970s and remained a major competitor into the late 1980s.Evert, the daughter of a noted tennis player, early began taking tennis lessons from her father. Her style evolved rapidly to feature a powerful two-hand backhand and a degree of concentration that often unnerved opponents. At age 15, she beat top-ranked Margaret Smith Court, and in 1971 she became the youngest player to reach the semifinals of the U.S. championship. The following year she advanced to the semifinal round of her first Wimbledon tournament and...
</Question>
<Choice>Evert, Chris</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American-born chess master who became the youngest grandmaster in history when he received the title in 1958. His youthful intemperance and brilliant playing drew the attention of the American public to the game of chess, particularly when he won the world championship in 1972.Fischer learned the moves of chess at age 6 and at 16 dropped out of high school to devote himself fully to the game. In 1958 he won the first of many American championships. In world championship candidate matches during 1970–71, Fischer won 20 consecutive games before losing once and drawing three times to former world...
</Question>
<Choice>Fischer, Bobby</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American world heavyweight boxing champion from February 16, 1970, when he knocked out Jimmy Ellis in five rounds in New York City, until January 22, 1973, when he was beaten by George Foreman at Kingston, Jamaica.During Frazier's amateur career he was one of the best heavyweights in the United States, but he lost in the Olympic trials to Buster Mathis in 1964 and made it to the Tokyo Olympic Games as a replacement boxer only when Mathis injured his hand. He won the gold medal in his weight division and then began his professional career in August 1965. A chunky man (5 feet 11 inches [1.8 metr...
</Question>
<Choice>Frazier, Joe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
one of the most durable players in American professional baseball and one of its great hitters. From June 1, 1925, to May 2, 1939, Gehrig, playing first base for the New York Yankees, appeared in 2,130 consecutive games, a record that stood until it was broken on September 6, 1995, by Cal Ripken, Jr., of the Baltimore Orioles. A quiet, gentle man, Gehrig was somewhat overshadowed by his colourful teammate Babe Ruth, whom he followed in the Yankees' batting order.Gehrig attended Columbia University before joining the Yankees organization. In each of seven major league seasons, he batted in 150...
</Question>
<Choice>Gehrig, Lou</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Canadian ice-hockey player who was considered by many to be the greatest player in the history of the National Hockey League (NHL).Gretzky began skating at age two and a half and was first taught hockey by his father. By age 6 he was playing as an all-star in novice hockey with boys 10 and 11 years old. He progressed through organized age-group hockey, and in 1977 at the Junior World Cup competition, he was the youngest player and the leading scorer. Gretzky turned professional for the 1978–79 season, playing for the Indianapolis Racers in the World Hockey Association (WHA). His contract soon...
</Question>
<Choice>Gretzky, Wayne</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Canadian-born American professional ice hockey player and administrator. His career record of 1,850 total points (goals and assists) in the National Hockey League (NHL) stood until it was broken by Wayne Gretzky in 1989. His record of 801 goals in the NHL was broken by Gretzky in 1994. For three decades Howe entertained fans with his skill and competitive fire and became known for the “Gordie Howe hat-trick,” which comprised a goal, an assist, and a fight in a single game.Howe played hockey from the age of five; he moved to the United States in 1944 and was put on the Detroit Red Wings' negoti...
</Question>
<Choice>Howe, Gordie</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American tennis player and writer who, in the 1920s and '30s, became known for her persistence and her on-court rivalry with Helen Wills (Moody).Jacobs was the national junior tennis champion in 1924–25 and attended the University of California, Berkeley, from 1926 to 1929. She was defeated by Helen Wills in the 1928 finals at Forest Hills, New York, and in the Wimbledon finals in 1929 and 1932. Though Wills was usually victorious, Jacobs's charisma and pluck—a sharp contrast to Wills's reserve—made her a popular favourite. Jacobs's only victory over her leading rival came by default at the fi...
</Question>
<Choice>Jacobs, Helen Hull</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American collegiate and professional basketball player, widely considered to be the greatest all-around player in the history of the game. He led the National Basketball Association (NBA) Chicago Bulls to six championships (1991–93, 1996–98).Jordan grew up in Wilmington, North Carolina, and entered the University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill in 1981. As a freshman, he made the winning basket against Georgetown in the 1982 national championship game. Jordan was named College Player of the Year in both his sophomore and junior years, leaving North Carolina after his junior year. He led the U...
</Question>
<Choice>Jordan, Michael</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian chess master who dominated world competition from the mid-1970s to the mid-1980s.Karpov moved to Leningrad (now St. Petersburg) with his family early in life. A child prodigy, he learned to play chess at the age of four and was rated a first-category player by the time he was nine. In 1969 he won the world junior championship at Stockholm, and a year later, at age 19, he became the world's youngest grandmaster. An almost uninterrupted series of successes in tournaments during 1971–74 made him the official challenger to Bobby Fischer of the United States for the 1975 world chess champio...
</Question>
<Choice>Karpov, Anatoly Yevgenyevich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American tennis player whose influence and playing style elevated the status of women's professional tennis beginning in the late 1960s. In her career she won 39 major titles, competing in both singles and doubles.King was athletically inclined from an early age. She first attracted international attention in 1961 by winning the Wimbledon doubles championship with Karen Hantz; theirs was the youngest team to win. She went on to capture a record 20 Wimbledon titles (singles 1966–68, 1972–73, and 1975; women's doubles 1961–62, 1965, 1967–68, 1970–73, 1979; mixed doubles 1967, 1971, 1973–74), in...
</Question>
<Choice>King, Billie Jean</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
world chess champion contender who was one of the fiercest competitors in the history of chess. During his prime years, he was known as “Viktor the Terrible.”As a youngster, Korchnoi lived through the World War II siege of Leningrad (1941–43). He became a Soviet master in 1951, an international master in 1954, and an international grandmaster in 1956. In the years from 1960 to 1970, he won four U.S.S.R. championships—by far the strongest national championships in the world during those years.In 1974 Korchnoi lost a chess match to his countryman Anatoly Karpov to determine Bobby Fischer's chall...
</Question>
<Choice>Korchnoi, Viktor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American track-and-field athlete, who won nine Olympic gold medals during the 1980s and '90s.Lewis qualified for the U.S. Olympic team in 1980 but did not compete, because of the U.S. boycott of the Moscow Games. At the 1984 Games in Los Angeles, Lewis won gold medals in the 100-metre (9.9 sec) and 200-metre (19.8 sec) races, in the long jump (8.54 metres [28.02 feet]), and as a member of the U.S. 4 × 100-metre relay team, which he anchored. Lewis became the third track-and-field athlete to win four gold medals in one Olympics, joining Americans Alvin Kraenzlein (1900) and Jesse Owens, the lat...
</Question>
<Choice>Lewis, Carl</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
coach in American professional gridiron football who became a national symbol of single-minded determination to win. In nine seasons (1959–67) as head coach of the previously moribund Green Bay Packers, he led the team to five championships of the National Football League (NFL) and, in the last two seasons, to victory in the first two Super Bowl games against the American Football League titleholder.At Fordham University, Lombardi was outstanding in the classroom as well as on the football field, where he was one of the group of linemen known as the “Seven Blocks of Granite.” After completing...
</Question>
<Choice>Lombardi, Vince</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American boxer who was world heavyweight champion from June 22, 1937, when he knocked out James J. Braddock in eight rounds in Chicago, until March 1, 1949, when he briefly retired. During his reign, the longest in the history of any weight division, he successfully defended his title 25 times, more than any other champion in any division, scoring 21 knockouts (his service in the U.S. Army from 1942 to 1945 no doubt prevented him from defending his title many more times). He was known as an extremely accurate and economical knockout puncher.Louis's father, a sharecropper, was committed to a st...
</Question>
<Choice>Louis, Joe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Argentine football (soccer) player who is generally regarded as the top footballer of the 1980s and one of the greatest of all time. Renowned for his ability to control the ball and create scoring opportunities for himself and others, he led club teams to championships in Argentina, Italy, and Spain, and he starred on the Argentine national team that won the 1986 World Cup.Maradona displayed football talent early, and at age eight he joined Las Cebollitas (“The Little Onions”), a boys' team that went on to win 136 consecutive games and a national championship. He signed with Argentinos Juniors...
</Question>
<Choice>Maradona, Diego Armando</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American tennis player who established himself as a leading competitor in the late 1970s and the '80s. He also was noted for his poor behaviour on court, which resulted in a number of fines and suspensions and, on Jan. 21, 1990, in his default at the Australian Open.McEnroe grew up in Douglaston, N.Y., and received tennis training at the Port Washington Tennis Academy nearby. He first attracted international attention as an amateur in 1977, when at the age of 18 he became the youngest man to reach the Wimbledon semifinals. He enrolled at Stanford (Calif.) University in 1977, but, after winning...
</Question>
<Choice>McEnroe, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
New Zealand rugby union football player and former national team captain (1971) whose outstanding performance as a lock forward made him a legendary figure in New Zealand and in international rugby history. Noted as one of the best locks of all time, Meads played 55 Test (international) matches (48 at lock, 7 at the number eight position) for the New Zealand national team, the All Blacks, between 1957 and 1971; on 11 occasions between 1961 and 1966 he played alongside his younger brother Stan.Meads provoked controversy in 1986 when he led the rebel New Zealand Cavaliers on tour of South Africa...
</Question>
<Choice>Meads, Colin Earl</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
("BOBBY"), British footballer (b. April 12, 1941, Barking, Essex, England--d. Feb. 24, 1993, London, England), was the "golden boy of English soccer" and captain of the national side that defeated West Germany 4-2 in the 1966 World Cup final at Wembley Stadium in London; it was England's only World Cup championship and the high point of Moore's 19-year, 1,000-game career. Moore, an inspired defensive player, made his professional debut with West Ham United in 1958, and within months he was captain of the England Youth side. In 1964 he was named Footballer of the Year after leading West Ham to...
</Question>
<Choice>Moore, Robert Frederick Chelsea</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American collegiate and professional gridiron football quarterback who was one of the best passers in football and a cultural sports icon of the 1960s.Namath excelled in several sports as a youth in the steel-mill town of Beaver Falls, near Pittsburgh. He played football at the University of Alabama (1962–64) under coach Bear Bryant, a famous developer of quarterbacks. While playing in college, he sustained the first of many knee injuries that ultimately shortened his career. The National Football League (NFL) and the American Football League (AFL) competed for him as a first-round draft choic...
</Question>
<Choice>Namath, Joe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Czech-born American tennis player, who dominated women's tennis in the late 1970s and '80s.Navratilova played in her first tennis tournament at eight years of age. A left-handed player who ranked number one in Czechoslovakia from 1972 to 1975, she won international notice when she led her team to victory in the 1975 Federation Cup. In that year she went into exile in the United States; she became a U.S. citizen in 1981.From 1975 Navratilova was consistently one of the top five women tennis players. She made her first claim to the number-one position in 1978, after winning the Virginia Slims ch...
</Question>
<Choice>Navratilova, Martina</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American professional golfer, a dominating figure in world golf from the 1960s to the '80s.While a student at Ohio State University, Nicklaus won the U.S. Amateur championship in 1959 and again in 1961. Also in 1961 Nicklaus set a record 282 for an amateur in the U.S. Open. After he turned professional in 1962, Nicklaus won the Masters Tournament six times (1963, 1965, 1966, 1972, 1975, 1986), the U.S. Open four times (1962, 1967, 1972, 1980), the Professional Golfers' Association of America (PGA) Championship five times (1963, 1971, 1973, 1975, 1980), and the British Open three times (1966, 1...
</Question>
<Choice>Nicklaus, Jack</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British athlete, who, along with his great rival, Sebastian Coe, dominated middle-distance running in the early 1980s. The winner of gold and bronze medals at the 1980 Olympic Games in Moscow, Ovett set six world records.Ovett first attracted international notice when he won the 800-metre race at the 1973 European junior championships in Duisburg, West Germany. He finished fifth in the 800 metres at the 1976 Olympics in Montreal. He first competed against Coe in Prague in 1978, beating him but finishing second in the 800-metre race; in that same year he set a world record of 8 min 13.51 sec in...
</Question>
<Choice>Ovett, Steve</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American track-and-field athlete, who set a world record in the running broad jump (also called long jump) that stood for 25 years and who won four gold medals at the 1936 Olympic Games in Berlin. His four Olympic victories were a blow to Adolf Hitler's intention to use the Games to demonstrate Aryan superiority.As a student in a Cleveland, Ohio, high school, Owens won three events at the 1933 National Interscholastic Championships in Chicago. In one day, May 25, 1935, while competing for Ohio State University (Columbus) in a Western (later Big Ten) Conference track-and-field meet at the Unive...
</Question>
<Choice>Owens, Jesse</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
professional American golfer, the first to win the Masters Tournament (Augusta, Ga.) four times and the first to earn $1 million in tournament prize money. During his professional career (1954–75) he won 92 tournaments, 60 of which were on the Professional Golfers' Association of America (PGA) tour. As a leading figure in world golf from the late 1950s through the mid-1960s, he attracted a vast following known as “Arnie's Army.”Palmer, who grew up in Latrobe, Pa., won the Pennsylvania State High School golf championship twice before attending Wake Forest University on a golf scholarship. After...
</Question>
<Choice>Palmer, Arnold</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
football (soccer) player, in his time probably the most famous and possibly the best-paid athlete in the world. He was part of the Brazilian national teams that won three World Cup championships (1958, 1962, and 1970).After playing for a minor league club at Bauru, São Paulo state, Pelé (whose nickname apparently is without significance) was rejected by major club teams in the city of São Paulo. In 1956, however, he joined the Santos Football Club, which, with Pelé at inside left forward, won nine São Paulo league championships and, in 1962 and 1963, both the Libertadores Cup and the Intercont...
</Question>
<Choice>Pelé</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
In Atlanta, Ga., on July 27, 1996, British oarsman Steve Redgrave joined an exclusive club; he had won a gold medal in four consecutive Olympic Games. Only the Hungarian fencer Aladar Gerevich, the U.S. shot-putter Al Oerter, the Danish yachtsman Paul Elvstrom, and the U.S. track star Carl Lewis had equaled or surpassed Redgrave's Olympic record, which included one gold in the coxed fours at the Los Angeles Olympics in 1984 and three in the coxless pairs, with Andy Holmes in 1988 and Matthew Pinsent in 1992 and 1996. Others may have won more medals, but few could sustain Redgrave's level of in...
</Question>
<Choice>Redgrave, Steven Geoffrey</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the first black baseball player to play in the American major leagues during the 20th century. On April 15, 1947, Robinson broke the decades-old colour bar of Major League Baseball when he appeared on the field for the National LeagueBrooklyn Dodgers. He played as an infielder and outfielder for the Dodgers from 1947 through 1956.Reared in Pasadena, California, Robinson became an outstanding all-around athlete at Pasadena Junior College and the University of California, Los Angeles (UCLA). He excelled in football, basketball, and track as well as baseball. Robinson withdrew from UCLA in his th...
</Question>
<Choice>Robinson, Jackie</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American professional boxer, six times a world champion: once as a welterweight (147 pounds), from 1946 to 1951, and five times as a middleweight (160 pounds), between 1951 and 1960. He is considered by many authorities to have been the best fighter in history.He won 89 amateur fights without defeat, fighting first under his own name and then as Ray Robinson, using the amateur certificate of another boxer of that name in order to qualify for a bout. He won Golden Gloves titles as a featherweight in 1939 and as a lightweight in 1940.Robinson won 40 consecutive professional fights before losing...
</Question>
<Choice>Robinson, Sugar Ray</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American collegiate basketball coach at the University of Kentucky (1930–72). He retired as the most successful coach in collegiate basketball, with 876 wins (surpassed in 1997 by Dean Smith). Rupp's teams won more than 82 percent of their games.Rupp grew up on a Kansas farm and was hardly aware of basketball until he went to college. He was a member of the University of Kansas Big Eight Conference championship team of 1923. After graduating from Kansas in 1923, he coached for several years at Iowa and Illinois high schools. In 1930 Rupp became coach at the University of Kentucky, where he rem...
</Question>
<Choice>Rupp, Adolph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American basketball player regarded in his day as the greatest defensive centre in the history of the National Basketball Association (NBA). He set standards by which other exceptionally tall players were judged (his height was 6 ft 10 in). On April 18, 1966, he became the first black coach of a major professional sports team (the Boston Celtics) in the United States.Reared in Oakland, Calif., Russell led the University of San Francisco to National Collegiate Athletic Association (NCAA) championships in two consecutive seasons (1954–55 and 1955–56). He played on the U.S. team that won the 1956...
</Question>
<Choice>Russell, Bill</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
professional baseball player. Largely because of his home-run hitting between 1919 and 1935, Ruth became, and perhaps remains to this day, America's most celebrated athlete.Part of the aura surrounding Ruth arose from his modest origins. Though the legend that he was an orphan is untrue, Ruth did have a difficult childhood. Both his parents, George Herman Ruth, Sr., and Kate Shamberger Ruth, came from working-class, ethnic (German) families. Ruth, Sr., owned and operated a saloon in a tough neighbourhood on the Baltimore waterfront. Living in rooms above the saloon, the Ruths had eight childre...
</Question>
<Choice>Ruth, Babe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German heavyweight boxer who, from June 12, 1930, when Jack Sharkey lost to him by disqualification, until June 21, 1932, when he was outpointed by Sharkey in 15 rounds, held the world heavyweight boxing title, the first European to do so.Schmeling became interested in boxing in 1921 and turned professional three years later. He won the German light heavyweight title in 1926 and added the heavyweight title in 1928. He pursued more challenging fights in the United Sates, where victories over top heavyweights Johnny Risko and Paolino Uzcudun in 1929 led to the 1930 fight against Sharkey.Schmelin...
</Question>
<Choice>Schmeling, Max</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
one of the most accomplished all-around athletes in history, who in 1950 was selected by American sportswriters and broadcasters as the greatest American athlete and the greatest gridiron football player of the first half of the 20th century.Predominantly of American Indian (Sauk and Fox) descent, Thorpe attended Haskell Indian School in Lawrence, Kansas, and Carlisle (Pennsylvania) Indian Industrial School. While playing football for Carlisle under coach Pop Warner, he was chosen as halfback on Walter Camp's All-America teams in 1911 and 1912. He was a marvel of speed, power, kicking, and all...
</Question>
<Choice>Thorpe, Jim</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American professional gridiron football quarterback who in 1969 was named the greatest all-time National Football League (NFL) quarterback.Unitas played football at St. Justin's High School (Pittsburgh), but his low weight (145 pounds [66 kg]) caused him to be rejected for an athletic scholarship at the University of Notre Dame. He played for the University of Louisville (Kentucky), where he grew to 6 feet 1 inch (1.85 metres) and 190 pounds (86 kg). He was drafted by the NFL Pittsburgh Steelers in the ninth round in 1955 but was released before the regular season began. He worked at construct...
</Question>
<Choice>Unitas, Johnny</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
outstanding American tennis player who was the top female competitor in the world for eight years (1927–33 and 1935).Wills began playing tennis when she was 13 and won her first major title, the U.S. girls' championship, in 1921. She repeated as national girls' champion in 1922 and won her first women's singles title in 1923 at the age of 17. With powerful overheads and serves, combined with extraordinary control, Wills soon dominated women's tennis; from 1926 until 1932 she did not lose a set in singles play. She was a seven-time U.S. champion (1923–25, 1927–29, and 1931) and eight-time Wimbl...
</Question>
<Choice>Wills, Helen</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American basketball coach who directed teams of the University of California at Los Angeles (UCLA) to 10 National Collegiate Athletic Association (NCAA) championships in 12 seasons (1964–65, 1967–73, 1975). Several of his UCLA players became professional basketball stars, notably Lew Alcindor (afterward Kareem Abdul-Jabbar), Bill Walton, and Gail Goodrich.At Purdue University in West Lafayette, Indiana, Wooden, a guard, gained All-America honours as a basketball player for three seasons (1930–32) and won a Western Conference (Big Ten) medal for athletic and scholastic excellence. He coached hi...
</Question>
<Choice>Wooden, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American golfer, who enjoyed one of the greatest amateur careers in the history of the game and became a dominant player on the professional circuit in the late 1990s. In 1997 Woods became the first golfer of either African American or Asian descent to win the Masters Tournament, one of the most prestigious events in the sport. With his victory at the 2001 Masters, Woods became the first player to win consecutively the four major tournaments of golf—the Masters, the United States Open, the British Open, and the Professional Golfers' Association of America (PGA) Championship.Woods was the child...
</Question>
<Choice>Woods, Tiger</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American sportswoman, one of the greatest athletes of the 20th century, performing in basketball, track and field, and later golf.From 1930 through 1932, Didrikson was a member of the women's All-America basketball team. During the same period she also won eight events and tied in a ninth in national championship competition in track and field. In the 1932 Women's Amateur Athletic Association (AAU), competing as a team by herself, Didrikson won six individual events and the team title, outscoring the 20-women runner-up team from the Illinois Athletic Club 30 points to 22. At the 1932 Olympic G...
</Question>
<Choice>Zaharias, Babe Didrikson</Choice>
</item>
</topics>