<topics>
<item>
<Question>
major American gangster.Anastasia immigrated to New York City from Italy in 1919 and, in the 1920s, rose through Giuseppe Masseria's gang. He was one of Masseria's executioners in 1931, at Lucky Luciano's command. In the late 1930s he became active head of “Murder, Inc.,” a notorious murder-for-hire organization, and in the late 1940s became boss of one of the Five Families of organized crime in New York City. He was murdered by two gunmen (hired by rival Vito Genovese) as he sat in a barber chair in the Park Sheraton Hotel.
</Question>
<Choice>Anastasia, Albert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American crime syndicate boss and founder of the murder-for-hire organization popularly known as Murder, Inc.Born on New York's Lower East Side, Buchalter derived his nickname from “Lepkeleh” (Yiddish for “Little Louis”). As a youth he was already into shoplifting and burglary and, by the age of 22 in 1919, had served two prison terms. In the 1920s he ganged up with a collection of Jewish, Irish, and Italian mobsters engaged mainly in extortion and labour racketeering, but also murder. Between 1932 and 1934 he allied with Lucky Luciano in founding the national crime syndicate. About 1933 he pu...
</Question>
<Choice>Buchalter, Louis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the most famous American gangster, who dominated organized crime in Chicago from 1925 to 1931.Capone's parents immigrated to the United States from Naples in 1893; Al, the fourth of nine children, quit school in Brooklyn after the sixth grade and joined Johnny Torrio's James Street Boys gang, rising eventually to the Five Points Gang. In a youthful scrape in a brothel-saloon, a young hoodlum slashed Capone with a knife or razor across his left cheek, prompting the later nickname “Scarface.”Torrio moved from New York to Chicago in 1909 to help run the giant brothel business there and, in 1919,...
</Question>
<Choice>Capone, Al</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
major organized crime boss in Brooklyn who founded an Italian-American Civil Rights League to deflect government investigations of his activities.Brooklyn-born, Colombo was still a teenager when his father, Anthony, was killed in 1938 in a gangland war. After service in the Coast Guard during World War II, he drifted into a life of petty crime. Gradually he rose in the ranks of organized crime to become head of one of New York's Five Families in 1964, inheriting the leadership once held by Joseph Profaci and temporarily quelling a gang war within the ranks. Colombo's activities included number...
</Question>
<Choice>Colombo, Joseph A., Sr.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
crime czar in Chicago from about 1902 until his death, owner of plush brothels, saloons, and a nightclub. Immigrating from Italy in 1895, he rose from poverty through petty crime and pimping to head a chain of brothels. In 1909 he imported Johnny Torrio from New York to head his gang of enforcers. In 1920 Torrio seized control by having Colosimo murdered (allegedly by Al Capone, then Torrio's henchman).
</Question>
<Choice>Colosimo, James</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
major American syndicate gangster, a close associate of Lucky Luciano, noted for his influence with politicians.Arriving in New York City at the age of four with his immigrant Calabrian parents, Costello grew up in East Harlem and became head of the 104th Street Gang, a group of young Italian hoodlums. In 1915 he went to prison for a year for carrying a concealed weapon; on release he allied himself with Lucky Luciano and, in the course of the 1920s, branched into bootlegging and gambling operations in New York, Florida, Louisiana, and other states. In 1931, after the death of crime bosses Giu...
</Question>
<Choice>Costello, Frank</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
head of one of the Five Families of organized crime in New York City from 1957 to 1976, with major interests in Brooklyn, and reputedly the “boss of bosses” of the U.S. national crime syndicate.Born in Sicily, Gambino immigrated to the United States in 1921 as a ship stowaway, settling in Brooklyn and becoming a gang member under, successively, Joe “the Boss” Masseria, Salvatore Maranzano, Philip and Vincent Mangano, and finally (in 1951) Albert Anastasia. When Anastasia was murdered in 1957 (allegedly by Gambino and another gunman and with Vito Genovese's approval), Gambino inherited leadersh...
</Question>
<Choice>Gambino, Carlo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
one of the most powerful of American crime syndicate bosses from the 1930s to the 1950s and a major influence even from prison, 1959–69.Genovese immigrated from a Neapolitan village to New York City in 1913, joined local gangs, and in the 1920s and '30s was Lucky Luciano's second-in-command in narcotics and other rackets. In 1937 he escaped to Italy to avoid prosecution on a murder charge and became a friend of Benito Mussolini, financing several Fascist operations while engaged in narcotics smuggling to the United States.At war's end he befriended U.S. military occupation authorities and boss...
</Question>
<Choice>Genovese, Vito</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
major American gangster, the top syndicate boss in Chicago from 1957 to 1966, who was noted for his friendships with show-business personalities and for his ruthlessness.Born and reared in Chicago's “Little Italy” on the near southwest side, Giancana began working for Al Capone in the 1920s and, by 1966, had been arrested some 70 times and served five years in prison for burglary and four years for operating an illegal still. In 1965–66 he spent a year in jail for contempt of a federal grand jury (1965) that had granted him immunity in return for testimony, an offer that he had rebuffed. After...
</Question>
<Choice>Giancana, Sam</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American organized-crime boss whose flamboyant lifestyle and frequent public trials made him a prominent figure in New York City in the 1980s and '90s.Gotti was the fifth of 13 children born to John and Fannie Gotti, both of whom were children of Italian immigrants. As a teenager, Gotti became a leader of a local gang in the East New York section of Brooklyn, and he became involved with the Gambino family, which controlled one of New York's largest organized-crime syndicates. After dropping out of high school, he frequently had skirmishes with the law and was arrested, mostly for petty crimes,...
</Question>
<Choice>Gotti, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
one of the most powerful and richest of U.S. crime syndicate chiefs and bankers, who had major interests in gambling, especially in Florida, pre-Castro Cuba, Las Vegas, and the Bahamas.A Polish Jew born in Russia's Pale of Settlement, Lansky immigrated with his parents to New York's Lower East Side in 1911. By 1918 he and Bugsy Siegel were running a floating crap game and then graduated into highly lucrative auto theft and resale. In the course of the 1920s Lansky's gang branched into burglaries, liquor smuggling, and other rackets and came under the aegis of crime boss Giuseppe Masseria. Lans...
</Question>
<Choice>Lansky, Meyer</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the most powerful chief of American organized crime in the early 1930s and a major influence even from prison, 1936–45, and after deportation to Italy in 1946.Luciano immigrated with his parents from Sicily to New York City in 1906 and, at the age of 10, was already involved in mugging, shoplifting, and extortion; in 1916 he spent six months in jail for selling heroin. Out of jail, he teamed up with Frank Costello and Meyer Lansky and other young gangsters; he earned his nickname “Lucky” for success at evading arrest and winning craps games. In 1920 he joined the ranks of New York's rising cri...
</Question>
<Choice>Luciano, Lucky</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American gangster of the Prohibition era, leader among the old-country-oriented Italians, known as “Moustache Petes,” many of whom were former members of the Sicilian Mafia and Neapolitan Camorra.Reared in Sicily, Maranzano immigrated to the United States after World War I and put together an organization of Sicilians with interests in bootlegging, gambling, and other rackets in New York City. In 1930–31 his gang and others headed by Castellammare-born mafiosi engaged in a bloody war—the Castellammare War—with New York's crime overlord, Joe (Giuseppe) Masseria. The internecine killings did not...
</Question>
<Choice>Maranzano, Salvatore</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
leading crime boss of New York City from the early 1920s until his murder in 1931.Emigrating from Sicily at age 16, Masseria associated with a band of Italian killers and Black Hand extortionists and committed burglaries and other petty crimes, but in 1920 he began to create the power that gave him control or a percentage of the profits of most of the Italian-run rackets in New York. In 1930 he declared war on Salvatore Maranzano (q.v.) and allied rivals, and some 60 gunmen and leaders on both sides were slaughtered in the resultant gang war. It ended on a Wednesday afternoon in April 1931, wh...
</Question>
<Choice>Masseria, Joe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chicago gangster and bootlegger of the Prohibition era.A childhood friend and, later, right-hand man of Dion O'Bannion, Moran and Earl “Hymie” Weiss inherited O'Bannion's gang in Chicago when the chief was killed in 1924. Moran became sole leader after Weiss was killed in late 1926. For the next three years Moran's gang and Al Capone's were locked in bloody warfare, climaxed in 1929 by the St. Valentine's Day Massacre(q.v.), in which several members of Moran's mob were slaughtered. His power reduced, he drifted into petty crimes, ending his days in prison for bank robberies (Ohio Penitentiary,...
</Question>
<Choice>Moran, George</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American gangster in Chicago who was Al Capone's chief enforcer and inherited Capone's criminal empire when Capone went to prison in 1931.Starting as a barber, Nitti became a fence for stolen goods and about 1920 joined Capone's gang. He was sent to prison for 18 months after pleading guilty in 1930 to income-tax evasion, but thereafter he nominally headed the syndicate that controlled Chicago's gambling, prostitution, and other rackets. In March 1943 he and eight others (including Paul “the Waiter” Ricca) were indicted for trying to extort $1,000,000 from four motion-picture companies (Loew's...
</Question>
<Choice>Nitti, Frank</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
bootlegger of the early 1920s, boss of the most feared Chicago gang next to that of his arch rivals, Johnny Torrio and Al Capone.From a life of petty crime O'Bannion rose during Prohibition to command the best distilleries and breweries in Chicago and dominated bootleg distribution on the North Side, including the elegant Gold Coast, and among Chicago's fashionable clubs and restaurants. His office was in a flower shop at 738 North State Street. It was there that he was murdered by agents of Al Capone. Three men entered the shop, ostensibly to pick up funeral flowers; one grasped his hand in g...
</Question>
<Choice>O'Bannion, Dion</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Chicago gangster who was considered “the brains” behind the operations of Al Capone and Capone's successors, Frank Nitti and Tony Accardo. He was the Chicago representative in the formation of the national crime syndicate in 1934, led by Lucky Luciano, Meyer Lansky, and other New York bosses.Ricca grew up in Naples and was convicted of murder there in 1917. He served two years in prison, murdered again, and fled to the United States (1919). After making his way to Chicago, he became Al Capone's bodyguard and eventually one of his chief aides. In 1943 he was indicted and convicted (with seven o...
</Question>
<Choice>Ricca, Paul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American gangster of the 1920s and '30s who ran bootlegging and other rackets in New York City.Born in the Bronx, Schultz took his alias from an old-time Bronx gangster and advanced from burglaries to bootlegging, ownership of breweries and speakeasies, and policy rackets in the Bronx and parts of Manhattan. His gang engaged in a number of bloody gang wars. In 1933 he was acquitted of a charge of income-tax fraud; but, in hiding out for months prior to the trial, he had lost much of his business to his New York rivals. From Newark, N.J., he tried to rebuild his New York rackets but became the...
</Question>
<Choice>Schultz, Dutch</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
New York and California gangster who was the U.S. crime syndicate's initial developer of Las Vegas gambling.Young Siegel began his career extorting money from Jewish pushcart peddlers on New York's Lower East Side; he then teamed up with Meyer Lansky about 1918 and took to car theft and later bootlegging and gambling rackets in New York, New Jersey, and Philadelphia; he and Lansky also ran a murder-for-hire operation, the forerunner of Murder, Inc. In 1931 he was one of the four executioners of Joe “the Boss” Masseria.In 1937 the syndicate leaders sent him to the West Coast to develop rackets...
</Question>
<Choice>Siegel, Bugsy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Japan's major crime boss (oyabun), who, after World War II, rose to head a giant crime organization, the Yamaguchi-gumi. Though centred in K?be, it had interests and affiliates nationwide and consisted of more than 10,000 members (known as yakuza) divided into more than 500 bands.Taoka was born to a poor farm family in a village on the island of Shikoku; his father died before Taoka was born, and his mother died when he was four years old. Raised by relatives, he left school in his early teens and in 1929 began associating with yakuza gangs in K?be; in the early 1930s he became an apprentice a...
</Question>
<Choice>Taoka Kazuo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American gangster who became a top crime boss in Chicago and, later, one of the founders of modern organized crime in America.Born in a village near Naples, Torrio was brought to New York City by his widowed mother when he was two. He became a brothel-saloonkeeper and leader of the James Street Boys, allying them with the Five Points Gang (1904–08). He then rose to become a rackets boss (i.e., engaged in activities involving extortion) in Brooklyn before being called to Chicago in 1909 to operate and expand Big Jim Colosimo's chain of brothels. In 1919 Torrio summoned his old friend Al Capone...
</Question>
<Choice>Torrio, Johnny</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American gangster, member of Lucky Luciano's mob family, who turned informer in 1962.Valachi held a rank in the Mafia equivalent to that of a sergeant, with interests chiefly in the numbers rackets and other gambling from the 1930s to the '50s. In 1959 he was convicted of narcotics violations and sentenced to 15 to 20 years in prison. In June 1962, in the federal prison at Atlanta, Ga., crime boss Vito Genovese, a fellow inmate, suspecting him (incorrectly) of having become an informer, gave him the kiss of death (a sign that he was to be killed). Valachi panicked, killed a fellow prisoner who...
</Question>
<Choice>Valachi, Joseph</Choice>
</item>
</topics>