<topics>
<item>
<Question>
American social reformer and pacifist, cowinner (with Nicholas Murray Butler) of the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1931. She is probably best known as the founder of Hull House in Chicago, one of the first social settlements in North America.Addams graduated from Rockford Female Seminary in Illinois in 1881 and was granted a degree the following year when the institution became Rockford College. Following the death of her father in 1881, her own health problems, and an unhappy year at the Woman's Medical College, Philadelphia, she was an invalid for two years. During neither subsequent travel in Eu...
</Question>
<Choice>Addams, Jane</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
founder of the American Red Cross.Barton was educated at home and began teaching at age 15. She attended the Liberal Institute at Clinton, New York (1850–51), and in 1852 she established in Bordentown, New Jersey, a free school that soon became so large that the townsmen would no longer allow a woman to run it. Rather than subordinate herself to a male principal, Barton resigned. She was then employed by the U.S. Patent Office in Washington, D.C., from 1854 to 1857 and again in 1860.At the outbreak of the American Civil War, Barton showed characteristic initiative in organizing facilities to r...
</Question>
<Choice>Barton, Clara</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman Catholic bishop of Dili who, with José Ramos-Horta, received the 1996 Nobel Prize for Peace for their efforts to bring peace to East Timor (Timor Timur) during the period that it was under Indonesian control (1975–99).Belo was ordained a bishop in 1983. As spiritual leader of a territory that is overwhelmingly Catholic, he became one of the primary spokesmen of the Timorese people. He denounced the brutal tactics and oppressive policies of the Indonesian government despite at least two attempts on his life, in 1989 and 1991. Following a massacre of peaceful demonstrators in Dili in 1991,...
</Question>
<Choice>Belo, Carlos Filipe Ximenes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British philanthropist, social reformer, and founder of free schools for poor children, the “ragged schools.”Carpenter was educated in the school run by her father, a Unitarian minister. In 1829 she and her mother and sisters opened a girls' school in Bristol. Later she founded a ragged school in a Bristol slum (1846), a reformatory for boys (1852), and one of England's first reformatory schools for girls (1854).In 1833, through the Indian leader Ram Mohun Roy and the Boston philanthropist Joseph Tuckerman, she became interested in India, which she visited four times. After her third visit (18...
</Question>
<Choice>Carpenter, Mary</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French jurist and president of the European Court of Human Rights. He won the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1968 for his involvement in the drafting of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights.The son of a Jewish merchant, Cassin studied law before entering the French Army in World War I. During the war he sustained a severe abdominal wound, the effects of which troubled him for the rest of his life. He later became a professor of international law in Paris and then, from 1924 to 1938, served as a French delegate to the League of Nations assemblies and disarmament conferences in Geneva. After the...
</Question>
<Choice>Cassin, René</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
née Jones British-born Australian philanthropist.Caroline Jones married an officer in the East India Company, Archibald Chisholm, in 1830. In 1838 she and her husband settled at Windsor, near Sydney, in Australia. Australia had large numbers of unemployed immigrant labourers at this time, and Caroline Chisholm established a home in Sydney for destitute immigrant girls, for whom she found jobs in the countryside. Her first report on her work, Female Immigration, Considered in a Brief Account of the Sydney Immigrants' Home (1842), was the most sizable publication by an Australia-based woman to t...
</Question>
<Choice>Chisholm, Caroline</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Northern Irish peace activist who, with Betty Williams and Ciaran McKeown, founded the Peace People, a grassroots movement of both Roman Catholic and Protestant citizens dedicated to ending the sectarian strife in Northern Ireland. For their work, Maguire and Williams shared the 1976 Nobel Prize for Peace.Although Maguire from a young age earned her living as a secretary, she also was from her youth a member of the Legion of Mary, a lay Catholic welfare organization, and through it she became deeply involved in voluntary social work among children and teenagers in various Catholic neighbourhoo...
</Question>
<Choice>Corrigan-Maguire, Mairéad</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
former consort (1981–96) of Charles, prince of Wales, and mother of the heir second in line to the British throne, Prince William of Wales (born 1982).Diana was born at Park House, the home that her parents rented on Queen Elizabeth II's estate at Sandringham and where her childhood playmates were the queen's younger sons, Prince Andrew and Prince Edward. She was the third child and youngest daughter of Edward John Spencer, Viscount Althorp, heir to the 7th Earl Spencer, and his first wife, Frances Ruth Burke Roche (daughter of the 4th Baron Fermoy). She became Lady Diana Spencer when her fath...
</Question>
<Choice>Diana, princess of Wales</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss humanitarian, founder of the Red Cross (now Red Cross and Red Crescent) and the World's Young Men's Christian Association. He was cowinner (with Frédéric Passy) of the first Nobel Prize for Peace in 1901.An eyewitness of the Battle of Solferino (June 24, 1859), which resulted in nearly 40,000 casualties, Dunant organized emergency aid services for the Austrian and French wounded. In Un Souvenir de Solférino (1862; A Memory of Solferino), he proposed the formation in all countries of voluntary relief societies for the prevention and alleviation of suffering in war and peacetime, without d...
</Question>
<Choice>Dunant, Henri</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
canonized July 16, 1228; feast day October 4; founder of the Franciscan orders of the Friars Minor (Ordo Fratrum Minorum), the woman's Order of St. Clare (or Poor Clares), and the lay Third Order. He was also a leader of the movement of evangelical poverty in the early 13th century. His evangelical zeal, consecration to poverty, charity, and personal charisma drew thousands of followers. Francis's devotion to the human Jesus and his desire to follow Jesus' example reflected and reinforced important developments in medieval spirituality. The Poverello (“Poor Little Man”) is one of the most vene...
</Question>
<Choice>Francis of Assisi, Saint</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
educational philanthropist and founder of the first American school for the deaf.After graduating from Yale College in 1805, Gallaudet studied theology at Andover. His interests soon turned to the education of the deaf, and he visited Europe, studying in England and France, where he learned the sign method of communication from Abbé Roch-Ambroise Sicard, head of the French Royal Institute for the Deaf. On Gallaudet's return to the United States in 1816, he and Laurent Clerc established the American Asylum for Deaf-mutes at Hartford, Conn., in support of which the U.S. Congress made a land gran...
</Question>
<Choice>Gallaudet, Thomas Hopkins</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American computer programmer and entrepreneur who cofounded Microsoft Corporation, the world's largest personal-computer software company.Gates wrote his first software program at the age of 13. In high school he helped form a group of programmers who computerized their school's payroll system and founded Traf-O-Data, a company that sold traffic-counting systems to local governments. In 1975 Gates, then a sophomore at Harvard University, joined his hometown friend Paul G. Allen to develop software for the first microcomputers. They began by adapting BASIC, a popular programming language used o...
</Question>
<Choice>Gates, Bill</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
social reformer who founded a sectarian organization to work for relief of the underprivileged of India. He led the moderate nationalists in the early years of the Indian independence movement.In 1902 Gokhale resigned as professor of history and political economy at Fergusson College, Pune, to enter politics. As an influential and respected member of the Indian National Congress, the leading nationalist organization, Gokhale advocated moderate and constitutional methods of agitation and gradual reform. Three years later he was elected president of the Congress.In addition to his political acti...
</Question>
<Choice>Gokhale, Gopal Krishna</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish-American educator and philanthropist who was principal in founding one of the earliest relief societies in the United States to provide assistance to the poor.Isabella Marshall grew up in Elderslie, near Paisley, Scotland, in a religious family and received a good education. In 1765 she married John Graham, an army surgeon whom she accompanied to Canada in 1767. They lived successively in Quebec, Montreal, and Fort Niagara and on the Caribbean island of Antigua, where John died in 1773.Graham then returned with her children to Scotland and opened a small school in Paisley. Later she o...
</Question>
<Choice>Graham, Isabella Marshall</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian businessman, philanthropist, and vigilant fighter for the rights of his Jewish co-religionists in the teeth of persecution by the Russian government. His father was the philanthropist Joseph Günzburg. His son David became a prominent Orientalist and bibliophile.For a time, Horace Günzburg ran the banking firm that his father had founded, but he closed it during a financial crisis, even though it was solvent. In 1863, along with his father, he founded the Society for the Promotion of Culture Among the Jews of Russia, a highly successful organization that disseminated Jewish culture in t...
</Question>
<Choice>Günzburg, Horace, Baron</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jewish philanthropist, banker, and financier who contributed much to the industrialization of 19th-century Russia and who successfully fought some of the discriminatory measures against Jews in Russia. His son Horace carried on his philanthropic work, and his grandson David was a well-known Orientalist and bibliophile.After an early career as a contractor for the government, he founded a banking firm in 1859 in St. Petersburg. Along with other wealthy Russian Jewish families, he also financed the building of much of Russia's railroad network. He was created a baron in the early 1870s.Günzburg...
</Question>
<Choice>Günzburg, Joseph, Baron</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
slender, stylish motion picture actress known for her radiant beauty, her ability to project an air of sophistication tempered by a charming innocence, and her tireless efforts to aid needy children.Although born in Belgium, Hepburn had British citizenship and attended school in England as a child. In 1939, however, at the onset of World War II, her mother (Hepburn's father left the family when she was six years old) moved the child to The Netherlands, thinking that neutral country safer than England. Throughout World War II, Hepburn endured hardships in Nazi-occupied Holland. She still manage...
</Question>
<Choice>Hepburn, Audrey</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English reformer and social worker whose humanitarian undertakings in South Africa caused her to be dubbed the “Angel of Love” by grateful Boer women.Hobhouse spent the first sheltered 35 years of her life at her father's rectory. Upon his death, she engaged in temperance work in the United States. At the outbreak of the South African War in 1899, she became an outspoken critic of British policy. And when she learned of the high mortality rate of Boer women and children in British concentration camps, she went to South Africa (December 1900) to discover the facts for herself. Her investigation...
</Question>
<Choice>Hobhouse, Emily</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British-born American entertainer and comic actor, known for his rapid-fire delivery of jokes and one-liners and for his success in virtually all entertainment media. He was also known for his decades of overseas tours to entertain American troops, and he received numerous awards and honours for his work as an entertainer and humanitarian.Hope was the fifth of seven sons of a stonemason and a former Welsh concert singer; his family immigrated to the United States when he was four years old. He grew up in Cleveland, Ohio, manifesting the first signs of his vocation at age 10 when he won a Charl...
</Question>
<Choice>Hope, Bob</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American author and educator who was blind and deaf. Her education and training represent an extraordinary accomplishment in the education of persons with these disabilities.Keller was afflicted at the age of 19 months with an illness (possibly scarlet fever) that left her blind, deaf, and mute. She was examined by Alexander Graham Bell at the age of six; as a result he sent to her a 20-year-old teacher, Anne Sullivan (Macy) from the Perkins Institution for the Blind in Boston, which Bell's son-in-law directed. Sullivan, a remarkable teacher, remained with Keller from March 1887 until her own...
</Question>
<Choice>Keller, Helen</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
outstanding Jewish philanthropist.Scion of an old Italian Jewish merchant family, Montefiore was taken to England as an infant. As a young man he accumulated such a fortune on the London stock exchange that he was able to retire in 1824. He subsequently helped found the Alliance Assurance Company, the Imperial Continental Gas Association (which pioneered gas lighting for homes), and the Provincial Bank of Ireland.In 1837 he was elected sheriff of London, the second Jew so honoured, and in 1847 he became high sheriff of Kent. Knighted in 1837, he became a baronet in 1846.An Orthodox Sefardic Je...
</Question>
<Choice>Montefiore, Sir Moses, Baronet</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian educator and originator of the educational system that bears her name. The Montessori system is based on belief in the child's creative potential, his drive to learn, and his right to be treated as an individual.After graduating in medicine from the University of Rome in 1896—the first woman in Italy to do so—Montessori was appointed assistant doctor at the psychiatric clinic of the University of Rome, where she became interested in the educational problems of mentally retarded children. Between 1899 and 1901 she served as director of the State Orthophrenic School of Rome, where her me...
</Question>
<Choice>Montessori, Maria</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American philanthropist, remembered most for her relief efforts in aid to France during and after World Wars I and II.Morgan was the daughter of J. Pierpont Morgan and grew up amid the wealth and cultural amenities he had amassed. She was educated privately and traveled frequently. Until her late 20s she passed her time in the social world to which she had been born. Under the tutelage of Elisabeth Marbury she began to broaden her horizons about 1900. In 1903 she joined Marbury, Florence J. Harriman, and others in organizing the Colony Club, New York's first social club for women. Morgan becam...
</Question>
<Choice>Morgan, Anne Tracy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Norwegian explorer, oceanographer, statesman, and humanitarian who led a number of expeditions to the Arctic (1888, 1893, 1895–96) and oceanographic expeditions in the North Atlantic (1900, 1910–14). For his relief work after World War I he was awarded the Nobel Prize for Peace (1922).
</Question>
<Choice>Nansen, Fridtjof</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
foundational philosopher of modern nursing, statistician, and social reformer. Nightingale was put in charge of nursing British and allied soldiers in Turkey during the Crimean War. She spent many hours in the wards, and her night rounds giving personal care to the wounded established her image as the “Lady with the Lamp.” Her efforts to formalize nursing education led her to establish the first scientifically based nursing school—the Nightingale School of Nursing, at St. Thomas' Hospital in London (opened 1860). She also was instrumental in setting up training for midwives and nurses in workh...
</Question>
<Choice>Nightingale, Florence</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American actor (b. Sept. 25, 1952, New York, N.Y.—d. Oct. 10, 2004, Mount Kisco, N.Y.), was first known to the moviegoing public as the title character in Superman (1978) and went on to star in three sequels as well as a number of other films. After a fall from a horse during an equestrian competition in 1995 broke his neck and left him a quadriplegic, however, he took on a new, even more heroic role—that of activist for medical research, including the search for a cure for spinal-cord injuries. Reeve grew up in Princeton, N.J., where he performed in school plays and was involved with the loca...
</Question>
<Choice>Reeve, Christopher</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American first lady (1933–45), the wife of Franklin D. Roosevelt, 32nd president of the United States, and a United Nations diplomat and humanitarian. She was, in her time, one of the world's most widely admired and powerful women.Eleanor was the daughter of Elliott Roosevelt and Anna Hall Roosevelt and the niece of Theodore Roosevelt, 26th president of the United States. She grew up in a wealthy family that attached great value to community service. Both her parents died before she was 10, and she and her surviving brother (another brother died when she was 9) were raised by relatives. The de...
</Question>
<Choice>Roosevelt, Eleanor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American philanthropist whose exceptional generosity in her lifetime, especially to numerous educational and social causes, is continued by the Russell Sage Foundation, which she established.Margaret Slocum graduated from the Troy (New York) Female Seminary (now the Emma Willard School) in 1847, and over the next 22 years she taught school occasionally as her health permitted. In 1869 she married the widower Russell B. Sage, a businessman who had built a fortune from wholesale groceries, banking, and railroad finance. Russell Sage's underwriting of the education of 40 Native American children,...
</Question>
<Choice>Sage, Margaret Olivia Slocum</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jamaican nurse who cared for British soldiers at the battlefront during the Crimean War.Her father was a Scottish soldier and her mother a free black Jamaican woman who was skilled in traditional medicine and provided care for invalids at her boardinghouse. In 1836 Grant married Edwin Horatio Seacole, and, during their trips to the Bahamas, Haiti, and Cuba, she augmented her knowledge of local medicines and treatments. After her husband's death in 1844, she gained further nursing experience during a cholera epidemic in Panama, and, after returning to Jamaica, she cared for yellow fever victims...
</Question>
<Choice>Seacole, Mary</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
founder of the Order of the Missionaries of Charity, a Roman Catholic congregation of women dedicated to the poor, particularly to the destitute of India. She was the recipient of numerous honours, including the 1979 Nobel Prize for Peace.The daughter of an ethnic Albanian grocer, she went to Ireland in 1928 to join the Sisters of Loretto at the Institute of the Blessed Virgin Mary and sailed only six weeks later to India as a teacher. She taught for 17 years at the order's school in Calcutta (Kolkata).In 1946 Sister Teresa experienced her “call within a call,” which she considered divine insp...
</Question>
<Choice>Teresa, Blessed Mother</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
South African Anglican cleric who in 1984 received the Nobel Prize for Peace for his role in the opposition to apartheid in South Africa.Tutu was born of Xhosa and Tswana parents and was educated in South African mission schools at which his father taught. Though he wanted a medical career, Tutu was unable to afford training and instead became a schoolteacher in 1955. He resigned his post in 1957. He then attended St. Peter's Theological College in Johannesburg and was ordained an Anglican priest in 1961. In 1962 he moved to London, where in 1966 he obtained an M.A. from King's College, London...
</Question>
<Choice>Tutu, Desmond</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Brazilian diplomat (b. March 15, 1948, Rio de Janeiro, Braz.—d. Aug. 19, 2003, Baghdad, Iraq), dedicated his life to attempting to bring peace, assisting refugees, and aiding humanitarian relief in many of the most volatile trouble spots all over the world. For over 30 years he worked at resolving conflicts—guiding such notable successes as the restoration of order in Kosovo in 1999 and the transition of East Timor to independence from Indonesia in 2002—and many thought he would follow Kofi Annan as UN secretary-general. Vieira de Mello was educated at the Sorbonne, earning a degree in philoso...
</Question>
<Choice>Vieira de Mello, Sérgio</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
founder and head (1961–2003) of the Jewish Documentation Centre in Vienna. Wiesenthal was a longtime Nazi-hunter who, with the cooperation of the Israeli, West German, and other governments, tracked down more than 1,000 war criminals.Wiesenthal received a degree in architectural engineering from the Technical University of Prague (1932) and settled in Lwów, Poland (now Lviv, Ukraine). When the city was seized by the Soviet Union in 1939, he had to close his “bourgeois” architectural practice but avoided being exiled to Siberia by bribing a commissar of the NKVD (Soviet secret police). After th...
</Question>
<Choice>Wiesenthal, Simon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British politician and philanthropist who from 1787 was prominent in the struggle to abolish the slave trade and then to abolish slavery itself in British overseas possessions.He studied at St. John's College at the University of Cambridge, where he became a close friend of the future prime minister William Pitt the Younger and was known as an amiable companion rather than an outstanding student. In 1780 both he and Pitt entered the House of Commons, and he soon began to support parliamentary reform and Roman Catholic political emancipation, acquiring a reputation for radicalism that later emb...
</Question>
<Choice>Wilberforce, William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American television personality, actress, and entrepreneur whose syndicated daily talk show was among the most popular of the genre. She became one of the richest and most influential women in the United States.Winfrey moved to Milwaukee, Wisconsin, at age six to live with her mother. In her early teens she was sent to Nashville, Tennessee, to live with her father, who proved to be a positive influence in her life.At age 19, Winfrey became a news anchor for the local CBS television station. Following her graduation from Tennessee State University in 1976, she was made a reporter and coanchor f...
</Question>
<Choice>Winfrey, Oprah</Choice>
</item>
</topics>