<topics>
<item>
<Question>
noted English scholar and murderer, whose notoriety was romanticized in a ballad by Thomas Hood and in the novel Eugene Aram (1832), by Bulwer-Lytton.In 1745, when Aram was schoolmaster at Knaresborough, a man named Daniel Clark, his intimate friend, after obtaining a considerable quantity of goods from tradesmen, disappeared. Suspicions of being concerned in this swindling transaction fell upon Aram. His garden was searched, and some of the goods were found there. However, because there was insufficient evidence to convict him of any crime, he was discharged. For several years he traveled thr...
</Question>
<Choice>Aram, Eugene</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American serial killer who murdered six people in New York City in 1976–77. His crimes plunged the city into a panic and unleashed one of the largest manhunts in New York history.Berkowitz was a difficult and occasionally violent child. His erratic behaviour, which began after the death of his adoptive mother in 1967, intensified when his adoptive father remarried in 1971 and moved to Florida without him. In 1971 Berkowitz joined the army, and he became an excellent marksman before he left the service in 1974. According to Berkowitz's diary, he set some 1,500 fires in New York City in the mid-...
</Question>
<Choice>Berkowitz, David</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
member of one of the United States' most distinguished acting families of the 19th century, who assassinated President Abraham Lincoln.The ninth of ten children born to the actor Junius Brutus Booth, he early showed excellent theatrical potential but also exhibited an emotional instability and a driving egocentricity that made it difficult for him to accept his brother Edwin's rise to acclaim as the foremost actor of the day.After an unsuccessful Baltimore theatrical debut in 1856, John played minor roles in Philadelphia until 1859, when he joined a Shakespearean stock company in Richmond, Vir...
</Question>
<Choice>Booth, John Wilkes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American woman suspected of murdering her stepmother and father; her trial became a national sensation in the United States.Borden was the daughter of a well-to-do businessman who married for a second time in 1865, three years after Lizzie's mother died. Lizzie was popular and engaged in charitable work. Her father, by contrast, was reputedly dour and parsimonious—as well as eminently wealthy—and Lizzie and her elder sister Emma were ever at odds with him and their stepmother, often over financial matters. On a Thursday morning, August 4, 1892, Mr. Borden left home to conduct his business, lea...
</Question>
<Choice>Borden, Lizzie</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American serial killer who murdered at least 11 women in the Boston area between 1962 and 1964. His crimes were the subject of numerous books and a film, though the exact number of victims—as well as his identity—remains a matter of controversy.The Boston Strangler's first victim, a 55-year-old woman, was sexually assaulted and strangled in her ransacked apartment on June 14, 1962. During the following months, several other women, ranging in age from 65 to 85 years, were murdered in similar circumstances, news of which engulfed the city in panic. The Boston police chief transferred nearly all...
</Question>
<Choice>Boston Strangler</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French noblewoman who was executed (1676) after poisoning numerous family members.She was the daughter of Antoine Dreux d'Aubray, a civil lieutenant of Paris, and in 1651 she married an army officer, Antoine Gobelin de Brinvilliers. An attractive libertine, she became the mistress of a friend of her husband, J.-B. Godin de Sainte-Croix. Her father intervened, and Sainte-Croix was sent to the Bastille in 1663. On his release he plotted with her to take revenge on d'Aubray by poisoning him. With the assistance of one of the king's apothecaries, Sainte-Croix obtained poisons, which she tested on...
</Question>
<Choice>
Brinvilliers, Marie-Madeleine-Marguérite d'Aubray, marquise de
</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman general who participated in the assassination of the dictator Julius Caesar, though he had been Caesar's protégé.After serving under Caesar in Gaul, Brutus was given command of Caesar's fleet. In 49, during the Civil War between Caesar and Pompey, he led a fleet at the siege of Massilia (now Marseille, France). Caesar then made him governor of Transalpine Gaul (48–46), designated him for a consulship in 42, and nominated him as one of his heirs in the event of the death of his primary successor, Octavian (later the emperor Augustus).After taking part in the assassination of Caesar in Mar...
</Question>
<Choice>Brutus Albinus, Decimus Junius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman politician, one of the leaders in the conspiracy that assassinated Julius Caesar in 44 BC. Brutus was the son of Marcus Junius Brutus (who was treacherously killed by Pompey the Great in 77) and Servilia (who later became Caesar's lover). After his adoption by an uncle, Quintus Servilius Caepio, he was commonly called Quintus Caepio Brutus.Brutus was brought up by another uncle, Cato the Younger, who imbued him with the principles of Stoicism. In the 50s he opposed Pompey's increasing power, but, upon Caesar's invasion of Italy in 49, Brutus was reconciled with Pompey and served under hi...
</Question>
<Choice>Brutus, Marcus Junius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American serial killer and rapist, one of the most notorious criminals of the late 20th century.Bundy had a difficult childhood—he had a strained relationship with his stepfather, and his shyness made him a frequent target of bullying. Later, however, his intelligence and social skills enabled him to enjoy a successful college career, and he developed a series of apparently normal emotional relationships with women. Despite this apparent stability, he sexually assaulted and killed several young women in Washington, Oregon, Colorado, Utah, and Florida between 1974 and 1978. Although he would ul...
</Question>
<Choice>Bundy, Ted</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
pair of infamous murderers for profit who killed their victims and sold the corpses to an anatomist for purposes of scientific dissection.Hare immigrated to Scotland from Ireland and wandered through several occupations before becoming keeper of a lodging house in Edinburgh, where Burke, also Irish-born, arrived in 1827. On November 29 an old pensioner died in the house, and Hare, angry that the deceased still owed 4 pounds in rent, devised a plan to steal the corpse from its coffin and sell it to recover the money he was owed. With Burke's aid, the pair sold the corpse to Robert Knox, a surge...
</Question>
<Choice>Burke, William; and Hare, William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prime mover in the conspiracy to assassinate Julius Caesar in 44 BC.Little is known of his early life. As a quaestor in 53 BC, Cassius served under Marcus Licinius Crassus and saved the remnants of the Roman army defeated by the Parthians at Carrhae (modern Harran, Turkey). For the next two years he successfully repelled the Parthian attacks on Syria. Cassius became tribune in 49, and the outbreak of the civil war between Caesar and the Optimates in that year saved him from being brought to trial for extortion in Syria. In that war he at first commanded part of the fleet of Caesar's opponent,...
</Question>
<Choice>Cassius Longinus, Gaius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Soviet serial killer who murdered at least 50 people between 1978 and 1990. His case is noteworthy not only because of the large number of his victims but because efforts by Soviet police to issue warnings to the public during their investigation were hampered by the country's official ideology, which asserted that serial murder was impossible in a communist society.Chikatilo grew up in the aftermath of the great Ukrainian famine of the 1930s, during which millions of people died and many resorted to cannibalism to survive. During his childhood, he was told constantly by his parents that he ha...
</Question>
<Choice>Chikatilo, Andrei Romanovich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the assassin of the French revolutionary Jean-Paul Marat.Descended from a noble family, educated in a convent at Caen, and royalist by sentiment, yet susceptible also to the ideals of the Enlightenment, Corday was living with an aunt in Caen when it became a centre of the “federalist” movement against the National Convention after the expulsion of the Girondins in May–June 1793. Inspired especially by Charles Barbaroux among the Girondin refugees, she left for Paris to work for the Girondin cause.There Corday solicited an interview with Marat because of the influence of his newspaper over the...
</Question>
<Choice>Corday, Charlotte</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American serial killer whose arrest in 1991 provoked controversy and resulted in an upsurge of popular interest in serial murder and other crimes.Dahmer committed his first murder in Bath township, Ohio, in 1978. A second murder followed in 1987, and during the next five years he killed another 15 boys and young men, most of them in Milwaukee, Wis. Although other serial murderers had claimed far more victims, Dahmer's crimes were particularly gruesome, involving cannibalism and necrophilia. In February 1992 Dahmer was sentenced to 15 consecutive life terms; a 16th consecutive life sentence was...
</Question>
<Choice>Dahmer, Jeffrey</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Belgian serial killer whose case provoked outrage at the lax response of law enforcement agencies. So intense was the public's reaction that more than one-third of Belgians with the surname Dutroux changed their names.Dutroux had a lengthy record as a juvenile delinquent and petty criminal, and the seriousness of his crimes increased as he grew older. Later, as an unemployed electrician, he acquired various landholdings with money gained through auto theft and pimping. In 1989 Dutroux was convicted of five sexual assaults and sentenced to 13 years in prison, though he was released after only t...
</Question>
<Choice>Dutroux, Marc</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American serial killer whose murders of 33 boys and young men in the 1970s received international media attention and shocked his suburban Chicago community, where he was known for his sociability and his performance as a clown at charitable events and childrens' parties.Gacy was born into a blue-collar family and seems to have had a fairly ordinary childhood. But he exhibited a growing tendency toward sadism, which resulted in several encounters with the law in the 1960s. In 1968, after his conviction for sexually assaulting a teenage boy, he was confined in the Iowa State Men's Reformatory (...
</Question>
<Choice>Gacy, John Wayne</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Colombian serial killer who was convicted of murdering 189 boys in the 1990s. Many of Garavito's victims lived in poor neighbourhoods apart from their families, who could not afford to support them, leading observers to speculate that their disappearances were ignored or overlooked.Garavito, the youngest of seven children, was raised in western Colombia. He attended school for only a few years and endured a difficult childhood, suffering abuse by his father and several neighbours. During his killing spree in the 1990s, many Colombian boys, most between the ages of 8 and 16, were reported missi...
</Question>
<Choice>Garavito, Luis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American serial killer whose gruesome crimes inspired popular books and films in the second half of the 20th century. Gein's case gained worldwide notoriety, and his behaviour inspired both Robert Bloch's powerful novel Psycho (1959) and two of the most influential horror films ever made, Psycho (1960), directed by Alfred Hitchcock and based on Bloch's book, and The Texas Chainsaw Massacre (1974).Gein endured a difficult childhood. His father was an alcoholic, and his mother was verbally abusive toward him. Gein nevertheless idolized her, a fact that apparently concerned his older brother Henr...
</Question>
<Choice>Gein, Ed</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-born American carpenter and burglar who in 1935 was convicted of kidnapping and murdering the 20-month-old son of Charles and Anne Morrow Lindbergh.Hauptmann attended an elementary school and a trade school, becoming a carpenter at age 14 in Kamenz, Ger. He served in the German army (1917–18) during World War I. After the war he apparently drifted into burglary, being convicted of breaking and entering in 1919 and being arrested for possession of stolen goods in 1922 (he escaped before trial). Twice in 1923 he was arrested for illegal entry into the United States.At the Lindbergh home i...
</Question>
<Choice>Hauptmann, Bruno</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Pakistani serial killer who murdered some 100 boys. His case attracted international attention not only because he was one of the deadliest serial killers in history but because, upon his conviction, he was sentenced to die in a manner similar to that in which he had tortured and killed his victims.Little is known about Iqbal's early life. Although complaints of sodomy were lodged against him in 1985 and 1990, he was never convicted of any of the charges. Iqbal surrendered to Pakistani authorities in 1999 after confessing to 100 murders during a six-month period. According to his confession, h...
</Question>
<Choice>Iqbal, Javed</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
pseudonymous murderer of at least five women, all prostitutes, in or near the Whitechapel district of London's East End, from August 7 to November 10, 1888. It is one of the most famous unsolved mysteries of English crime.All but one of Jack the Ripper's victims were killed while soliciting customers on the street. In each instance the victim's throat was cut, and the body was usually mutilated in a manner indicating that the murderer had at least some knowledge of human anatomy. On one occasion half of a human kidney, which may have been extracted from a murder victim, was mailed to the polic...
</Question>
<Choice>Jack the Ripper</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German serial killer whose widely analyzed career influenced European society's understanding of serial murder, sexual violence, and sadism in the first half of the 20th century.Kürten, the third of 13 children, experienced a violent childhood. His father, an abusive alcoholic, was imprisoned for three years for attempting to molest Kürten's 13-year-old sister. Before he was 10 years old, Kürten had apparently murdered two schoolmates. During his teenage years he committed numerous petty crimes, and by the time of his last arrest he had been sentenced to prison nearly 30 times. In the Düsseldo...
</Question>
<Choice>Kürten, Peter</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
two celebrated Chicago murderers of 1924, who confessed to the kidnapping and murder of 14-year-old Robert (“Bobbie”) Franks for an “intellectual” thrill. Pleading guilty, Nathan F. Leopold, Jr. (in full Nathan Freudenthal Leopold, Jr.; ), and Richard A. Loeb (—) were defended in a bench trial by famed lawyer Clarence Darrow, who secured them life imprisonment rather than execution.Wealthy and intellectually brilliant (Leopold had graduated from the University of Chicago at 18, Loeb from the University of Michigan at 17), the two had committed several petty acts of theft and arson before attem...
</Question>
<Choice>Leopold, Nathan F, Jr.; and Loeb, Richard A.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American criminal and cult leader whose followers carried out several notorious murders in the late 1960s. Their crimes inspired the best-selling book Helter Skelter (1974).Manson was born to a 16-year-old girl and a man he would never know. After his mother was imprisoned for armed robbery, he lived with an aunt and uncle in West Virginia. Beginning at age nine, he spent much of his life in juvenile reformatories or in prison for crimes that included petty larceny, armed robbery, burglary, and auto theft.Following his release from prison in 1967, Manson moved to San Francisco, where he attrac...
</Question>
<Choice>Manson, Charles</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American terrorist (b. April 23, 1968, Pendleton, N.Y.—d. June 11, 2001, Terre Haute, Ind.), was put to death after having been convicted of bombing the Alfred P. Murrah Federal Building in Oklahoma City, Okla., on April 19, 1995; 168 persons died in the blast. McVeigh was the first federal prisoner to be executed since 1963.
</Question>
<Choice>McVeigh, Timothy James</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
assassin of Alessandro, grand duke of Tuscany. He was one of the more noted writers of the Medici family.He was the son of one Pierfrancesco of a younger, cadet branch of the Medici family. He was a writer of considerable elegance, the author of several plays, one of which, the Aridosio, was held to be among the best of his age, and he was a worshipper of Greco-Roman antiquity. Notwithstanding these tastes, when in Rome he knocked off the heads of some of the finest statues of the age of Adrian, an act by which Pope Clement VII was so incensed that he threatened to have him hanged. Thereupon L...
</Question>
<Choice>Medici, Lorenzino de'</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nazi doctor at Auschwitzextermination camp (1943–45) who selected prisoners for execution in the gas chambers and conducted medical experiments on inmates in pseudoscientific racial studies.Mengele's father was founder of a company that produced farm machinery, Firma Karl Mengele &amp; Söhne, in the village of Günzburg in Bavaria. Mengele studied philosophy in Munich in the 1920s, coming under the influence of the racial ideology of Alfred Rosenberg, and then took a medical degree at the University of Frankfurt am Main. He enlisted in the Sturmabteilung (SA; “Assault Division”) in 1933. An ard...
</Question>
<Choice>Mengele, Josef</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian serial killer or killers who murdered at least 16 people in the hills outside Florence between 1968 and 1985. The case inspired Thomas Harris's novel Hannibal (1999).In 1968 a man and a woman were murdered in a parked car near Florence by a mysterious killer whom the Italian media later dubbed Il Mostro di Firenze (“The Monster of Florence”). Although the husband of the female victim was convicted of the crime and sentenced to 14 years in prison, other couples continued to be murdered after his confinement. In 1974 the killer attacked another couple, this time mutilating the body of th...
</Question>
<Choice>Monster of Florence</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American swindler and confidence trickster who is widely considered the country's first known serial killer.Mudgett was born into a wealthy family and showed signs of high intelligence from an early age. Always interested in medicine, he allegedly trapped animals and performed surgery on them; some accounts of his life even suggest that he killed a childhood playmate. Mudgett attended medical school at the University of Michigan, where he was expelled for stealing corpses, which he used for experiments and for making false insurance claims.In 1886 Mudgett moved to Chicago and took a job as a p...
</Question>
<Choice>Mudgett, Herman Webster</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
accused assassin of U.S. President John F. Kennedy in Dallas on Nov. 22, 1963. He himself was fatally shot two days later by Jack Ruby (1911–67) in the Dallas County Jail. A special President's Commission on the Assassination of President John F. Kennedy, headed by Chief Justice Earl Warren, investigated from Nov. 29, 1963, to Sept. 24, 1964, and concluded that Oswald alone had fired the shots killing Kennedy and that there was no evidence that either Oswald or Ruby had been part of any conspiracy. In January 1979 a special U.S. House of Representatives Assassinations Committee, after a two-ye...
</Question>
<Choice>Oswald, Lee Harvey</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
South Slav nationalist who assassinated Archduke Francis Ferdinand, heir to the Austro-Hungarian throne, and his consort, Sophie, Duchess von Hohenberg (née Chotek), at Sarajevo, Bosnia, on June 28, 1914. Princip's act gave Austria-Hungary the excuse that it had sought for opening hostilities against Serbia and thus precipitated World War I. In Yugoslavia—the South Slav state that he had envisioned—Princip came to be regarded as a national hero.Born into a Bosnian Serb peasant family, Princip was trained in terrorism by the Serbian secret society known as the Black Hand (true name Ujedinjenje...
</Question>
<Choice>Princip, Gavrilo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American assassin of the black civil-rights leader Martin Luther King, Jr.Ray had been a small-time crook, a robber of gas stations and stores, who had served time in prison, once in Illinois and twice in Missouri, and received a suspended sentence in Los Angeles. He escaped from the Missouri State Penitentiary on April 23, 1967; and in Memphis, Tenn., nearly a year later, on April 4, 1968, from a window of a neighbouring rooming house, he shot King, who was standing on the balcony of a motel room.Ray fled to Toronto, secured a Canadian passport through a travel agency, flew to London (May 5),...
</Question>
<Choice>Ray, James Earl</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British doctor and serial killer who murdered at least 215 of his patients. His crimes raised troubling questions about the powers and responsibilities of the medical community in Britain and about the adequacy of procedures for certifying sudden death.Shipman was born into a working-class family in Manchester. A bright child, he became interested in medicine as he watched his mother receive morphine injections to ease the pain she suffered while dying of lung cancer. In 1970 he received a medical degree from Leeds University, and a few years later he became a general practitioner in Todmorden...
</Question>
<Choice>Shipman, Harold</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American criminal, a convicted murderer who became a self-taught ornithologist during his 54 years in prison, 42 of them in solitary confinement, and made notable contributions to the study of birds.At the age of 13 Stroud ran away from home and, by the age of 18, was in Juneau, Alaska, working as a pimp and living with a dance-hall girl. An argument over the girl led to his fighting and killing a man. Pleading guilty to manslaughter on Aug. 23, 1909, he was sentenced to 12 years in federal prison on McNeil Island in Puget Sound. After stabbing a fellow prisoner and proving generally troubleso...
</Question>
<Choice>Stroud, Robert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American serial killer who murdered at least seven people in 1989–90. Her case drew national attention to issues such as the relationship between gender and violence and the legal treatment of acts of self-defense by women. Her life was the subject of a documentary, Aileen: The Selling of a Serial Killer (1992), and a film, Monster (2003).Wuornos had a deeply troubled childhood. Her parents separated before her birth, and her father later spent time in mental hospitals for child molestation. When Wuornos was four years old, she and her brother were sent to live with her grandparents. In her ea...
</Question>
<Choice>Wuornos, Aileen</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
unidentified American serial killer who is believed to have murdered six people, primarily in northern California, between 1966 and 1969. The case inspired the influential 1971 film Dirty Harry, which starred Clint Eastwood.The Zodiac killer's apparent first victim, an 18-year-old college student, was stabbed to death in Riverside, Calif., in 1966. Although this murder is commonly attributed to the Zodiac killer, some experts claim it was not committed by him. Soon after the murder, a local newspaper received a letter that provided details of the crime and declared that the victim was neither...
</Question>
<Choice>Zodiac killer</Choice>
</item>
</topics>