<topics>
<item>
<Question>
in Greek mythology, son of the mortal Peleus, king of the Myrmidons, and the Nereid, or sea nymph, Thetis. He was the bravest, handsomest, and greatest warrior of the army of Agamemnon in the Trojan War. According to Homer, Achilles was brought up by his mother at Phthia with his cousin and inseparable companion Patroclus. One of the non-Homeric tales of his childhood relates that Thetis dipped Achilles in the waters of the River Styx, by which he became invulnerable, except for the part of his heel by which she held him—the proverbial “Achilles' heel.”The later mythographers related that Pele...
</Question>
<Choice>Achilles</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
in Greek mythology, son of the minor god Aristaeus and Autonoë (daughter of Cadmus, the founder of Thebes in Boeotia); he was a Boeotian hero and hunter. According to Ovid's Metamorphoses, Actaeon accidentally saw Artemis (goddess of wild animals, vegetation, and childbirth) while she was bathing on Mount Cithaeron; for this reason he was changed by her into a stag and was pursued and killed by his own 50 hounds. In another version, he offended Artemis by boasting that his skill as a hunter surpassed hers.The story was well-known in antiquity, and several of the tragic poets presented it on th...
</Question>
<Choice>Actaeon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
mythical hero of Troy and Rome, son of the goddess Aphrodite and Anchises. Aeneas was a member of the royal line at Troy and cousin of Hector. He played a prominent part in the war to defend his city against the Greeks, being second only to Hector in ability. Homer implies that Aeneas did not like his subordinate position, and from that suggestion arose a later tradition that Aeneas helped to betray Troy to the Greeks. The more common version, however, made Aeneas the leader of the Trojan survivors after Troy was taken by the Greeks. In any case, Aeneas survived the war, and his figure was thu...
</Question>
<Choice>Aeneas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
in Greek legend, son of Telamon, king of Salamis, described in the Iliad as being of great stature and colossal frame, second only to the Greek hero Achilles in strength and bravery. He engaged Hector (the chief Trojan warrior) in single combat and later, with the aid of the goddess Athena, rescued the body of Achilles from the hands of the Trojans. He competed with the Greek hero Odysseus for the armour of Achilles but lost, which so enraged him that it caused his death. According to a later story Ajax' disappointment drove him mad. On coming to his senses he slew himself with the sword that...
</Question>
<Choice>Ajax</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
hero of one of the best-known stories in The Thousand and One Nights.The son of a deceased Chinese tailor and his poor widow, Aladdin is a lazy, careless boy who meets an African magician claiming to be his uncle. The magician brings Aladdin to the mouth of a cave and bids him enter and bring out a wonderful lamp that is inside, giving him a magic ring for his safety in the meantime. Aladdin goes in and returns with the lamp but refuses to hand it over to the magician until he is safely out of the cave. The magician thereupon shuts him inside the cave with the lamp and departs. Wringing his ha...
</Question>
<Choice>Aladdin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
legendary British king who appears in a cycle of medieval romances (known as the matter of Britain) as the sovereign of a knightly fellowship of the Round Table. It is not certain how or where (in Wales or in those parts of northern Britain inhabited by Brythonic-speaking Celts) these legends originated or whether the figure Arthur was based on a historical person. See alsoArthurian legend.Assumptions that a historical Arthur led Welsh resistance to the West Saxon advance from the middle Thames are based on a conflation of two early writers, the religious polemicist Gildas and the historian Ne...
</Question>
<Choice>Arthur</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
in Greek mythology, son of the Titan Iapetus and the Oceanid Clymene (or Asia) and brother of Prometheus (creator of mankind). In Homer's Odyssey, Book I, Atlas seems to have been a marine creature who supported the pillars that held heaven and earth apart. These were thought to rest in the sea immediately beyond the most western horizon, but later the name of Atlas was transferred to a range of mountains in northwestern Africa. Atlas was subsequently represented as the king of that district, turned into a rocky mountain by the hero Perseus, who, to punish Atlas for his inhospitality, showed h...
</Question>
<Choice>Atlas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
heroic poem, the highest achievement of Old English literature and the earliest European vernacular epic. Preserved in a single manuscript (Cotton Vitellius A XV) from c. 1000, it deals with events of the early 6th century and is believed to have been composed between 700 and 750. It did not appear in print until 1815. Although originally untitled, it was later named after the Scandinavian hero Beowulf, whose exploits and character provide its connecting theme. There is no evidence of a historical Beowulf, but some characters, sites, and events in the poem can be historically verified.The poem...
</Question>
<Choice>Beowulf</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
giant lumberjack, mythical hero of the lumber camps in the United States, a symbol of bigness, strength, and vitality. The tales and anecdotes that form the Paul Bunyan legend are typical of the tradition of frontier tall tales. Paul and his companions, Babe the Blue Ox and Johnny Inkslinger, are undismayed by rains that last for months, giant mosquitoes, or adverse geography. The tales describe how Paul, who fashions lakes and rivers at will, created Puget Sound, the Grand Canyon, and the Black Hills. They celebrate the lumbermen's prodigious appetites. Paul's camp stove covers an acre, and h...
</Question>
<Choice>Bunyan, Paul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Castilian military leader and national hero. His popular name, El Cid (from Spanish Arabic al-s?d, “lord”), dates from his lifetime.
</Question>
<Choice>Cid, the</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
in the mythology and folklore of the North American Plains, California, and Southwest Indians, the chief animal of the age before humans. Coyote's exploits as a creator, lover, magician, glutton, and trickster are celebrated in a vast number of oral tales (seetrickster tale). He was typically portrayed as a demiurge (independent creative force), as a maker of fateful decisions, as the being who secured for humans such necessities as fire and daylight, and as the originator of human arts. In all cases, his transgression of normative social boundaries frequently resulted in social or physical ch...
</Question>
<Choice>Coyote</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
fictitious character who is a symbol of libertinism. Originating in popular legend, he was first given literary personality in the tragic drama El burlador de Sevilla (1630; “The Seducer of Seville,” translated in The Trickster of Seville and the Stone Guest), attributed to the Spanish dramatist Tirso de Molina. Through Tirso's tragedy, Don Juan became a universal character, as familiar as Don Quixote, Hamlet, and Faust. Subsequently, he became the hero-villain of plays, novels, and poems; his legend was assured enduring popularity through Mozart's opera Don Giovanni (1787).The legend of Don J...
</Question>
<Choice>Don Juan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
ancient Sumerian hero and king of Uruk (Erech), a city-state in southern Mesopotamia, who is thought to have lived at the end of the 4th or beginning of the 3rd millennium BC. Along with Lugalbanda and Gilgamesh, Enmerkar is one of the three most significant figures in the surviving Sumerian epics.Although scholars once assumed that there was only one epic relating Enmerkar's subjugation of a rival city, Aratta, it is now believed that two separate epics tell this tale. One is called Enmerkar and the Lord of Aratta. The longest Sumerian epic yet discovered, it is the source of important inform...
</Question>
<Choice>Enmerkar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
hero of one of the most durable legends in Western folklore and literature, the story of a German necromancer or astrologer who sells his soul to the devil in exchange for knowledge and power. There was a historical Faust, indeed perhaps two, one of whom more than once alluded to the devil as his Schwager, or crony. One or both died about 1540, leaving a tangled legend of sorcery and alchemy, astrology and soothsaying, studies theological and diabolical, necromancy and, indeed, sodomy. Contemporary references indicate that he was widely traveled and fairly well known, but all observers testify...
</Question>
<Choice>Faust</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the pure knight in Arthurian romance, son of Lancelot du Lac and Elaine (daughter of Pelles), who achieved the vision of God through the Holy Grail. In the first romance treatments of the Grail story (e.g., Chrétien de Troyes's 12th-century Conte du Graal), Perceval was the Grail hero. But during the 13th century a new, austerely spiritual significance was given to the Grail theme, and a new Grail winner was required whose genealogy could be traced back to the House of David in the Old Testament. Galahad was, moreover, made the son of Lancelot so that an achievement inspired by earthly love (L...
</Question>
<Choice>Galahad</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the best known of all ancient Mesopotamian heroes. Numerous tales in the Akkadian language have been told about Gilgamesh, and the whole collection has been described as an odyssey—the odyssey of a king who did not want to die.The fullest extant text of the Gilgamesh epic is on 12 incomplete Akkadian-language tablets found at Nineveh in the library of the Assyrian king Ashurbanipal (reigned 668–627 BCE). The gaps that occur in the tablets have been partly filled by various fragments found elsewhere in Mesopotamia and Anatolia. In addition, five short poems in the Sumerian language are known fr...
</Question>
<Choice>Gilgamesh</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
in Greek legend, the eldest son of the Trojan king Priam and his queen Hecuba. He was the husband of Andromache and the chief warrior of the Trojan army. In Homer's Iliad he is represented as an ideal warrior and the mainstay of Troy. His character is drawn in most favourable colours as a good son, a loving husband and father, and a trusty friend. His leave-taking of Andromache in the sixth book of the Iliad, and his departure to meet Achilles for the last time, are movingly described. He is an especial favourite of Apollo, and later poets even described him as son of that god. His chief explo...
</Question>
<Choice>Hector</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
most famous Greco-Roman legendary hero. Traditionally, Heracles was the son of Zeus and Alcmene (seeAmphitryon), granddaughter of Perseus. Zeus swore that the next son born of the Perseid house should become ruler of Greece, but by a trick of Zeus's jealous wife, Hera, another child, the sickly Eurystheus, was born first and became king; when Heracles grew up, he had to serve him and also suffer the vengeful persecution of Hera. His first exploit, in fact, was the strangling of two serpents that she had sent to kill him in his cradle.Later, Heracles waged a victorious war against the kingdom o...
</Question>
<Choice>Heracles</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(Ojibwa: “He Makes Rivers”), a legendary chief (c. 1450) of the Onondaga tribe of North American Indians, to whom Indian tradition attributes the formation of what became known as the Iroquois Confederacy. In his miraculous character, Hiawatha was the incarnation of human progress and civilization. He taught agriculture, navigation, medicine, and the arts, conquering by his magic all the powers of nature that war against man. The story of Hiawatha is told in Henry Wadsworth Longfellow's Song of Hiawatha (1855), a long poem, written in the metre of the Finnish Kalevala, that enjoyed wide popula...
</Question>
<Choice>Hiawatha</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
fictional character created by the Scottish writer Sir Arthur Conan Doyle. The prototype for the modern mastermind detective, Holmes first appeared in Conan Doyle's A Study in Scarlet, published in Beeton's Christmas Annual of 1887. As the world's first and only “consulting detective,” he pursued criminals throughout Victorian and Edwardian London, the south of England, and continental Europe. Although the fictional detective had been anticipated by Edgar Allan Poe's C. Auguste Dupin and Émile Gaboriau's Monsieur Lecoq, Holmes made a singular impact upon the popular imagination and has become...
</Question>
<Choice>Holmes, Sherlock</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
third of ancient China's mythological emperors, a culture hero and patron saint of Daoism.Huangdi is reputed to have been born about 2704 BC and to have begun his rule as emperor in 2697. His legendary reign is credited with the introduction of wooden houses, carts, boats, the bow and arrow, and writing. Huangdi himself is credited with defeating “barbarians” in a great battle somewhere in what is now Shanxi—the victory winning him the leadership of tribes throughout the Huang He (Yellow River) plain. Some traditions also credit him with the introduction of governmental institutions and the us...
</Question>
<Choice>Huangdi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
in Greek mythology, leader of the Argonauts and son of Aeson, king of Iolcos in Thessaly. His father's half-brother Pelias seized Iolcos, and thus for safety Jason was sent away to the Centaur Chiron. Returning as a young man, Jason was promised his inheritance if he fetched the Golden Fleece for Pelias, a seemingly impossible task. After many adventures (seeArgonaut) Jason abstracted the fleece with the help of the enchantress Medea, whom he married. On their return Medea murdered Pelias, but she and Jason were driven out by Pelias' son and had to take refuge with King Creon of Corinth. Later...
</Question>
<Choice>Jason</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
hero of a widely sung U.S. black folk ballad. It describes his contest with a steam drill, in which John Henry crushed more rock than did the machine but died “with his hammer in his hand.” Writers and artists see in John Henry a symbol of man's foredoomed struggle against the machine and of the black man's tragic battle with the white man.Some factual basis exists for the ballad of John Henry. When the Chesapeake and Ohio Railroad drove the Big Bend Tunnel through the Allegheny Mountains in West Virginia, from 1870 to 1873, steel drivers hammered steel drills into the rock to make holes into...
</Question>
<Choice>John Henry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
one of the greatest knights in Arthurian romance; he was the lover of Arthur's queen, Guinevere, and was the father of the pure knight Sir Galahad.Lancelot's name first appeared as one of Arthur's knights in Chrétien de Troyes's 12th-century romance of Erec, and the same author later made him the hero of Lancelot; ou, le chevalier de la charrette, which retold an existing legend about Guinevere's abduction, making Lancelot her rescuer and lover. It also mentioned Lancelot's upbringing by a fairy in a lake, a story that received fuller treatment in the German poem Lanzelet. These two themes wer...
</Question>
<Choice>Lancelot</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the knight of the swan, hero of German versions of a legend widely known in variant forms from the European Middle Ages onward. It seems to bear some relation to the northern European folktale of “The Seven Swans,” but its actual origin is uncertain. The basic story tells of a mysterious knight who arrives—in a boat drawn by a swan—to help a noble lady in distress. He marries her but forbids her to ask his origin; she later forgets this promise, and he leaves her, never to return.The first German version of this old legend—which itself probably derives from a fairy tale of seven brothers who a...
</Question>
<Choice>Lohengrin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
renegade lawman in the American West, a fictional character of American radio and television programs, books, films, and comics.In all media the Lone Ranger fictions are similar. John Reid was born in 1850 and was the sole survivor of a group of Texas Rangers who were ambushed by outlaws who killed five rangers, including his older brother, Daniel. The Indian Tonto found him and nursed him to health. Reid then donned a black mask made from his dead brother's vest, mounted his stallion, Silver, and roamed the West as the Lone Ranger to aid those in need, to fight evil, and to establish justice....
</Question>
<Choice>Lone Ranger</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
one of the major figures in the surviving Sumerian epics and the hero of the tale called the Lugalbanda Epic, or Lugalbanda and Enmerkar. See Enmerkar.
</Question>
<Choice>Lugalbanda</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
in Greek mythology, the most famous of the monster figures known as Gorgons. She was usually represented as a winged female creature having a head of hair consisting of snakes; unlike the Gorgons, she was sometimes represented as very beautiful. Medusa was the only Gorgon who was mortal; hence her slayer, Perseus, was able to kill her by cutting off her head. From the blood that spurted from her neck sprang Chrysaor and Pegasus, her two sons by Poseidon. The severed head, which had the power of turning into stone all who looked upon it, was given to Athena, who placed it in her shield; accordi...
</Question>
<Choice>Medusa</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
enchanter and wise man in Arthurian legend and romance of the Middle Ages, linked with personages in ancient Celtic mythology (especially with Myrddin in Welsh tradition). He appeared in Arthurian legend as an enigmatic figure, fluctuations and inconsistencies in his character being often dictated by the requirements of a particular narrative or by varying attitudes of suspicious regard toward magic and witchcraft. Thus, treatments of Merlin reflect different stages in the development of Arthurian romance itself.Geoffrey of Monmouth, in Historia regum Britanniae (1135–38), adapted a story, tol...
</Question>
<Choice>Merlin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
in Greek mythology, a fabulous monster of Crete that had the body of a man and the head of a bull. It was the offspring of Pasiphae, the wife of Minos, and a snow-white bull sent to Minos by the god Poseidon for sacrifice. Minos, instead of sacrificing it, kept it alive; Poseidon as a punishment made Pasiphae fall in love with it. Her child by the bull was shut up in the Labyrinth created for Minos by Daedalus.A son of Minos, Androgeos, was later killed by the Athenians; to avenge his death, Minos demanded that seven Athenian youths and seven maidens should be sent every ninth year (or, accord...
</Question>
<Choice>Minotaur</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
fairy enchantress of Arthurian legend and romance.Geoffrey of Monmouth's Vita Merlini (c. 1150) named her as the ruler of Avalon, a marvelous island where King Arthur was to be healed of his wounds, and it described her as skilled in the arts of healing and of changing shape. In Chrétien de Troyes's romance of Erec (c. 1165), she first appeared as King Arthur's sister. In 12th- and 13th-century elaborations of Arthurian legend, two themes, of healing and of hostility (owing to unrequited love), were developed: in the early 13th-century Vulgate cycle, for example, she was responsible for stirri...
</Question>
<Choice>Morgan Le Fay</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
hero of Homer's epic poem the Odyssey and one of the most frequently portrayed figures in Western literature. According to Homer, Odysseus was king of Ithaca, son of Laertes and Anticleia (the daughter of Autolycus of Parnassus), and father, by his wife, Penelope, of Telemachus. (In later tradition, Odysseus was instead the son of Sisyphus and fathered sons by Circe, Calypso, and others.)Homer portrayed Odysseus as a man of outstanding wisdom and shrewdness, eloquence, resourcefulness, courage, and endurance. In the Iliad, Odysseus appears as the man best suited to cope with crises in personal...
</Question>
<Choice>Odysseus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
ancient Greek legendary hero endowed with superhuman musical skills. He became the patron of a religious movement based on sacred writings said to be his own.Traditionally, Orpheus was the son of a Muse (probably Calliope, the patron of epic poetry) and Oeagrus, a king of Thrace (other versions give Apollo). According to some legends, Apollo gave Orpheus his first lyre. Orpheus's singing and playing were so beautiful that animals and even trees and rocks moved about him in dance.Orpheus joined the expedition of the Argonauts, saving them from the music of the Sirens by playing his own, more po...
</Question>
<Choice>Orpheus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
hero of Arthurian romance, distinguished by his quality of childlike (often uncouth) innocence, which protected him from worldly temptation and set him apart from other knights in Arthur's fellowship. This quality also links his story with the primitive folktale theme of a great fool or simple hero. In Chrétien de Troyes's poem Le Conte du Graal (12th century), Perceval's great adventure was a visit to the castle of the wounded Fisher King, where he saw a mysterious dish (or grail) but, having previously been scolded for asking too many questions, failed to ask the question that would have hea...
</Question>
<Choice>Perceval</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
in Greek mythology, the slayer of the Gorgon Medusa and the rescuer of Andromeda from a sea monster. Perseus was the son of Zeus and Danaë, the daughter of Acrisius of Argos. As an infant he was cast into the sea in a chest with his mother by Acrisius, to whom it had been prophesied that he would be killed by his grandson. After Perseus had grown up on the island of Seriphus, where the chest had grounded, King Polydectes of Seriphus, who desired Danaë, tricked Perseus into promising to obtain the head of Medusa, the only mortal among the Gorgons.Aided by Hermes and Athena, Perseus pressed the...
</Question>
<Choice>Perseus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
a pugnacious, wisecracking cartoon sailor who possesses superhuman strength after ingesting an always-handy can of spinach. Popeye was created by Elzie Crisler Segar, who in 1929 introduced the character into his existing newspaper cartoon strip, Thimble Theatre.Popeye is a scrappy little seaman with bulging forearms, a squinty eye, and a screwed-up face, punctuated with an ever-present pipe in his mouth. He is always ready for a fight instead of a reasonable discussion, has a gravelly voice, and is constantly mumbling under his breath. His credo is “I yam what I yam, and that's all what I yam...
</Question>
<Choice>Popeye</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
legendary outlaw hero of a series of English ballads, some of which date from at least as early as the 14th century. Robin Hood was a rebel, and many of the most striking episodes in the tales about him show him and his companions robbing and killing representatives of authority and giving the gains to the poor. Their most frequent enemy was the Sheriff of Nottingham, a local agent of the central government (though internal evidence from the early ballads makes it clear that the action took place chiefly in south Yorkshire, not in Nottinghamshire). Other enemies included wealthy ecclesiastical...
</Question>
<Choice>Robin Hood</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Israelite hero portrayed in an epic narrative in the Old Testament (Judg. 13–16). He was a Nazirite (q.v.) and a legendary warrior whose incredible exploits hint at the weight of Philistine pressure on Israel during much of the early, tribal period of Israel in Canaan (1200–1000). The Book of Judges ranks him with other divinely inspired warriors who delivered the community to establish themselves as its judges.The Old Testament narrative, only alluding to Samson's “twenty years” activity as a judge, presents a few episodes, principally concerned with the beginning and the end of his activity....
</Question>
<Choice>Samson</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
legendary Roman hero who is said to have saved Rome (c. 509 BC) from conquest by the Etruscan king Lars Porsena. According to the legend, Mucius volunteered to assassinate Porsena, who was besieging Rome, but killed his victim's attendant by mistake. Brought before the Etruscan royal tribunal, he declared that he was one of 300 noble youths who had sworn to take the king's life. He demonstrated his courage to his captors by thrusting his right hand into a blazing altar fire and holding it there until it was consumed. Deeply impressed and fearing another attempt on his life, Porsena ordered Muc...
</Question>
<Choice>Scaevola, Gaius Mucius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
figure from the heroic literature of the ancient Germanic people. He appears in both German and Old Norse literature, although the versions of his stories told by these two branches of the Germanic tradition do not always agree. He plays a part in the story of Brunhild (q.v.), in which he meets his death, but in other stories he is the leading character and triumphs. A feature common to all versions is his outstanding strength and courage.One story tells of Siegfried's fight with a dragon, and another of how he acquired a treasure from two brothers who quarreled over their inheritance. These t...
</Question>
<Choice>Siegfried</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
hero of The Thousand and One Nights who recounts his adventures on seven voyages. He is not to be confused with Sindbad the Wise, hero of the frame story of the Seven Wise Masters.The stories of Sindbad's travails, which were a relatively late addition to The Thousand and One Nights, were based on the experiences of merchants from Basra (Iraq) trading under great risk with the East Indies and China, probably in the early ?Abb?sid period (750–c. 850). A strong infusion of the miraculous in the stories has exaggerated the dangers encountered.In the frame story Sindbad is marooned or shipwrecked...
</Question>
<Choice>Sindbad the Sailor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
20th-century American comic-strip superhero who first appeared in Action Comics in June 1938 and in a newspaper strip in January of the following year; both were written by Jerry Siegel and drawn by Joseph Shuster. Superman, the “man of steel,” later became the protagonist of a radio show, animated-film cartoons, a novel, a Broadway musical, a television series, and motion pictures.Superman, as the story goes, was sent as a baby to Earth by his parents from their home on the doomed planet Krypton. He was found and reared in mid-America by Martha and Jonathan Kent, who named him Clark. As a boy...
</Question>
<Choice>Superman</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss legendary hero who symbolized the struggle for political and individual freedom.The historical existence of Tell is disputed. According to popular legend, he was a peasant from Bürglen in the canton of Uri in the 13th and early 14th centuries who defied Austrian authority, was forced to shoot an apple from his son's head, was arrested for threatening the governor's life, saved the same governor's life en route to prison, escaped, and ultimately killed the governor in an ambush. These events supposedly helped spur the people to rise up against Austrian rule.The classic form of the legend...
</Question>
<Choice>Tell, William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
great hero of Attic legend, son of Aegeus, king of Athens, and Aethra, daughter of Pittheus, king of Troezen (in Argolis), or of the sea god, Poseidon, and Aethra. Legend relates that Aegeus, being childless, was allowed by Pittheus to have a child (Theseus) by Aethra. When Theseus reached manhood, Aethra sent him to Athens. On the journey he encountered many adventures. At the Isthmus of Corinth he killed Sinis, called the Pine Bender because he killed his victims by tearing them apart between two pine trees. Next Theseus dispatched the Crommyonian sow (or boar). Then from a cliff he flung th...
</Question>
<Choice>Theseus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Germanic hero who appears in the Middle High German poems of Ortnit and Wolfdietrich in Das Heldenbuch (seeHeldenbuch, Das) as the son of Hugdietrich, emperor of Constantinople. Repudiated by his father, who mistakenly believes him illegitimate, he is brought up by the emperor's faithful retainer Berchtung von Meran. Berchtung and his 16 sons support Wolfdietrich, who, after his father's death, is driven from his inheritance by his own brothers. After a long exile in Lombardy at the court of King Ortnit, the hero returns to liberate Berchtung's imprisoned sons and regain his kingdom. Among the...
</Question>
<Choice>Wolfdietrich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
one of the most popular of the legendary Japanese warrior heroes and a member of the martial Minamoto clan. In his exploits he is always accompanied by four trusty lieutenants. One adventure concerns his vanquishing the boy-faced giant Shuten-d?ji (“Drunkard Boy”), who lived on human blood and who together with his repulsive retainers terrorized the countryside around his stronghold on ?ye-yama. To gain admittance to the stronghold, Yorimitsu and his companions disguised themselves as mountain priests. They first befuddled the creatures with a magic drink, then threw off their priestly robes t...
</Question>
<Choice>Yorimitsu</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
in ancient Greek religion, chief deity of the pantheon, a sky and weather god who was identical with the Roman god Jupiter. His name clearly comes from that of the sky god Dyaus of the ancient Hindu Rigveda. Zeus was regarded as the sender of thunder and lightning, rain, and winds, and his traditional weapon was the thunderbolt. He was called the father (i.e., the ruler and protector) of both gods and men.According to a Cretan myth that was later adopted by the Greeks, Cronus, king of the Titans, upon learning that one of his children was fated to dethrone him, swallowed his children as soon a...
</Question>
<Choice>Zeus</Choice>
</item>
</topics>