<topics>
<item>
<Question>
Palestinian guerrilla leader (b. 1948/49?, near Haifa?, Palestine/Israel?—d. March 8/9, 2004, near Baghdad, Iraq), was best known as the mastermind behind the 1985 hijacking of the Italian cruise ship Achille Lauro, during which a wheelchair-bound American Jewish man, Leon Klinghoffer, was shot and pushed into the sea; this act brought worldwide condemnation, and Abbas was sentenced in absentia to life in prison in Italy. Abbas grew up in a Palestinian refugee camp in Syria and, under the nom de guerre Abu Abbas, became a rising star in Ahmad Jibril's Popular Front for the Liberation of Palest...
</Question>
<Choice>Abbas, Abu</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
leader of a revolutionary movement in Khor?s?n who, while acting as an agent for the ?Abb?sid family, was instrumental in the downfall of the Umayyad caliphate and in placing the ?Abb?sids on the throne.There are numerous versions of Ab? Muslim's background, but it seems most likely that he was descended from a slave of Persian origin and was therefore a maw?l? (non-Arab Muslim, accorded lowly status under the Umayyads). The emissary of the ?Abb?sid imam, who was briefly incarcerated, met Ab? Muslim while in prison (741) and later arranged for his release. Ab? Muslim was instructed by the imam...
</Question>
<Choice>Abu Muslim</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Arabic“Father of the Struggle”militant leader of the Fatah Revolutionary Council, more commonly known as the Ab? Ni??l Organization (ANO), or Ab? Ni??l Group, a Palestinian organization that engaged in numerous acts of terrorism beginning in the mid-1970s.Ab? Ni??l and his family fled Palestine after the 1948 war following the creation of the state of Israel, and for the next 20 years he lived in Jordan and Saudi Arabia. In the late 1960s he joined Y?sir ?Araf?t's guerrilla group, Fatah, a component of the Palestine Liberation Organization (PLO), which had as its aim wresting Palestine from Is...
</Question>
<Choice>Abu Nidal</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
president of Sinn Féin, the political wing of the Irish Republican Army (IRA), one of the chief architects of Sinn Féin's shift to a policy of seeking a peaceful settlement to sectarian violence in Northern Ireland, and a member of the British Parliament (from West Belfast) and the Northern Ireland Assembly.Born into a strongly republican family, Adams became involved in predominantly Roman Catholic civil rights protests in Belfast, Northern Ireland, which became increasingly violent in the late 1960s. By early 1970 he was suspected of heading a unit of the IRA, a republican paramilitary organ...
</Question>
<Choice>Adams, Gerry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
early advocate of American independence from Great Britain, major figure in the Continental Congress (1774–77), author of the Massachusetts constitution (1780), signer of the Treaty of Paris (1783), first American ambassador to the Court of St. James (1785–88), first vice president (1789–97) and second president (1797–1801) of the United States. Although Adams was regarded by his contemporaries as one of the most significant statesmen of the revolutionary era, his reputation faded in the 19th century, only to ascend again during the last half of the 20th century. The modern edition of his corr...
</Question>
<Choice>Adams, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician of the American Revolution, leader of the Massachusetts “radicals,” who was a delegate to the Continental Congress (1774–81) and a signer of the Declaration of Independence. He was later lieutenant governor (1789–93) and governor (1794–97) of Massachusetts.
</Question>
<Choice>Adams, Samuel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American hero and martyr of the Boston Massacre.Attucks' life prior to the day of his death is still shrouded in mystery. Most historians say that he was black; others argue that his ancestry was both African and Natick Indian. In any event, in the fall of 1750, a resident of Framingham, Mass., advertised for the recovery of a runaway slave named Crispus—usually thought to be the Crispus in question. In the 20-year interval between his escape from slavery and his death at the hands of British soldiers, Attucks probably spent a good deal of time aboard whaling ships.All that is definitely known...
</Question>
<Choice>Attucks, Crispus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American patriot, the subject of heroic tales of the Revolutionary War and early America.Anna Warner was orphaned and was reared by an uncle. On September 6, 1781, a large British force under the turncoat General Benedict Arnold landed on the coast near Groton and stormed Fort Griswold. American casualties were very high, and among them was Warner's uncle, Edward Mills. She walked several miles to the scene of battle, found her uncle after much difficulty, and learned that he was mortally wounded. At his request she hurried home, saddled a horse for her aunt, and herself carried her infant cou...
</Question>
<Choice>Bailey, Anna Warner</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
principal leader of the Algerian War of Independence against France, the first prime minister (1962–63) and first elected president (1963–65) of the Algerian republic, who steered his country toward a socialist economy.Ben Bella was the son of a farmer and small businessman in Maghnia in the département of Oran. There, he successfully completed his early studies at the French school and continued his education in the neighbouring city of Tlemcen, where he first became aware of racial discrimination and also mingled with the fringes of the nationalist movement.He was conscripted into the French...
</Question>
<Choice>Ben Bella, Ahmed</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
mastermind of numerous terrorist attacks against the United States and other Western powers, including the 1993 bombing of New York City's World Trade Center, the 2000 suicide bombing of the U.S. warship Cole in the Yemeni port of Aden, and the September 11, 2001, attacks on the World Trade Center in New York City and the Pentagon near Washington, D.C. (seeSeptember 11 attacks).Bin Laden was one of more than 50 children of one of Saudi Arabia's wealthiest families. He attended King Abdul Aziz University, where he received a degree in civil engineering. Shortly after the Soviet Union invaded Af...
</Question>
<Choice>bin Laden, Osama</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
South American soldier and statesman who led the revolutions against Spanish rule in the Viceroyalty of New Granada. He was president of Gran Colombia (1819–30) and dictator of Peru (1823–26).The son of a Venezuelan aristocrat of Spanish descent, Bolívar was born to wealth and position. After his father died when the boy was three years old and his mother died six years later, his uncle administered his inheritance and provided him with tutors. At the age of 16, Bolívar was sent to Europe to complete his education. For three years he lived in Spain and in 1801 married the daughter of a Spanish...
</Question>
<Choice>Bolívar, Simón</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian revolutionary who led an Indian national force against the Western powers during World War II.The son of a wealthy and prominent Bengali lawyer, Bose studied at Presidency College, Calcutta (Kolkata), from which he was expelled in 1916 for nationalist activities, and the Scottish Churches College (graduating in 1919). He then was sent by his parents to the University of Cambridge in England to prepare for the Indian Civil Service. In 1920 he passed the civil service examination, but in April 1921, after hearing of the nationalist turmoils in India, he resigned his candidacy and hurried...
</Question>
<Choice>Bose, Subhas Chandra</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
ancient British queen who in AD 60 led a revolt against Roman rule.Boudicca's husband, Prasutagus, was king of the Iceni (in what is now Norfolk) as a client under Roman suzerainty. When Prasutagus died in 60 with no male heir, he left his private wealth to his two daughters and to the emperor Nero, trusting thereby to win imperial protection for his family. Instead, the Romans annexed his kingdom, humiliated his family, and plundered the chief tribesmen. While the provincial governor Suetonius Paulinus was absent in 60, Boudicca raised a rebellion throughout East Anglia. The insurgents burned...
</Question>
<Choice>Boudicca</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
architect of Tunisia's independence and first president of Tunisia (1957–87), one of the major voices of moderation and gradualism in the Arab world.
</Question>
<Choice>Bourguiba, Habib</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
militant American abolitionist whose raid on the federal arsenal at Harpers Ferry, Virginia (now in West Virginia), in 1859 made him a martyr to the antislavery cause and was instrumental in heightening sectional animosities that led to the American Civil War (1861–65).Moving about restlessly through Ohio, Pennsylvania, Massachusetts, and New York, Brown was barely able to support his large family in any of several vocations at which he tried his hand: tanner, sheep drover, wool merchant, farmer, and land speculator. Though he was white, in 1849 Brown settled with his family in a black communi...
</Question>
<Choice>Brown, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
political leader of Cuba (from 1959) who transformed his country into the first communist state in the Western Hemisphere. Castro became a symbol of communist revolution in Latin America. He held the title of premier until 1976 and then began a long tenure as president of the Council of State and the Council of Ministers, handing over provisional power in July 2006 because of health problems and formally relinquishing the presidency in February 2008.Castro was born in southeastern Cuba. His father, Angel Castro y Argiz, an immigrant from Spain, was a fairly prosperous sugarcane farmer in a loc...
</Question>
<Choice>Castro, Fidel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Piedmontese statesman, a conservative whose exploitation of international rivalries and of revolutionary movements brought about the unification of Italy (1861) under the House of Savoy, with himself as the first prime minister of the new kingdom.
</Question>
<Choice>Cavour, Camillo Benso, conte di</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
pirate leader of Ming forces against the Manchu conquerors of China, best known for establishing Chinese control over Taiwan.Zheng Chenggong was born in a small Japanese coastal town to a Japanese mother and a Chinese father, Zheng Zhilong, a maritime adventurer who made a fortune through trade and piracy in the Taiwan Strait. Zheng Chenggong was raised by his mother in Japan until the age of seven, when his father, having been given an official position in maritime defense by the Ming dynasty, recalled him to the ancestral home in southern Fujian. There, separated from his mother, Zheng was g...
</Question>
<Choice>Cheng Ch'eng-kung</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
hero of the Irish struggle for independence, best remembered for his daring strategy in directing the campaign of guerrilla warfare during the intensification of the Anglo-Irish War (1919–21).Collins was employed as a British civil servant in London from 1906 until he returned to Ireland in 1916. He fought in the Easter Rising, was arrested and held in detention at Frongoch, Merioneth, but was released in December 1916. In December 1918 he was one of 27 out of 73 elected Sinn Féin members (most of whom were in jail) to be present when the Dáil Éireann (Irish Assembly) convened in Dublin and de...
</Question>
<Choice>Collins, Michael</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American Revolutionary War heroine who is said to have saved General George Washington's army from a British attack.Lydia Barrington married William Darragh, a teacher, in 1753. Shortly thereafter she immigrated with her husband to America, settling in Philadelphia. She worked as a nurse and midwife with considerable skill and success. In a story first published in 1827 and later elaborated upon, she was credited with having saved Washington's army in the following manner: During the British occupation of Philadelphia, General William Howe had his headquarters opposite the Darragh house. On th...
</Question>
<Choice>Darragh, Lydia Barrington</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian brigand chief who repeatedly fought against the French occupation of Naples; he is celebrated as a popular guerrilla leader in folk legends and in the novels of the French writer Alexandre Dumas père.After committing various crimes, the young Pezza joined the mountain bandits then plundering the Italian countryside. His ferocity earned him the name Fra Diavolo, or Brother Devil, among the victimized peasants. In 1798 Cardinal Fabrizio Ruffo, chief adviser to King Ferdinand IV of Naples, pardoned Diavolo for two murders and hired him to fight the French. Diavolo's men disrupted the Fren...
</Question>
<Choice>Diavolo, Fra</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
one of the most militant and dedicated leaders of the Risorgimento, the movement aimed at the unification of Italy.As a young man, Fabrizi helped plan and execute the 1831 Milan rising against the Austrians. Unsuccessful in his attempt to revive the revolution in Modena, he was forced to flee but was captured by the Austrians and imprisoned in Venice. Freed in May 1832, he went to Marseille, where he joined the revolutionary group “Young Italy,” whose founder, Giuseppe Mazzini, became his friend and political ally.After an ill-fated attempt to stir up an insurrection in Savoy (February 1834),...
</Question>
<Choice>Fabrizi, Nicola</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
West Indian psychoanalyst and social philosopher, known for his theory that some neuroses are socially generated and for his writings on behalf of the national liberation of colonial peoples.After attending schools in Martinique and France, Fanon served in the French army during World War II and afterward completed his studies in medicine and psychiatry at the University of Lyon. In 1953–56 he served as head of the psychiatry department of Blida-Joinville Hospital in Algeria, which was then part of France. He joined the Algerian liberation movement in 1954 and in 1956 became an editor of its n...
</Question>
<Choice>Fanon, Frantz</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British soldier and best-known participant in the Gunpowder Plot. Its object was to blow up the palace at Westminster during the state opening of Parliament, while James I and his chief ministers met within, in reprisal for increasing oppression of Roman Catholics in England.Fawkes was a member of a prominent Yorkshire family and a convert to Roman Catholicism. His adventurous spirit, as well as his religious zeal, led him to leave Protestant England (1593) and enlist in the Spanish army in the Netherlands. There he won a reputation for great courage and cool determination. Meanwhile, the inst...
</Question>
<Choice>Fawkes, Guy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American printer and publisher, author, inventor and scientist, and diplomat. One of the foremost of the Founding Fathers, Franklin helped draft the Declaration of Independence and was one of its signers, represented the United States in France during the American Revolution, and was a delegate to the Constitutional Convention. He made important contributions to science, especially in the understanding of electricity, and is remembered for the wit, wisdom, and elegance of his writing.
</Question>
<Choice>Franklin, Benjamin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American bondsman who planned the first major slave rebellion in U.S. history (Aug. 30, 1800). His abortive revolt greatly increased the whites' fear of the slave population throughout the South.The son of an African-born mother, Gabriel grew up as the slave of Thomas H. Prosser. Gabriel became a deeply religious man, strongly influenced by biblical example. In the spring and summer of 1800, he laid plans for a slave insurrection aimed at creating an independent black state in Virginia with himself as king. He planned a three-pronged attack on Richmond, Va., that would seize the arsenal, take...
</Question>
<Choice>Gabriel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian patriot and soldier of the Risorgimento, a republican who, through his conquest of Sicily and Naples with his guerrilla Redshirts, contributed to the achievement of Italian unification under the royal House of Savoy.
</Question>
<Choice>Garibaldi, Giuseppe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
self-proclaimed prince of Wales whose unsuccessful rebellion against England was the last major Welsh attempt to throw off English rule. He became a national hero upon the resurgence of Welsh nationalism in the 19th and 20th centuries.A descendant of the princes of Powys, Glendower inherited several manors in northern Wales. He studied law in London and then served with the forces of Henry Bolingbroke, an opponent of King Richard II and afterward King Henry IV. When he returned to Wales, he found that England's oppressive rule had crippled the Welsh economy and aroused popular resentment. In S...
</Question>
<Choice>Glendower, Owen</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
hero of the Mexican efforts to secure independence.Guerrero began his military career in 1810, and soon the early Mexican independence leader José Maria Morelos commissioned him to promote the revolutionary movement in the highlands of southwestern Mexico. After Morelos' execution by the Spanish in 1815, Guerrero continued to lead his guerrilla forces against the Spanish until 1821, when he joined forces with Agustín de Iturbide and with him issued the Plan of Iguala, which became the political platform for the conservative wing of the Mexican independence movement. The Mexican forces triumphe...
</Question>
<Choice>Guerrero, Vicente</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
militant Palestinian and leader of the Popular Front for the Liberation of Palestine (PFLP).?abash was forced to flee Palestine in 1948, after the State of Israel was established there, and earned a medical degree at the American University of Beirut. In the early 1950s he was active in the “Youth of Vengeance” group, which advocated violent attacks on traditional Arab governments. ?abash founded the militant PFLP after his goal to liberate Palestine through Arab unity proved unrealistic following the Arab defeat by Israel in the Six-Day War of 1967 (seeArab-Israeli wars). Under the leadership...
</Question>
<Choice>Habash, George</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American Revolutionary officer who attempted to spy on the British and was hanged.A graduate of Yale University (1773) and a schoolteacher, Hale joined a Connecticut regiment in 1775, served in the siege of Boston, and was commissioned a captain (1776). He went to New York with William Heath's brigade and is said to have participated in the capture of a provision sloop from under the guns of a British man-of-war. Hale was captured by the British while attempting to return to his regiment, having penetrated the British lines on Long Island to obtain information. He was hanged without trial the...
</Question>
<Choice>Hale, Nathan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Catholic priest who is called the father of Mexican independence.Ordained a priest in 1789, he had an uneventful early career, though his interest in the economic advancement of his parishioners in Dolores, through the introduction of newer methods of agriculture, made him suspect by the Spanish authorities. In 1808 Spain was invaded by French troops, and Napoleon forced the abdication of King Ferdinand VII in favour of the French emperor's brother Joseph Bonaparte. Though Spanish officials in Mexico were loath to oppose the new king, many Mexicans formed secret societies—some supporting Ferdi...
</Question>
<Choice>Hidalgo y Costilla, Miguel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
founder of the Indochina Communist Party (1930) and its successor, the Viet-Minh (1941), and president from 1945 to 1969 of the Democratic Republic of Vietnam (North Vietnam). As the leader of the Vietnamese nationalist movement for nearly three decades, Ho was one of the prime movers of the post-World War II anticolonial movement in Asia and one of the most influential communist leaders of the 20th century.
</Question>
<Choice>Ho Chi Minh</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
draftsman of the Declaration of Independence of the United States and the nation's first secretary of state (1789–94), second vice president (1797–1801), and, as the third president (1801–09), the statesman responsible for the Louisiana Purchase. An early advocate of total separation of church and state, he also was the founder and architect of the University of Virginia and the most eloquent American proponent of individual freedom as the core meaning of the American Revolution. (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America.)Long...
</Question>
<Choice>Jefferson, Thomas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American naval hero in the American Revolution, renowned for his victory over British ships of war off the east coast of England (September 23, 1779).Apprenticed at age 12 to John Younger, a Scottish merchant shipper, John Paul sailed as a cabin boy on a ship to Virginia, where he visited his older brother William at Fredericksburg. When Younger's business failed in 1766, Paul found work as chief mate of a Jamaica-owned slaver brigantine. After two years he quit the slave trade and shipped passage for Scotland. When both master and chief mate died of fever en route, he brought the ship safely...
</Question>
<Choice>Jones, John Paul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician who led Zambia to independence in 1964 and served as that country's president until 1991.
</Question>
<Choice>Kaunda, Kenneth</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
African statesman and nationalist, the first prime minister (1963–64) and then the first president (1964–78) of independent Kenya.
</Question>
<Choice>Kenyatta, Jomo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British-born Irish militant (b. Feb. 17, 1928, London, Eng.—d. May 17, 2001, Navan, County Meath, Ire.), was the first chief of staff of the Provisional Irish Republican Army after the hard-line militarist wing's split from the Official IRA in 1969. Originally drawn to the Irish republican cause by his Belfast, N.Ire.-born mother, he joined the IRA in his 20s and later changed his name. As the leader of the Provos, he advocated implacable violent resistance to British rule in Northern Ireland and was credited with waging a terrorist campaign, including at least one fatal bombing. In 1973, howe...
</Question>
<Choice>MacStiofain, Sean</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Genoese propagandist and revolutionary, founder of the secret revolutionary society Young Italy (1832), and a champion of the movement for Italian unity known as the Risorgimento. An uncompromising republican, he refused to participate in the parliamentary government that was established under the monarchy of the House of Savoy when Italy became unified and independent (1861).
</Question>
<Choice>Mazzini, Giuseppe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Lebanese Sh??ite Muslim cleric and secretary-general (1991–92) of the militant Hezbollah (“Party of God”) movement.M?saw? studied at a Sh??ite madrasah (religious college) in Al-Najaf, Iraq, where he was strongly influenced by the teachings of Iranian cleric Ayatollah Ruhollah Khomeini. M?saw? returned to Lebanon in 1978 and four years later—inspired by the successful Khomeini-led Islamic revolution in Iran—helped to form Hezbollah in an effort to resist the Israeli occupation of southern Lebanon (1982) and to promote Sh??ite interests in that country. Although he denied any direct involvement...
</Question>
<Choice>Musawi, 'Abbas al-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Russian revolutionary known for his organizational scheme for a professional revolutionary party and for his ruthless murder of one of the members of his organization.During 1868–69 Nechayev participated in the student revolutionary movement in St. Petersburg and composed his “Catechism of a Revolutionary,” which embodied his militant philosophy and a morality under which any means was justified that served the revolutionary end. In March 1869 he went to Geneva, where he met the exiled Russian anarchist Mikhail Bakunin. A close collaboration between the two developed.In September 1869 Nechayev...
</Question>
<Choice>Nechayev, Sergey Gennadiyevich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ghanaian nationalist leader who led the Gold Coast's drive for independence from Britain and presided over its emergence as the new nation of Ghana. He headed the country from independence in 1957 until he was overthrown by a coup in 1966.
</Question>
<Choice>Nkrumah, Kwame</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician who was prime minister (1962–70) and twice president (1966–71, 1980–85) of Uganda. He led his country to independence in 1962, but his two terms in office (both of which were ended by military coups) were consumed by struggles between Uganda's northern and southern ethnic groups.Obote was born the third of nine children in a farming family in north-central Uganda. He first attended Busoga College in Mwiri and then Makerere College in Kampala from 1948 to 1949, but he was expelled from the latter for his political activities before he could graduate. The British colonial government p...
</Question>
<Choice>Obote, Milton</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Irish patriot, among the most famous of all the O'Neills.Shane, the eldest legitimate son of Conn O'Neill, was a chieftain whose support the English considered worth gaining; but he rejected overtures from the Earl of Sussex, the lord deputy, and refused to help the English against the Scottish settlers on the coast of Antrim. He allied himself instead with the MacDonnells, the most powerful of these immigrants. Nevertheless, Queen Elizabeth I of England was disposed to come to terms with Shane, who after his father's death was de facto chief of the O'Neill clan. She recognized his claims to t...
</Question>
<Choice>O'Neill, Shane</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
heroine of the Battle of Monmouth Court House during the American Revolution.According to legend, at the Battle of Monmouth (June 28, 1778), Mary Hays, wife of artilleryman William Hays, carried water to cool both the cannon and the soldiers in her husband's battery—hence the nickname “Molly Pitcher.” Legend also asserts that when William Hays collapsed or was wounded, she took her husband's place in the gun crew for the rest of the battle.Patriotic prints and literature depicting the alleged event initially referred to “Captain Molly.” The less martial and more nurturing “Molly Pitcher” did n...
</Question>
<Choice>Pitcher, Molly</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
folk hero of the American Revolution whose dramatic horseback ride on the night of April 18, 1775, warning Boston-area residents that the British were coming, was immortalized in a ballad by Henry Wadsworth Longfellow.His father, Apollos De Revoire (later changed to Revere), was a Huguenot refugee who had come to Boston as a child and had been apprenticed to a silversmith. This craft he taught his son Paul Revere, who became one of America's greatest artists in silver. As a boy Revere received sufficient education to enable him later to read the difficult metallurgical books of his period. Alt...
</Question>
<Choice>Revere, Paul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
radical Jacobin leader and one of the principal figures in the French Revolution. In the latter months of 1793 he came to dominate the Committee of Public Safety, the principal organ of the Revolutionary government during the Reign of Terror, but in 1794 he was overthrown and executed in the Thermidorian Reaction.
</Question>
<Choice>Robespierre, Maximilien de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
revolutionary who violently opposed both the imperial and the Soviet regimes in Russia. He wrote several pseudonymous novels based on his career as a terrorist.Savinkov joined the Socialist-Revolutionary Party in 1903 and was a leader of its terrorist organization. He was responsible for the assassination of the antiliberal government minister Vyacheslav Konstantinovich Plehve (1904) and of the grand duke Sergey Aleksandrovich (1905), the tsar's uncle and governor-general of Moscow.During World War I, Savinkov served in the French army. After the February Revolution, he returned to Russia (191...
</Question>
<Choice>Savinkov, Boris Viktorovich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
patriot leader in New York City before the American Revolution, who earned the nickname “King Sears” by virtue of his prominent role in inciting and commanding anti-British demonstrations.A merchant whose shipping activities included privateering, Sears first exhibited his patriot leanings when the Stamp Act crisis erupted in 1765. He became a mob leader during the anti-British riots in New York City, and he belonged to the newly formed patriot organization the Sons of Liberty.Sears led the boycott of British goods during colonial protests of the Townshend Acts. Repeal of the Townshend Acts pr...
</Question>
<Choice>Sears, Isaac</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Uruguayan rebel leader, founder of the leftist Tupamaro National Liberation Front (1963), a guerrilla movement that waged a relentless battle against the police and the army from 1967 to 1972.Sendic quit law school in the late 1950s to join the Socialist Party, but when the party was defeated in two elections, he resigned to organize striking sugarcane workers and other rebellious groups. Beginning in the late 1960s, the Tupamaros gained notoriety through such exploits as the distribution of stolen food to the poor, the bombing of an exclusive dance hall, and the 1970 abduction and murder of D...
</Question>
<Choice>Sendic, Raúl</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
leader in the Gladiatorial War (73–71) against Rome.A Thracian by birth, Spartacus served in the Roman Army, perhaps deserted, led bandit raids, and was caught and sold as a slave. With about 70 fellow gladiators he escaped a gladiatorial training school at Capua in 73 and took refuge on Mount Vesuvius, where other runaway slaves joined the band. After defeating two Roman forces in succession, the rebels overran most of southern Italy. Ultimately their numbers grew to at least 90,000. Spartacus defeated the two consuls for the year 72 and fought his way northward toward the Alps, hoping to be...
</Question>
<Choice>Spartacus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
black American bondsman who led the only effective, sustained slave rebellion (August 1831) in U.S. history. Spreading terror throughout the white South, his action set off a new wave of oppressive legislation prohibiting the education, movement, and assembly of slaves and stiffened proslavery, antiabolitionist convictions that persisted in that region until the American Civil War (1861–65).Turner was born the property of a prosperous small-plantation owner in a remote area of Virginia. His mother was an African native who transmitted a passionate hatred of slavery to her son. He learned to re...
</Question>
<Choice>Turner, Nat</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
self-educated black who planned the most extensive slave revolt in U.S. history (Charleston, 1822).Sold as a boy in 1781 to a Bermuda slaver captain named Joseph Vesey, young Denmark, who assumed his master's surname, accompanied him on numerous voyages and in 1783 settled with his owner in Charleston.In 1800 Denmark was allowed to purchase his freedom with $600 he had won in a street lottery. He was already familiar with the great Haitian slave revolt of the 1790s, and while working as a carpenter he read anti-slavery literature. Dissatisfied with his second-class status as a freedman and det...
</Question>
<Choice>Vesey, Denmark</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
one of Scotland's greatest national heroes, leader of the Scottish resistance forces during the first years of the long, and ultimately successful, struggle to free Scotland from English rule.His father, Sir Malcolm Wallace, was a small landowner in Renfrew. In 1296 King Edward I of England deposed and imprisoned the Scottish king John de Balliol and declared himself ruler of Scotland. Sporadic resistance had already occurred when, in May 1297, Wallace and a band of some 30 men burned Lanark and killed its English sheriff. Wallace then organized an army of commoners and small landowners and at...
</Question>
<Choice>Wallace, Sir William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American general and commander in chief of the colonial armies in the American Revolution (1775–83) and subsequently first president of the United States (1789–97). (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America.)Washington's father, Augustine Washington, had gone to school in England, had tasted seafaring life, and then settled down to manage his growing Virginia estates. His mother was Mary Ball, whom Augustine, a widower, had married early the previous year. Washington's paternal lineage had some distinction; an early forebear wa...
</Question>
<Choice>Washington, George</Choice>
</item>
</topics>