<topics>
<item>
<Question>
American astronaut who was the second man to set foot on the Moon.A graduate of the U.S. Military Academy, West Point, N.Y. (1951), Aldrin became an air force pilot. He flew 66 combat missions in Korea and later served in West Germany. In 1963 he wrote a dissertation on orbital mechanics to earn a Ph.D. from the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Cambridge. Later that year he was chosen as an astronaut.On Nov. 11, 1966, he joined James A. Lovell, Jr., on the four-day Gemini 12 flight. Aldrin's record 5 12-hour walk in space proved that man can function effectively in the vacuum of space.Ap...
</Question>
<Choice>Aldrin, Edwin Eugene, Jr.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Norwegian explorer who was the first to reach the South Pole, the first to make a ship voyage through the Northwest Passage, and one of the first to cross the Arctic by air. He was one of the greatest figures in the field of polar exploration.Amundsen studied medicine for a while and then took to sea. In 1897 he sailed as first mate on the Belgica in a Belgian expedition that was the first to winter in the Antarctic. In 1903, with a crew of six on his 47-ton sloop Gjöa, Amundsen became the first man to sail through the Northwest Passage and around the northern Canadian coast; his east-west jou...
</Question>
<Choice>Amundsen, Roald</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. astronaut who participated in the Apollo 8 flight (Dec. 21–27, 1968), during which the first manned voyage around the Moon was made. The astronauts, including Anders, Frank Borman, and James Lovell, remained in an orbit about 70 miles (112 km) above the surface of the Moon for about 20 hours, transmitting television pictures back to Earth and verifying that lunar landmarks could be used for navigation to lunar landing sites. On one of Apollo 8's orbits of the Moon, Anders took the famous “Earthrise” photograph.Anders graduated from the U.S. Naval Academy at Annapolis, Md., in 1955. He rec...
</Question>
<Choice>Anders, William A</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. astronaut, the first person to set foot on the Moon.Armstrong became a licensed pilot on his 16th birthday and a naval air cadet in 1947. His studies in aeronautical engineering at Purdue University in West Lafayette, Indiana, were interrupted in 1950 by the Korean War, in which he was shot down once and was awarded three Air Medals. In 1955 he became a civilian research pilot for the National Advisory Committee for Aeronautics (NACA), later the National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA). He flew more than 1,100 hours, testing various supersonic fighters as well as the X-15rocke...
</Question>
<Choice>Armstrong, Neil</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish conquistador and explorer, who was head of the first stable settlement on the South American continent (1511) and who was the first European to sight the Pacific Ocean (on Sept. 25 [or 27], 1513, from “a peak in Darién”).
</Question>
<Choice>Balboa, Vasco Núñez de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American explorer who was the first woman to participate in and successfully finish several arduous expeditions to the Arctic and Antarctic.Bancroft grew up in rural Minnesota in what she described as a family of risk takers. Although she struggled with a learning disability, she graduated from St. Paul Academy and became a gym teacher, coach, and wilderness instructor in the Saint Paul area.When an opportunity arose to participate in the 1986 Steger International North Pole Expedition, Bancroft resigned her teaching position. After 56 days she and five other team members arrived at the North...
</Question>
<Choice>Bancroft, Ann</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British computer scientist, generally credited as the inventor of the World Wide Web. In 2004 he was awarded a knighthood by Queen Elizabeth II of the United Kingdom and the inaugural Millennium Technology Prize (€1 million) by the Finnish Technology Award Foundation.Computing came naturally to Berners-Lee, as both of his parents worked on the Ferranti Mark I, the first commercial computer. (Seecomputer: The first stored-program machines.) After graduating in 1976 from the University of Oxford, Berners-Lee designed computer software for two years at Plessey Telecommunications Ltd., located in...
</Question>
<Choice>Berners-Lee, Sir Tim</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Anglo-American physician who is considered the first woman doctor of medicine in modern times.Elizabeth Blackwell was of a large, prosperous, and cultured family and was well educated by private tutors. Financial reverses and the family's liberal social and religious views prompted them to immigrate to the United States in the summer of 1832. Soon after taking up residence in New York, her father, Samuel Blackwell, became active in abolitionist activities. The Blackwells moved to Jersey City, New Jersey, in 1835 and to Cincinnati, Ohio, in 1838. Soon afterward Samuel Blackwell's death left the...
</Question>
<Choice>Blackwell, Elizabeth</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
astronaut who was the first African American launched into space.Bluford received an undergraduate degree in aerospace engineering from Pennsylvania State University in 1964 and was commissioned as an officer in the U.S. Air Force, where he trained as a fighter pilot. He flew 144 combat missions during the Vietnam War. In 1978 he earned a doctorate in aerospace engineering from the Air Force Institute of Technology.Bluford was one of 35 individuals selected in 1978 from 10,000 applicants in NASA's first competition to become space shuttle astronauts. On August 30, 1983, he rode into Earth orbi...
</Question>
<Choice>Bluford, Guion S., Jr.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. astronaut who, in Apollo 8 with James A. Lovell and William A. Anders in December 1968, made the first manned flight around the Moon. The astronauts remained in an orbit about 112 km (70 miles) above the surface of the Moon for about 20 hours, transmitting television pictures back to Earth and verifying that lunar landmarks could be used for navigation to lunar landing sites. Three years earlier Borman and Lovell had made the Gemini 7 endurance flight in which they remained in space for 330 hours 35 minutes. Borman and Lovell also performed the first space rendezvous, coming within a few...
</Question>
<Choice>Borman, Frank</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
explorer who led the first expedition known to attempt the crossing of Australia from south to north.Sponsored by the Royal Society of Victoria, Burke left Melbourne with a party of 18 in August 1860. The plan was to establish bases from which an advance party would leave to prepare for those with bulkier supplies. But about midway, at the Barcoo River (Coopers Creek), the impatient Burke decided to make the rest of the trip accompanied only by his second in command, William John Wills, and by Charles Gray and John King. The four reached northern Australia in February 1861 but could not penetr...
</Question>
<Choice>Burke, Robert O'Hara</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British explorer and diplomat (of the same family as the poet Robert Burns) who gained renown for his explorations in what are now Pakistan, Afghanistan, Turkmenistan, Uzbekistan, and Iran. For his accomplishments he was knighted in 1839.Burnes became interested in the geography of Afghanistan and central Asia while serving as an officer in the northwestern Indian state of Kutch (1823–29). He traveled in 1831 up the Indus River from Sind (Pakistan), delivering gifts to the local rulers, exploring the regions he visited, and eventually reaching the Punjab city of Lahore, now in Pakistan. The fo...
</Question>
<Choice>Burnes, Sir Alexander</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
navigator and explorer who by his voyages in 1497 and 1498 helped lay the groundwork for the later British claim to Canada. The exact details of his life and of his voyages are still subjects of controversy among historians and cartographers.Cabot moved to Venice in 1461, or possibly earlier, and became a citizen of that city in 1476. While employed by a Venetian mercantile firm, he traveled to the eastern shores of the Mediterranean and visited Mecca, a great trading centre where Oriental and Western goods were exchanged. He became skilled in navigational techniques and seems to have envisage...
</Question>
<Choice>Cabot, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American biologist well known for her writings on environmental pollution and the natural history of the sea.Carson early developed a deep interest in the natural world. She entered Pennsylvania College for Women with the intention of becoming a writer but soon changed her major field of study from English to biology. After taking her bachelor's degree in 1929, she did graduate work at Johns Hopkins University (M.A., 1932) and in 1931 joined the faculty of the University of Maryland, where she taught for five years. From 1929 to 1936 she also taught in the Johns Hopkins summer school and pursu...
</Question>
<Choice>Carson, Rachel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian-born French astronomer who, among others, discovered the Cassini Division, the dark gap between the rings A and B of Saturn; he also discovered four of Saturn's moons. In addition, he was the first to record observations of the zodiacal light.Cassini's early studies were principally observations of the Sun, but after he obtained more powerful telescopes, he turned his attention to the planets. He was the first to observe the shadows of Jupiter'ssatellites as they passed between that planet and the Sun. His observation of spots on the surface of the planet allowed him to measure Jupiter...
</Question>
<Choice>Cassini, Gian Domenico</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American frontiersman who won fame as an explorer by sharing with Meriwether Lewis the leadership of their epic expedition to the Pacific Northwest (1804–06). He later played an essential role in the development of the Missouri Territory and was superintendent of Indian affairs at St. Louis.The ninth of John and Ann (Rogers) Clark's 10 children, Clark was born on the family's tobacco plantation in Virginia. In 1785 the family relocated to Louisville, Ky., lured there by tales of the Ohio Valley told by William Clark's older brother, George Rogers Clark, one of the military heroes of the Americ...
</Question>
<Choice>Clark, William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronaut, the first woman to pilot and, later, to command a U.S. space shuttle.Collins's love of airplanes and flying began as a child. At age 19 she saved money earned from part-time jobs and began taking flying lessons. She graduated with a bachelor's degree in mathematics and economics from Syracuse (New York) University in 1978. She then became one of four women admitted to Air Force Undergraduate Pilot Training at Vance Air Force Base in Oklahoma. The first women astronauts were doing their parachute training at the same base at that time, and Collins realized that the goal of b...
</Question>
<Choice>Collins, Eileen</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
master navigator and admiral whose four transatlantic voyages (1492–93, 1493–96, 1498–1500, and 1502–04) opened the way for European exploration, exploitation, and colonization of the Americas. He has long been called the “discoverer” of the New World, although Vikings such as Leif Eriksson had visited North America five centuries earlier. Columbus made his transatlantic voyages under the sponsorship of Ferdinand II and Isabella I, the Catholic Monarchs of Aragon, Castile, and Leon in Spain. He was at first full of hope and ambition, an ambition partly gratified by his title “Admiral of the Oc...
</Question>
<Choice>Columbus, Christopher</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British naval captain, navigator, and explorer, who explored the seaways and coasts of Canada (1759, 1763–67) and conducted three expeditions to the Pacific Ocean (1768–71; 1772–75; 1776–79), ranging from the Antarctic ice fields to the Bering Strait and from the coasts of North America to Australia and New Zealand.
</Question>
<Choice>Cook, James</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polish astronomer who proposed that the planets have the Sun as the fixed point to which their motions are to be referred; that the Earth is a planet which, besides orbiting the Sun annually, also turns once daily on its own axis; and that very slow, long-term changes in the direction of this axis account for the precession of the equinoxes. This representation of the heavens is usually called the heliocentric, or “Sun-centred,” system—derived from the Greek helios, meaning “Sun.” Copernicus's theory had important consequences for later thinkers of the scientific revolution, including such maj...
</Question>
<Choice>Copernicus, Nicolaus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French naval officer and ocean explorer, known for his extensive underseas investigations.After graduating from France's naval academy in 1933, he was commissioned a second lieutenant. However, his plans to become a navy pilot were undermined by an almost fatal automobile accident in which both his arms were broken. Cousteau, not formally trained as a scientist, was drawn to undersea exploration by his love both of the ocean and of diving. In 1943 Cousteau and French engineer Émile Gagnan developed the first fully automatic compressed-air Aqua-Lung. Cousteau helped to invent many other tools u...
</Question>
<Choice>Cousteau, Jacques-Yves</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British biophysicist, who, with James Watson and Maurice Wilkins, received the 1962 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine for their determination of the molecular structure of deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA), the chemical substance ultimately responsible for hereditary control of life functions. This accomplishment became a cornerstone of genetics and was widely regarded as one of the most important discoveries of 20th-century biology.During World War II, Crick interrupted his education to work as a physicist in the development of magnetic mines for use in naval warfare, but afterward he turned t...
</Question>
<Choice>Crick, Francis Harry Compton</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polish-born French physicist, famous for her work on radioactivity and twice a winner of the Nobel Prize. With Henri Becquerel and her husband, Pierre Curie, she was awarded the 1903 Nobel Prize for Physics. She was the sole winner of the 1911 Nobel Prize for Chemistry. She was the first woman to win a Nobel Prize, and she is the only woman to win the award in two different fields.From childhood she was remarkable for her prodigious memory, and at the age of 16 she won a gold medal on completion of her secondary education at the Russian lycée. Because her father, a teacher of mathematics and p...
</Question>
<Choice>Curie, Marie</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English naturalist whose theory of evolution by natural selection became the foundation of modern evolutionary studies. An affable country gentleman, Darwin at first shocked religious Victorian society by suggesting that animals and humans shared a common ancestry. However, his nonreligious biology appealed to the rising class of professional scientists, and by the time of his death evolutionary imagery had spread through all of science, literature, and politics. Darwin, himself an agnostic, was accorded the ultimate British accolade of burial in Westminster Abbey, London. (In February 2009, f...
</Question>
<Choice>Darwin, Charles</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American cardiovascular surgeon, educator, international medical statesman, and pioneer in surgical procedures for treatment of defects and diseases of the cardiovascular system.In 1932 DeBakey devised the “roller pump,” an essential component of the heart-lung machine that permitted open-heart surgery. He also developed an efficient method of correcting aortic aneurysms by grafting frozen blood vessels to replace diseased vessels. By 1953 DeBakey had developed a technique of using plastic tubing (Dacron) instead of arterial homographs to replace diseased vessels. In 1953 he performed the firs...
</Question>
<Choice>DeBakey, Michael</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American motion-picture and television producer and showman, famous as a pioneer of animated cartoon films and as the creator of such cartoon characters as Mickey Mouse and Donald Duck. He also planned and built Disneyland, a huge amusement park that opened near Los Angeles in 1955, and before his death he had begun building a second such park, Walt Disney World, near Orlando, Florida. The Disney Company he founded has become one of the world's largest entertainment conglomerates.
</Question>
<Choice>Disney, Walt</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English admiral who circumnavigated the globe (1577–80) and was the most renowned seaman of the Elizabethan Age.
</Question>
<Choice>Drake, Sir Francis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American aviator, one of the world's most celebrated, who was the first woman to fly alone over the Atlantic Ocean.Earhart moved often with her family and completed high school in Chicago in 1916. She worked as a military nurse in Canada during World War I and as a social worker at Denison House in Boston after the war. She learned to fly (against her family's wishes) in 1920–21 and in 1922 bought her first plane, a Kinner Canary. On June 17–18, 1928, she became the first woman to fly across the Atlantic, although she was only a passenger in a plane flown by Wilmer Stutz and Louis Gordon. The...
</Question>
<Choice>Earhart, Amelia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German-born physicist who developed the special and general theories of relativity and won the Nobel Prize for Physics in 1921 for his explanation of the photoelectric effect. Einstein is generally considered the most influential physicist of the 20th century.
</Question>
<Choice>Einstein, Albert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
founder of the first European settlement on Greenland (c. 986) and the father of Leif Eriksson, one of the first Europeans to reach North America.As a child, Erik left his native Norway for western Iceland with his father, Thorvald, who had been exiled for manslaughter. In the Scandinavian style of the time he was known as Erik Thorvaldson and in his youth was nicknamed Erik the Red. When Erik was similarly exiled from Iceland about 980, he decided to explore the land to the west (Greenland). That land, visible in distorted form because of the effect of looming (a type of mirage) from the moun...
</Question>
<Choice>Erik The Red</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English physicist and chemist whose many experiments contributed greatly to the understanding of electromagnetism.Faraday, who became one of the greatest scientists of the 19th century, began his career as a chemist. He wrote a manual of practical chemistry that reveals his mastery of the technical aspects of his art, discovered a number of new organic compounds, among them benzene, and was the first to liquefy a “permanent” gas (i.e., one that was believed to be incapable of liquefaction). His major contribution, however, was in the field of electricity and magnetism. He was the first to prod...
</Question>
<Choice>Faraday, Michael</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Scottish bacteriologist best known for his discovery of penicillin. Fleming had a genius for technical ingenuity and original observation. His work on wound infection and lysozyme, an antibacterial enzyme found in tears and saliva, guaranteed him a place in the history of bacteriology. But it was his discovery of penicillin in 1928, which started the antibiotic revolution, that sealed his lasting reputation. Fleming was recognized for this achievement in 1945, when he received the Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine, along with Australian pathologist Howard Walter Florey and British biochem...
</Question>
<Choice>Fleming, Sir Alexander</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Soviet cosmonaut who in 1961 became the first man to travel into space.The son of a carpenter on a collective farm, Gagarin graduated as a molder from a trade school near Moscow in 1951. He continued his studies at the industrial college at Saratov and concurrently took a course in flying. On completing this course, he entered the Soviet Air Force cadet school at Orenburg, from which he graduated in 1957.Gagarin's 4 34-ton Vostok 1 spacecraft was launched at 9:07 AM Moscow time on April 12, 1961, orbited Earth once in 1 hour 29 minutes at a maximum altitude of 187 miles (301 km), and landed at...
</Question>
<Choice>Gagarin, Yury Alekseyevich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian natural philosopher, astronomer, and mathematician who made fundamental contributions to the sciences of motion, astronomy, and strength of materials and to the development of the scientific method. His formulation of (circular) inertia, the law of falling bodies, and parabolic trajectories marked the beginning of a fundamental change in the study of motion. His insistence that the book of nature was written in the language of mathematics changed natural philosophy from a verbal, qualitative account to a mathematical one in which experimentation became a recognized method for discoveri...
</Question>
<Choice>Galileo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Portuguese navigator whose voyages to India (1497–99, 1502–03, 1524) opened up the sea route from western Europe to the East by way of the Cape of Good Hope.
</Question>
<Choice>Gama, Vasco da, 1er Conde Da Vidigueira</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the first U.S. astronaut to orbit Earth, completing three orbits in 1962. (Soviet cosmonaut Yury Gagarin, the first person in space, had made a single orbit of Earth in 1961).Glenn joined the U.S. Marine Corps in 1943 and flew 59 missions during World War II and 90 missions during the Korean War. He was a test pilot from 1954 and was promoted to lieutenant colonel in 1959. Of the seven U.S. military pilots selected in that year for Project Mercury astronaut training, he was the oldest. Glenn served as a backup pilot for Alan B. Shepard, Jr., and Virgil I. Grissom, who made the first two U.S. s...
</Question>
<Choice>Glenn, John H., Jr.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
second U.S. astronaut to travel in space and the command pilot of the ill-fated Apollo 1 crew. He and his fellow astronauts Edward H. White and Roger B. Chaffee were killed, becoming the first casualties of the U.S. space program, when a flash fire swept their space capsule during a simulation of the scheduled Feb. 21, 1967, launching of Apollo 1.Commissioned in the U.S. Air Force in 1951, Grissom flew 100 missions in the Korean War, earning the Distinguished Flying Cross and the Air Medal with cluster. He was a test pilot and flying instructor until 1959, when he was selected as one of the or...
</Question>
<Choice>Grissom, Virgil I.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American black explorer who accompanied Robert E. Peary on most of his expeditions, including that to the North Pole in 1909.Orphaned as a youth, Henson went to sea at the age of 12 as a cabin boy on the sailing ship Katie Hines. Later, while working in a store in Washington, D.C., he met Peary, who hired him as a valet for his next expedition to Nicaragua (1888). Peary, impressed with Henson's ability and resourcefulness, employed him as an attendant on his seven subsequent expeditions to the Arctic (1891–92; 1893–95; 1896; 1897; 1898–1902; 1905–06; 1908–09). In 1909 Peary and Henson, accompa...
</Question>
<Choice>Henson, Matthew Alexander</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
New Zealand mountain climber and Antarctic explorer who, with the Sherpa mountaineer Tenzing Norgay, was the first to reach the summit of Mount Everest (29,035 feet [8,850 metres]; seeResearcher's Note: Height of Mount Everest), the highest mountain in the world.Hillary's father was a beekeeper, an occupation he also pursued. He began climbing in New Zealand's Southern Alps while in high school. After military service in World War II, he resumed climbing and became determined to scale Everest. In 1951 he joined a New Zealand party to the central Himalayas and later that year participated in a...
</Question>
<Choice>Hillary, Sir Edmund</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American manufacturer, aviator, and motion-picture producer much publicized for his aversion to publicity as well as for the uses to which he put his vast wealth.He studied at the California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, and later at the Rice Institute of Technology, Houston. Orphaned at 17, he quit school and took control of his father's Hughes Tool Company, Houston. In 1926 he moved to Hollywood, where he produced Hell's Angels (1930) and Scarface (1932) and introduced Jean Harlow and Paul Muni to the screen. Later The Outlaw (1941) introduced Jane Russell.In 1948 he bought a controllin...
</Question>
<Choice>Hughes, Howard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Egyptian Neoplatonist philosopher who was the first notable woman in mathematics.The daughter of Theon, also a notable mathematician and philosopher, Hypatia became the recognized head of the Neoplatonist school of philosophy at Alexandria about 400, and her eloquence, modesty, and beauty, combined with her remarkable intellectual gifts, attracted a large number of pupils. Among them was Synesius of Cyrene, afterward bishop of Ptolemais (c. 410), several of whose letters to her are still extant.Hypatia lectured on mathematics and on the philosophical teachings of two Neoplatonists: Plotinus (c...
</Question>
<Choice>Hypatia</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
queen of Castile (1474–1504) and of Aragon (1479–1504), ruling the two kingdoms jointly from 1479 with her husband, Ferdinand II of Aragon (Ferdinand V of Castile). Their rule effected the permanent union of Spain and the beginning of an overseas empire in the New World, led by Christopher Columbus under Isabella's sponsorship.
</Question>
<Choice>Isabella I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician and the first African American woman to become an astronaut. In 1992 she spent more than a week orbiting Earth in the space shuttle Endeavour.Jemison moved with her family to Chicago at the age of three. There she was introduced to science by her uncle and developed interests throughout her childhood in anthropology, archaeology, evolution, and astronomy. While still a high school student, she became interested in biomedical engineering, and after graduating in 1973, at the age of 16, she entered Stanford University. There she received degrees in chemical engineering and Afr...
</Question>
<Choice>Jemison, Mae</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Norse explorer widely held to have been the first European to reach the shores of North America. The 13th- and 14th-century Icelandic accounts of his life and additional later evidence show that he was certainly a member of an early Viking voyage to North America, but it remains doubtful whether he led the initial expedition.The second of three sons of Erik the Red, the first European colonizer of Greenland, Leif sailed from Greenland to Norway in 1000, according to the Icelandic Eiríks saga (“Saga of Erik”), and was there converted to Christianity by the Norwegian king Olaf I Tryggvason. The...
</Question>
<Choice>Leif Eriksson the Lucky</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Soviet cosmonaut, the first man to climb out of a spacecraft in space.After early schooling in Kaliningrad, Leonov joined the Soviet air force in 1953. He completed his flight training in 1957 and served as a fighter pilot until 1959, when he was selected for cosmonaut training.On March 18, 1965, Voskhod 2 was launched into space with Leonov and Pavel Belyayev aboard. During the second orbit Leonov let himself out of the spacecraft by means of an air lock while about 110 miles (177 km) above the Crimea. Tethered to the ship, Leonov made observations, took motion pictures, and practiced maneuve...
</Question>
<Choice>Leonov, Aleksey Arkhipovich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American explorer, who with William Clark led the Lewis and Clark Expedition through the uncharted American interior to the Pacific Northwest in 1804–06. He later served as governor of Upper Louisiana Territory.Born to William Lewis and Lucy Meriwether, Meriwether Lewis grew up on Locust Hill, the family's plantation in Ivy Creek, Va.—near Monticello, home of the future U.S. president Thomas Jefferson. Lewis's father died while serving in the Continental Army in 1779. His mother then married John Marks and relocated her family to Georgia before being widowed again by 1792. Returning to Virgini...
</Question>
<Choice>Lewis, Meriwether</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American aviator, one of the best-known figures in aeronautical history, remembered for the first nonstop solo flight across the Atlantic, from New York to Paris, on May 20–21, 1927.Lindbergh's early years were spent chiefly in Little Falls, Minnesota, and in Washington, D.C., where for 10 years his father represented the 6th district of Minnesota in Congress. His formal education ended during his second year at the University of Wisconsin in Madison, when his growing interest in aviation led to enrollment in a flying school in Lincoln, Nebraska, and the purchase of a World War I Curtiss Jenny...
</Question>
<Choice>Lindbergh, Charles A.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British surgeon and medical scientist who was the founder of antisepticmedicine and a pioneer in preventive medicine. While his method, based on the use of antiseptics, is no longer employed, his principle—that bacteria must never gain entry to an operation wound—remains the basis of surgery to this day. He was made a baronet in 1883 and raised to the peerage in 1897.
</Question>
<Choice>Lister, Joseph, Baron Lister, Of Lyme Regis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. astronaut, commander of the nearly disastrous Apollo 13 flight to the Moon in 1970.Lovell, a graduate (1952) of the U.S. Naval Academy, Annapolis, Md., became a test pilot and, at the time (1963) he was selected for the manned space program, was serving as a flight instructor and safety officer. He accompanied Frank Borman on the record-breaking 14-day flight of Gemini 7. Launched Dec. 4, 1965, Gemini 7 was joined in space by Gemini 6, launched 11 days later and manned by Walter M. Schirra, Jr., and Thomas P. Stafford, for the first successful space rendezvous. Lovell joined Edwin E. Aldr...
</Question>
<Choice>Lovell, James A, Jr.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Portuguese navigator and explorer who sailed under the flags of both Portugal (1505–12) and Spain (1519–21). From Spain he sailed around South America, discovering the Strait of Magellan, and across the Pacific. Though he was killed in the Philippines, his ships continued westward to Spain, accomplishing the first circumnavigation of the Earth. The voyage was successfully terminated by the Basque navigator Juan Sebastián del Cano.
</Question>
<Choice>Magellan, Ferdinand</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American teacher who was chosen to be the first private citizen in space. The death of McAuliffe and her fellow crew members in the 1986 space shuttleChallenger disaster was deeply felt by the nation and had a strong effect on the U.S. space program.Christa Corrigan earned her B.A. from Framingham (Massachusetts) State College in 1970 and the same year married Steve McAuliffe. She received her M.A. in education from Bowie (Maryland) State College (now University) in 1978. In 1970 she began a teaching career that impressed both her colleagues and her students with her energy and dedication.When...
</Question>
<Choice>McAuliffe, Christa Corrigan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Norwegian explorer, oceanographer, statesman, and humanitarian who led a number of expeditions to the Arctic (1888, 1893, 1895–96) and oceanographic expeditions in the North Atlantic (1900, 1910–14). For his relief work after World War I he was awarded the Nobel Prize for Peace (1922).
</Question>
<Choice>Nansen, Fridtjof</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American theoretical physicist and science administrator, noted as director of the Los Alamos laboratory during development of the atomic bomb (1943–45) and as director of the Institute for Advanced Study, Princeton (1947–66). Accusations of disloyalty led to a government hearing that resulted in the loss of his security clearance and of his position as adviser to the highest echelons of the U.S. government. The case became a cause célèbre in the world of science because of its implications concerning political and moral issues relating to the role of scientists in government.Oppenheimer was t...
</Question>
<Choice>Oppenheimer, J. Robert</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French chemist and microbiologist who was one of the most important founders of medical microbiology. Pasteur's contributions to science, technology, and medicine are nearly without precedent. He pioneered the study of molecular asymmetry; discovered that microorganisms cause fermentation and disease; originated the process of pasteurization; saved the beer, wine, and silk industries in France; and developed vaccines against anthrax and rabies.Pasteur's academic positions were numerous, and his scientific accomplishments earned him France's highest decoration, the Legion of Honour, as well as...
</Question>
<Choice>Pasteur, Louis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swiss oceanic engineer, economist, and physicist, who helped his father, Auguste Piccard, build the bathyscaphe for deep-sea exploration and who also invented the mesoscaphe, an undersea vessel for exploring middle depths.He was born in Brussels while his Swiss-born father was a professor at the University of Brussels. After graduating from the École Nouvelle de Suisse Romande in Lausanne, Switz., in 1943, he studied at the University of Geneva, taking a year off in 1944–45 in order to serve with the French First Army. Upon receiving his licentiate in 1946, he taught at the university for two...
</Question>
<Choice>Piccard, Jacques</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Venetian merchant and adventurer, who traveled from Europe to Asia in 1271–95, remaining in China for 17 of those years, and whose Il milione (“The Million”), known in English as the Travels of Marco Polo, is a classic of travel literature.
</Question>
<Choice>Polo, Marco</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spanish explorer who founded the oldest settlement in Puerto Rico and later discovered Florida (1513) while searching for the mythical fountain of youth.Born into a noble family, Ponce de León was a page in the royal court of Aragon and later fought in a campaign against the Moors in Granada. It is possible that he began his career of exploration in 1493 as part of Christopher Columbus' second expedition to the New World. In 1502 he was in the West Indies as a captain serving under Nicolás de Ovando, governor of Hispaniola. As a reward for suppressing an Indian mutiny, Ponce de León was named...
</Question>
<Choice>Ponce de León, Juan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English adventurer and writer, a favourite of Queen Elizabeth I, who knighted him in 1585. Accused of treason by Elizabeth's successor, James I, he was imprisoned in the Tower of London and eventually put to death.Raleigh was a younger son of Walter Raleigh (d. 1581) of Fardell in Devon, by his third wife, Katherine Gilbert (née Champernowne). In 1569 he fought on the Huguenot (French Protestant) side in the Wars of Religion in France, and he is known later to have been at Oriel College, Oxford (1572), and at the Middle Temple law college (1575). In 1580 he fought against the Irish rebels in M...
</Question>
<Choice>Raleigh, Sir Walter</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American astronaut, the first American woman to travel into outer space. Only two other women preceded her: Valentina Tereshkova (1963) and Svetlana Savitskaya (1982), both from the former Soviet Union.Ride showed great early promise as a tennis player, but she eventually gave up her plans to play professionally and attended Stanford University, where she earned bachelor's degrees in English and physics (1973). In 1978, as a doctoral candidate and teaching assistant in laser physics at Stanford, she was selected by the National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA) as one of six women as...
</Question>
<Choice>Ride, Sally</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Shoshone Indian woman who, as interpreter, traveled thousands of wilderness miles with the Lewis and Clark Expedition (1804–06), from the Mandan-Hidatsa villages in the Dakotas to the Pacific Northwest.Separating fact from legend in Sacagawea's life is difficult; historians disagree on the dates of her birth and death and even on her name. In Hidatsa, Sacagawea (pronounced with a hard g) translates into “Bird Woman.” Alternatively, Sacajawea means “Boat Launcher” in Shoshone. Others favor Sakakawea. The Lewis and Clark journals generally support the Hidatsa derivation.A Lemhi Shoshone woman, s...
</Question>
<Choice>Sacagawea</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American physician and medical researcher who developed the first safe and effective vaccine for polio.Salk received his M.D. in 1939 from New York University College of Medicine, where he worked with Thomas Francis, Jr., who was conducting killed-virus immunology studies. Salk joined Francis in 1942 at the University of Michigan School of Public Health and became part of a group that was working to develop an immunization against influenza.In 1947 Salk became associate professor of bacteriology and head of the Virus Research Laboratory at the University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine. At Pi...
</Question>
<Choice>Salk, Jonas Edward</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British Antarctic explorer who attempted to reach the South Pole.Educated at Dulwich College (1887–90), Shackleton entered the mercantile marine service in 1890 and became a sublieutenant in the Royal Naval Reserve in 1901. He joined Captain Robert Falcon Scott's British National Antarctic (Discovery) Expedition (1901–04) as third lieutenant and took part, with Scott and Edward Wilson, in the sledge journey over the Ross Ice Shelf when latitude 82° 16? 33? S was reached. His health suffered, and he was invalided out on the supply ship Morning in March 1903. In January 1908 he returned to Antar...
</Question>
<Choice>Shackleton, Sir Ernest Henry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first U.S. astronaut to travel in space.Shepard graduated from the U.S. Naval Academy, Annapolis, Md., in 1944 and served in the Pacific during World War II. He became a naval test pilot, and in 1958 he graduated from the Naval War College, Newport, R.I. In 1959 he became one of the original seven astronauts chosen for the U.S. Mercury program by the National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA).On May 5, 1961, Shepard made a 15-minute suborbital flight in the Freedom 7 spacecraft, which reached an altitude of 115 miles (185 km). The flight came 23 days after Major Yury Gagarin of the S...
</Question>
<Choice>Shepard, Alan B., Jr.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English explorer and early leader of the Jamestown Colony, the first permanent English settlement in North America. Smith played an equally important role as a cartographer and a prolific writer who vividly depicted the natural abundance of the New World, whetting the colonizing appetite of prospective English settlers.Smith grew up on his family's farm and was apprenticed in his teens to a wealthy merchant. At age 16 or 17, his adventuresome spirit found an outlet on the battlefields of continental Europe, where he fought for the Netherlands in its war of independence from Spain. Having retur...
</Question>
<Choice>Smith, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British American explorer of central Africa, famous for his rescue of the Scottish missionary and explorer David Livingstone and for his discoveries in and development of the Congo region. He was knighted in 1899.
</Question>
<Choice>Stanley, Sir Henry Morton</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nepalese“Wealthy-Fortunate Follower of Religion”Tibetan mountaineer who, with Edmund (later Sir Edmund) Hillary of New Zealand, was the first person to set foot on the summit of Mount Everest, the world's highest peak (29,035 feet [8,850 metres]; seeResearcher's Note: Height of Mount Everest).It is not known exactly when, how, or under what conditions Tenzing came to live in Khumbu as a young boy. Among the ethnic Sherpas, immigrant Tibetans such as Tenzing are known as Khambas and have low status and little or no wealth. Tenzing worked for several years for an affluent family in Khumjung, and...
</Question>
<Choice>Tenzing Norgay</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Soviet cosmonaut, the first woman to travel into space. On June 16, 1963, she was launched in the spacecraft Vostok 6, which completed 48 orbits in 71 hours. In space at the same time was Valery F. Bykovsky, who had been launched two days earlier in Vostok 5; both landed on June 19.Although she had no pilot training, Tereshkova was an accomplished amateur parachutist and on this basis was accepted for the cosmonaut program when she volunteered in 1961. She left the program just after her flight, and on November 3, 1963, she was married to Andriyan G. Nikolayev, another cosmonaut. From 1966 unt...
</Question>
<Choice>Tereshkova, Valentina</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
merchant and explorer-navigator who took part in early voyages to the New World (1499–1500, 1501–02) and occupied the influential post of piloto mayor (“master navigator”) in Sevilla (1508–12). The name for the Americas is derived from his given name.
</Question>
<Choice>Vespucci, Amerigo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American geneticist and biophysicist who played a crucial role in the discovery of the molecular structure of deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA), the substance that is the basis of heredity. For this accomplishment he was awarded the 1962 Nobel Prize for Physiology or Medicine with Francis Crick and Maurice Wilkins.Watson enrolled at the University of Chicago when only 15 and graduated in 1947. From his virus research at Indiana University (Ph.D., 1950), and from the experiments of Canadian-born American bacteriologist Oswald Avery, which proved that DNA affects hereditary traits, Watson became convi...
</Question>
<Choice>Watson, James Dewey</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American test pilot and U.S. Air Force officer who was the first man to exceed the speed of sound in flight.Yeager enlisted in the U.S. Army in September 1941, shortly after graduating from high school, and was assigned to the Army Air Corps. He was commissioned a reserve flight officer in 1943 and became a pilot in the fighter command of the Eighth Air Force stationed in England. He flew 64 missions over Europe during World War II, shot down 13 German aircraft, and was himself shot down over France (he escaped capture with the help of the French underground). After the war he became a flight...
</Question>
<Choice>Yeager, Chuck</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Bangladeshi economist and founder of the Grameen Bank, an institution that provides microcredit (small loans to poor people possessing no collateral) to help its clients establish creditworthiness and financial self-sufficiency. In 2006 Yunus and Grameen received the Nobel Prize for Peace.After teaching economics at Chittagong University from 1961 to 1965, Yunus won a Fulbright scholarship. He studied and taught at Vanderbilt University from 1965 to 1972, earning a Ph.D. in economics in 1969. He returned to Chittagong University as head of the economics department in 1972 and began studying th...
</Question>
<Choice>Yunus, Muhammad</Choice>
</item>
</topics>