<topics>
<item>
<Question>
one of Britain's most renowned pirates of the late 17th century, and the model for Daniel Defoe's hero in Life, Adventures, and Pyracies, of the Famous Captain Singleton (1720).Avery reputedly served in the Royal Navy and on merchantmen, as well as on buccaneer and slave ships, before beginning a life of piracy about 1691. In 1694, joining a ship in the service of Spain, he helped plot a mutiny and was elected captain of his new pirate ship, renamed the Fancy. In 1695, after preying on various ships en route around Africa, the Fancy was joined by other pirate ships, and under Avery's leadershi...
</Question>
<Choice>Avery, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(Redbeard),Barbary pirate and later admiral of the Ottoman fleet, by whose initiative Algeria and Tunisia became part of the Ottoman Empire. For three centuries after his death, Mediterranean coastal towns and villages were ravaged by his pirate successors.Khi?r was one of four sons of a Turk from the island of Lesbos. Hatred of the Spanish and Portuguese who attacked North Africa between 1505 and 1511 encouraged Khi?r and his brother ?Ar?j to intensify their piracy. They hoped, with the aid of Turks and Muslim emigrants from Spain, to wrest an African domain for themselves and had begun to su...
</Question>
<Choice>Barbarossa</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
matriarch of an outlaw gang of brothers and allies engaged in kidnapping and in payroll, post-office, and bank robberies in the 1920s and '30s. The activities of the gang, which included her sons, the “Bloody Barkers”—Herman (1894–1927), Arthur, known as “Doc” (1899–1939), and Fred (1902–35)—ranged throughout the midwestern United States from Minnesota to Texas. All met violent deaths. Ma Barker and Fred were killed at a Florida resort in a gun battle with the FBI; Arthur was killed in an attempted escape from Alcatraz; Herman, cornered by Kansas police, shot himself. A fourth brother, Lloyd (...
</Question>
<Choice>Barker, Ma</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
one of the most notorious gunfighters of the American West, reputed to have killed at least 27 men before being gunned down at about age 21.Born on New York City's East Side, Billy as a child migrated with his parents to Kansas; his father died there, and the mother and her two boys moved to Colorado, where she remarried. The family moved to New Mexico, and, in his early teens, Billy fell into a career of thievery and lawlessness, wandering throughout the Southwest and northern Mexico, often with gangs. In December 1880 he was captured by Sheriff Patrick Floyd Garrett and stood trial for murde...
</Question>
<Choice>Billy the Kid</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
California hooded robber believed to have held up some 28 stagecoaches from 1875 to 1883. Twice he left verse for the occasion, signed “Black Bart,” the more famous being: “I've labored long and hard for bread/ For honor and for riches/ But on my corns too long you've tred/ You fine haired Sons of Bitches.”Born in New York state, he served in the American Civil War and lived in Illinois and then San Francisco (as Charles E. Bolton) for several years before taking to stage robbing late in life. Finally, in 1883, during an abortive robbery, he dropped a handkerchief, and Pinkerton agents traced...
</Question>
<Choice>Black Bart</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
one of history's most famous pirates, who became an imposing figure in American folklore.Thought to have been active as a privateer for the British during the War of the Spanish Succession (1701–13), Blackbeard was first heard of as a pirate late in 1716. The following year he converted a captured French merchantman into a 40-gun warship, Queen Anne's Revenge, and soon became notorious for outrages along the Virginia and Carolina coasts and in the Caribbean Sea. In 1718 Blackbeard established his base in a North Carolina inlet, forcibly collected tolls from shipping in Pamlico Sound, and made...
</Question>
<Choice>Blackbeard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
robbery team that became notorious in the United States through their flamboyant encounters with police and the sensationalization of their exploits by the country's newspapers.Barrow had been a criminal long before he met Parker in January 1930. After 20 months in prison in 1930–32, he teamed up with Parker, and the two began a crime spree that lasted 21 months. Often working with confederates—including Barrow's brother Buck and Buck's wife, Blanche, as well as Ray Hamilton and W.D. Jones—Bonnie and Clyde, as they were popularly known, robbed gas stations, restaurants, and small-town banks—th...
</Question>
<Choice>Bonnie and Clyde</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
early American frontiersman and legendary hero who helped blaze a trail through Cumberland Gap, a notch in the Appalachian Mountains near the juncture of Virginia, Tennessee, and Kentucky.Boone had little formal schooling but learned to read and write. As a youth he moved with his family (English Quakers) to the North Carolina frontier. Most of his life was spent as a wandering hunter and trapper.Many white men had traversed Kentucky before Boone; hence, the legend that he was its discoverer needs qualification. Boone first went a short way through Cumberland Gap to hunt in the fall of 1767, a...
</Question>
<Choice>Boone, Daniel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American frontiersman, trapper, soldier, and Indian agent who made an important contribution to the westward expansion of the United States. His career as an Indian fighter earned him both folk hero status through its aggrandizement in the dime novels of his day and condemnation from some later revisionist historians as an agent of the displacement and decimation of the native peoples of the West.At 15 Carson ran away from his home in Missouri to join a caravan of traders bound for Santa Fe. From experienced frontiersmen he learned fur trapping and trading, a career he pursued for 15 years.A c...
</Question>
<Choice>Carson, Kit</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American outlaw and foremost member of the Wild Bunch (q.v.), a collection of bank and train robbers who ranged through the western United States in the 1880s and '90s.Robert Parker took his alias from Mike Cassidy, an older outlaw from whom he learned cattle rustling and gunslinging (1884–87). Thereafter—except for two years of chiefly cowboying (1891–92) and two years (1894–96) in Wyoming State Prison—he was teamed up with a succession of outlaws. His favourite friend and confederate was Elzy Lay, with whom, alone or in a gang, he helped rob a number of trains, banks, and paymasters and rust...
</Question>
<Choice>Cassidy, Butch</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
buffalo hunter, U.S. Army scout, and Indian fighter who dramatized the facts and flavour of the American West through fiction and melodrama. His colourful Wild West exhibition (later known as Buffalo Bill's Wild West and Congress of Rough Riders of the World) became an international institution.Cody's father died in 1857, and at the age of 11 the boy went to work as a mounted messenger in Kansas for the wagon-freight firm that later became Russell, Majors, and Waddell, backers of the Pony Express. Before the end of his teens, Cody had become an accomplished horse wrangler, hunter, and Indian f...
</Question>
<Choice>Cody, William F</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American frontiersman and politician who became a legendary figure.His father, having little means, hired him out to more prosperous backwoods farmers, and Davy's schooling amounted to 100 days of tutoring with a neighbour. Successive moves west to middle Tennessee brought him close to the area of the Creek War, in which he made a name for himself from 1813 to 1815. In 1821 he was elected to the Tennessee legislature, winning popularity through campaign speeches filled with yarns and homespun metaphors. In the legislature an opposing speaker referred to Crockett as the “gentleman from the cane...
</Question>
<Choice>Crockett, Davy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American gunslinger who became notorious as the most quick-tempered killer of the Wild Bunch (q.v.), a group of Western outlaws. His brothers, Lonny and Johnny, also gained reputations as Western badmen, as did their uncle, George Sutherland (“Flat Nose”) Curry.Kid Curry, primarily a bank and train robber, was imprisoned in 1902, escaped in June 1903, robbed a train in Parachute, Colo., on July 7, and, according to Pinkerton agents, was wounded by a pursuing posse and shot himself dead. Another story has him surviving, joining Butch Cassidy in South America, and dying in Bolivia in 1909, while...
</Question>
<Choice>Curry, Kid</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
most famous of all U.S. bank robbers, whose short career of robberies and escapes from June 1933 to July 1934 won media headlines.Born in Indianapolis but spending his adolescence on a farm in nearby Mooresville, Dillinger joined the navy in 1923; he served on the USS Utah but deserted after only a few months. In September 1924, caught in the foiled holdup of a Mooresville grocer, he served much of the next decade (1924–33) in Indiana state prisons. While in prison he learned the craft of bank robbery from tough professionals. Upon parole on May 22, 1933, he turned his knowledge to profit, tak...
</Question>
<Choice>Dillinger, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
legendary frontiersman of the American West, who was an itinerant saloonkeeper, gambler, lawman, gunslinger, and confidence man. The first major biography, Stuart N. Lake's Wyatt Earp, Frontier Marshal (1931), written with Earp's collaboration, established the rather fictionalized portrait of a fearless lawman.Earp and his four brothers—James C. (1841–1926), Virgil W. (1843–1906), Morgan (1851–82), and Warren B. (1855–1900)—spent their early lives in Illinois and Iowa but, toward the end of the American Civil War (1864), moved with their parents to San Bernardino, Calif. In 1868 the family mov...
</Question>
<Choice>Earp, Wyatt</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American gunman whose run-ins with police and violent bank robberies made newspaper headlines.In 1911 Floyd moved with his family to Oklahoma, eventually settling in Akins. Originally a farmer, he was drawn into crime by the poverty of the Dust Bowl. After serving a term in prison (1925–29) for a payroll robbery, Floyd mixed with gangsters in Kansas City, Missouri, and adopted the machine gun as his professional trademark. He teamed up with others to rob banks in Ohio (where he was captured in 1930, but subsequently escaped), Michigan, and Kentucky. After nearly being apprehended by the police...
</Question>
<Choice>Floyd, Pretty Boy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
notorious Japanese pirate leader. Originally a government official, he was dispatched by the court to eliminate pirates plaguing the Inland Sea, which connects central and south Japan. A traitor to the trust placed in him, Sumitomo became the leader of the pirates and other dissident local bands and thereby gained control of most of the strategic areas along the waterway before he was defeated in 941. His actions helped to weaken Japan's central government.
</Question>
<Choice>Fujiwara Sumitomo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
most notorious killer and quick-draw gunman of the Texas frontier. He killed at least 21 men in gun duels and ambushes in the period 1868–77.Reaching adolescence as the defeated South entered the Reconstruction period, Hardin was virulently antiblack and anti-Yankee and, in 1868 at the age of 15, killed his first man, an ex-slave. From then on he led a life of gunslinging, dueling, gambling, and drinking. In the course of his career he outgunned and killed at least eight Union soldiers and four black policemen pursuing him on various murder charges. Finally, in flight from Texas, he was caught...
</Question>
<Choice>Hardin, John Wesley</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American frontiersman, army scout, and lawman, who helped bring order to the frontier West. His reputation as a marksman gave rise to legends and tales about his life.As a child in Illinois, Hickok worked on neighbouring farms and helped his father in assisting escaped slaves. He left home in 1856 to farm in Kansas and there became involved in the Free State (antislavery) movement. He later served as a village constable in Monticello, Kansas. While working as a teamster in 1861, he killed Dave McCanles at Rock Creek (Nebraska Territory), and legends about him probably began in the exaggerated...
</Question>
<Choice>Hickok, Wild Bill</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
gambler, gunman, and sometime dentist of the American West.Holliday was reared in Georgia in the genteel tradition of the Old South, graduated from the Pennsylvania College of Dental Surgery in 1872, and, already consumptive, moved west for drier climes. He practiced dentistry briefly in Dallas but soon discovered his prowess as a gambler, a poker and faro player, and began drifting throughout the West—Jacksboro, Texas; Pueblo and Denver, Colo.; Cheyenne, Wyo.; Deadwood, S.D.; Dodge City, Kan.; Trinidad and Leadville, Colo.; and Las Vegas, N.M., ending up in Tombstone, Ariz., in 1880. During t...
</Question>
<Choice>Holliday, Doc</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
two brothers who were among the most notorious outlaws of the American West, engaging in robberies that came to typify the hazards of the 19th-century frontier as it has been portrayed in motion-picture Westerns.Reared on a Missouri farm, Jesse and Frank shared their family's sympathy with the Southern cause when the American Civil War broke out (1861). Frank joined William C. Quantrill's Confederate guerrillas, becoming friends with Cole Younger, a fellow member. Jesse followed suit by joining “Bloody” Bill Anderson's guerrilla band. At the end of the war the bands surrendered, but Jesse was...
</Question>
<Choice>James, Jesse; and James, Frank</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
most famous of the bushrangers, Australian rural outlaws of the 19th century.In 1877 Kelly shot and injured a policeman who was trying to arrest his brother, Dan Kelly, for horse theft. The brothers fled to the bush, where two other men joined them to form the Kelly gang. The Kelly gang's perpetration of a series of daring robberies in the Victoria–New South Wales borderland (1878–80) captured the imagination of the public. Some viewed Ned Kelly as a personification of the plight of workers set against large landowners in an economically depressed period.In June 1880, after several police shoo...
</Question>
<Choice>Kelly, Ned</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
17th-century British privateer and semilegendary pirate who became celebrated in English literature as one of the most colourful outlaws of all time. Fortune seekers have hunted his buried treasure in vain through succeeding centuries.Kidd's early career is obscure. It is believed he went to sea as a youth. After 1689 he was sailing as a legitimate privateer for Great Britain against the French in the West Indies and off the coast of North America. In 1690 he was an established sea captain and shipowner in New York City, where he owned property; at various times he was dispatched by both New Y...
</Question>
<Choice>Kidd, William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American gunman and bank robber noted for his vicious killings and youthful looks.From petty crime Nelson graduated into labour racketeering, working for Al Capone (1929–31) and other bootleg bosses; he was let go, however, proving too violent even for them. He then turned to bank robberies, joining with John Dillinger on two occasions (1934). Listed as Public Enemy Number One by the Federal Bureau of Investigation (FBI), he was killed in a wild shoot-out with FBI agents.
</Question>
<Choice>Nelson, Baby Face</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
noted Highland outlaw whose reputation as a Scottish Robin Hood was exaggerated in Sir Walter Scott's novel Rob Roy (1818) and in some passages in the poems of William Wordsworth. He frequently signed himself Rob Roy (“Red Rob”), in reference to his dark red hair.Rob's father, Donald MacGregor, a younger brother of the chief of the clan MacGregor, received a military commission from the deposed King James II after the Glorious Revolution (1688–89). Rob was a freebooter with uncertain loyalty to James and was probably also engaged in cattle stealing and blackmail, old and at that time still hon...
</Question>
<Choice>Rob Roy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
pirate captain of a succession of ships—the “Royal Rover,” “Fortune,” “Royal Fortune,” and “Good Fortune”—who burned and plundered ships from the coasts of West Africa to the coasts of Brazil and the Caribbean and as far north as Newfoundland. His conquests are said to have included more than 400 vessels and, in terms of sheer numbers, are rivalled only by the feats of Sir Henry Morgan.Roberts took to piracy late, after the age of 37, but he quickly rose to captaincy. He even designed a flag for himself, portraying a giant figure of himself standing, sword in hand, astride two skulls labelled...
</Question>
<Choice>Roberts, Bartholomew</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American big-time gambler, bootlegger, and friend of high-placed politicians and businessmen, who dominated influence-peddling in the 1920s in New York City. He was the prototype for F. Scott Fitzgerald's character Meyer Wolfsheim in The Great Gatsby, “the man who fixed the World's Series back in 1919.” Rothstein allegedly masterminded the bribery in the Black Sox baseball scandal.Born on New York's East Side, of a middle-class Jewish family, Rothstein in his teens was already involved in gambling and loansharking and, by the 1920s, had cultivated the friendship of politicians and businessmen...
</Question>
<Choice>Rothstein, Arnold</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American outlaw of Texas and the Oklahoma Indian Territory.Myra Belle Shirley grew up in Carthage, Missouri, from the age of two. After the death of an elder brother, who early in the Civil War had become a bushwhacker and had perhaps ridden with guerrilla leader William C. Quantrill's raiders, and following also the burning of Carthage in 1863, the family moved to a farm at Scyene, near Dallas, Texas. At the end of the war the remnants of Quantrill's gang turned to undisguised outlawry, becoming notorious as the gangs led by the Younger brothers and by Jesse and Frank James. They occasionally...
</Question>
<Choice>Starr, Belle</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American outlaw, reputed to be the best shot and fastest gunslinger of the Wild Bunch, a group of robbers and rustlers who ranged through the Rocky Mountains and plateau desert regions of the West in the 1880s and '90s.Harry Longabaugh left home when he was 15 and took his nickname from the town of Sundance, where he was imprisoned (for his first and only time) from August 1887 to February 1889 for stealing a horse. After release he headed for the hideout of Hole in the Wall in central Wyoming and began his outlaw career.At the turn of the century, the Sundance Kid joined with Butch Cassidy an...
</Question>
<Choice>Sundance Kid</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
celebrated American bank robber and prison escapee who earned his nickname “the Actor” because of his talent for disguises, posing as a guard, messenger, policeman, diplomat, or window cleaner to fool authorities.Raised in a tough Irish-American district in Brooklyn, he was a veteran thief and hoodlum by the time that he was a teenager and, at the age of 21, was arrested and acquitted on a murder charge. After a prison term for safecracking (1926–27), he engaged in bank and store robberies. In 1930 in Manhattan, he robbed his first bank, and a jeweler as well, while disguised as a Western Unio...
</Question>
<Choice>Sutton, Willie</Choice>
</item>
</topics>