<topics>
<item>
<Question>
Nigerian military leader, who served as head of state (1993–98).Abacha received his formal military training at Nigerian and British military training colleges. He rose through the ranks in the Nigerian military and by 1983 had achieved the rank of brigadier when he assisted Ibrahim Babangida in overthrowing Shehu Shagari, who had been elected to his second presidential term in 1983. Muhammad Buhari became Nigeria's leader, but just two years later Babangida overthrew Buhari and installed himself as leader with Abacha second in command. Elections were held in 1993 and were won by Moshood Abiol...
</Question>
<Choice>Abacha, Sani</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
a prominent figure in India's struggle for independence, who fought for the rights of Kashmir and won for it a semiautonomous status within India.Abdullah was educated at the Prince of Wales College (Jammu) and the Islamia College (Lahore) and received a master's degree in physics from Aligarh Muslim University in 1930. He championed the rights of the Muslim majority of the state during British rule in India and fought against the discrimination exercised by the Hindu ruling house. In 1931, after Abdullah served the first of what would be many terms of imprisonment, he founded the Kashmir Musl...
</Question>
<Choice>Abdullah, Sheikh Muhammad</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
president of Sinn Féin, the political wing of the Irish Republican Army (IRA), one of the chief architects of Sinn Féin's shift to a policy of seeking a peaceful settlement to sectarian violence in Northern Ireland, and a member of the British Parliament (from West Belfast) and the Northern Ireland Assembly.Born into a strongly republican family, Adams became involved in predominantly Roman Catholic civil rights protests in Belfast, Northern Ireland, which became increasingly violent in the late 1960s. By early 1970 he was suspected of heading a unit of the IRA, a republican paramilitary organ...
</Question>
<Choice>Adams, Gerry</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
early advocate of American independence from Great Britain, major figure in the Continental Congress (1774–77), author of the Massachusetts constitution (1780), signer of the Treaty of Paris (1783), first American ambassador to the Court of St. James (1785–88), first vice president (1789–97) and second president (1797–1801) of the United States. Although Adams was regarded by his contemporaries as one of the most significant statesmen of the revolutionary era, his reputation faded in the 19th century, only to ascend again during the last half of the 20th century. The modern edition of his corr...
</Question>
<Choice>Adams, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spartan king (338–331) who rebelled unsuccessfully against Alexander the Great.A member of the Eurypontid house (one of the two royal families of Sparta), Agis succeeded to the throne of his father, Archidamus III. While Alexander was invading Anatolia, Agis, profiting from the Macedonian general's absence from Greece, led the Greek cities in revolt. With Persian money and 8,000 Greek mercenaries, he tried to hold Crete against Alexander. In 331 he raised a coalition in the Peloponnese and laid siege to Megalopolis. Alexander's regent, Antipater, made peace with the Thracians (with whom he had...
</Question>
<Choice>Agis III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Macedonia (336–323 BC). He overthrew the Persian Empire, carried Macedonian arms to India, and laid the foundations for the Hellenistic world of territorial kingdoms. Already in his lifetime the subject of fabulous stories, he later became the hero of a full-scale legend bearing only the sketchiest resemblance to his historical career.
</Question>
<Choice>Alexander the Great</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Albanian brigand who, by murder and intrigue, became pasha, or provincial governor, of Janina from 1788. He extended his capricious rule within the Ottoman Empire over much of Albania and Macedonia, Epirus, Thessaly, and the Morea.His father, Veli, bey of Tepelenë, died a poor man when Ali was 14. His mother, Khamco, formed a brigand band to restore the political and material fortunes of the family, and Ali became a notorious brigand leader. After service with the pasha of Negroponte (Euboea), he joined the wealthy pasha of Delvino, whose daughter he married in 1768. Becoming lieutenant to the...
</Question>
<Choice>Ali Pasa Tepelenë</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
town (“parish”), Salisbury district, administrative and historic county of Wiltshire, England, in the valley of the River Avon. It is rich in prehistoric remains, including Stonehenge, 1.5 miles (2.5 km) west, the greatest surviving megalithic structure in the British Isles. At Amesbury (Ambresbyrig, or Ambresbery) a Witan, or Witenagemot, the Anglo-Saxon kings' council of wise men, was held in 932. Now a small market town, Amesbury also caters to the needs of tourists visiting Stonehenge and serves such neighbouring army camps as Larkhill. Pop. (2001) 8,907.
</Question>
<Choice>Amesbury</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
military officer and president (1971–79) of Uganda whose regime was noted for its brutality.A member of the small Kakwa ethnic group of northwestern Uganda, Amin had little formal education and joined the King's African Rifles of the British colonial army in 1946 as an assistant cook. He quickly rose through the ranks, serving in the Allied forces' Burma (Myanmar) campaign during World War II and in the British action against the Mau Mau revolt in Kenya (1952–56). Amin was one of the few Ugandan soldiers elevated to officer rank before Ugandan independence in 1962, and he became closely associ...
</Question>
<Choice>Amin, Idi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ghanaian international civil servant, who was the secretary-general of the United Nations (UN) from 1997 to 2006. He was the corecipient, with the United Nations, of the Nobel Prize for Peace in 2001.Annan, whose father was governor of Asante province and a hereditary paramount chief of the Fante people, studied at the University of Science and Technology in Kumasi before enrolling at Macalester College in St. Paul, Minn., U.S., where he received a bachelor's degree in economics. He continued his studies at the Institute for Advanced International Studies in Geneva. He earned a master's degree...
</Question>
<Choice>Annan, Kofi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Romanian marshal and statesman who became dictator of the pro-German government during World War II.After World War I, Antonescu served as military attaché in Paris and in London and, in 1934, as chief of the Romanian general staff. Named minister of defense in 1937, he retained office with the establishment of King Carol II's corporatist dictatorship (1938), only to be dismissed after a few weeks as a sympathizer of the principal Romanian fascist group, the Iron Guard. On the domestic front, he was an anticommunist and an anti-Semite, but he favoured France and Great Britain in international...
</Question>
<Choice>Antonescu, Ion</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
president (1996–2004) of the Palestinian Authority, chairman (1969–2004) of the Palestine Liberation Organization (PLO), and leader of Fatah, the largest of the constituent PLO groups. In 1993 he led the PLO to a peace agreement with the Israeli government. ?Araf?t and Yitzhak Rabin and Shimon Peres of Israel were jointly awarded the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1994.?Araf?t was one of seven children of a well-to-do merchant whose wife was related to the anti-Zionist grand mufti of Jerusalem, Am?n al-?usayn? (died 1974). The date and place of ?Araf?t's birth are disputed. A birth certificate regis...
</Question>
<Choice>'Arafat, Yasir</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
president of Costa Rica (1986–90; 2006– ) and recipient of the Nobel Peace Prize in 1987 for his Central American peace plan.Born into one of the wealthiest coffee-growing families in Costa Rica, Arias studied economics at the University of Costa Rica and earned a Ph.D. in political science from the University of Essex in England. In the 1960s he began working for the moderate socialist National Liberation Party (Partido de Liberación Nacional; PLN), and in 1972 he was appointed minister of planning in the government of President José Figueres Ferrer, a post he held until 1977. He was elected...
</Question>
<Choice>Arias Sánchez, Oscar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
patriot officer who served the cause of the American Revolution until 1779, when he shifted his allegiance to the British; thereafter his name became an epithet for traitor in the United States.Upon the outbreak of hostilities at Lexington, Massachusetts (April 1775), Arnold volunteered for service and participated with Ethan Allen in the successful colonial attack on British-held Fort Ticonderoga, New York, the following month. That autumn he was appointed by General George Washington to command an expedition to capture Quebec. He marched with 700 men by way of the Maine wilderness, a remarka...
</Question>
<Choice>Arnold, Benedict</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Achaemenid king of Persia (reigned 404–359/358).He was the son and successor of Darius II and was surnamed (in Greek) Mnemon, meaning “the mindful.” When Artaxerxes took the Persian throne, the power of Athens had been broken in the Peloponnesian War (431–404), and the Greek towns across the Aegean Sea in Ionia were again subjects of the Achaemenid Empire. In 404, however, Artaxerxes lost Egypt, and in the following year his brother Cyrus the Younger began preparations for his rebellion. Although Cyrus was defeated and killed at Cunaxa (401), the rebellion had dangerous repercussions, for it n...
</Question>
<Choice>Artaxerxes II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Turkish“Kemal, Father of Turks”soldier, statesman, and reformer who was the founder and first president (1923–38) of the Republic of Turkey. He modernized the country's legal and educational systems and encouraged the adoption of a European way of life, with Turkish written in the Latin alphabet and with citizens adopting European-style names.One of the great figures of the 20th century, Atatürk rescued the surviving Turkish remnant of the defeated Ottoman Empire at the end of World War I. He galvanized his people against invading Greek forces who sought to impose the Allied will upon the war-...
</Question>
<Choice>Atatürk, Kemal</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the Huns from 434 to 453 (ruling jointly with his elder brother Bleda until 445). He was one of the greatest of the barbarian rulers who assailed the Roman Empire, invading the southern Balkan provinces and Greece and then Gaul and Italy. In legend he appears under the name Etzel in the Nibelungenlied and under the name Atli in Icelandic sagas.
</Question>
<Choice>Attila</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Arabic“Tiger”emperor (1526–30) and founder of the Mughal dynasty of India. A descendant of the Mongol conqueror Chinggis (Genghis) Khan and also of the Turkic conqueror Timur (Tamerlane), B?bur was a military adventurer, a soldier of distinction, and a poet and diarist of genius, as well as a statesman.
</Question>
<Choice>Babur</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British army officer who became a national hero for his 217-day defense of Mafeking (now Mafikeng) in the South African War of 1899–1902; he later became famous as founder of the Boy Scouts and Girl Guides (also called Girl Scouts).In 1884–85 Baden-Powell became noted for his use of observation balloons in warfare in Bechuanaland (now Botswana) and the Sudan. From Oct. 12, 1899, to May 17, 1900, he defended Mafeking, holding off a much larger Boer force until the siege was lifted. After the war he recruited and trained the South African constabulary. On returning to England in 1903, he was app...
</Question>
<Choice>
Baden-Powell, Robert Stephenson Smyth Baden-Powell, 1st Baron
</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nazi leader, head of the Gestapo in Lyon from 1942 to 1944, who was held responsible for the death of some 4,000 persons and the deportation of some 7,500 others.Barbie was a member of the Hitler Youth and in 1935 joined the Sicherheitsdienst (SD; “Security Service”), a special branch of the SS. After German forces overran western Europe in World War II, Barbie served in The Netherlands and then, in 1942, was made chief of Gestapo Department IV in Lyon. (The SD was closely related to the Gestapo, and personnel were frequently transferred from one to the other.) In this position he became espec...
</Question>
<Choice>Barbie, Klaus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
soldier and political leader who twice ruled Cuba—first in 1933–44 with an efficient government and again in 1952–59 as a dictator, jailing his opponents, using terrorist methods, and making fortunes for himself and his associates.The son of impoverished farmers, Batista worked in a variety of jobs until he joined the army in 1921, starting as a stenographer. He rose to the rank of sergeant and developed a large personal following. In September 1933 he organized the “sergeants' revolt”; it toppled the provisional regime of Carlos Manuel de Céspedes, which had replaced the dictatorial regime of...
</Question>
<Choice>Batista, Fulgencio</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Zionist leader who was prime minister of Israel from 1977 to 1983. Begin was the co-recipient, with Egyptian president Anwar el-S?d?t, of the 1978 Nobel Prize for Peace for their achievement of a peace treaty between Israel and Egypt that was formally signed in 1979.Begin received a law degree from the University of Warsaw in 1935. Active in the Zionist movement throughout the 1930s, he became (1938) the leader of the Polish branch of the Betar youth movement, dedicated to the establishment of a Jewish state on both sides of the Jordan River. When the Germans invaded Warsaw in 1939, he escaped...
</Question>
<Choice>Begin, Menachem</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
principal leader of the Algerian War of Independence against France, the first prime minister (1962–63) and first elected president (1963–65) of the Algerian republic, who steered his country toward a socialist economy.Ben Bella was the son of a farmer and small businessman in Maghnia in the département of Oran. There, he successfully completed his early studies at the French school and continued his education in the neighbouring city of Tlemcen, where he first became aware of racial discrimination and also mingled with the fringes of the nationalist movement.He was conscripted into the French...
</Question>
<Choice>Ben Bella, Ahmed</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Zionist statesman and political leader, the first prime minister (1948–53, 1955–63) and defense minister (1948–53; 1955–63) of Israel. It was Ben-Gurion who, on May 14, 1948, at Tel Aviv, delivered Israel's declaration of independence. His charismatic personality won him the adoration of the masses, and, after his retirement from the government and, later, from the Knesset (the Israeli house of representatives), he was revered as the “Father of the Nation.”Ben-Gurion, born David Gruen, was the son of Victor Gruen, one of the leaders in P?o?sk of the “Lovers of Zion,” a movement that was dissem...
</Question>
<Choice>Ben-Gurion, David</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
controversial figure in post-World War II British politics and one of the finest orators of the time. To achieve mastery as a speaker, he had first to overcome a speech impediment. He was the architect of the national health service and leader of the left-wing (Bevanite) group of the Labour Party.The son of a miner, Bevan became a collier's helper at 13 but had to leave the mines in a few years because of eye disease. After two years at Central Labour College, London, he entered politics and in 1929 was elected to the House of Commons as Labour member from Ebbw Vale. Throughout World War II he...
</Question>
<Choice>Bevan, Aneurin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
African military leader who was president of the Central African Republic (1966–76) and self-styled emperor of the Central African Empire (1976–79).The son of a village headman, Bokassa attended local mission schools before joining the French army in 1939. He distinguished himself in the French conflict in Indochina, and by 1961 he had achieved the rank of captain. At the request of President David Dacko, Bokassa left the French armed forces to head the army of the newly independent Central African Republic. On Dec. 31, 1965, Bokassa used his position as supreme military commander to overthrow...
</Question>
<Choice>Bokassa, Jean-Bédel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
South American soldier and statesman who led the revolutions against Spanish rule in the Viceroyalty of New Granada. He was president of Gran Colombia (1819–30) and dictator of Peru (1823–26).The son of a Venezuelan aristocrat of Spanish descent, Bolívar was born to wealth and position. After his father died when the boy was three years old and his mother died six years later, his uncle administered his inheritance and provided him with tutors. At the age of 16, Bolívar was sent to Europe to complete his education. For three years he lived in Spain and in 1801 married the daughter of a Spanish...
</Question>
<Choice>Bolívar, Simón</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
powerful party leader in Nazi Germany, one of Adolf Hitler's closest lieutenants.An avowed and vocal pan-German in his youth, Bormann participated in right-wing German Free Corps activities after the close of World War I. Bormann was imprisoned in 1924 for participation in a political murder, and after his release he joined the National Socialists. He became head of the Nazi press in Thuringia in 1926 and from 1928 held posts in the high command of the Sturmabteilung (Storm Troopers). In 1933 he became chief of staff to the deputy führer, Rudolf Hess.On May 12, 1941, Hitler appointed Bormann t...
</Question>
<Choice>Bormann, Martin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French politician and statesman, an ardent promoter of the League of Nations, who was awarded the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1920.Trained in law, Bourgeois entered the civil service in 1876 and by 1887 had advanced to the position of prefect of police for the Seine département. In 1888 he was elected to the National Assembly as a deputy from the Marne district. After serving in a number of ministerial posts, he became premier (Nov. 1, 1895–April 21, 1896). Later, he was the head of the Radical-Socialist Party. He represented the Marne (1905–23) in the Senate and was its president from 1920 to 19...
</Question>
<Choice>Bourgeois, Léon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
architect of Tunisia's independence and first president of Tunisia (1957–87), one of the major voices of moderation and gradualism in the Arab world.
</Question>
<Choice>Bourguiba, Habib</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German statesman, leader of the German Social Democratic Party of Germany (Sozialdemokratische Partei Deutschlands, or SPD) from 1964 to 1987, and chancellor of the Federal Republic of Germany from 1969 to 1974. He was awarded the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1971 for his efforts to achieve reconciliation between West Germany and the countries of the Soviet bloc.Brandt passed his university entrance examination in 1932. A year later, however, when the Nazis came to power, his activities as a young Social Democrat brought him into conflict with the Gestapo, and he was forced to flee the country to...
</Question>
<Choice>Brandt, Willy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish statesman and pioneer of social democracy whose conciliatory international diplomacy in the first two decades of the 20th century was recognized by the award of the 1921 Nobel Prize for Peace, which he shared with Norwegian diplomat Christian Lous Lange.After studying science in Stockholm and Uppsala, Branting in 1883 began work for the radical newspaper Tiden, becoming its editor shortly thereafter. In 1886 he assumed the editorship of the Social-Demokraten, and, when the Social Democratic Party was formed in 1889, he was prominent among its founders. After the death of activist Axel...
</Question>
<Choice>Branting, Karl Hjalmar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman who served 11 times as premier of France, holding a total of 26 ministerial posts between 1906 and 1932. His efforts for international cooperation, the League of Nations, and world peace brought him the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1926, which he shared with Gustav Stresemann of Germany.As a law student, Briand became associated with left-wing causes, writing for such publications as Le Peuple, La Lanterne, and Petite République, and in 1904 he joined Jean Jaurès in founding L'Humanité. In 1894 Briand succeeded in getting the sharply divided French trade unionists to adopt the general st...
</Question>
<Choice>Briand, Aristide</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman general who participated in the assassination of the dictator Julius Caesar, though he had been Caesar's protégé.After serving under Caesar in Gaul, Brutus was given command of Caesar's fleet. In 49, during the Civil War between Caesar and Pompey, he led a fleet at the siege of Massilia (now Marseille, France). Caesar then made him governor of Transalpine Gaul (48–46), designated him for a consulship in 42, and nominated him as one of his heirs in the event of the death of his primary successor, Octavian (later the emperor Augustus).After taking part in the assassination of Caesar in Mar...
</Question>
<Choice>Brutus Albinus, Decimus Junius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman politician, one of the leaders in the conspiracy that assassinated Julius Caesar in 44 BC. Brutus was the son of Marcus Junius Brutus (who was treacherously killed by Pompey the Great in 77) and Servilia (who later became Caesar's lover). After his adoption by an uncle, Quintus Servilius Caepio, he was commonly called Quintus Caepio Brutus.Brutus was brought up by another uncle, Cato the Younger, who imbued him with the principles of Stoicism. In the 50s he opposed Pompey's increasing power, but, upon Caesar's invasion of Italy in 49, Brutus was reconciled with Pompey and served under hi...
</Question>
<Choice>Brutus, Marcus Junius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. diplomat, a key member of the United Nations for more than two decades, and winner of the 1950 Nobel Prize for Peace for his successful negotiation of an Arab-Israeli truce in Palestine the previous year.Bunche worked his way through the University of California at Los Angeles and graduated in 1927. He also earned graduate degrees in government and international relations at Harvard University (1928, 1934) and studied in England and South Africa. In 1928 he joined the faculty of Howard University, Washington, D.C., where he set up a department of political science. Meanwhile, he traveled...
</Question>
<Choice>Bunche, Ralph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
third vice president of the United States (1801–05), who killed his political rival, Alexander Hamilton, in a duel (1804), and whose turbulent political career ended with his arrest for treason in 1807.Burr, the son of Aaron Burr and Esther Edwards, came from a prominent New Jersey family and was a grandson of the theologian Jonathan Edwards. He studied law and served on the staff of General George Washington during the American Revolution (1775–83) but was transferred after antagonizing him.In 1782 Burr was admitted to the New York state bar, and his law practice in New York City soon flouris...
</Question>
<Choice>Burr, Aaron</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
celebrated Roman general and statesman, the conqueror of Gaul (58–50 BC), victor in the Civil War of 49–45 BC, and dictator (46–44 BC), who was launching a series of political and social reforms when he was assassinated by a group of nobles in the Senate House on the Ides of March.Caesar changed the course of the history of the Greco-Roman world decisively and irreversibly. The Greco-Roman society has been extinct for so long that most of the names of its great men mean little to the average, educated modern man. But Caesar's name, like Alexander's, is still on people's lips throughout the Chr...
</Question>
<Choice>Caesar, Julius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor from 37 to 41, in succession to Tiberius, who effected the transfer of the last legion that had been under a senatorial proconsul (in Africa) to an imperial legate, thus completing the emperor's monopoly of army command. Accounts of his reign by ancient historians are so biased against him that the truth is almost impossible to disentangle.Born Gaius Caesar, he became known as Caligula (Little Boot), a childhood nickname bestowed on him by the soldiers of his father, Germanicus Caesar, nephew and adoptive son of Tiberius. The deaths of his father in AD 19, of his mother, Agrippin...
</Question>
<Choice>Caligula</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Romania (1930–40), whose controversial reign ultimately gave rise to a personal, monarchical dictatorship.The eldest son of King Ferdinand I, Carol became crown prince upon the death of his great uncle, King Carol I (October 1914). His domestic life was a constant source of scandal, marked as it was by a morganatic marriage with an officer's daughter, Zizi Lambrino; a second unhappy marriage to Helen, daughter of King Constantine I of Greece; and a continuing liaison with a Jewish adventuress, Magda Lupescu—an affair that finally obliged him to renounce his rights to the throne and go...
</Question>
<Choice>Carol II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
39th president of the United States (1977–81), who served as the nation's chief executive during a time of serious problems at home and abroad. His perceived inability to deal successfully with those problems led to an overwhelming defeat in his bid for reelection. After leaving office he embarked on a career of diplomacy and advocacy, for which he was awarded the Nobel Prize for Peace in 2002. (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America.)The son of Earl Carter, a peanut warehouser who had served in the Georgia state legislature,...
</Question>
<Choice>Carter, Jimmy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prime mover in the conspiracy to assassinate Julius Caesar in 44 BC.Little is known of his early life. As a quaestor in 53 BC, Cassius served under Marcus Licinius Crassus and saved the remnants of the Roman army defeated by the Parthians at Carrhae (modern Harran, Turkey). For the next two years he successfully repelled the Parthian attacks on Syria. Cassius became tribune in 49, and the outbreak of the civil war between Caesar and the Optimates in that year saved him from being brought to trial for extortion in Syria. In that war he at first commanded part of the fleet of Caesar's opponent,...
</Question>
<Choice>Cassius Longinus, Gaius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
political leader of Cuba (from 1959) who transformed his country into the first communist state in the Western Hemisphere. Castro became a symbol of communist revolution in Latin America. He held the title of premier until 1976 and then began a long tenure as president of the Council of State and the Council of Ministers, handing over provisional power in July 2006 because of health problems and formally relinquishing the presidency in February 2008.Castro was born in southeastern Cuba. His father, Angel Castro y Argiz, an immigrant from Spain, was a fairly prosperous sugarcane farmer in a loc...
</Question>
<Choice>Castro, Fidel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Communist official who was leader of Romania from 1965 until he was overthrown and killed in a revolution in 1989.A member of the Romanian Communist youth movement during the early 1930s, Ceau?escu was imprisoned in 1936 and again in 1940 for his Communist Party activities. In 1939 he married Elena Petrescu (b. Jan. 7, 1919, Oltenia region, Rom.—d. Dec. 25, 1989, near Bucharest), a Communist activist. While in prison, Ceau?escu became a protégé of his cell mate, the Communist leader Gheorghe Gheorghiu-Dej, who would become the undisputed Communist leader of Romania beginning in 1952. Escaping...
</Question>
<Choice>Ceausescu, Nicolae</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British statesman and winner of the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1937. He was one of the principal draftsmen of the League of Nations Covenant in 1919 and one of the most loyal workers for the League until its supersession by the United Nations in 1945.Cecil was the third son of the 3rd marquess of Salisbury, who was three times British prime minister. During World War I, Cecil was successively undersecretary of state for foreign affairs, minister of blockade, and assistant secretary of state for foreign affairs. As early as 1916 he began to draw up an international peacekeeping agreement, and in...
</Question>
<Choice>Cecil, Robert Gascoyne-Cecil, 1st Viscount</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British foreign secretary from 1924 to 1929, who helped bring about the Locarno Pact (1925), a group of treaties intended to secure peace in western Europe by eliminating the possibility of border disputes involving Germany. The pact gained for Chamberlain a share (with Vice President Charles G. Dawes of the United States) of the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1925.The eldest son of the statesman Joseph Chamberlain, Austen was half-brother to the future prime minister Neville Chamberlain. Entering the House of Commons in 1892, he rose to be postmaster general (1902) and chancellor of the Exchequer (...
</Question>
<Choice>Chamberlain, Sir Austen</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the Franks (768–814), king of the Lombards (774–814), and emperor (800–814).
</Question>
<Choice>Charlemagne</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
minister of the Song dynasty (960–1279) who led a peace party that opposed continued prosecution of a war to regain former Chinese territory in the North. He is remembered as a traitor, however, in Chinese history.After Juchen tribes had occupied the North and captured the Song emperor in 1127, a Song prince, later known as the Gaozong emperor (reigned 1127–62), reestablished the dynasty in the South—often referred to as the Nan (Southern) Song (1127–1279). Later, when the patriotic general Yue Fei attempted to reconquer the occupied northern territory, Qin Hui argued that such a campaign woul...
</Question>
<Choice>Ch'in Kuei</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British statesman, orator, and author who as prime minister (1940–45, 1951–55) rallied the British people during World War II and led his country from the brink of defeat to victory.After a sensational rise to prominence in national politics before World War I, Churchill acquired a reputation for erratic judgment in the war itself and in the decade that followed. Politically suspect in consequence, he was a lonely figure until his response to Adolf Hitler's challenge brought him to leadership of a national coalition in 1940. With Franklin D. Roosevelt and Joseph Stalin he then shaped Allied st...
</Question>
<Choice>Churchill, Sir Winston</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician who in the last years of the Roman Republic formed the so-called First Triumvirate with Julius Caesar and Pompey to challenge effectively the power of the Senate. His death led to the outbreak of the Civil War between Caesar and Pompey (49–45).Crassus fled from Rome when Gaius Marius captured the city in 87. As a young officer, he supported Lucius Cornelius Sulla during the civil war (83–82) between Sulla and the followers of Marius, returning to Rome to help Sulla seize power in 82. The hostility between Pompey and Crassus probably originated in Sulla's clear preference for Pompey....
</Question>
<Choice>Crassus, Marcus Licinius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sioux Indian chief of the Oglala tribe who was an able tactician and determined warrior in the Sioux resistance to the white man's invasion of the northern Great Plains.As early as 1865 Crazy Horse was a leader in his people's defiance of U.S. plans to construct a road to the goldfields in Montana. He participated in the massacre of Captain William J. Fetterman and his troop of 80 men (Dec. 21, 1866) as well as in the Wagon Box fight (Aug. 2, 1867), both near Fort Phil Kearny, in Wyoming Territory. Refusing to honour the reservation provisions of the Second Treaty of Fort Laramie (1868), Crazy...
</Question>
<Choice>Crazy Horse</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English soldier and statesman who led parliamentary forces in the English Civil Wars; he was lord protector of England, Scotland, and Ireland from 1653 to 1658 during the republican Commonwealth.As one of the generals on the parliamentary side in the English Civil War against King Charles I, Cromwell helped to bring about the overthrow of the Stuart monarchy, and, as lord protector, he raised his country's status once more to that of a leading European power from the decline it had gone through since the death of Queen Elizabeth I. A man of outstanding gifts and a forceful character, he was on...
</Question>
<Choice>Cromwell, Oliver</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
head of the dominant Dge-lugs-pa (Yellow Hat) order of Tibetan Buddhists and, until 1959, both spiritual and temporal ruler of Tibet.The first of the line was Dge-'dun-grub-pa (1391–1475), founder and abbot of Tashilhunpo monastery (central Tibet). In accordance with the belief in reincarnate lamas, which began to develop in the 14th century, his successors were conceived as his rebirths and came to be regarded as physical manifestations of the compassionate bodhisattva (“buddha-to-be”), Avalokiteshvara.The second head of the Dge-lugs-pa order, Dge-'dun-rgya-mtsho (1475–1542), became the head...
</Question>
<Choice>Dalai Lama</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician and leader of the Swaraj (Independence) Party in Bengal under British rule.After failing the competitive entrance examination for the British-dominated Indian Civil Service, Das entered the legal profession. He defended many accused of political offenses and took an active part in nationalistic journalism.Bitterly opposing British rule in India and rejecting all ideas of political or economic development of India along Western lines, he idealized the life of the ancient Indian village and saw a golden age in ancient Indian history. He supported the noncooperation movement launched a...
</Question>
<Choice>Das, Chitta Ranjan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
second of the Israelite kings (after Saul), reigning c. 1000 to c. 962 BC, who established a united kingdom over all Israel, with Jerusalem as its capital. In Jewish tradition he became the ideal king, the founder of an enduring dynasty, around whose figure and reign clustered messianic expectations of the people of Israel. Since he was a symbol of fulfillment in the future, the New Testament writers emphasized that Jesus was of the lineage of David. He was also held in high esteem in the Isl?mic tradition.
</Question>
<Choice>David</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
30th vice president of the United States (1925–29) in the Republican administration of President Calvin Coolidge. An ambassador and author of the “Dawes Plan” for managing Germany's reparations payments after World War I, he was awarded the Nobel Prize for Peace jointly with Sir Austen Chamberlain in 1925.Dawes was the son of General Rufus R. Dawes, a Union officer during the American Civil War and later a member of Congress, and Mary Beman Gates. Educated at Marietta College in Ohio and Cincinnati Law School, Dawes practiced law in Lincoln, Nebraska (1887–94), and then moved to Evanston, Illi...
</Question>
<Choice>Dawes, Charles G.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
soldier and statesman who led Israel to dramatic victories over its Arab neighbours and became a symbol of security to his countrymen.Dayan was born on Israel's first kibbutz and was raised on the country's first successful cooperative farm settlement (moshav), Nahalal. He began his military career in 1937, when he learned guerrilla warfare from the British officer Captain Orde Wingate in the special night squadrons. These were organized to fight Arab rebel bands in Palestine, and they formed the nucleus of a Jewish army. Convinced that the Jews would have to fight for their independence, Daya...
</Question>
<Choice>Dayan, Moshe</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician who as president of South Africa (1989–94) brought the apartheid system of racial segregation to an end and negotiated a transition to majority rule in his country. He and Nelson Mandela jointly received the 1993 Nobel Prize for Peace for their collaboration in efforts to establish nonracial democracy in South Africa.De Klerk was the son of a leading politician. He received a law degree (with honours) from Potchefstroom University in 1958. Soon afterward he began to establish a successful law firm in Vereeniging, becoming active in civic and business affairs there. In 1972 he was el...
</Question>
<Choice>de Klerk, F.W.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Irish politician and patriot, prime minister (1932–48, 1951–54, 1957–59), and president (1959–73) of Ireland. An active revolutionary from 1913, he became president of Sinn Féin in 1918 and founded the Fianna Fáil party in 1926. In 1937 he took the Irish Free State out of the British Commonwealth and made his country a “sovereign” state, renamed Ireland, or Éire. His academic attainments also inspired wide respect; he became chancellor of the National University of Ireland in 1921.
</Question>
<Choice>de Valera, Eamon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
tyrant of Syracuse from 405 who, by his conquests in Sicily and southern Italy, made Syracuse the most powerful Greek city west of mainland Greece. Although he saved Greek Sicily from conquest by Carthage, his brutal military despotism harmed the cause of Hellenism.After working as a clerk in a public office, Dionysius distinguished himself fighting in the war with Carthage that broke out in Sicily in 409. He took advantage of a crisis in the war to make himself tyrant in 405. Over the next eight years he ruthlessly consolidated and expanded his power. He built a wall around Syracuse and forti...
</Question>
<Choice>Dionysius The Elder</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
president of Haiti whose 14-year regime was of unprecedented duration in that country.Duvalier graduated in 1934 from the University of Haiti School of Medicine, where he served as a hospital staff physician until 1943, when he became prominently active in the U.S.-sponsored anti-yaws campaign.A contributor to the daily Action Nationale (1934), Duvalier was markedly influenced by the mystic scholar Lorimer Denis and became a member of Le Groupe des Griots, a circle of writers who embraced black nationalism and voodoo as the key sources of Haitian culture.A supporter of President Dumarsais Esti...
</Question>
<Choice>Duvalier, François</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German high official who was hanged by the state of Israel for his part in the Holocaust, the Nazi extermination of Jews during World War II.During World War I, Eichmann's family moved from Germany to Linz, Austria. His pre-Nazi life was rather ordinary. He worked as a traveling salesman in Oberösterreich (Upper Austria) for an oil company but lost his job during the Great Depression.Eichmann joined the Nazi Party in April 1932 in Linz and rose through the party hierarchy. In November 1932 he became a member of Heinrich Himmler's SS, the Nazi paramilitary corps, and, on leaving Linz in 1933, h...
</Question>
<Choice>Eichmann, Adolf</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
34th president of the United States (1953–61), who had been supreme commander of the Allied forces in western Europe during World War II. (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America.)
</Question>
<Choice>Eisenhower, Dwight D.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
general and leader of the Nationalist forces that overthrew the Spanish democratic republic in the Spanish Civil War (1936–39); thereafter he was the head of the government of Spain until 1973 and head of state until his death in 1975.
</Question>
<Choice>Franco, Francisco</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German politician and lawyer who served as governor-general of Poland during World War II.Frank fought in World War I, studied economics and jurisprudence, and in 1921 joined the German Workers' Party (which became the Nazi Party). He eventually became the party's chief legal counsel and Hitler's personal lawyer. After the Nazis came to power in Germany in 1933, Frank was appointed to a variety of important posts, including president of the Reichstag and minister of justice in the Nazi government.After the German invasion of Poland in 1939, Frank was appointed governor-general, becoming the su...
</Question>
<Choice>Frank, Hans</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American printer and publisher, author, inventor and scientist, and diplomat. One of the foremost of the Founding Fathers, Franklin helped draft the Declaration of Independence and was one of its signers, represented the United States in France during the American Revolution, and was a delegate to the Constitutional Convention. He made important contributions to science, especially in the understanding of electricity, and is remembered for the wit, wisdom, and elegance of his writing.
</Question>
<Choice>Franklin, Benjamin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician who served as prime minister of India for three consecutive terms (1966–77) and a fourth term (1980–84). She was assassinated by Sikh extremists.She was the only child of Jawaharlal Nehru, the first prime minister of independent India. She attended Visva-Bharati University, West Bengal, and the University of Oxford, and in 1942 she married Feroze Gandhi (died 1960), a fellow member of the Indian National Congress (Congress Party). She was a member of the working committee of the ruling Congress Party from 1955, and in 1959 she was elected to the largely honorary post of party presid...
</Question>
<Choice>Gandhi, Indira</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
leader of the Indian nationalist movement against British rule, considered to be the father of his country. He is internationally esteemed for his doctrine of nonviolent protest to achieve political and social progress.Gandhi was the youngest child of his father's fourth wife. His father, Karamchand Gandhi, who was the dewan (chief minister) of Porbandar, the capital of a small principality in Gujarat in western India under British suzerainty, did not have much in the way of a formal education. He was, however, an able administrator who knew how to steer his way between the capricious princes,...
</Question>
<Choice>Gandhi, Mohandas Karamchand</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mexican diplomat and advocate of nuclear disarmament, corecipient with Alva Myrdal of Sweden of the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1982.After receiving his law degree in Mexico and completing graduate study at the University of Paris and at the International Law Academy in The Hague, García Robles entered Mexico's foreign service in 1939 and was a delegate to the 1945 San Francisco Conference, at which the United Nations (UN) was founded. He subsequently worked in the UN Secretariat for several years. As director general in the Mexican Ministry of Foreign Affairs during the late 1950s, García Robles...
</Question>
<Choice>García Robles, Alfonso</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French soldier, writer, statesman, and architect of France's Fifth Republic.
</Question>
<Choice>Gaulle, Charles de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Mongolian warrior-ruler, one of the most famous conquerors of history, who consolidated tribes into a unified Mongolia and then extended his empire across Asia to the Adriatic Sea.Genghis Khan was a warrior and ruler of genius who, starting from obscure and insignificant beginnings, brought all the nomadic tribes of Mongolia under the rule of himself and his family in a rigidly disciplined military state. He then turned his attention toward the settled peoples beyond the borders of his nomadic realm and began the series of campaigns of plunder and conquest that eventually carried the Mongol ar...
</Question>
<Choice>Genghis Khan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Bedonkohe Apache leader of the Chiricahua Apache, who led his people's defense of their homeland against the military might of the United States.For generations the Apaches had resisted white colonization of their homeland in the Southwest by both Spaniards and North Americans. Geronimo continued the tradition of his ancestors from the day he was admitted to the warriors' council in 1846, participating in raids into Sonora and Chihuahua in Mexico. He was further embittered by the death of his mother, wife, and children at the hands of Mexicans in 1858. He then rose to the leadership of a band...
</Question>
<Choice>Geronimo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Soviet official, the general secretary of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union (CPSU) from 1985 to 1991 and president of the Soviet Union in 1990–91. His efforts to democratize his country's political system and decentralize its economy led to the downfall of communism and the breakup of the Soviet Union in 1991. In part because he ended the Soviet Union's postwar domination of eastern Europe, Gorbachev was awarded the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1990.Gorbachev was the son of Russian peasants in Stavropol territory (kray) in southwestern Russia. He joined the Komsomol (Young Communist League)...
</Question>
<Choice>Gorbachev, Mikhail</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
a leader of the Nazi Party and one of the primary architects of the Nazi police state in Germany. He was condemned to hang as a war criminal by the International Military Tribunal at Nürnberg in 1946 but took poison instead and died the night his execution was ordered.Göring was born in Bavaria, the second son by the second wife of Heinrich Ernst Göring, at the time German consul general in Haiti. The family was reunited in Germany on the father's retirement in 1896. Göring was brought up near Nürnberg, in the small castle of Veldenstein, whose owner was Hermann, Ritter (knight) von Epenstein,...
</Question>
<Choice>Göring, Hermann</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
national French hero, an outstanding military leader during the early part of the Hundred Years' War (1337–1453). After attaining the highest military position as constable of France in 1370, he brilliantly used the strategy of avoiding set battles with the English until the French had sufficient advantage to defeat them soundly.After fighting a duel with Sir Thomas Canterbury at the successful defense of the city of Rennes against an English siege in 1356–57, du Guesclin was awarded a pension by the Dauphin (the future king Charles V) in December 1357. Appointed captain of Pontorson, he remai...
</Question>
<Choice>Guesclin, Bertrand du</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
theoretician and tactician of guerrilla warfare, prominent communist figure in the Cuban Revolution (1956–59), and later guerrilla leader in South America. After his execution by the Bolivian army, he was regarded as a martyred hero by generations of leftists worldwide, and his image became an icon of leftist radicalism and anti-imperialism.Guevara was the eldest of five children in a middle-class family of Spanish-Irish descent and leftist leanings. Although suffering from asthma, he excelled as an athlete and a scholar, completing his medical studies in 1953. He spent many of his holidays tr...
</Question>
<Choice>Guevara, Che</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
emperor of Ethiopia from 1930 to 1974 who sought to modernize his country and who steered it into the mainstream of post-World War II African politics. He brought Ethiopia into the League of Nations and the United Nations and made Addis Ababa the major centre for the Organization of African Unity (now African Union).Tafari was a great-grandson of Sahle Selassie of Shewa (Shoa) and a son of Ras (Prince) Makonnen, a chief adviser to Emperor Menilek II. Educated at home by French missionaries, Tafari at an early age favourably impressed the emperor with his intellectual abilities and was promoted...
</Question>
<Choice>Haile Selassie I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American Revolutionary officer who attempted to spy on the British and was hanged.A graduate of Yale University (1773) and a schoolteacher, Hale joined a Connecticut regiment in 1775, served in the siege of Boston, and was commissioned a captain (1776). He went to New York with William Heath's brigade and is said to have participated in the capture of a provision sloop from under the guns of a British man-of-war. Hale was captured by the British while attempting to return to his regiment, having penetrated the British lines on Long Island to obtain information. He was hanged without trial the...
</Question>
<Choice>Hale, Nathan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish economist and statesman who served as second secretary-general of the United Nations (1953–61) and enhanced the prestige and effectiveness of the UN. He was posthumously awarded the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1961.The son of Hjalmar Hammarskjöld, prime minister of Sweden (1914–17) and chairman of the Nobel Prize Foundation (1929–47), Dag Hammarskjöld studied law and economics at the universities of Uppsala and Stockholm and taught political economy at Stockholm (1933–36). He then joined the Swedish civil service as permanent undersecretary in the Ministry of Finance and subsequently beca...
</Question>
<Choice>Hammarskjöld, Dag</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Czech playwright, poet, and political dissident, who, after the fall of communism, was president of Czechoslovakia (1989–92) and of the Czech Republic (1993–2003).Havel was the son of a wealthy restaurateur whose property was confiscated by the communist government of Czechoslovakia in 1948. As the son of bourgeois parents, Havel was denied easy access to education but managed to finish high school and study on the university level. He found work as a stagehand in a Prague theatrical company in 1959 and soon began writing plays with Ivan Vysko?il. By 1968 Havel had progressed to the position o...
</Question>
<Choice>Havel, Václav</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
one of the chief organizers of the British Labour Party. He was Britain's secretary of state for foreign affairs from June 1929 to August 1931 and won the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1934.An iron molder at Robert Stephenson's locomotive works and foundry in Newcastle upon Tyne, Northumberland, Henderson became secretary of the Newcastle local of the Ironfounders' Union, served as a Liberal Party member of the municipal councils of Newcastle, Darlington, and Durham, and in 1903 was elected mayor of Darlington. Later that year he was sent to the House of Commons as a Labour Party member from Barnar...
</Question>
<Choice>Henderson, Arthur</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of England (1509–47) who presided over the beginnings of the English Renaissance and the English Reformation. His six wives were, successively, Catherine of Aragon (the mother of the future queen Mary I), Anne Boleyn (the mother of the future queen Elizabeth I), Jane Seymour (the mother of Henry's successor, Edward VI), Anne of Cleves, Catherine Howard, and Catherine Parr.
</Question>
<Choice>Henry VIII</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nazi German official who was Heinrich Himmler's chief lieutenant in the Schutzstaffel (“Protective Echelon”), the paramilitary corps commonly known as the SS. He played a key role in organizing the Holocaust during the opening years of World War II.Heydrich's father, who directed a musical conservatory and sang Wagnerian roles in the opera, exposed his son to the cult of Richard Wagner, and his mother was a stern disciplinarian; the family was falsely suspected of partial Jewish ancestry. Heydrich joined a Freikorps paramilitary unit in 1919 and entered the German navy in 1922. Commissioned as...
</Question>
<Choice>Heydrich, Reinhard</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German National Socialist (Nazi) politician, police administrator, and military commander who became the second most powerful man in the Third Reich.The son of a Roman Catholic secondary-school master, Himmler studied agriculture after World War I and joined rightist paramilitary organizations. As a member of one of these, Ernst Röhm's Reichskriegsflagge (“Imperial War Flag”), he participated in November 1923 in Adolf Hitler's abortive Beer Hall Putsch in Munich. Himmler joined the Nazi Party in 1925, rose steadily in the party hierarchy, and was elected a deputy to the Reichstag (the German p...
</Question>
<Choice>Himmler, Heinrich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
leader of the National Socialist (Nazi) Party (from 1920/21) and chancellor (Kanzler) and Führer of Germany (1933–45). He was chancellor from January 30, 1933, and, after President Paul von Hindenburg's death, assumed the twin titles of Führer and chancellor (August 2, 1934).Hitler's father, Alois (born 1837), was illegitimate. For a time he bore his mother's name, Schicklgruber, but by 1876 he had established his family claim to the surname Hitler. Adolf never used any other surname.
</Question>
<Choice>Hitler, Adolf</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
founder of the Indochina Communist Party (1930) and its successor, the Viet-Minh (1941), and president from 1945 to 1969 of the Democratic Republic of Vietnam (North Vietnam). As the leader of the Vietnamese nationalist movement for nearly three decades, Ho was one of the prime movers of the post-World War II anticolonial movement in Asia and one of the most influential communist leaders of the 20th century.
</Question>
<Choice>Ho Chi Minh</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German soldier and Nazi partisan who served as commandant of the Auschwitz extermination camp (1940–45), during a period when as many as 1,000,000 to 2,500,000 inmates perished there.After serving in World War I, Hoess joined conservative cliques, was arrested and imprisoned (1923–28), and then joined the Nazi Party, becoming a member of the SS. In 1934 he began serving on the staff at Dachau concentration camp and in 1940 was given command of Auschwitz, where he devised increasingly efficient methods of mass gassing and cremation. In 1945 he was made a deputy inspector of all concentration ca...
</Question>
<Choice>Hoess, Rudolf Franz</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. lawyer and politician, a leader of the struggle by U.S. emigrants in Mexican territory to win control of Texas (1834–36) and make it part of the United States.In his youth Houston moved with his family to a farm in rural Tennessee after the death of his father in 1807. He ran away in his mid-teens and lived for nearly three years with the Cherokee Indians in eastern Tennessee, where he took the name Black Raven and learned the native language, skills, and customs. Houston thus developed a rapport with the Indians that was unique for his day. As a consequence, after service in the War of 1...
</Question>
<Choice>Houston, Sam</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
dictatorial president of Mexico (Feb. 18, 1913–July 15, 1914), whose regime united disparate revolutionary forces in common opposition to him.Born of Indian parents, Huerta trained at the Chapultepec Military College and eventually rose to the rank of general in the army during the rule of the dictator Porfirio Díaz. Though an admirer of Díaz, Huerta served his successor, the liberal President Francisco Madero, as chief of staff of the army. When part of the army in Mexico City rebelled against Madero in February 1913, Huerta joined forces with the rebels, compelled Madero to resign, and assum...
</Question>
<Choice>Huerta, Victoriano</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. secretary of state (1933–44) whose initiation of the reciprocal trade program to lower tariffs set in motion the mechanism for expanded world trade in the second half of the 20th century. In 1945 he received the Nobel Prize for Peace for his part in organizing the United Nations.As a young Tennessee attorney, Hull early identified with the Democratic Party. He served in the U.S. House of Representatives for 22 years (1907–21, 1923–31) and in the Senate (1931–33). Appointed secretary of state by President Franklin D. Roosevelt at the beginning of the New Deal, he called for a reversal of h...
</Question>
<Choice>Hull, Cordell</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
leader of the Social Democratic and Labour Party (SDLP) in Northern Ireland from 1979 to 2001. He served in the British Parliament from 1983 and the European Parliament from 1979; he was a member of the Northern Ireland Assembly from 1998 to 2000. In 1998 he and David Trimble, leader of the Ulster Unionist Party, were awarded the Nobel Prize for Peace.Originally a schoolteacher, Hume, a Roman Catholic, became a moderate leader in the Northern Ireland civil rights movement in the 1960s and won a seat in the Northern Ireland parliament in 1969. A founding member of the SDLP, he was elected its l...
</Question>
<Choice>Hume, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
reign name (nianhao) of the Chinese emperor (reigned 1368–98) who founded the Ming dynasty that ruled China for nearly 300 years. During his reign, the Hongwu emperor instituted military, administrative, and educational reforms that centred power in the emperor.
</Question>
<Choice>Hung-wu</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
grand prince of Moscow (1533–84) and the first to be proclaimed tsar of Russia (from 1547). His reign saw the completion of the construction of a centrally administered Russian state and the creation of an empire that included non-Slav states. Ivan engaged in prolonged and largely unsuccessful wars against Sweden and Poland, and, in seeking to impose military discipline and a centralized administration, he instituted a reign of terror against the hereditary nobility.
</Question>
<Choice>Ivan IV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
draftsman of the Declaration of Independence of the United States and the nation's first secretary of state (1789–94), second vice president (1797–1801), and, as the third president (1801–09), the statesman responsible for the Louisiana Purchase. An early advocate of total separation of church and state, he also was the founder and architect of the University of Virginia and the most eloquent American proponent of individual freedom as the core meaning of the American Revolution. (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America.)Long...
</Question>
<Choice>Jefferson, Thomas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian Muslim politician, founder and first governor-general (1947–48) of Pakistan.
</Question>
<Choice>Jinnah, Mohammed Ali</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
national heroine of France, a peasant girl who, believing that she was acting under divine guidance, led the French army in a momentous victory at Orléans that repulsed an English attempt to conquer France during the Hundred Years' War. Captured a year afterward, Joan was burned by the English and their French collaborators as a heretic. She became the greatest national heroine of her compatriots. Her achievement was a decisive factor in the later awakening of French national consciousness.Joan was the daughter of a tenant farmer at Domrémy, on the borders of the duchies of Bar and Lorraine. I...
</Question>
<Choice>Joan of Arc, Saint</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American naval hero in the American Revolution, renowned for his victory over British ships of war off the east coast of England (September 23, 1779).Apprenticed at age 12 to John Younger, a Scottish merchant shipper, John Paul sailed as a cabin boy on a ship to Virginia, where he visited his older brother William at Fredericksburg. When Younger's business failed in 1766, Paul found work as chief mate of a Jamaica-owned slaver brigantine. After two years he quit the slave trade and shipped passage for Scotland. When both master and chief mate died of fever en route, he brought the ship safely...
</Question>
<Choice>Jones, John Paul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nez Percé chief who, faced with settlement by whites of tribal lands in Oregon, led his followers in a dramatic effort to escape to Canada.The Nez Percé tribe was one of the most powerful in the Pacific Northwest and in the first half of the 19th century one of the most friendly to whites. Many Nez Percé, including Chief Joseph's father, were converted to Christianity and Chief Joseph was educated in a mission school. The advance of white settlers into the Pacific Northwest after 1850 caused the United States to press the Indians of the region to surrender their lands and accept resettlement o...
</Question>
<Choice>Joseph, Chief</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hawaiian sovereign known for his firm opposition to the annexation of his kingdom by the United States. As Kamehameha IV, he strove to curb the political power of the American Protestant missionaries in the Hawaiian Islands. Dedicated to protecting his people, who were rapidly dying out because of disease, he sponsored many social and economic reforms. He established Hawaii's commercial and political relations with other nations on a solid base and tried to balance each country's influence on island life.The son of Kekuanaoa, governor of Oahu, and Kinau, a woman chief who had been kuhina nui (...
</Question>
<Choice>Kamehameha IV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician who led Zambia to independence in 1964 and served as that country's president until 1991.
</Question>
<Choice>Kaunda, Kenneth</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. secretary of state (1925–29) whose most important achievement was the Kellogg-Briand Pact of 1928, a multilateral agreement designed to prohibit war as an instrument of national policy. He was awarded the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1929.Kellogg studied law and was admitted to the bar in 1877. He achieved prominence as a lawyer representing the U.S. government in antitrust cases and served in the U.S. Senate (1917–23) and as U.S. ambassador to Great Britain (1923–25).As secretary of state under President Calvin Coolidge (1925–29), Kellogg generally followed an isolationist policy regarding E...
</Question>
<Choice>Kellogg, Frank B.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
35th president of the United States (1961–63), who faced a number of foreign crises, especially in Cuba and Berlin, but managed to secure such achievements as the Nuclear Test-Ban Treaty and the Alliance for Progress. He was assassinated while riding in a motorcade in Dallas. (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America.)
</Question>
<Choice>Kennedy, John F.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
U.S. attorney general and adviser during the administration of his brother Pres. John F. Kennedy (1961–63). Later U.S. senator (1965–68), he was assassinated while campaigning for the presidential nomination.Robert interrupted his studies at Harvard University to serve in the U.S. Navy during World War II but returned to the university and was graduated in 1948. After receiving his law degree from the University of Virginia Law School in 1951, he began his political career in Massachusetts the next year with the management of his brother John's successful campaign for the U.S. Senate. Robert K...
</Question>
<Choice>Kennedy, Robert F.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
African statesman and nationalist, the first prime minister (1963–64) and then the first president (1964–78) of independent Kenya.
</Question>
<Choice>Kenyatta, Jomo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Iranian Sh??ite cleric who led the revolution that overthrew Mohammad Reza Shah Pahlavi in 1979 (seeIranian Revolution) and who was Iran's ultimate political and religious authority for the next 10 years.Khomeini was the grandson and son of mullahs (Sh??ite religious leaders). When he was about five months old, his father was killed on the orders of a local landlord. The young Khomeini was raised by his mother and aunt and then, after their deaths, by his older brother, Mortaza (later known as Ayatollah Pasandideh). He was educated in various Islamic schools, and he settled in the city of Qom...
</Question>
<Choice>Khomeini, Ruhollah</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
South Korean politician, who became a prominent opposition leader during the tenure of President Park Chung Hee. He became the first opposition leader to win election to his country's presidency (1998–2003). Kim received the Nobel Prize for Peace in 2000 for his efforts to restore democracy in South Korea and to improve relations with North Korea.Kim was the son of a middle-class farmer, and he graduated from the Mokp'o Commercial High School at the top of his class in 1943. He began working as a clerk in a Japanese-owned shipping company and in 1945 took over the company, eventually becoming...
</Question>
<Choice>Kim Dae Jung</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
communist leader of North Korea from 1948 until his death in 1994. He was the nation's premier from 1948 to 1972, chairman of its dominant Korean Workers (Communist) Party from 1949, and president and head of state from 1972.Kim was the son of parents who fled to Manchuria in 1925 to escape the Japanese rule of Korea. He joined the Korean guerrilla resistance against the Japanese occupation in the 1930s and adopted the name of an earlier legendary Korean guerrilla fighter against the Japanese. Kim was noticed by the Soviet military authorities, who sent him to the Soviet Union for military and...
</Question>
<Choice>Kim Il-sung</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Korean military officer and head of the Korean Central Intelligence Agency (KCIA; now the National Intelligence Service) who, on Oct. 26, 1979, assassinated the South Korean president, Park Chung Hee.Kim was the lifelong friend and confidant of Park. They were born in the same hometown and were in the same class at the Korean Military Academy. Kim rose to the rank of lieutenant general after having been chief of army security command and the deputy director of the KCIA. After the top KCIA officer in Washington, D.C., defected during an investigation of South Korean influence in the U.S. Congre...
</Question>
<Choice>Kim Jae Kyu</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
North Korean politician, son of the former North Korean premier and (communist) Korean Workers' Party (KWP) chairman Kim Il-sung, and successor to his father as ruler of North Korea.The official North Korean version of Kim Jong Il's life, different from the biography documented elsewhere, says that he was born at a guerrilla base camp on Mount Paektu, the highest point on the Korean peninsula; it attributes many precocious abilities to him; and it claims his birth was accompanied by such auspicious signs as the appearance of a double rainbow in the sky. During the Korean War (1950–53) he was p...
</Question>
<Choice>Kim Jong Il</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American political scientist, who, as adviser for national security affairs and secretary of state, was a major influence in the shaping of foreign policy from 1969 to 1976 under Presidents Richard M. Nixon and Gerald R. Ford. In 1973 he was jointly awarded the Nobel Prize for Peace with Le Duc Tho of North Vietnam for their efforts to negotiate a peaceful settlement of the Vietnam War.Kissinger's family immigrated to the United States in 1938 to escape the Nazi persecution of Jews. He became a naturalized citizen in 1943. He served in the U.S. Army during World War II and in the postwar U.S....
</Question>
<Choice>Kissinger, Henry A.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
farmer, soldier, and statesman, noted in South African history as the builder of the Afrikaner nation. He was president of the Transvaal, or South African Republic, from 1883 until his flight to Europe in 1900, after the outbreak of the South African (Boer) War.
</Question>
<Choice>Kruger, Paul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British archaeological scholar, military strategist, and author best known for his legendary war activities in the Middle East during World War I and for his account of those activities in The Seven Pillars of Wisdom (1926).
</Question>
<Choice>Lawrence, T E</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Vietnamese politician and corecipient in 1973 (with Henry Kissinger) of the Nobel Prize for Peace, which he declined.Le Duc Tho was one of the founders of the Indochinese Communist Party in 1930. For his political activities he was imprisoned by the French in 1930–36 and 1939–44. After his second release he returned to Hanoi in 1945 and helped lead the Viet Minh, the Vietnamese independence organization, as well as a revived communist party called the Vietnam Workers' Party. He was the senior Viet Minh official in southern Vietnam until the Geneva Accords of 1954. From 1955 he was a member of...
</Question>
<Choice>Le Duc Tho</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Confederate general, commander of the Army of Northern Virginia, the most successful of the Southern armies during the American Civil War (1861–65). In February 1865 he was given command of all the Southern armies. His surrender at Appomattox Courthouse April 9, 1865, is commonly viewed as signifying the end of the Civil War.
</Question>
<Choice>Lee, Robert E.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
founder of the Russian Communist Party (Bolsheviks), inspirer and leader of the Bolshevik Revolution (1917), and the architect, builder, and first head (1917–24) of the Soviet state. He was the founder of the organization known as Comintern (Communist International) and the posthumous source of “Leninism,” the doctrine codified and conjoined with Marx's works by Lenin's successors to form Marxism-Leninism, which became the Communist worldview.If the Bolshevik Revolution is—as some people have called it—the most significant political event of the 20th century, then Lenin must for good or ill be...
</Question>
<Choice>Lenin, Vladimir Ilich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
16th president of the United States (1861–65), who preserved the Union during the American Civil War and brought about the emancipation of the slaves. (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America.)(In February 2009, on the 200th anniversary of Abraham Lincoln's birth, Britannica asked two prominent contributors to answer some Lincoln-related questions on the Britannica Blog. Noted historian James McPherson, author Tried by War and of Britannica's article “Translating Thought in Action: Grant's Personal Memoirs,” addresses Lincoln'...
</Question>
<Choice>Lincoln, Abraham</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Zulu chief, teacher and religious leader, and president of the African National Congress (1952–60) in South Africa. He was the first African to be awarded a Nobel Prize for Peace (1960), in recognition of his nonviolent struggle against racial discrimination.Albert John Mvumbi (Zulu: “Continuous Rain”) Luthuli was born in Rhodesia, where his father, John Bunyan Luthuli, a missionary interpreter, had gone from Zululand. After his father's death, the 10-year-old Albert returned to South Africa and learned Zulu traditions and duties in the household of his uncle, the chief of Groutville, a commun...
</Question>
<Choice>Luthuli, Albert John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Irish statesman who was awarded the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1974 for his efforts on behalf of human rights.MacBride was the son of the Irish actress and patriot Maud Gonne and her husband, Major John MacBride, who was executed in 1916 for his part in the Easter Rising of that year against the British. Educated in Paris and Ireland, Seán MacBride, like his parents, was a fighter for Irish liberty and an opponent of the partition, and at age 24 he was chief of staff of the Irish Republican Army. He worked as a journalist and then became a lawyer.Eventually accepting the fact of partition and th...
</Question>
<Choice>MacBride, Seán</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Jewish guerrilla leader who defended his country from invasion by the Seleucid king Antiochus IV Epiphanes, preventing the imposition of Hellenism upon Judaea, and preserving the Jewish religion.The son of Mattathias, an aged priest who took to the mountains in rebellion when Antiochus attempted to impose the Greek religion on the Jews, Judas took over the rebel leadership on his father's death and proved to be a military genius, overthrowing four Seleucid armies in quick succession and restoring the Temple of Jerusalem. This deed is celebrated in the Jewish festival of lights, ?anukka. On Ant...
</Question>
<Choice>Maccabeus, Judas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
black nationalist and first black president of South Africa (1994–99). His negotiations in the early 1990s with South African Pres. F.W. de Klerk helped end the country's apartheid system of racial segregation and ushered in a peaceful transition to majority rule. Mandela and de Klerk were jointly awarded the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1993 for their efforts.
</Question>
<Choice>Mandela, Nelson</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
principal Chinese Marxist theorist, soldier, and statesman who led his nation's communist revolution. Leader of the Chinese Communist Party from 1935, he was chairman (chief of state) of the People's Republic of China from 1949 to 1959 and chairman of the party until his death.When China emerged from a half century of revolution as the world's most populous nation and launched itself on a path of economic development and social change, Mao Zedong occupied a critical place in the story of the country's resurgence. To be sure, he did not play a dominant role throughout the whole struggle. In the...
</Question>
<Choice>Mao Zedong</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
a founder and fourth prime minister (1969–74) of the State of Israel.In 1906 Goldie Mabovitch's family emigrated to Milwaukee, Wis., where she attended the Milwaukee Normal School (now University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee) and later became a leader in the Milwaukee Labor Zionist Party. In 1921 she and her husband, Morris Myerson, emigrated to Palestine and joined the Mer?avya kibbutz. She became the kibbutz's representative to the Histadrut (General Federation of Labour), the secretary of that organization's Women's Labour Council (1928–32), and a member of its executive committee (1934 until Wor...
</Question>
<Choice>Meir, Golda</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician and administrator, who, as Serbia's party leader and president (1989–97), pursued Serbian nationalist policies that contributed to the breakup of the socialist Yugoslav federation. He subsequently embroiled Serbia in a series of conflicts with the successor Balkan states. From 1997 to 2000 he served as president of the Federal Republic of Yugoslavia.Miloševi? was born in Serbia of Montenegrin parents and joined the Communist Party of Yugoslavia (from 1963 the League of Communists of Yugoslavia [LCY]) when he was 18 years old. He graduated from the University of Belgrade with a law d...
</Question>
<Choice>Miloševic, Slobodan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
president of Zaire (now the Democratic Republic of the Congo), who seized power in a 1965 coup and ruled for some 32 years before being ousted in a rebellion in 1997.Mobutu was educated in missionary schools and began his career in 1949 in the Belgian Congolese army, the Force Publique, rising from a clerk to a sergeant major, the highest rank then open to Africans. While still in the army, Mobutu contributed articles to newspapers in Léopoldville (now Kinshasa). After his discharge in 1956 he became a reporter for the daily L'Avenir (“The Future”) and later editor of the weekly Actualités Afr...
</Question>
<Choice>Mobutu Sese Seko</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British field marshal and one of the outstanding Allied commanders in World War II.Montgomery, the son of an Ulster clergyman, was educated at St. Paul's School, London, and the Royal Military Academy (Sandhurst). Having served with distinction in World War I (in which he was twice wounded), he was recognized as a first-rate trainer of troops, with a forcible insistence on physical fitness, youth, and efficiency in leadership. Early in World War II, he led a division in France, and, after the evacuation of Allied troops from Dunkirk, he commanded the southeastern section of England in anticipa...
</Question>
<Choice>Montgomery, Bernard Law Montgomery, 1st Viscount</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English humanist and statesman, chancellor of England (1529–32), who was beheaded for refusing to accept King Henry VIII as head of the Church of England. He is recognized as a saint by the Roman Catholic Church.
</Question>
<Choice>More, Sir Thomas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Italian prime minister (1922–43) and the first of 20th-century Europe's fascist dictators.
</Question>
<Choice>Mussolini, Benito</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Swedish diplomat, government minister, author, and advocate of nuclear disarmament. She was the corecipient with Alfonso García Robles of Mexico of the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1982.Alva Reimer married the Swedish economist Gunnar Myrdal in 1924. After a career as a teacher, she served as principal director of the United Nations Department of Social Welfare during 1949–50 and became director of the UNESCO Department of Social Sciences in 1951. From 1955 to 1961 she served as ambassador of the Swedish government to India, with related duties in neighbouring Burma (Myanmar) and Ceylon (Sri Lanka...
</Question>
<Choice>Myrdal, Alva Reimer</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian political leader and theorist.Narayan was educated at universities in the United States, where he became a Marxist. Upon his return to India in 1929, he joined the Indian National Congress (Congress Party). In 1932 he was sentenced to a year's imprisonment for his participation in the civil disobedience movement against British rule in India. Upon release he took a leading part in the formation of the Congress Socialist Party, a left-wing group within the Congress Party, the organization that led the campaign for Indian independence. He was imprisoned by the British again in 1939 for hi...
</Question>
<Choice>Narayan, Jaya Prakash</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first prime minister of independent India (1947–64), who established parliamentary government and became noted for his “neutralist” policies in foreign affairs. He was also one of the principal leaders of India's independence movement in the 1930s and '40s.
</Question>
<Choice>Nehru, Jawaharlal</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British naval commander in the wars with Revolutionary and Napoleonic France, who won crucial victories in such battles as those of the Nile (1798) and of Trafalgar (1805), where he was killed by enemy fire on the HMS Victory. In private life he was known for his extended love affair with Emma, Lady Hamilton, while both were married.
</Question>
<Choice>Nelson, Horatio Nelson, Viscount</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the fifth Roman emperor (AD 54–68), stepson and heir of the emperor Claudius. He became infamous for his personal debaucheries and extravagances and, on doubtful evidence, for his burning of Rome and persecutions of Christians.
</Question>
<Choice>Nero</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
political and cultural leader of the Maori community in New Zealand. He was a major force behind the improvement of government policy toward the Maori in the early 20th century.Earning his law degree in 1897, Ngata became the first Maori graduate of a New Zealand university and worked briefly as a lawyer before becoming active in the nationalist Young Maori Party. In 1905 he began his 39-year term of office in Parliament, representing the eastern Maori constituency. He was knighted in 1927, and he served as minister of native affairs from 1928 to 1934.In 1931 Ngata inaugurated his Maori land-d...
</Question>
<Choice>Ngata, Sir Apirana Turupa</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
37th president of the United States (1969–74), who, faced with almost certain impeachment for his role in the Watergate Scandal, became the first American president to resign from office. He was also vice president (1953–61) under Pres. Dwight D. Eisenhower. (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America.)
</Question>
<Choice>Nixon, Richard M.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ghanaian nationalist leader who led the Gold Coast's drive for independence from Britain and presided over its emergence as the new nation of Ghana. He headed the country from independence in 1957 until he was overthrown by a coup in 1966.
</Question>
<Choice>Nkrumah, Kwame</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British statesman and advocate of international disarmament who received the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1959. Fluent in seven languages, he campaigned widely for 40 years for peace through multilateral disarmament.The son of Canadian-born Quakers, Baker added his wife's surname, Noel, to his own about 1926. He studied at Haverford College in Pennsylvania, at King's College, Cambridge, and at the universities of Munich and Paris. A noted athlete, he ran in the 1912 and 1920 Olympic Games, and as captain of the British team at the 1920 Games in Antwerp he won the silver medal in the 1,500 metres....
</Question>
<Choice>Noel-Baker, Philip John Noel-Baker, Baron</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Panamanian military leader, commander of the Panamanian Defense Forces (1983–89), who, for the years of his command, was the actual power behind the civilian president.Noriega was born into a poor family of Colombian extraction. Educated at one of the top high schools in Panama, he was awarded a scholarship to the Chorrillos Military School in Lima. Upon his return to Panama, he was commissioned a sublieutenant in the National Guard and stationed in Colón, where he rose through the ranks and became acquainted with Captain Omar Torrijos. Noriega participated in the military coup that toppled th...
</Question>
<Choice>Noriega, Manuel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
twice king of Cambodia (1941–55 and 1993–2004), who also served as prime minister, head of state, and president. He attempted to steer a neutral course for Cambodia in its civil and foreign wars of the late 20th century.Sihanouk was, on his mother's side, the grandson of King Monivong (reigned 1927–41), whom he succeeded to the throne at age 18. At the time Cambodia was a French protectorate, and Sihanouk wielded little power. However, near the end of World War II, the occupying Japanese encouraged the young king to declare Cambodia's independence from France. When French military forces moved...
</Question>
<Choice>Norodom Sihanouk</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first prime minister of independent Tanganyika (1961), who became the first president of the new state of Tanzania (1964). Nyerere was also the major force behind the Organization of African Unity (OAU; now the African Union).Nyerere was a son of the chief of the small Zanaki ethnic group. He was educated at Tabora Secondary School and Makerere College in Kampala, Uganda. A convert to Roman Catholicism, he taught in several Roman Catholic schools before going to Edinburgh University. He was the first Tanganyikan to study at a British university. He graduated with an M.A. in history and economi...
</Question>
<Choice>Nyerere, Julius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician who was prime minister (1962–70) and twice president (1966–71, 1980–85) of Uganda. He led his country to independence in 1962, but his two terms in office (both of which were ended by military coups) were consumed by struggles between Uganda's northern and southern ethnic groups.Obote was born the third of nine children in a farming family in north-central Uganda. He first attended Busoga College in Mwiri and then Makerere College in Kampala from 1948 to 1949, but he was expelled from the latter for his political activities before he could graduate. The British colonial government p...
</Question>
<Choice>Obote, Milton</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian political leader and diplomat, one of the world's leading women in public life in the 20th century.She was the daughter of Motilal Nehru, a wealthy and aristocratic nationalist leader, and sister of Jawaharlal Nehru, the first prime minister of independent India. In 1921, after receiving a private education in India and abroad, she married Ranjit Sitaram Pandit (d. 1944), a fellow Congress worker. (In accordance with conservative Hindu custom, her name was wholly changed upon her marriage, to reflect her husband's clan.) In her family's tradition she became an active worker in the India...
</Question>
<Choice>Pandit, Vijaya Lakshmi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian barrister and statesman, one of the leaders of the Indian National Congress during the struggle for Indian independence. During the first three years of Indian independence after 1947, he served as deputy prime minister, minister of home affairs, minister of information, and minister of states.
</Question>
<Choice>Patel, Vallabhbhai Jhaverbhai</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician, diplomat, and prime minister of Canada (1963–68), who was prominent as a mediator in international disputes. He was awarded the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1957.Pearson served in World War I (1914–18) and lectured in history at the University of Toronto (1924–28), after studying there and at the University of Oxford. He joined the Canadian foreign service in 1928 and became first secretary in the Department of External Affairs. He served on two royal commissions (1931) and as counselor of the Canadian high commissioner's office in London (1935).Recalled to Canada in 1941, Pearson then...
</Question>
<Choice>Pearson, Lester B.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
tyrant of ancient Athens whose unification of Attica and consolidation and rapid improvement of Athens' prosperity helped to make possible the city's later preeminence in Greece.
</Question>
<Choice>Peisistratus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Polish-born Israeli statesman, who served as prime minister of Israel (1984–86 and 1995–96) and leader of the Israel Labour Party (1977–92, 1995–97, and 2003–05). In 1993, in his role as Israeli foreign minister, Peres helped negotiate a peace accord with Y?sir ?Araf?t, chairman of the Palestine Liberation Organization (PLO), for which they, along with Israeli Prime Minister Yitzhak Rabin, were jointly awarded the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1994.Peres immigrated with his family to Palestine in 1934. In 1947 he joined the Haganah movement, a Zionist military organization, under the direction of D...
</Question>
<Choice>Peres, Shimon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
second wife of Argentine president Juan Perón, who, during her husband's first term as president (1946–52), became a powerful though unofficial political leader, revered by the lower economic classes.Eva Duarte married Col. Juan Perón, a widower, in 1945 after an undistinguished career as a stage and radio actress. She participated in her husband's 1945–46 presidential campaign, winning the adulation of the masses, whom she addressed as los descamisados (Spanish: “the shirtless ones”).Although she never held any government post, Evita acted as de facto minister of health and labour, awarding g...
</Question>
<Choice>Perón, Eva</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
army colonel who became president of Argentina (1946–52, 1952–55, 1973–74) and was founder and leader of the Peronist movement.
</Question>
<Choice>Perón, Juan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
leader of the military junta that overthrew the socialist government of President Salvador Allende of Chile on Sept. 11, 1973, and head of Chile's military government (1974–90).Pinochet, a graduate of the military academy in Santiago (1936), was a career military officer who was appointed army commander in chief by President Allende 18 days before the coup, which he planned and led. Pinochet was named head of the victorious junta's governing council, and he moved to crush Chile's liberal opposition; in its first three years, the regime arrested approximately 130,000, many of whom were tortured...
</Question>
<Choice>Pinochet, Augusto</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Khmer political leader whose totalitarian regime (1975–79) imposed severe hardships on the Cambodian people. His radical communist government forced the mass evacuations of cities, killed or displaced millions of people, and left a legacy of brutality and impoverishment.The son of a landowning farmer, Saloth Sar was sent at age 5 or 6 to live with an older brother in Phnom Penh, where he was educated. A mediocre student, he failed the entrance examinations for high school and so instead studied carpentry for a year at a technical school in Phnom Penh. In 1949 he went to Paris on a scholarship...
</Question>
<Choice>Pol Pot</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French statesman, bank director, and teacher who was premier of the Fifth French Republic from 1962 to 1968 and president from 1969 until his death.The son of a schoolteacher, Pompidou graduated from the École Normale Supérieure and then taught school in Marseilles and Paris. During World War II he fought as a lieutenant and won the Croix de Guerre. In late 1944 he was introduced to Charles de Gaulle, who was then head of the provisional French government. At this time Pompidou was a complete stranger to politics, but he soon proved adept at interpreting and presenting de Gaulle's policies. Po...
</Question>
<Choice>Pompidou, Georges</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Ottawa Indian chief who became a great intertribal leader when he organized a combined resistance—known as Pontiac's War (1763–64)—to British power in the Great Lakes area.Little is known of Pontiac's early life, but by 1755 he had become a tribal chief. His commanding manner and talent for strategic planning also enabled him to become the leader of a loose confederacy among the Ottawa, the Potawatomi, and the Ojibwa. In 1760 he met Major Robert Rogers, a British colonial ranger on his way to occupy Michilimackinac (St. Ignace, Mich.) and other forts surrendered by the French during the French...
</Question>
<Choice>Pontiac</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first president of the Republic of India (1950–62). A lawyer turned journalist, he was a comrade of Mahatma Gandhi in the earliest noncooperation movements for independence and was also president of the Indian National Congress (1934, 1939, and 1947).Raised in a landowning family of modest means, Prasad was a graduate of the Calcutta Law College. He practiced at the Calcutta High Court and in 1916 transferred to the Patna High Court and founded the Bihar Law Weekly. In 1917 he was recruited by Gandhi to help in a campaign to improve conditions for peasants exploited by British indigo planters...
</Question>
<Choice>Prasad, Rajendra</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
de facto leader of Libya from 1969 and a controversial Arab statesman.The son of an itinerant Bedouin farmer, Qaddafi was born in a tent in the Libyan desert. He proved a talented student and graduated from the University of Libya in 1963. A devout Muslim and ardent Arab nationalist, Qaddafi early began plotting to overthrow the Libyan monarchy of King Idr?s I. He graduated from the Libyan military academy in 1965 and thereafter rose steadily through the ranks, all the while continuing to plan a coup with the help of his fellow army officers. On Sept. 1, 1969, Qaddafi seized control of the gov...
</Question>
<Choice>Qaddafi, Muammar al-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Israeli statesman and soldier who, as prime minister of Israel (1974–77, 1992–95), led his country toward peace with its Palestinian and Arab neighbours. He was chief of staff of Israel's armed forces during the Six-Day War (June 1967). Along with Shimon Peres, his foreign minister, and Palestine Liberation Organization (PLO) chairman Y?sir ?Araf?t, Rabin received the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1994.Rabin graduated from Kadourie Agricultural School in Kfar Tabor and in 1941 joined the Palmach, the Jewish Defense Forces' commando unit. He participated in actions against the Vichy French in Syria...
</Question>
<Choice>Rabin, Yitzhak</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Siberian peasant and mystic whose ability to improve the condition of Aleksey Nikolayevich, the hemophiliac heir to the Russian throne, made him an influential favourite at the court of Emperor Nicholas II and Empress Alexandra.Although he attended school, the peasant Grigory Yefimovich Novykh remained illiterate, and his reputation for licentiousness earned him the surname Rasputin, Russian for “debauched one.” He evidently underwent a religious conversion at age 18, and eventually he went to the monastery at Verkhoture, where he was introduced to the Khlysty (Flagellants) sect. Rasputin perv...
</Question>
<Choice>Rasputin, Grigory Yefimovich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
a principal chief of the Oglala Teton Dakota (Sioux), who successfully resisted (1865–67) the U.S. government's development of the Bozeman Trail to newly discovered goldfields in Montana Territory.Red Cloud had no hereditary title of his own but emerged as a natural leader and spokesman of his people through the force of his own character and through bravery in battle. Determined to protect the Indians' prime hunting grounds, Red Cloud in 1865 led the opposition of both Sioux and Cheyenne when the U.S. government began to build and fortify a road from Fort Laramie, in present Wyoming, by way o...
</Question>
<Choice>Red Cloud</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German diplomat, foreign minister under the Nazi regime (1933–45), and chief negotiator of the treaties with which Germany entered World War II.Ribbentrop was the son of an army officer in a middle-class family. After attending schools in Germany, Switzerland, France, and England, he went to Canada (1910), but he returned to Germany at the outbreak of World War I, in which he served as a hussar on the Eastern Front. He was then assigned to the German military mission in Turkey. Upon his return to Germany at the end of the war, Ribbentrop worked as a Sekt (sparkling wine) salesman until his mar...
</Question>
<Choice>Ribbentrop, Joachim von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
duke of Aquitaine (from 1168) and of Poitiers (from 1172) and king of England, duke of Normandy, and count of Anjou (1189–99). His knightly manner and his prowess in the Third Crusade (1189–92) made him a popular king in his own time as well as the hero of countless romantic legends. He has been viewed less kindly by more recent historians and scholars.
</Question>
<Choice>Richard I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the last Plantagenet and Yorkist king of England. He usurped the throne of his nephew Edward V in 1483 and perished in defeat to Henry Tudor (thereafter Henry VII) at the Battle of Bosworth Field. For almost 500 years after his death he was generally depicted as the worst and most wicked of kings. Although some of these charges are now regarded as excessive and the work of his enemies and his supporters have attempted to rehabilitate him, modern scholars take a more balanced approach that avoids the extremes of either side.
</Question>
<Choice>Richard III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
, (cardinal and duke of ),chief minister to King Louis XIII of France from 1624 to 1642. His major goals were the establishment of royal absolutism in France and the end of Spanish-Habsburg hegemony in Europe.
</Question>
<Choice>
Richelieu, Armand-Jean du Plessis, cardinal et duc de
</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Germany's top aviator and leading ace in World War I.Members of a prosperous family, Richthofen and his younger brother Lothar followed their father into military careers. In 1912 Richthofen became a lieutenant in the 1st Uhlan Cavalry Regiment of the Prussian Army. As a member of this regiment, he fought in Russia after the outbreak of World War I and then participated in the invasion of Belgium and France. When trench warfare settled in and the cavalry became sidelined, Richthofen joined the infantry. In 1915 he transferred to the Imperial Air Service and in September 1916 entered combat as...
</Question>
<Choice>Richthofen, Manfred, Freiherr von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Scotland (1306–29), who freed Scotland from English rule, winning the decisive Battle of Bannockburn (1314) and ultimately confirming Scottish independence in the Treaty of Northampton (1328).
</Question>
<Choice>Robert I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
32nd president of the United States (1933–45). The only president elected to the office four times, Roosevelt led the United States through two of the greatest crises of the 20th century: the Great Depression and World War II. In so doing, he greatly expanded the powers of the federal government through a series of programs and reforms known as the New Deal, and he served as the principal architect of the successful effort to rid the world of German National Socialism and Japanese militarism. (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of A...
</Question>
<Choice>Roosevelt, Franklin D.</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
26th president of the United States (1901–09) and writer, naturalist, and soldier. He expanded the powers of the presidency and of the federal government in support of the public interest in conflicts between big business and labour and steered the nation toward an active role in world politics, particularly in Europe and Asia. He won the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1906 for mediating an end to the Russo-Japanese War, and he secured the route and began construction of the Panama Canal (1904–14). (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of A...
</Question>
<Choice>Roosevelt, Theodore</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American lawyer and statesman, winner of the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1912.Root received his law degree from New York University in 1867 and became a leading corporation lawyer. As U.S. attorney for the southern district of New York (1883–85) he came into close contact with Theodore Roosevelt, then a leader in New York Republican politics, and became Roosevelt's friend and legal adviser.As secretary of war in President William McKinley's (and, after McKinley's assassination, Roosevelt's) cabinet (1899–1903), Root worked out governmental arrangements for the former Spanish areas then under U.S....
</Question>
<Choice>Root, Elihu</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Egyptian army officer and politician who was president of Egypt from 1970 until his assassination in 1981. He initiated serious peace negotiations with Israel, an achievement for which he shared the 1978 Nobel Prize for Peace with Israeli Prime Minister Menachem Begin. Under their leadership, Egypt and Israel made peace with each other in 1979.S?d?t graduated from the Cairo Military Academy in 1938. During World War II he plotted to expel the British from Egypt with the help of the Germans. The British arrested and imprisoned him in 1942, but he escaped two years later. In 1946 S?d?t was arres...
</Question>
<Choice>Sadat, Anwar el-</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
president of Iraq (1979–2003), whose brutal rule was marked by costly and unsuccessful wars against neighbouring countries.
</Question>
<Choice>Saddam Hussein</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Muslim sultan of Egypt, Syria, Yemen, and Palestine, founder of the Ayy?bid dynasty, and the most famous of Muslim heroes. In wars against the Christian Crusaders, he achieved great success with the capture of Jerusalem (Oct. 2, 1187), ending its nearly nine decades of occupation by the Franks.Saladin was born into a prominent Kurdish family. On the night of his birth, his father, Najm al-D?n Ayy?b, gathered his family and moved to Aleppo, there entering the service of ?Imad al-D?n Zang? ibn Aq Sonqur, the powerful Turkish governor in northern Syria. Growing up in Ba?lbek and Damascus, Saladin...
</Question>
<Choice>Saladin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prime minister of Japan between 1964 and 1972, who presided over Japan's post-World War II reemergence as a major world power. For his policies on nuclear weapons, which led to Japan's signing of the Treaty on the Non-proliferation of Nuclear Weapons, he was awarded (with cowinner Sean MacBride) the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1974.After graduating with a degree in law from Tokyo Imperial University (now University of Tokyo) in 1924, Sat? joined the Ministry of Railways, becoming the chief of its bureau of control in 1941 and vice-minister for transportation in 1948. That same year he joined the...
</Question>
<Choice>Sato Eisaku</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Nazi politician and head of the Nazi youth movement.The son of a former German theatre director and an American mother, Schirach studied at the University of Munich. He joined the National Socialist Party in 1925 and was elected to the Reichstag in 1932. He was appointed Reichsleiter (Reich leader) in June 1933 and entered Adolf Hitler's inner circle. On June 18, 1933, Schirach was made youth leader of the German Reich (Jugendführer des Deutsches Reich), a post he held until 1945, directing all Nazi youth organizations, including the Hitler Youth (Hitler Jugend). In August 1940 he was also app...
</Question>
<Choice>Schirach, Baldur von</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Zulu chief (1816–28), founder of Southern Africa's Zulu Empire. He is credited with creating a fighting force that devastated the entire region. His life is the subject of numerous colourful and exaggerated stories, many of which are debated by historians.
</Question>
<Choice>Shaka</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Indian statesman, prime minister of India (1964–66) after Jawaharlal Nehru.A member of Mahatma Gandhi's noncooperation movement against British government in India, he was imprisoned for a short time (1921). Upon release he studied in the Kashi Vidyapitha, a nationalist university, where he graduated with the title of shastri (“learned in the scriptures”). He then returned to politics as a follower of Gandhi, was imprisoned several more times, and attained influential positions in the Congress Party of the state of the United Provinces, now Uttar Pradesh state.Shastri was elected to the legisl...
</Question>
<Choice>Shastri, Lal Bahadur</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Teton Dakota Indian chief under whom the Sioux tribes united in their struggle for survival on the North American Great Plains. He is remembered for his lifelong distrust of white men and his stubborn determination to resist their domination.Sitting Bull was born into the Hunkpapa division of the Teton Sioux. He joined his first war party at age 14 and soon gained a reputation for fearlessness in battle. He became a leader of the powerful Strong Heart warrior society and, later, was a participant in the Silent Eaters, a select group concerned with tribal welfare. As a tribal leader Sitting Bul...
</Question>
<Choice>Sitting Bull</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
leader in the Gladiatorial War (73–71) against Rome.A Thracian by birth, Spartacus served in the Roman Army, perhaps deserted, led bandit raids, and was caught and sold as a slave. With about 70 fellow gladiators he escaped a gladiatorial training school at Capua in 73 and took refuge on Mount Vesuvius, where other runaway slaves joined the band. After defeating two Roman forces in succession, the rebels overran most of southern Italy. Ultimately their numbers grew to at least 90,000. Spartacus defeated the two consuls for the year 72 and fought his way northward toward the Alps, hoping to be...
</Question>
<Choice>Spartacus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
secretary-general of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union (1922–53) and premier of the Soviet state (1941–53), who for a quarter of a century dictatorially ruled the Soviet Union and transformed it into a major world power.During the quarter of a century preceding his death, the Soviet dictator Joseph Stalin probably exercised greater political power than any other figure in history. Stalin industrialized the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics, forcibly collectivized its agriculture, consolidated his position by intensive police terror, helped to defeat Germany in 1941–45, and extended Sov...
</Question>
<Choice>Stalin, Joseph</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
chancellor (1923) and foreign minister (1923, 1924–29) of the Weimar Republic, largely responsible for restoring Germany's international status after World War I. With French foreign minister Aristide Briand, he was awarded the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1926 for his policy of reconciliation and negotiation.
</Question>
<Choice>Stresemann, Gustav</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
leader of the Indonesian independence movement and Indonesia's first president (1949–66), who suppressed the country's original parliamentary system in favour of an authoritarian “Guided Democracy” and who attempted to balance the Communists against the army leaders. He was deposed in 1966 by the army under Suharto.
</Question>
<Choice>Sukarno</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
scholar, mathematician, philosopher, and militant nationalist who helped lay the foundation for India's independence. He founded (1914) and served as president of the Indian Home Rule League. In 1916 he concluded the Lucknow Pact with Mohammed Ali Jinnah, which provided for Hindu-Muslim unity in the struggle for independence.Tilak was born into a cultured, middle-class, Brahman family. After earning his university degree, Tilak studied law but then decided to teach mathematics in a private school in Poona (now Pune). The school became the basis for his political career. He developed the school...
</Question>
<Choice>Tilak, Bal Gangadhar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
soldier and statesman who was prime minister of Japan during most of World War II (1941–44) and who was subsequently tried and executed for war crimes.A graduate of the Imperial Military Academy and the Military Staff College, T?j? served briefly as military attaché in Japan's embassy in Berlin after World War I. He was an esteemed administrator and skillful field commander and became noted as a stern disciplinarian. In 1928 he was made commander of the lst Infantry Regiment, which in 1936 participated in the mutiny of the Tokyo garrison. In 1937 he was named chief of staff of the Kwantung Arm...
</Question>
<Choice>Tojo Hideki</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first grand inquisitor in Spain, whose name has become synonymous with the Christian Inquisition's horror, religious bigotry, and cruel fanaticism.The nephew of a noted Dominican cardinal and theologian, Juan de Torquemada, the young Torquemada joined the Dominicans and in 1452 became prior of the monastery of Santa Cruz at Segovia, an office that he held for 22 years. He was closely associated with the religious policy of King Ferdinand II and Queen Isabella I, to whom he was both confessor and adviser (to Isabella, from her childhood). He was convinced that the existence of the Marranos (Jew...
</Question>
<Choice>Torquemada, Tomás de</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
politician who served as first minister of the Northern Ireland Assembly (1998–2002), leader of the Ulster Unionist Party (UUP; 1995–2005), and a member of the British Parliament (1990–2005). In 1998 Trimble and John Hume, leader of the Social Democratic and Labour Party (SDLP), were awarded the Nobel Prize for Peace.While a professor of law at Queen's University of Belfast, Trimble was elected to the Northern Ireland Constitutional Convention for the Vanguard Unionist Progressive Party (VUPP) in 1975. The VUPP opposed direct rule of Northern Ireland by the British government and pushed for st...
</Question>
<Choice>Trimble, David</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
dictator of the Dominican Republic from 1930 until his assassination in 1961.Trujillo entered the Dominican army in 1918 and was trained by U.S. Marines during the U.S. occupation (1916–24) of the country. He rose from lieutenant to commanding colonel of the national police between 1919 and 1925, becoming a general in 1927. Trujillo seized power in the military revolt against Pres. Horacio Vásquez in 1930. From that time until his assassination 31 years later, Trujillo remained in absolute control of the Dominican Republic through his command of the army, by placing family members in office, a...
</Question>
<Choice>Trujillo, Rafael</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
statesman whose 27 years as Liberia's 17th president constituted the longest tenure in that office in the history of Africa's first republic (proclaimed in 1847). He was responsible for numerous reforms and social policies, including enactment of suffrage and property rights for all female residents of 21 or older; authorization of direct participation in government by all tribespeople, who comprise about 80 percent of the population; and the establishment of a nationwide public-school system.A descendant of early American immigrants, mostly liberated slaves, Tubman grew up in poverty and unde...
</Question>
<Choice>Tubman, William V S</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American politician who, with his “Tweed ring” cronies, systematically plundered New York City of sums estimated at between $30,000,000 and $200,000,000.Tweed was a bookkeeper and a volunteer fireman when elected alderman on his second try in 1851, and the following year he was also elected to a term in Congress. He gradually strengthened his position in Tammany Hall (the executive committee of New York City's Democratic Party organization), and in 1856 he was elected to a new, bipartisan city board of supervisors, after which he held other important positions in the city government. Meanwhile...
</Question>
<Choice>Tweed, William Marcy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
South African professor, editor, and statesman who as prime minister (1958–66) rigorously developed and applied the policy of apartheid, or separation of the races.When Verwoerd was three months old, his family migrated to South Africa. A brilliant scholar at the University of Stellenbosch, he was appointed professor of applied psychology there in 1927. In 1933 he changed to the chair of sociology and social work.Verwoerd became prominent in politics in 1937, when he was appointed editor of the new Nationalist daily, Die Transvaler, in Johannesburg. He held that post until the National Party w...
</Question>
<Choice>Verwoerd, Hendrik Frensch</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
labour activist who helped form and led (1980–90) communist Poland's first independent trade union, Solidarity. The charismatic leader of millions of Polish workers, he went on to become the president of Poland (1990–95). He received the Nobel Prize for Peace in 1983.Wa??sa, the son of a carpenter, received only primary and vocational education and in 1967 began work as an electrician at the huge Lenin Shipyard in Gda?sk. He witnessed the 1970 food riots in Gda?sk in which police killed a number of demonstrators. When new protests against Poland's communist government erupted in 1976, Wa??sa e...
</Question>
<Choice>Walesa, Lech</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
one of Scotland's greatest national heroes, leader of the Scottish resistance forces during the first years of the long, and ultimately successful, struggle to free Scotland from English rule.His father, Sir Malcolm Wallace, was a small landowner in Renfrew. In 1296 King Edward I of England deposed and imprisoned the Scottish king John de Balliol and declared himself ruler of Scotland. Sporadic resistance had already occurred when, in May 1297, Wallace and a band of some 30 men burned Lanark and killed its English sheriff. Wallace then organized an army of commoners and small landowners and at...
</Question>
<Choice>Wallace, Sir William</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American general and commander in chief of the colonial armies in the American Revolution (1775–83) and subsequently first president of the United States (1789–97). (For a discussion of the history and nature of the presidency, seepresidency of the United States of America.)Washington's father, Augustine Washington, had gone to school in England, had tasted seafaring life, and then settled down to manage his growing Virginia estates. His mother was Mary Ball, whom Augustine, a widower, had married early the previous year. Washington's paternal lineage had some distinction; an early forebear wa...
</Question>
<Choice>Washington, George</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
28th president of the United States (1913–21), an American scholar and statesman best remembered for his legislative accomplishments and his high-minded idealism. Wilson led his country into World War I and became the creator and leading advocate of the League of Nations, for which he was awarded the 1919 Nobel Prize for Peace. During his second term the Nineteenth Amendment to the U.S. Constitution, giving women the right to vote, was passed and ratified. He suffered a paralytic stroke while seeking American public support for the Treaty of Versailles (October 1919), and his incapacity, which...
</Question>
<Choice>Wilson, Woodrow</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
one of China's greatest generals and national heroes.In 1126 North China was overrun by the nomadic Juchen (Jin), and the Song capital at Kaifeng was taken. The former emperor Huizong, who had abdicated in 1125, together with his son, the Qinzong emperor (reigned 1125/26–27), was carried into captivity. Another son of Huizong, later known as the Gaozong emperor (reigned 1127–62), reestablished the dynasty in the south, hence its designation as the Nan (Southern) Song (1127–1279).Retreating southward with Gaozong, Yue Fei assumed command of the Song forces. He prevented the advance of the Juche...
</Question>
<Choice>Yüeh Fei</Choice>
</item>
</topics>