<topics>
<item>
<Question>
American official of the Central Intelligence Agency (CIA) who was entrusted with discovering Soviet spies, and who himself became one of the most successful double agents for the Soviet Union and Russia.The son of a CIA analyst, Ames attended the University of Chicago for two years before becoming a CIA trainee in 1962; he also attended George Washington University (B.A., 1967). In 1969–72 Ames was posted to Ankara, Tur., where he recruited U.S. spies from among Soviet nationals. He then lived in the United States until 1981, when he was posted to Mexico City, where he met his second wife, Ma...
</Question>
<Choice>Ames, Aldrich</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British army officer who negotiated with the American general Benedict Arnold and was executed as a spy during the American Revolution (1775–83).Sent to America in 1774, André became chief intelligence officer to the British commander in chief, General Sir Henry Clinton, in New York City. From May 1779 he carried on a secret correspondence with Arnold, who had become disillusioned with the American cause. In August 1780 Arnold was appointed commandant of the fort at West Point, New York, which, at a meeting with André on September 21, he agreed to surrender for £20,000.While returning to New Y...
</Question>
<Choice>André, John</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
patriot officer who served the cause of the American Revolution until 1779, when he shifted his allegiance to the British; thereafter his name became an epithet for traitor in the United States.Upon the outbreak of hostilities at Lexington, Massachusetts (April 1775), Arnold volunteered for service and participated with Ethan Allen in the successful colonial attack on British-held Fort Ticonderoga, New York, the following month. That autumn he was appointed by General George Washington to command an expedition to capture Quebec. He marched with 700 men by way of the Maine wilderness, a remarka...
</Question>
<Choice>Arnold, Benedict</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British diplomat and spy for the Soviet Union.After escaping from the Netherlands at the beginning of World War II, Blake served in the Royal Navy until 1948, when he entered the Foreign Office and was appointed vice-consul in Seoul. Blake was interned (1950–53) after North Korean troops captured Seoul, and he secretly became a communist. After his repatriation (1953) he was assigned to the British military government in Berlin (1955), where he had access to information of the British secret service. Recalled in 1959, he worked for the intelligence branch of the Foreign Office (MI-6) and then...
</Question>
<Choice>Blake, George</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British art historian who late in his life was revealed to have been a Soviet spy.While a fellow of Trinity College, Cambridge, in the 1930s Blunt became a member of a circle of disaffected young men led by Guy Burgess, under whose influence he was soon involved in espionage on behalf of the Soviet Union. His public career was brilliant. From 1937 he published scores of scholarly papers and books by which he largely established art history in Great Britain. He was an authority on 17th-century painting, particularly that of Nicolas Poussin. During World War II he served in MI-5, a military inte...
</Question>
<Choice>Blunt, Anthony</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
spy for the Confederacy during the American Civil War and later an actress and lecturer.Boyd attended Mount Washington Female College in Baltimore, Maryland, from 1856 to 1860. In Martinsburg, Virginia, at the outbreak of the Civil War, she joined in fund-raising activities on behalf of the Confederacy. When the town was occupied by Union forces in July 1861, she associated freely with officers, gleaning bits of military information that she sent by messenger to Confederate authorities. She and her mother denied entry to Union soldiers who wanted to raise a flag over their house in Martinsburg...
</Question>
<Choice>Boyd, Belle</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British diplomat who spied for the Soviet Union in World War II and early in the Cold War period.At the University of Cambridge in the 1930s, Burgess was part of a group of upper-middle-class students—including Donald Maclean, Kim Philby, and Anthony Blunt—who disagreed with the notion of a capitalist democracy. These men were recruited by Soviet intelligence operatives to become secret agents, and Burgess began supplying information from his posts as a BBC correspondent from 1936 to 1938, a member of the MI6 intelligence agency from 1938 to 1941, and a member of the British Foreign Office fro...
</Question>
<Choice>Burgess, Guy; and Maclean, Donald</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
third vice president of the United States (1801–05), who killed his political rival, Alexander Hamilton, in a duel (1804), and whose turbulent political career ended with his arrest for treason in 1807.Burr, the son of Aaron Burr and Esther Edwards, came from a prominent New Jersey family and was a grandson of the theologian Jonathan Edwards. He studied law and served on the staff of General George Washington during the American Revolution (1775–83) but was transferred after antagonizing him.In 1782 Burr was admitted to the New York state bar, and his law practice in New York City soon flouris...
</Question>
<Choice>Burr, Aaron</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
ecclesiastic, writer, soldier, spy, and diplomatist, chiefly remembered as the prince of Italian adventurers and as the man who made the name Casanova synonymous with “libertine.” His autobiography, which perhaps exaggerates some of his escapades, is a splendid description of 18th-century society in the capitals of Europe.The son of an actor, Casanova was expelled as a young man from the seminary of St. Cyprian for scandalous conduct and launched on a colourful, dissolute career. After a time in the service of a Roman Catholic cardinal, he was a violinist in Venice, joined the Masonic Order (1...
</Question>
<Choice>Casanova, Giovanni Giacomo</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American journalist, Communist Party member (1923–38), and a principal figure in the Alger Hiss case, one of the most publicized espionage incidents of the Cold War. (He assumed his mother's maiden name, Whittaker, in the 1920s, and he subsequently used a number of aliases.)At various times Chambers was an editor of the New Masses, The Daily Worker, and Time magazine. In August 1948, before a congressional committee, he identified Hiss as a fellow member of a communist spy ring in Washington, D.C., during the 1930s. Chambers produced copies of State Department documents typed on Hiss's typewri...
</Question>
<Choice>Chambers, Whittaker</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
one of the most famous spies of World War II, who worked for Nazi Germany in 1943–44 while he was employed as valet to Sir Hughe Montgomery Knatchbull-Hugessen, British ambassador to neutral Turkey from 1939. He photographed secret documents from the embassy safe and turned the films over to the former German chancellor Franz von Papen, at that time German ambassador in Ankara. For this service the Hitler government paid Cicero large sums in British money, most of it counterfeited in Germany. Despite the evident authenticity of the films, the Nazi officials in Berlin mistrusted Cicero and are...
</Question>
<Choice>Cicero</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
French army officer whose trial for treason began a 12-year controversy, known as the Dreyfus Affair, that deeply marked the political and social history of the FrenchThird Republic.Dreyfus was the son of a wealthy Jewish textile manufacturer. In 1882 he entered the École Polytechnique and decided on a military career. By 1889 he had risen to the rank of captain. Dreyfus was assigned to the War Ministry when, in 1894, he was accused of selling military secrets to the German military attaché. He was arrested on October 15, and on December 22 he was convicted and sentenced to life imprisonment....
</Question>
<Choice>Dreyfus, Alfred</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
former U.S. State Department official who was convicted in January 1950 of perjury concerning his dealings with Whittaker Chambers, who accused him of membership in a communist espionage ring. His case, which came at a time of growing apprehension about the domestic influence of communism, seemed to lend substance to Senator Joseph R. McCarthy's sensational charges of communist infiltration into the State Department. It also brought to national attention Richard M. Nixon, then a U.S. representative from California, who was prominent in the investigation that led to the indictment of Hiss.Hiss...
</Question>
<Choice>Hiss, Alger</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
one of the Twelve Apostles, notorious for betraying Jesus. Judas' surname is more probably a corruption of the Latin sicarius (“murderer” or “assassin”) than an indication of family origin, suggesting that he would have belonged to the Sicarii, the most radical Jewish group, some of whom were terrorists. Other than his apostleship, his betrayal, and his death, little else is revealed about Judas in the Gospels. Always the last on the list of the Apostles, he was their treasurer. John 12:6 introduces Judas' thievery by saying, “. . . as he had the money box he used to take what was put into it....
</Question>
<Choice>Judas Iscariot</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
dancer and courtesan whose name has become a synonym for the seductive female spy. She was shot by the French on charges of spying for Germany during World War I, although the nature and extent of her espionage activities remain uncertain.The daughter of a prosperous hatter, she attended a teachers' college in Leiden. In 1895 she married an officer of Scottish origin, Captain Campbell MacLeod, in the Dutch colonial army, and from 1897 to 1902 they lived in Java and Sumatra. The couple returned to Europe but later separated, and she began to dance professionally in Paris in 1905 under the name...
</Question>
<Choice>Mata Hari</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
British intelligence officer until 1951 and the most successful Soviet double agent of the Cold War period.While a student at the University of Cambridge, Philby became a Communist and in 1933 a Soviet agent. He worked as a journalist until 1940, when Guy Burgess, a British secret agent who was himself a Soviet double agent, recruited Philby into the MI-6 section of the British intelligence service. By the end of World War II, Philby had become head of counterespionage operations for MI-6, in which post he was responsible for combating Soviet subversion in western Europe. In 1949 he was sent t...
</Question>
<Choice>Philby, Kim</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Norwegian army officer whose collaboration with the Germans in their occupation of Norway during World War II established his name as a synonym for “traitor.”Quisling entered the army in 1911 and served as military attaché in Petrograd (St. Petersburg; 1918–19) and in Helsinki (1919–21). He assisted in relief work in Russia under the famous Arctic explorer and humanitarian Fridtjof Nansen and later for the League of Nations. In the absence of diplomatic relations between Britain and Soviet Russia, he represented British interests at the Norwegian legation in Moscow (1927–29). As minister of de...
</Question>
<Choice>Quisling, Vidkun</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the first American civilians to be executed for espionage and the first to suffer that penalty during peacetime.Ethel Greenglass worked as a clerk for some years after her graduation from high school in 1931. When she married Julius Rosenberg in 1939, the year he earned a degree in electrical engineering, the two were already active members of the Communist Party. In the following year Julius obtained a job as a civilian engineer with the U.S. Army Signal Corps, and he and Ethel began working together to disclose U.S. military secrets to the Soviet Union. Later, Ethel's brother, Sergeant David...
</Question>
<Choice>Rosenberg, Julius; and Rosenberg, Ethel</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
American boardinghouse operator, who, with three others, was convicted of conspiracy to assassinate President Abraham Lincoln.At age 17 Mary Jenkins married John Harrison Surratt, a land owner. Following a fire that destroyed their home, the couple in 1852 opened a tavern that also served as their residence. By 1857 John Surratt had fallen into serious debt, and the outbreak of the American Civil War completed his ruin; he died in 1862. The couple's youngest son, John, returned to help run the tavern, and during the war it became a safe house for Confederates. In 1864 Mary rented the tavern to...
</Question>
<Choice>Surratt, Mary</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
English statesman and the principal secretary to Queen Elizabeth I from 1573 to 1590. He was a skilled diplomat whose knowledge of languages and capacity to organize espionage activities made him invaluable in the execution of Elizabeth's foreign policy. In addition, he was a staunch Puritan who uncovered a number of dangerous Roman Catholic conspiracies against the queen.The son of a lawyer, Walsingham was admitted to the bar in 1552, and in 1563 he obtained his first seat in Parliament. William Cecil (later Baron Burghley), the principal secretary, soon discovered his potential; from 1568 to...
</Question>
<Choice>Walsingham, Sir Francis</Choice>
</item>
</topics>