<topics>
<item>
<Question>
tyrant of Syracuse, in Sicily, from 317 to c. 304 and self-styled king of Sicily after c. 304. A champion of Hellenism, he waged war unsuccessfully against Carthage.Agathocles moved from his native town to Syracuse about 343 and served with distinction in the army. Twice banished for attempting to overthrow the oligarchical party, he returned in 317 with an army, banished or murdered about 10,000 citizens (including the oligarchs), and set himself up as tyrant.Agathocles then embarked on a long series of wars. His first campaigns (316–c. 313), against the other Sicilian Greeks, brought a numbe...
</Question>
<Choice>Agathocles</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Sparta from 399 to 360 who commanded the Spartan army throughout most of the period of Spartan supremacy (404–371) in Greece. An excellent military tactician, he is usually cited as the embodiment of the aggressive Spartan spirit that sought to further Spartan interests at the expense of Hellenic unity.Agesilaus was born into the Eurypontid house (one of the two royal families of Sparta) and was the son of King Archidamus II. He succeeded Agis II with aid from Lysander. At the time that he assumed power, Sparta, which had defeated Athens in 404, was at war with Persia in Asia Minor. Sa...
</Question>
<Choice>Agesilaus II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spartan king (244–241) who failed in his attempt to reform Sparta's economic and political structure.Agis succeeded his father, Eudamidas II, at the age of 19. Drawing upon the tradition of the Spartan lawgiver Lycurgus, Agis sought to reform a system that distributed the land and wealth unequally and burdened the poor with debt. He proposed the cancellation of debts and the division of the Spartan homeland into 4,500 lots for citizens. By this time the number of full citizens had dwindled to 700. Full citizenship was to be extended to many perioeci (voteless freemen) and foreigners, and 15,00...
</Question>
<Choice>Agis IV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
seventh king of the northern kingdom of Israel (reigned c. 874–c. 853 BC), according to the Old Testament, and son of King Omri.Omri left to Ahab an empire that comprised not only territory east of the Jordan River, in Gilead and probably Bashan, but also the land of Moab, whose king was tributary. The southern kingdom of Judah, if not actually subject to Omri, was certainly a subordinate ally. And Ahab's marriage to Jezebel, daughter of Ethbaal of Sidon, revived an alliance with the Phoenicians that had been in abeyance since the time of Solomon.Throughout Ahab's reign, however, a fierce bord...
</Question>
<Choice>Ahab</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Judah (c. 735–720 BC) who became an Assyrian vassal (2 Kings 16; Isaiah 7–8).Ahaz assumed the throne of Judah at the age of 20 or 25. Sometime later his kingdom was invaded by Pekah, king of Israel, and Rezin, king of Syria, in an effort to force him into an alliance with them against the powerful state of Assyria. Acting against the counsel of the prophet Isaiah, Ahaz appealed for aid to Tiglath-pileser III, king of Assyria, to repel the invaders. Assyria defeated Syria and Israel, and Ahaz presented himself as a vassal to the Assyrian king. Not only was Judah's political situation un...
</Question>
<Choice>Ahaz</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king (reigned 570–526 BCE) of the 26th dynasty (664–525 BCE; seeancient Egypt: The Late period [664–332 BCE]) of ancient Egypt, a general who seized the throne during a revolt against King Apries. The account of the 5th-century-BCEGreek historianHerodotus reveals Amasis as a shrewd and opportunistic ruler who, while promoting Greek trade with Egypt, strictly regulated it.In 570, after Apries's unsuccessful campaign against Cyrene (in modern Libya), the Egyptian troops mutinied, and, when Amasis was sent to pacify them, the mutineers proclaimed him king. In the ensuing civil war the Egyptians u...
</Question>
<Choice>Ahmose II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king (1353–36 BCE) of ancient Egypt of the 18th dynasty, who established a new cult dedicated to the Aton, the sun's disk (hence his assumed name, Akhenaton, meaning “beneficial to Aton”).
</Question>
<Choice>Akhenaton</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
chief of the Visigoths from 395 and leader of the army that sacked Rome in August 410, an event that symbolized the fall of the Western Roman Empire.A nobleman by birth, Alaric served for a time as commander of Gothic troops in the Roman army, but shortly after the death of the emperor Theodosius I in 395, he left the army and was elected chief of the Visigoths. Charging that his tribe had not been given subsidies promised by the Romans, Alaric marched westward toward Constantinople (now Istanbul) until he was diverted by Roman forces. He then moved southward into Greece, where he sacked Pirae...
</Question>
<Choice>Alaric</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the Visigoths, who succeeded his father Euric on Dec. 28, 484. He was married to Theodegotha, daughter of Theodoric, the Ostrogothic king of Italy.His dominions comprised Aquitaine, Languedoc, Roussillon, and parts of western Spain. Alaric, like his father, was an Arian Christian, but he mitigated the persecution of Catholics and authorized the Catholic council at Agde in 506. To provide a law code for his Roman subjects, he appointed a commission to prepare an abstract of Roman laws and imperial decrees. This influential code, issued in 506, is generally known as the Lex Romana Visigo...
</Question>
<Choice>Alaric II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Syria and Pergamum (Greek Asia Minor) and ruler of the remains of the Seleucid Empire (150–145 BC).The pretended son of Antiochus IV Epiphanes, he won the Seleucid throne with the help of mercenaries, challenging and slaying Demetrius I Soter, the direct Seleucid heir. With the support of the Roman Senate and the Egyptian Ptolemaic dynasty, he ruled the remains of the Seleucid Empire until he was killed in battle against Demetrius II Nicator, son of Demetrius I Soter.During his reign, Alexander pacified Palestine by naming Jonathan Maccabeus as Jewish governor but alienated the populat...
</Question>
<Choice>Alexander Balas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Macedonia (336–323 BC). He overthrew the Persian Empire, carried Macedonian arms to India, and laid the foundations for the Hellenistic world of territorial kingdoms. Already in his lifetime the subject of fabulous stories, he later became the hero of a full-scale legend bearing only the sketchiest resemblance to his historical career.
</Question>
<Choice>Alexander the Great</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Lydia, in west-central Anatolia (reigned c. 610–c. 560 BC), whose conquest created the powerful but short-lived Lydian empire.Soon after succeeding his father, King Sadyattes, Alyattes started five consecutive years of raids that devastated the farmland around the Greek city of Miletus on the southwestern coast of Anatolia. He moved eastward, battling the Medes for five years, until an eclipse of the Sun brought an end to the fighting. Alyattes also fought with the Carians to the south, whom he conquered, and with the nomadic Cimmerians to the east, whom he drove from western Anatolia....
</Question>
<Choice>Alyattes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Macedonia from about 393 to 370/369. His skillful diplomacy created a minor role for Macedonia in Greek affairs and prepared the way for its emergence as a great power under his son Philip II (ruled 359–336).Amyntas came to the throne during the disorders that plagued Macedonia after the death of the powerful king Archelaus (ruled c. 413–399). Amyntas soon had to fight off attacks by the Illyrians (of present-day Albania) and by the Chalcidian League, a confederation of cities of the Chalcidice peninsula, east of Macedonia. The threat from the latter was removed when intervention by Sp...
</Question>
<Choice>Amyntas III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
traditionally the fourth king of Rome, from 642 to 617 BC. The details of his reign, provided by Roman historians such as Livy (64 or 59 BC–AD 17), must be regarded as largely legendary—e.g., the settlement of the Aventine Hill outside Rome, the first extension of Rome beyond the Tiber River to the Janiculum Hill, and the founding of the port of Ostia at the mouth of the Tiber.
</Question>
<Choice>Ancus Marcius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Western Roman emperor who reigned from April 12, 467, to July 11, 472.The son-in-law of the Eastern emperor Marcian, Anthemius was appointed to his office by Marcian's successor, Leo I, who wanted help in attacking the Vandals in North Africa. The powerful patrician Ricimer, kingmaker of the Western Empire, accepted Anthemius with the stipulation that his daughter, Alypia, marry Ricimer. Anthemius's popularity in Italy suffered, however, because as a Greek and a philosopher he was suspected of wanting to restore paganism. The vast expedition against the Vandals ended in utter defeat for the Ro...
</Question>
<Choice>Anthemius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek“One-Eyed”Macedonian general under Alexander the Great who founded the Macedonian dynasty of the Antigonids (306–168 BC), becoming king in 306. An exceptional strategist and combat leader, he was also an astute ruler who cultivated the friendship of Athens and other Greek city-states.
</Question>
<Choice>Antigonus I Monophthalmus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Macedonia from 276 BC who rebuilt his kingdom's power and established its hegemony over Greece.Antigonus II was the son of Demetrius I Poliorcetes and grandson of Antigonus I. While Demetrius was busy fighting in Macedonia and Asia Minor, Antigonus, as his regent, was engaged in maintaining Macedonian hegemony in Greece, which had been achieved in 287 BC. Demetrius was taken prisoner in 285 by Seleucus I, who then claimed the Macedonian kingship. This contested title was assumed by Antigonus himself on the death of his father two years later; however, he did not count the beginning of...
</Question>
<Choice>Antigonus II Gonatas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Macedonia (from 227 BC) who, in defeating Cleomenes of Sparta, ended that city's long independence. His surname may have signified “one who is about to give but never does.”Antigonus, a descendant of Antigonus I, was the son of Demetrius II (a half brother of Antigonus II) and Olympias of Larissa. On the death of Demetrius II (229 BC), Antigonus was made guardian of his son Philip. After two years, Antigonus married Demetrius' widow, Phthia, and assumed the crown.His first military task was to secure Macedonia against barbarians on its borders. He then became involved in Greek affairs,...
</Question>
<Choice>Antigonus III Doson</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the Seleucid kingdom of Syria, who ruled about 292–281 BC in the east and 281–261 over the whole kingdom. Under great external pressures, he consolidated his kingdom and encouraged the founding of cities.Antiochus was the son of Seleucus I, founder of the Seleucid kingdom, and his Sogdian queen, Apama. When an invasion of nomads threatened the eastern possessions of his father's realm (between the Caspian and Aral seas and the Indian Ocean), Antiochus was appointed king (292). He restored some of the damage caused by the invaders and rebuilt three cities. Because his father still had i...
</Question>
<Choice>Antiochus I Soter</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the Seleucid dominions in the Middle East, who succeeded his father, Antiochus I, in 261 BC and spent much of his reign at war with Egypt, recovering much territory in Anatolia.Finding a willing ally in Antigonus, ruler of Macedonia, who had suffered at the hands of Ptolemy II of Egypt, Antiochus waged the Second Syrian War (259–255) against Ptolemy to avenge his father's losses. While Antigonus defeated the Egyptian fleet at sea, Antiochus reconquered much of Anatolia, including the cities of Miletus and Ephesus, and also the Phoenician coast.In Miletus, Antiochus overthrew a tyrant a...
</Question>
<Choice>Antiochus II Theos</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Seleucid king of the Hellenistic Syrian Empire from 223 BC to 187, who rebuilt the empire in the East but failed in his attempt to challenge Roman ascendancy in Europe and Asia Minor. He reformed the empire administratively by reducing the provinces in size, established a ruler cult (with himself and his consort Laodice as divine), and improved relations with neighbouring countries by giving his daughters in marriage to their princes.The son of Seleucus II, Antiochus succeeded his brother Seleucus III as king. He retained from the previous administration Hermias as chief minister, Achaeus as g...
</Question>
<Choice>Antiochus III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek“God Manifest”Seleucid king of the Hellenistic Syrian kingdom who reigned from 175 to 164 BC. As a ruler he was best known for his encouragement of Greek culture and institutions. His attempts to suppress Judaism brought on the Wars of the Maccabees.
</Question>
<Choice>Antiochus IV Epiphanes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
who, after reuniting his country, ruled as king of the Seleucid state of Syria in 139/138–129 BC and successfully recovered much of his forefathers' territory before he was slain by the Parthians.The son of Demetrius I and brother of Demetrius II, both Seleucid kings, Antiochus spent his youth in the Greek islands. In 141 his brother was captured while fighting the Parthians. Cleopatra Thea, Demetrius II's queen, meanwhile was regent; but a usurper, Tryphon, had risen and threatened to seize full power. At this point, Antiochus VII, an energetic prince, arrived in Syria (139), married Cleopatr...
</Question>
<Choice>Antiochus VII Sidetes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Macedonian general, regent of Macedonia (334–23) and of the Macedonian Empire (321–319) whose death signalled the end of centralized authority in the empire. One of the leading men in Macedonia at the death of Philip II in 336, he helped to secure the succession to the Macedonian throne for Philip's son, Alexander the Great, who upon departure for the conquest of Asia (334) appointed Antipater regent in Macedonia with the title of general in Europe. Antipater's main task was to hold the northern frontiers against hostile tribes and to keep order among the Greek states. He ruled Greece by coope...
</Question>
<Choice>Antipater</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor from AD 138 to 161. Mild-mannered and capable, he was the fourth of the “five good emperors” who guided the empire through an 84-year period (96–180) of internal peace and prosperity. His family originated in Gaul, and his father and grandfathers had all been consuls.After serving as consul in 120, Antoninus was assigned by the emperor Hadrian (ruled 117–138) to assist with judicial administration in Italy. He governed the province of Asia (c. 134) and then became an adviser to the Emperor. In 138 Antoninus was adopted by Hadrian and designated as his successor. Hadrian specified...
</Question>
<Choice>Antoninus Pius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
fourth king (reigned 589–570 BCE) of the 26th dynasty (664–525 BCE; seeancient Egypt: The Late period [664–332 BCE]) of ancient Egypt; he succeeded his father, Psamtik II.Apries failed to help his ally King Zedekiah of Judah against the invading armies of Nebuchadrezzar II of Babylon, but after the fall of Jerusalem he received many Jewish refugees into Egypt. Later, according to Herodotus, he took the Phoenician port of Sidon, but, because of his subsequent failure in an attack on Cyrene in Libya, the Egyptian army mutinied and elected their general Amasis as king instead (570). Apries was im...
</Question>
<Choice>Apries</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Eastern Roman emperor conjointly with his father, Theodosius I, from 383 to 395, then solely until 402, when he associated his son Theodosius II with his own rule. Frail and ineffectual, he was dominated by his ministers, Rufinus, Eutropius, and Anthemius, and by his wife Eudoxia. His empire was a prey to the Goths, and Eudoxia abetted the persecution of the patriarch St. John Chrysostom.
</Question>
<Choice>Arcadius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the founder of the Sasanian empire in ancient Persia (reigned AD 224–241).Ardashir was the son of Babak, who was the son or descendant of Sasan and was a vassal of the chief petty king in Persis, Gochihr. After Babak got Ardashir the military post of argabad in the town of Darabgerd (near modern Darab, Iran), Ardashir extended his control over several neighbouring cities. Meanwhile, Babak had slain Gochihr and taken the title of king. Although Babak's request that the Parthian king Artabanus V allow him to transmit the crown to his eldest son, Shapur, was refused, Shapur nevertheless succeeded...
</Question>
<Choice>Ardashir I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
early Achaemenid king of Persia (reigned c. 640–c. 615).The son of the previous king, Teispes, Ariaramnes ruled over Persis (modern Fars, in southwestern Iran); his brother Cyrus I was given control of Anshan in Elam, north of the Persian Gulf. A campaign by the Medes, however, broke the power of Ariaramnes, and he and his son Arsames, who succeeded him, became vassals of Media (in modern northwest Iran). Dating to the reign of Ariaramnes is an important gold tablet written in cuneiform—the first historical inscription in Old Persian from Achaemenid times. The tablet not only traces the royal...
</Question>
<Choice>Ariaramnes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
German tribal leader who inflicted a major defeat on Rome by destroying three legions under Publius Quinctilius Varus in the Teutoburg Forest (southeast of modern Bielefeld, Ger.), late in the summer of AD 9. This defeat severely checked the emperor Augustus' plans, the exact nature of which is uncertain, for the country between the Rhine and Elbe rivers.Arminius was a chief of the Cherusci. In the service of the Romans he had obtained both citizenship and equestrian rank. Six years after the Teutoburg Forest Massacre, Germanicus Caesar engaged Arminius in battle, capturing his wife, Thusnelda...
</Question>
<Choice>Arminius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Achaemenid king of Persia (reigned November 338–June 336 BC); he was the youngest son of Artaxerxes III Ochus and Atossa.Arses had been placed on the throne by the eunuch Bagoas, who had murdered Arses' father and all his brothers. Little is known of Arses' short reign; the major external event was the invasion of Asia Minor by Philip II of Macedon, ostensibly because Arses refused to make reparation to Philip for Artaxerxes' aid to the city of Perinthus against Philip.The young Arses objected to the tyrannical control by Bagoas and attempted to poison him. Instead, Arses and all his children...
</Question>
<Choice>Arses</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Parthia (reigned 211–191 BC) in southwestern Asia. In 209 he was attacked by the Seleucid king Antiochus III of Syria, who took Hecatompylos, the Arsacid capital (the present location of which is uncertain), and Syrinx in Hyrcania. Finally, however, Antiochus concluded a treaty with Artabanus, who after 206 lost much territory to Euthydemus, ruler of Bactria.
</Question>
<Choice>Artabanus I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Parthia (reigned c.AD 12–c. 38).At first king of Media Atropatene, Artabanus III took the Parthian throne in AD 9 or 10 from Vonones and was proclaimed king about two years later in Ctesiphon, the Parthian capital on the Tigris River. Vonones fled to Armenia, but Artabanus forced him to abdicate in AD 15 or 16. During the first part of Artabanus' reign there was peace with Rome. Although faced with internal unrest, he was apparently a strong king and helped restore the authority of the central government. A letter written by Artabanus in December of 21 to the magistrates and the city o...
</Question>
<Choice>Artabanus III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
last king of the Parthian empire (reigned c.AD 213–224) in southwest Asia.He was the younger son of Vologases IV, who died probably in 207, and was ruling the Median provinces at the time of his rebellion (c. 213) against his brother, Vologases V. By 216 he had apparently extended his power over the Mesopotamian part of the empire, although Vologases continued to strike coins at the Seleucia mint until 222 or 223. The Roman emperor Caracalla attacked Artabanus in 216, ravaging much of Media and desecrating the Parthian royal tombs at Arbela (modern ?Arbil, Iraq). In 217 Artabanus counterattack...
</Question>
<Choice>Artabanus V</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Achaemenid king of Persia (reigned 465–425 BC).He was surnamed in Greek Macrocheir (“Longhand”) and in Latin Longimanus. A younger son of Xerxes I and Amestris, he was raised to the throne by the commander of the guard, Artabanus, who had murdered Xerxes. A few months later, Artaxerxes slew Artabanus in a hand-to-hand fight. His reign, though generally peaceful, was disturbed by several insurrections, the first of which was the revolt of his brother the satrap of Bactria. More dangerous was the rebellion of Egypt under Inaros, who received assistance from the Athenians. Achaemenid rule in Egyp...
</Question>
<Choice>Artaxerxes I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Achaemenid king of Persia (reigned 404–359/358).He was the son and successor of Darius II and was surnamed (in Greek) Mnemon, meaning “the mindful.” When Artaxerxes took the Persian throne, the power of Athens had been broken in the Peloponnesian War (431–404), and the Greek towns across the Aegean Sea in Ionia were again subjects of the Achaemenid Empire. In 404, however, Artaxerxes lost Egypt, and in the following year his brother Cyrus the Younger began preparations for his rebellion. Although Cyrus was defeated and killed at Cunaxa (401), the rebellion had dangerous repercussions, for it n...
</Question>
<Choice>Artaxerxes II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Achaemenid king of Persia (reigned 359/358–338 BC).He was the son and successor of Artaxerxes II and was called Ochus before he took the throne. Artaxerxes III was a cruel but energetic ruler. To secure his throne he put to death most of his relatives. In 356 he ordered all the satraps (governors) of the Achaemenid empire to dismiss their mercenaries. He also forced Athens to conclude peace and to acknowledge the independence of its rebellious allies (355).Artaxerxes then attempted to subjugate Egypt, which had been independent since 404. Failure of the first attempt (351) encouraged the Phoen...
</Question>
<Choice>Artaxerxes III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
one of the founders of the ancient kingdom of Armenia (reigned 190–159 BC).After the defeat of the Seleucid king Antiochus III the Great by the Romans in the Battle of Magnesia (190), Artaxias and Zariadres, who were Antiochus' satraps (governors) in Armenia, revolted and established themselves with Roman consent as kings of Greater Armenia and its district of Sophene to the southwest, respectively. They united their efforts to enlarge their domains at the expense of neighbouring areas and are considered the creators of historical Armenia. Artaxias built his capital, Artaxata, on the Araxes (n...
</Question>
<Choice>Artaxias</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
last of the great kings of Assyria (reigned 668 to 627 BC), who assembled in Nineveh the first systematically organized library in the ancient Middle East.
</Question>
<Choice>Ashurbanipal</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Assyria 883–859 BC, whose major accomplishment was the consolidation of the conquests of his father, Tukulti-Ninurta II, leading to the establishment of the New Assyrian Empire. Although, by his own testimony, he was a brilliant general and administrator, he is perhaps best known for the brutal frankness with which he described the atrocities committed on his captives. The details of his reign are known almost entirely from his own inscriptions and the splendid reliefs in the ruins of his palace at Calah (now Nimrud, Iraq).The annals of Ashurnasirpal II give a detailed account of the c...
</Question>
<Choice>Ashurnasirpal II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
last major emperor in the Mauryan dynasty of India. His vigorous patronage of Buddhism during his reign (c. 265–238 BCE; also given as c. 273–232 BCE) furthered the expansion of that religion throughout India. Following his successful but bloody conquest of the Kalinga country on the east coast, Ashoka renounced armed conquest and adopted a policy that he called “conquest by dharma” (i.e., by principles of right life).In order to gain wide publicity for his teachings and his work, Ashoka made them known by means of oral announcements and by engravings on rocks and pillars at suitable sites. Th...
</Question>
<Choice>Asoka</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the last king of the Median empire (reigned 585–550 BC). According to Herodotus, the Achaemenian Cyrus the Great was Astyages' grandson through his daughter Mandane, but this relationship is probably legendary. According to Babylonian inscriptions, Cyrus, king of Anshan (in southwestern Iran), began war against Astyages in 553 BC; in 550 the Median troops rebelled, and Astyages was taken prisoner. Then Cyrus occupied and plundered Ecbatana, the Median capital. A somewhat different account of these events is given by the Greek writer Ctesias.
</Question>
<Choice>Astyages</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
chieftain of the Visigoths from 410 to 415 and the successor of his brother-in-law Alaric.In 412 Ataulphus led the Visigoths, who had recently sacked Rome (410), from Italy to settle in southern Gaul. Two years later he married the Roman princess Galla Placidia (sister of the emperor Honorius), who had been seized at Rome. Driven from Gaul, he retreated into Spain early in 415 and was in that year assassinated at Barcelona. The 5th-century historian Paulus Orosius records Ataulphus' statement that his original aim had been to overthrow the Roman Empire, but that later, recognizing the inabilit...
</Question>
<Choice>Ataulphus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
in the Old Testament, the daughter of Ahab and Jezebel and wife of Jeham, king of Judah. After the death of Ahaziah, her son, Athaliah usurped the throne and reigned for seven years. She massacred all the members of the royal house of Judah (II Kings 11:1–3), except Joash. A successful revolution was organized in favour of Joash, and she was killed. The story of Athaliah forms the subject of one of Jean Racine's best tragedies, Athalie.
</Question>
<Choice>Athaliah</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Visigothic chieftain from 364 to 376 who fiercely persecuted the Christians in Dacia (approximately modern Romania). The persecutions occurred between 369 and 372; his most important victim was St. Sabas the Goth. In 376 Athanaric was defeated by the Huns. He fled with a few followers to Transylvania (region in present-day Romania), but the bulk of his people, led by Fritigern, fled to the Roman Empire. Athanaric, too, took refuge there in 381 but died at Constantinople a fortnight after his arrival.
</Question>
<Choice>Athanaric</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
ruler of Pergamum from 241 to 197 BC, with the title of king after about 230. He succeeded his uncle, Eumenes I (reigned 263–241), and by military and diplomatic skill created a powerful Pergamene kingdom.Attalus' mother, Antiochis, was a princess of the Seleucid house, a dynasty founded in Syria by one of the successors of Alexander the Great. Shortly before 230 Pergamum was attacked by the Galatians (Celts who had settled in central Anatolia in the 3rd century BC) because Attalus had refused to pay them the customary tribute. Attalus crushed his enemy in a battle outside the walls of Pergamu...
</Question>
<Choice>Attalus I Soter</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Pergamum from 138 to 133 BC who, by bequeathing his domains to Rome, ended the history of Pergamum as an independent political entity. He was the son of Eumenes II (reigned 197–159) and nephew of Attalus II Philadelphus (reigned 159–138). Little is known of his reign. Attalus is said to have behaved tyrannically at first, but he evidently settled down to a quiet and studious life. His motives for bequeathing Pergamum to Rome are obscure. In 129 Rome organized the kingdom into the province of Asia.
</Question>
<Choice>Attalus III Philometor Euergetes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the Huns from 434 to 453 (ruling jointly with his elder brother Bleda until 445). He was one of the greatest of the barbarian rulers who assailed the Roman Empire, invading the southern Balkan provinces and Greece and then Gaul and Italy. In legend he appears under the name Etzel in the Nibelungenlied and under the name Atli in Icelandic sagas.
</Question>
<Choice>Attila</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first Roman emperor, following the republic, which had been finally destroyed by the dictatorship of Julius Caesar, his great-uncle and adoptive father. His autocratic regime is known as the principate because he was the princeps, the first citizen, at the head of that array of outwardly revived republican institutions that alone made his autocracy palatable. With unlimited patience, skill, and efficiency, he overhauled every aspect of Roman life and brought durable peace and prosperity to the Greco-Roman world.Gaius Octavius was born on September 23, 63 BC, of a prosperous family that had lon...
</Question>
<Choice>Augustus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor from 270 to 275. By reuniting the empire, which had virtually disintegrated under the pressure of invasions and internal revolts, he earned his self-adopted title restitutor orbis (“restorer of the world”).Aurelian, born near the Danube River, had established himself as an army officer when, about 260, from outside pressure and internal fragmentation of authority, the frontiers of the empire suddenly collapsed. With his compatriot Claudius, Aurelian led the cavalry of the emperor Gallienus (253–268), and, upon Gallienus's assassination in 268, Claudius became emperor. The new rul...
</Question>
<Choice>Aurelian</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Western Roman emperor (455–456).Born of a distinguished Gallic family, Avitus was a son-in-law of the Christian writer Sidonius Apollinaris, whose poetry is an important source for our knowledge of him. By taking advantage of his great influence with the Visigoths who were settled at Toulouse, Avitus was able in 451 to persuade their king, Theodoric I, to join the Roman general Aetius in repelling the invasion of Gaul by the Huns under Attila. Avitus was appointed magister utriusque militiae (“master of both services”) by the Western emperor Petronius Maximus (reigned 455). When Maximus was ki...
</Question>
<Choice>Avitus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of ancient Egypt (reigned 1323–19 BCE) of the 18th dynasty, who rose from the ranks of the civil service and the military to become king after the death of Tutankhamen.Ay first appears as a member of the court of Akhenaton, at his capital city of Akhetaton, where Ay's large private tomb is found. His military functions included master of the horse and troop leader, but his primary title, “God's Father,” indicates an especially close relationship to the royal family. Ay's wife, Tiy, also served as the nurse of Nefertiti, Akhenaton's queen, and it has been surmised that Ay and Tiy were her...
</Question>
<Choice>Ay</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
confidential minister of the Achaemenid king Artaxerxes III of Persia. His name was the Greek form of an Old Persian name often used for eunuchs.Bagoas was commander in chief of the Achaemenid forces in the conquest of Egypt (343 BC) and gained wealth by selling back to the priests at an exorbitant price the sacred writings looted from Egyptian temples. He worked in close partnership with Mentor of Rhodes and rose to such power that he became the real master of the Achaemenid Empire, Artaxerxes doing nothing without his advice. In 338 Bagoas murdered Artaxerxes and all the king's sons except A...
</Question>
<Choice>Bagoas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sasanian king (reigned 273–276).A son of Shapur I, during his father's reign he governed the province of Atropatene. His succession to his brother Hormizd I strengthened the position of the Zoroastrian clergy and their high priest Karter, and at their insistence Bahram imprisoned Mani, the founder of the antimaterialist, ascetic religion of Manichaeism. Subsequent religious persecution was directed not only at Manichaeans but at Christians and Buddhists as well. Bahram, distinguished by his characteristic radiate crown, is portrayed on a rock sculpture at Bishapur (in southern Iran), although...
</Question>
<Choice>Bahram I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sasanian king (reigned 276–293), the son and successor of Bahram I.Soon after becoming king, he was forced to defend his position against a brother, Hormizd, viceroy of the eastern provinces. In 283, exploiting Bahram's preoccupations, the Roman emperor Carus invaded Mesopotamia unopposed and entered Ctesiphon, the Sasanian capital. Carus' sudden death, however, forced the Romans to withdraw, and soon thereafter the overthrow of Hormizd made Bahram secure. Numerous southern Persian rock sculptures depict Bahram wearing his winged crown, and several include his queen. Because female portraits a...
</Question>
<Choice>Bahram II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sasanian king (reigned 420–438). He was celebrated in literature, art, and folklore for his chivalry, romantic adventures, and huntsmanship.He was educated at the court of al-Mundhir, the Lakhmid Arab king of al-?ira, in Mesene, whose support helped him gain the throne after the assassination of his father, Yazdegerd I. He was apparently also supported by Mihr-Naresh, chief minister of Yazdegerd's last years, to whom Bahram later delegated much of the governmental administration.Bahram carried on an inconclusive war with the Romans (421–422), and in 427 he crushed an invasion in the east by th...
</Question>
<Choice>Bahram V</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Sasanian king (reigned 484–488), succeeding his brother Firuz I. Soon after he ascended the throne, Balash was threatened by the dominance of invading Hephthalites, a nomadic eastern tribe. Supported by Zarmihr, a feudal chief, Balash suppressed an uprising by his rebel brother Zareh. Later, however, he was abandoned by Zarmihr, and shortly afterward he was deposed and blinded. The crown was given to a son of Firuz, Kavadh I.
</Question>
<Choice>Balash</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor for three months in 238.A patrician, Balbinus was a Salian priest, twice a consul, and proconsul in Asia. In 238, when the Senate led a rebellion of the Italian cities against Maximinus (emperor 235–238), it placed the government in the hands of a board of 20, one of whom was Balbinus, and then chose Balbinus and Pupienus Maximus to be joint emperors. Pupienus, a former city prefect, was extremely unpopular with the people of Rome. When the enraged populace besieged the Senate and emperors in the Capitol, Balbinus and Pupienus extricated themselves by appointing as caesar the you...
</Question>
<Choice>Balbinus, Decimus Caelius Calvinus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(6th century BC), king of Persia in 522–521 BC.Bardiya was the son of Cyrus the Great of Persia. According to both the Greek historian Herodotus and the Persian king Darius's account in his inscription at Bisitun, Bardiya was murdered by his brother, King Cambyses, but was later successfully impersonated by Gaumata, a Magian, who was able to seize the throne when Cambyses died in 522 BC. The usurper reigned for only eight months, however, before he was slain by Darius and other Persian nobles suspicious of his origin. Certain modern historians consider that Darius, who succeeded to the throne,...
</Question>
<Choice>Bardiya</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
coregent of Babylon who was killed at the capture of the city by the Persians.Belshazzar had been known only from the biblical Book of Daniel (chapters 5, 7–8) and from Xenophon's Cyropaedia until 1854, when references to him were found in Babylonian cuneiform inscriptions. Though he is referred to in the Book of Daniel as the son of Nebuchadrezzar, the Babylonian inscriptions indicate that he was in fact the eldest son of Nabonidus, who was king of Babylon from 555 to 539, and of Nitocris, who was perhaps a daughter of Nebuchadrezzar. When Nabonidus went into exile (550), he entrusted Belshaz...
</Question>
<Choice>Belshazzar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
queen of Egypt, daughter of Ptolemy IX, the most strong-willed member of the royal family. She ruled during a period of violent civil strife.Daughter of either Cleopatra Selene or Cleopatra IV, Berenice first married her uncle, Ptolemy X, sometime before 101. After the death in 101 of the dowager queen, Cleopatra III, the widow of Ptolemy VIII, Berenice became full queen. In 87 Ptolemy X was expelled from Egypt by an insurrection of the people of Alexandria, who believed that he had assassinated the dowager queen. He recruited a mercenary army in Syria and, after returning to Egypt, plundered...
</Question>
<Choice>Berenice III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
one of the early kings of the Indian kingdom of Magadha. His expansion of the kingdom, especially his annexation of the kingdom of Anga to the east, is considered to have laid the foundations for the later expansion of the Mauryan empire. He is also known for his cultural achievements and was a great friend and protector of the Buddha. Bimbisara built the city of Rajagriha, famous in Buddhist writings. He was succeeded on the throne by his son Ajatashatru, who murdered his father to obtain power.
</Question>
<Choice>Bimbisara</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
ancient British queen who in AD 60 led a revolt against Roman rule.Boudicca's husband, Prasutagus, was king of the Iceni (in what is now Norfolk) as a client under Roman suzerainty. When Prasutagus died in 60 with no male heir, he left his private wealth to his two daughters and to the emperor Nero, trusting thereby to win imperial protection for his family. Instead, the Romans annexed his kingdom, humiliated his family, and plundered the chief tribesmen. While the provincial governor Suetonius Paulinus was absent in 60, Boudicca raised a rebellion throughout East Anglia. The insurgents burned...
</Question>
<Choice>Boudicca</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
celebrated Roman general and statesman, the conqueror of Gaul (58–50 BC), victor in the Civil War of 49–45 BC, and dictator (46–44 BC), who was launching a series of political and social reforms when he was assassinated by a group of nobles in the Senate House on the Ides of March.Caesar changed the course of the history of the Greco-Roman world decisively and irreversibly. The Greco-Roman society has been extinct for so long that most of the names of its great men mean little to the average, educated modern man. But Caesar's name, like Alexander's, is still on people's lips throughout the Chr...
</Question>
<Choice>Caesar, Julius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor from 37 to 41, in succession to Tiberius, who effected the transfer of the last legion that had been under a senatorial proconsul (in Africa) to an imperial legate, thus completing the emperor's monopoly of army command. Accounts of his reign by ancient historians are so biased against him that the truth is almost impossible to disentangle.Born Gaius Caesar, he became known as Caligula (Little Boot), a childhood nickname bestowed on him by the soldiers of his father, Germanicus Caesar, nephew and adoptive son of Tiberius. The deaths of his father in AD 19, of his mother, Agrippin...
</Question>
<Choice>Caligula</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
ruler of Anshanc. 600–559 BC. Cambyses was the son of Cyrus I and succeeded his father in Anshan (northwest of Susa in Elam) as a vassal of King Astyages of Media. According to the 5th-century-BC Greek historian Herodotus, Cambyses married a daughter of Astyages, by whom he became the father of Cyrus II the Great.
</Question>
<Choice>Cambyses I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Achaemenid king of Persia (reigned 529–522 BC), who conquered Egypt in 525; he was the eldest son of King Cyrus II the Great by Cassandane, daughter of a fellow Achaemenid. During his father's lifetime Cambyses was in charge of Babylonian affairs. In 538 he performed the ritual duties of a Babylonian king at the important New Year festival, and in 530, before Cyrus set out on his last campaign, he was appointed regent in Babylon.The conquest of Egypt, planned by Cyrus, was the major achievement of Cambyses' reign. The invasion took place during the reign of Psamtik III. Cambyses received assis...
</Question>
<Choice>Cambyses II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(reigned c. 321–c. 297 BCE), founder of the Mauryan dynasty and the first emperor to unify most of India under one administration. Credited with saving the country from maladministration and freeing it from foreign domination, he fasted to death in sorrow for his famine-stricken people.Chandragupta was born into a family left destitute by the death of his father, chief of the migrant Mauryas, in a border fray. His maternal uncles left him with a cowherd who brought him up as his own son. Later he was sold to a hunter to tend cattle. Purchased by a Brahman politician, Kautilya (also called Chan...
</Question>
<Choice>Candra Gupta</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor, ruling jointly with his father, Septimius Severus, from 198 to 211 and then alone from 211 until his assassination in 217. His principal achievements were his colossal baths in Rome and his edict of 212, giving Roman citizenship to all free inhabitants of the empire. Caracalla, whose reign contributed to the decay of the empire, has often been regarded as one of the most bloodthirsty tyrants in Roman history.Caracalla was the elder son of the future emperor Lucius Septimius Severus, a North African, and Julia Domna, a Syrian. He was originally named Bassianus, after his maternal...
</Question>
<Choice>Caracalla</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the British tribe of Trinovantes, and the son of Cunobelinus (q.v.).Caratacus' kingdom, embracing the Atrebates of Hampshire and probably the Dobunni of Gloucestershire, lay in the west. At the time of the Roman invasion of Britain during the reign of Claudius, he led the native resistance against Aulus Plautius (AD 43–47) and, after being defeated, withdrew into south Wales. He was finally defeated by Ostorius Scapula in AD 50, somewhere on the Welsh marches, in the territory of the Ordovices. He himself fled to the Brigantes, whose queen, Cartimandua, delivered him to the Romans. He...
</Question>
<Choice>Caratacus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor from AD 283 to 285.With the title of Caesar, he was sent by his father, the emperor Carus, to the army of the Rhine in 282. On his father's death in the summer of 283, Carinus became emperor in the West, his brother Numerian becoming emperor in the East. After a campaign on the Rhine, Carinus returned to Rome where, in September 284, he celebrated games in honour of Carus' victories in Persia the year before.Near Verona in the spring of 285, Carinus defeated Aurelius Julianus, the governor of Venetia, who had proclaimed himself emperor. Shortly afterward Carinus was killed by his...
</Question>
<Choice>Carinus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor 282–283.Carus was probably from either Gaul or Illyricum and had served as prefect of the guard to the emperor Probus (276–282), whom he succeeded. Like his predecessors, Carus adopted the name Marcus Aurelius as a part of his imperial title. After a brief Danube campaign he led his troops against the Sasanians, penetrating beyond the Tigris, where he died suddenly and mysteriously, allegedly struck by lightning. His sons Numerian and Carinus succeeded him.
</Question>
<Choice>Carus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
son of the Macedonian regent Antipater and king of Macedonia from 305 to 297.Cassander was one of the diadochoi (“successors”), the Macedonian generals who fought over the empire of Alexander the Great after his death in 323. After Antipater's death in 319, Cassander refused to acknowledge the new regent, Polyperchon. With the aid of Antigonus I Monophthalmus, ruler of Phrygia, Cassander seized Macedonia and most of Greece, including Athens (319–317). When Antigonus returned from the eastern provinces intending to reunite Alexander's empire under his own sovereignty, Cassander joined forces wi...
</Question>
<Choice>Cassander</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the Salian Franks, one of the first of the Merovingians and the father of Clovis I.The Salian Franks, in treaty with the Roman Empire, had settled in Belgica Secunda, between the Meuse and Somme rivers, making their capital at Tournai. Childeric's role as a barbarian ally of the Romans was important. He helped the Roman military commander Aegidius to repel the Visigoths near Orléans (463); at the request of Aegidius' successor, Count Paulus, he attacked the Visigoths again in 469. Soon afterward he cleared Anglo-Saxon pirates from the district southwest of Orléans around Angers. Childe...
</Question>
<Choice>Childeric I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
major political figure who solidified the power of the Zhou dynasty (1046–256 BCE) in its early years. Confucius esteemed Zhougong as a paragon for later Chinese rulers and ministers.Zhougong was a brother of the powerful Wuwang, the founder of the Zhou dynasty, whose reign Zhougong helped consolidate. Upon Wuwang's death, Zhougong resisted the temptation to seize the throne and chose instead to serve as counselor to Wuwang's young son Chengwang, whom he then began to train in the art of governing. No sooner had Zhougong assumed the role of regent, however, than a large rebellion broke out hea...
</Question>
<Choice>Chou-kung</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor (AD 41–54), who extended Roman rule in North Africa and made Britain a province.
</Question>
<Choice>Claudius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor in 268–270, whose major achievement was the decisive defeat of the Gothic invaders (hence the name Gothicus) of the Balkans in 269.Claudius was an army officer under the emperor Gallienus from 260 to 268—a period of devastation of much of the Roman Empire by invading tribes. Rising to the command of Gallienus' newly formed cavalry, Claudius succeeded to the throne upon the emperor's assassination in 268. The new ruler speedily suppressed the rebellion of the usurper Aureolus and drove from Italy the Alemanni tribe, which had been summoned by the insurgents.During his brief reign,...
</Question>
<Choice>Claudius Gothicus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spartan king from 519 BC to his death, a ruler who consolidated his city's position as the leading power in the Peloponnesus. He refused to commit Spartan forces overseas against the Persians but readily intervened in the affairs of his Greek rival, Athens. A member of the Agiad house, he succeeded his father Anaxandridas as king.In 510 he led an army to Athens and expelled the tyrant Hippias. Three years later at Athens he supported Isagoras, the leader of the oligarchs, against the democratic Cleisthenes. Both Cleomenes and Isagoras, however, were forced to withdraw. Next Cleomenes raised a...
</Question>
<Choice>Cleomenes I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spartan king (235–222) who reorganized Sparta's political structure and struggled unsuccessfully to destroy the Achaean League. A member of the Agiad house, he was the son of King Leonidas II. The conflict with the Achaean League under Aratus of Sicyon began in 229. In 227 Cleomenes defeated the Achaeans at Mt. Lycaeum and at Ladoceia near Megalopolis. The next year he captured Mantineia and severely defeated the Achaeans at Hecatombaeum, near Dyme. After Cleomenes took Pellene, Phlius, Argos, and other cities, Aratus was forced to call upon King Antigonus Doson of Macedonia for assistance. An...
</Question>
<Choice>Cleomenes III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek“Famous in Her Father”Egyptian queen, famous in history and drama as the lover of Julius Caesar and later the wife of Mark Antony. She became queen on the death of her father, Ptolemy XII, in 51 BC and ruled successively with her two brothers Ptolemy XIII (51–47) and Ptolemy XIV (47–44) and her son Ptolemy XV Caesar (44–30). After the Roman armies of Octavian (the future emperor Augustus) defeated their combined forces, Antony and Cleopatra committed suicide, and Egypt fell under Roman domination. Cleopatra actively influenced Roman politics at a crucial period, and she came to represent,...
</Question>
<Choice>Cleopatra</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the Franks and ruler of much of Gaul from 481 to 511, a key period during the transformation of the Roman Empire into Europe. His dynasty, the Merovingians, survived more than 200 years, until the rise of the Carolingians in the 8th century. While he was not the first Frankish king, he was the kingdom's political and religious founder.Clovis was the son of the pagan Frankish king Childeric and the Thuringian queen Basina. He succeeded his father in 481 as the ruler of the Salian Franks and other Frankish groups around Tournai (now in Belgium). Although the chronology of his reign is im...
</Question>
<Choice>Clovis I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor from 177 to 192 (sole emperor after 180). His brutal misrule precipitated civil strife that ended 84 years of stability and prosperity within the empire.In 177 Lucius was made coruler and heir to his father, the emperor Marcus Aurelius (reigned 161–180). Lucius joined Marcus in his campaign against invading German tribes along the Danube, but after the death of Marcus (March 180) he quickly came to terms with the Germans.Soon after he became sole ruler, Lucius changed his name to Marcus Aurelius Commodus Antoninus. In 182 Commodus' sister Lucilla conspired with a group of senator...
</Question>
<Choice>Commodus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor from 337 to 350.The youngest son of Constantine the Great (reigned 306–337), Constans was proclaimed caesar by his father on December 25, 333. When Constantine died on September 9, 337, Constans and his two brothers, Constantius II and Constantine II, each adopted the title of Augustus and divided the empire among themselves. Constans took control of Italy, Africa, and Illyricum (in the northwestern Balkans). In 340 Constantine II—ruler of Spain, Gaul, and Britain—invaded northern Italy but was defeated and killed by Constans's army at Aquileia. This victory gave Constans, who at...
</Question>
<Choice>Constans I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the first Roman emperor to profess Christianity. He not only initiated the evolution of the empire into a Christian state but also provided the impulse for a distinctively Christian culture that prepared the way for the growth of Byzantine and Western medieval culture.Constantine was born probably in the later AD 280s. A typical product of the military governing class of the later 3rd century, he was the son of Flavius Valerius Constantius, an army officer, and his wife (or concubine) Helena. In AD 293 his father was raised to the rank of Caesar, or deputy emperor (as Constantius I Chlorus), a...
</Question>
<Choice>Constantine I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor from 337 to 340.The second son of Constantine the Great (ruled 306–337), he was given the title of caesar by his father on March 1, 317. When Constantine the Great died in 337, Constantine II and his brothers, Constans and Constantius II, each adopted the title augustus and divided the empire among themselves. Constantine II became ruler of Britain, Gaul, and Spain. He soon claimed Italy and Africa from Constans and, early in 340, unexpectedly invaded Italy. Penetrating to Aquileia, Constantine was met by the vanguard of the army of Constans and was killed in the ensuing battle.
</Question>
<Choice>Constantine II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor and father of Constantine I the Great. As a member of a four-man ruling body (tetrarchy) created by the emperor Diocletian, Constantius held the title caesar from 293 to 305 and caesar augustus in 305–306.Of Illyrian descent, Constantius had a distinguished military career before serving as governor of Dalmatia (in modern Croatia). In 289 he left his concubine, Helena, mother of Constantine, and married Theodora, the stepdaughter of the emperor Maximian; with Theodora he had three children, Dalmatius, Constantius, and Constantia. On March 1, 293, Constantius was adopted by Maximi...
</Question>
<Choice>Constantius I Chlorus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor from AD 337 to 361, who at first shared power with his two brothers, Constantine II (d. 340) and Constans I (d. 350), but who was sole ruler from 353 to 361.The third son of Constantine I the Great and Fausta, Constantius served under his father as caesar from Nov. 8, 324, to Sept. 9, 337. When Constantine died on May 22, 337, the troops massacred many of his relatives, including Constantine's half-brother, Constantius, consul in 335 and father of the future emperor Julian. In Julian's Letter to the Athenians (361) he openly accuses Constantius of murdering his father. The histor...
</Question>
<Choice>Constantius II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor in 421.Constantius came from Naissus (modern Niš, Yugos.) in the province of Moesia. In 411, as magister militum (“master of the soldiers”) under the western Roman emperor Flavius Honorius (reigned 393–423), Constantius helped to overthrow the usurping emperor Constantine (Flavius Claudius Constantinus) at Arelate (modern Arles, Fr.). He drove the Visigoths from southern Gaul into Spain in 415 but later recalled the tribe and settled it in southwestern Gaul. In 417 he married the emperor's half sister Galla Placidia. Appointed coemperor of the West by Honorius, with the title aug...
</Question>
<Choice>Constantius III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
last king of Lydia (reigned c. 560–546), who was renowned for his great wealth. He conquered the Greeks of mainland Ionia (on the west coast of Anatolia) and was in turn subjugated by the Persians.A member of the Mermnad dynasty, Croesus succeeded to the throne of his father, Alyattes, after a struggle with his half brother. Croesus is said to have acted as viceroy and commander in chief before his father's death. He completed the conquest of mainland Ionia by capturing Ephesus and other cities in western Anatolia. Lack of sea power forced him to form alliances with, rather than conquer, the i...
</Question>
<Choice>Croesus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Media (located in what is now northwestern Iran), who reigned from 625 to 585 BC. According to the 5th-century-BC Greek historian Herodotus, Cyaxares renewed the war with the Assyrians after his father, Phraortes, had been slain in battle. While besieging Nineveh, he was attacked and defeated by a great army of Scythians, who then ruled Media (653–625) until their chiefs were slain by Cyaxares at a banquet. It was probably Cyaxares, not his father, as is maintained by Herodotus, who united the tribes of ancient Iran. He also reorganized the Median army, dividing it into spearmen, bowme...
</Question>
<Choice>Cyaxares</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
conqueror who founded the Achaemenian empire, centred on Persia and comprising the Near East from the Aegean Sea eastward to the Indus River. He is also remembered in the Cyrus legend—first recorded by Xenophon, Greek soldier and author, in his Cyropaedia—as a tolerant and ideal monarch who was called the father of his people by the ancient Persians. In the Bible he is the liberator of the Jews who were captive in Babylonia.
</Question>
<Choice>Cyrus II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Persia in 522–486 BC, one of the greatest rulers of the Achaemenid dynasty, who was noted for his administrative genius and for his great building projects. Darius attempted several times to conquer Greece; his fleet was destroyed by a storm in 492, and the Athenians defeated his army at Marathon in 490.
</Question>
<Choice>Darius I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the last king (reigned 336–330 BC) of the Achaemenid dynasty.Darius belonged to a collateral branch of the royal family and was placed on the throne by the eunuch Bagoas, who had poisoned the two previous kings, Artaxerxes III and Arses. When Darius asserted his independence, Bagoas also attempted his murder but was forced by the king to drink the poison himself.In 337 Philip II of Macedon had formed the League of Corinth for the purpose of liberating the Greek cities under Achaemenid rule and, early in 336, had sent an advance force into Asia Minor. In July, however, he was assassinated, perh...
</Question>
<Choice>Darius III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
second of the Israelite kings (after Saul), reigning c. 1000 to c. 962 BC, who established a united kingdom over all Israel, with Jerusalem as its capital. In Jewish tradition he became the ideal king, the founder of an enduring dynasty, around whose figure and reign clustered messianic expectations of the people of Israel. Since he was a symbol of fulfillment in the future, the New Testament writers emphasized that Jesus was of the lineage of David. He was also held in high esteem in the Islamic tradition.
</Question>
<Choice>David</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the Dacians, a people who lived in the territory known presently as Romania.Decebalus unified the various Dacian tribes into one nation and led them in wars against the Roman emperors Domitian and Trajan. When Decebalus came to power in 85, he immediately organized an army and attacked the Roman province of Moesia (southeastern Balkans), killing its governor, Oppius Sabinus. In 86 or 87 Decebalus annihilated a Roman army under Cornelius Fuscus, Domitian's praetorian praefect, but he was severely defeated by Tettius Julianus in 88. Fortunately for Decebalus, a pretender rebelled against...
</Question>
<Choice>Decebalus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor (249–251) who fought the Gothic invasion of Moesia and instituted the first organized persecution of Christians throughout the empire.Although Decius's origins are not known, it is certain that he was a senator and a consul before acceding to the throne. About 245 the emperor Philip the Arabian entrusted him with a command on the Danube; there, in 249, Decius was proclaimed emperor, allegedly against his will. After killing Philip in battle near Verona, Decius took the field against the Goths, who had crossed the Danube and overrun Moesia and Thrace. The final engagement in this...
</Question>
<Choice>Decius, Gaius Messius Quintus Trajanus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Bactria who was the son and successor of Euthydemus. The historical evidence for Demetrius' reign is slight and open to varying interpretations. According to some scholars, he ruled from about 190 to about 167, when he was killed by Eucratides, who then became king. Earlier, Demetrius had made such extensive conquests in northern India that for a brief time he virtually reestablished there the great Mauryan Empire that had collapsed about 184. Other scholars, however, contend that it was a younger Demetrius (likewise a Bactrian king but not directly related to the son of Euthydemus) wh...
</Question>
<Choice>Demetrius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Macedonia from 294 to 288 BC.Demetrius was the son of Alexander the Great's general Antigonus I Monophthalmus, in whose campaigns he commanded with distinction and whose empire, based in Asia, he attempted to rebuild. Unsuccessful against Ptolemy I Soter, satrap of Egypt, and against the Nabataeans, he liberated Athens from the Macedonian Cassander in 307 BC and in 306 decisively defeated Ptolemy at Salamis (Cyprus). From his unsuccessful siege of Rhodes (305) he won the title Poliorcetes (“the Besieger”). Recalled by his father from Greece, he fought in the Battle of Ipsus, in which h...
</Question>
<Choice>Demetrius I Poliorcetes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek“Saviour”king of Syria from 162 to 150 BC. He was one of the line of rulers of the Seleucid dynasty, founded in 312 by a Macedonian successor of Alexander the Great.The son of King Seleucus IV Philopator (reigned 187 to 175), Demetrius was sent to Rome as a hostage during his father's reign. While he was away, Syria came under the rule of his uncle, Antiochus IV Ephiphanes (d. 164), and then of his cousin, Antiochus V. Aided by the Greek statesman and historian Polybius, Demetrius escaped from Rome in 162 and returned to Syria to claim the throne. He defeated the rebel general Timarchus a...
</Question>
<Choice>Demetrius I Soter</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Macedonia from 239 to 229 BC.Demetrius gained distinction as a boy by defeating and dethroning Alexander of Epirus, thus saving Macedonia (c. 263). On his accession he was faced by an Aetolian and Achaean coalition, later joined by an Epirote League. Thus threatened, he was drawn northward by a Dardanian invasion, and after a defeat there he died. His failure seriously weakened both kingdom and monarchy.
</Question>
<Choice>Demetrius II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek“Victor”king of Syria from 145 to 139 and from 129 to 125 BC.The son of King Demetrius I Soter, he went into exile when his father was killed fighting the usurper Alexander Balas in 150. Demetrius returned to Syria (147) with an army of Cretan mercenaries, deposed Balas in 145, and installed himself on the throne. In 140 he drove back a Parthian invasion but was defeated and captured by the Parthians in 139. Demetrius was released from captivity in 129 and returned to Syria, but, during his second reign, he controlled only part of the kingdom. He was assassinated about four years later.
</Question>
<Choice>Demetrius II Nicator</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
wealthy Roman senator who became emperor (March 28–June 1, 193) by being the highest bidder in an auction for the support of the Praetorian Guard.A member of one of the most prominent families of Mediolanum (now Milan), Didius Severus Julianus had a long and distinguished public career. After commanding the legion at Mogontiacum (now Mainz), about 167, he governed northeastern Gaul, Dalmatia, the lower Rhine, Bithynia, and Africa. He was consul in 175.During the political disturbances of Commodus' reign he was banished to Mediolanum. Commodus was murdered on the eve of Jan. 1, 193, however, an...
</Question>
<Choice>Didius Julianus, Marcus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor (284–305), who restored efficient government to the empire after the near anarchy of the 3rd century. His reorganization of the fiscal, administrative, and military machinery of the empire laid the foundation for the Byzantine Empire in the East and temporarily shored up the decaying empire in the West. His reign is also noted for the last great persecution of the Christians.
</Question>
<Choice>Diocletian</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
satrap (governor) of the Seleucid province of Bactria, who, with his son of the same name, founded the Greek kingdom of Bactria.At first subject to the Seleucid king Antiochus I and later to Antiochus II, Diodotus rebelled in about 250 and took the title of king. Little is known of his reign, but, according to some scholars, the Seleucid king Seleucus II, in order to secure Diodotus' friendship, married one of his sisters to him during a time (246) when the Seleucid Empire was in chaos. Diodotus was succeeded by his son, Diodotus II, and after his death was called by the cult-name Soter (Savio...
</Question>
<Choice>Diodotus I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Bactria, the son and successor of Diodotus I.Although his father's freedom from Seleucid control is uncertain, Diodotus II unquestionably ruled as an independent king and issued coinage in his own name. He further proclaimed the independence of the kingdom of Bactria by entering into an alliance with the Parthians against Seleucus II, in contrast with his father's friendly policy toward the Seleucid Kingdom. At an uncertain date (perhaps c. 235), Diodotus II was overthrown by the usurper Euthydemus.
</Question>
<Choice>Diodotus II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
second king of the 3rd dynasty (c. 2650–c. 2575 BCE) of ancient Egypt, who undertook the construction of the earliest important stone building in Egypt. His reign, which probably lasted 19 years, was marked by great technological innovation in the use of stone architecture. His minister, Imhotep, a talented architect and physician, was himself deified in later periods.Djoser probably succeeded his brother to the throne. Through his mother, he was related to the last ruler of the 2nd dynasty (c. 2775–c. 2650). With the help of Imhotep, the king erected a funerary complex at ?aqqarah, outside th...
</Question>
<Choice>Djoser</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor (AD 81–96), known chiefly for the reign of terror under which prominent members of the Senate lived during his last years.Titus Flavius Domitianus was the second son of the future emperor Vespasian and Flavia Domitilla. During the civil war of AD 69 over the imperial crown, Domitian remained unharmed in Rome, but on December 18 he took refuge in the Capitol with his uncle Flavius Sabinus, escaping into hiding when the Capitol was stormed by supporters of Vitellius. On the entry of his father's supporters into Rome two days later he was saluted as Caesar, and he became praetor nex...
</Question>
<Choice>Domitian</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor from 218 to 222, notable chiefly for his eccentric behaviour.The family of his mother, Julia Soaemias, were hereditary high priests of the god Baal at Emesa (in ancient Syria), worshiped in that locality under the name Elah-Gabal (thus Elagabalus). The emperor Caracalla (211–217), Bassianus's cousin, was murdered in 217 and replaced by the praetorian prefect Macrinus. Bassianus's mother and his grandmother, Julia Maesa, won the support of the nearby troops by passing him off as an illegitimate son of Caracalla, whose name he assumed for official purposes. Soon thereafter (218) th...
</Question>
<Choice>Elagabalus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the Ostrogoths, the ruler of a vast empire in Ukraine. Although the exact limits of his territory are obscure, it evidently stretched south of the Pripet Marshes between the Don and Dniester rivers.The only certain facts about Ermanaric are that his great deeds caused him to be feared by neighbouring peoples and that he committed suicide because he despaired of successfully resisting the Huns, who invaded his territories in the 370s. His kingdom was thereupon destroyed and his people became subject to the Huns for about 75 years.At an early date Ermanaric became the centre of popular t...
</Question>
<Choice>Ermanaric</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the last important king of Greek Bactria.Called “the Great” on the coins he minted, Eucratides probably came to power in a coup. Much of his reign was spent in wars against pretenders to the throne and neighbouring rulers. “Demetrius, king of the Indians,” an heir of Euthydemus I, besieged him for five months, but Eucratides escaped and eventually triumphed. Near the end of his reign, he invaded and conquered Paropamisadae and Gandhara in northwest India. While returning home, he was assassinated and his body desecrated by a son, perhaps Plato Epiphanes (“God Manifest”), the rarity of whose co...
</Question>
<Choice>Eucratides</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Pergamum from 197 until his death. A brilliant statesman, he brought his small kingdom to the peak of its power and did more than any other Attalid monarch to make Pergamum a great centre of Greek culture in the East.Eumenes was the eldest son and successor of Attalus I Soter (ruled 241–197), and he continued his father's policy of cooperation with Rome. His military skill contributed substantially to the victory of Roman and Pergamene forces over the Seleucid king Antiochus III in the battle of Magnesia, in Lydia (autumn of 190). As his reward Eumenes was given control over the Thraci...
</Question>
<Choice>Eumenes II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of a great Visigothic realm (usually called the kingdom of Toulouse) in the western part of the Roman Empire that included what is now southwestern France (south of the Loire and west of the Rhône) and most of Spain. He is best known for the code of law that bears his name, the Code of Euric.Euric ascended the throne after assassinating his brother, King Theodoric II, at the Visigothic capital of Toulouse (466). He ruled as a federate of the Roman Empire until 475, when he was recognized as an independent king. He continued to defy Roman authority by extending his boundaries in Gaul and o...
</Question>
<Choice>Euric</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Bactria. At first he was probably a satrap (governor) of the Bactrian king Diodotus II, whom he later killed and whose throne he usurped. In 208 he was attacked by the Seleucid king Antiochus III, and a long war was fought between them. Euthydemus, having failed in his attempt to defend the line of the Arius (Harirud) River, fell back to his capital, Bactra (probably Balkh in northern Afghanistan), where he withstood a two-year siege. Finally a peace was concluded by which Euthydemus kept his kingdom while acknowledging Seleucid overlordship. Later, Euthydemus took territory from Parth...
</Question>
<Choice>Euthydemus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman commander and statesman whose cautious delaying tactics (whence the nickname Cunctator, meaning “delayer,” which was not his official cognomen) during the early stages of the Second Punic War (218–201) gave Rome time to recover its strength and take the offensive against the invading Carthaginian army of Hannibal. Fabianism has come to mean a gradual or cautious policy.Fabius was consul in 233 and 228 and censor in 230. He may have been a Roman emissary to Carthage in 218 to demand reparations for Hannibal's seizure of Saguntum, in Spain. After Hannibal's victory over the Romans at Lake...
</Question>
<Choice>Fabius Maximus Cunctator, Quintus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the Vandals and the Alani (428–477) who conquered a large part of Roman Africa and in 455 sacked Rome.Gaiseric succeeded his brother Gunderic at a time when the Vandals were settled in Baetica (modern Andalusia, Spain). In May 428 Gaiseric transported all his people, purported by him to number 80,000, to Africa. Evidently he was invited to Africa by the governor, Count Bonifacius, who wished to use the military strength of the Vandals in his struggle against the imperial government.Gaiseric caused great devastation as he moved eastward from the Strait of Gibraltar across Africa. He tur...
</Question>
<Choice>Gaiseric</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor for seven months (AD 68–69), whose administration was priggishly upright, though his advisers allegedly were corrupt.Galba was the son of the consul Gaius Sulpicius Galba and Mummia Achaica, and in addition to great wealth and ancient lineage he enjoyed the favour of the emperors Augustus and Tiberius. He began his senatorial career before the normal age, became consul (AD 33), received command of the Upper German army (40–42), and served a proconsulship in Africa (44–45).Galba was appointed governor of Nearer Spain in 60 and served in that post for eight years. In 68, believing...
</Question>
<Choice>Galba</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor from 305 to 311, notorious for his persecution of Christians.Galerius was born of humble parentage and had a distinguished military career. On March 1, 293, he was nominated as caesar by the emperor Diocletian, who governed the Eastern part of the empire. Galerius divorced his wife and married Diocletian's daughter, Valeria. After ruling from Egypt from 293 to 295, Galerius assumed command of defensive operations against the Sasanians in 297. After being defeated, he then won a decisive victory that increased his influence with Diocletian. Galerius next proceeded to the Balkans a...
</Question>
<Choice>Galerius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor jointly with his father, Valerian, from 253 until 260, then sole emperor to 268.Gallienus ruled an empire that was disintegrating under pressures from foreign invaders. The Senate proclaimed him co-emperor because it saw that no one man could run the vast military operations needed to defend the empire. Valerian took charge of the eastern frontiers, while Gallienus fought a series of campaigns against the Goths on the Rhine and defeated the Alemanni at Milan in 258. He next crushed the successive revolts of Ingenuus and Regalianus in Illyricum. In June 260 Valerian was taken pris...
</Question>
<Choice>Gallienus, Publius Licinius Egnatius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor from 251 to 253.Gallus came from an ancient family of Perusia (modern Perugia, Italy), whose ancestry could be traced to the pre-Roman Etruscan aristocracy. He served the emperor Decius with loyalty and distinction as legate of Moesia and was proclaimed emperor after the defeat and death (June 251) of Decius at the hands of the Goths. Gallus then concluded an unfavourable treaty with the enemy. He adopted Decius's son Hostilian as his coruler and at the same time made his own son, Volusianus, a secondary and later coemperor. Hostilian died of plague shortly after receiving his ti...
</Question>
<Choice>Gallus, Gaius Vibius Trebonianus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the first woman ruler of China, wife of Gaozu, the first emperor (reigned 206–195 BC) of the Han dynasty (206 BC–AD 220).After Gaozu's death, his and Gaohou's young son, the emperor Huidi (reigned 195–188 BC), ascended the throne. Gaohou, whose ambition had spurred her husband's rise to power, acted as regent and seized real power for herself. A cruel, vindictive woman, she consolidated her position by ignoring members of Gaozu's family and promoting her own relatives to important posts.Following Huidi's death, Gaohou arranged for another infant to succeed him, but when the new young ruler beg...
</Question>
<Choice>Gaohou</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor from 209 to 211, jointly with his father, Septimius Severus (reigned 193–211), and his brother, Caracalla (reigned 198–217). The younger son of Septimius Severus and Julia Domna, he was given the title caesar on Jan. 28, 198, when his elder brother Caracalla became joint emperor (as augustus) with their father. In 210 Geta was himself made an augustus, and he became coemperor upon his father's death at Eboracum (present-day York, Eng.) in February 211. The furious rivalry that developed between the brothers remained concealed from public view as long as their father lived, but, a...
</Question>
<Choice>Geta, Publius Septimius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor for three weeks in March to April 238.Gordian was an elderly senator with a taste for literature. The Greek writer Flavius Philostratus dedicated his Lives of the Sophists to him. Early in 238, when Gordian was proconsul in Africa, a group of wealthy young landowners resisted and killed the tax collectors who had been sent to Africa by the emperor Maximinus (reigned 235–238). The insurgents proclaimed Gordian emperor, and the Senate recognized him. Gordian killed himself upon learning of the death of his son and coruler, Gordian II, in a battle against the governor of Numidia, Ca...
</Question>
<Choice>Gordian I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor who ruled jointly for three weeks in March-April 238 with his father, Gordian I. He was killed in a battle with Capellianus, governor of Numidia.
</Question>
<Choice>Gordian II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor from 238 to 244.After the deaths of the joint emperors Gordian I and Gordian II in 238, the Roman Senate proclaimed two elderly senators, Pupienus and Balbinus, joint emperors. However, the people and the Praetorian Guard in Rome distrusted the Senate's nominees and insisted on making the 13-year-old Gordian (grandson of Gordian I and nephew of Gordian II) caesar and heir to the throne. After his own troops murdered the deposed emperor Maximinus (reigned 235–238), the Praetorian Guard rioted, killed Pupienus and Balbinus, and in August 238 proclaimed the young Gordian sole empero...
</Question>
<Choice>Gordian III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Parthia (reigned 91–87 or 91–81/80 BC).Gotarzes first appeared as “satrap of satraps” under the Parthian king Mithradates II in a Greek inscription at Bisitun, Iran. A name carved nearby, Gotarses Geopothros (Son of Gew), may also represent him (or Gotarzes II, according to some scholars). While Mithradates was preoccupied with Rome, Gotarzes established himself as an independent monarch in Babylonia, and after Mithradates' death Gotarzes remained, with his queen, Asibatum, as sole ruler of the Parthian Empire. Not long afterward, however, Mithradates' son Orodes I asserted his heredit...
</Question>
<Choice>Gotarzes I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor from 367 to 383. During part of his reign he shared this office with his father, Valentinian I (reigned 364–375), and his uncle Valens (reigned 364–378). By proclaiming the eight-year-old Gratian as Augustus (coruler), his father sought to assure a peaceful succession to imperial power. The boy's education was entrusted to the poet Ausonius, whom he appointed praetorian prefect. Upon the death of Valentinian I (November 17, 375), Gratian was appointed sole ruler of the West. Shortly thereafter he recognized as a colleague his four-year-old half brother, Valentinian, who had been...
</Question>
<Choice>Gratian</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
barbarian general during the last days of the Roman Empire in the west, and king of the Burgundians (c. 474–516).The nephew of the barbarian emperor-maker Ricimer, Gundobad briefly held the supreme military command in the Roman service. In 473 he emulated his uncle when he himself placed a puppet, Glycerius, on the throne of Ravenna, but the subsequent deposition of Glycerius by Julius Nepos, the appointee of the eastern emperor, sent Gundobad fleeing back to his Burgundians. After becoming joint ruler (with his brothers) of the Burgundians, he murdered his brother Chilperic; the latter's daug...
</Question>
<Choice>Gundobad</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Lydia, in western Anatolia (now Turkey), from about 680 to about 652 BC; he founded the Mermnad dynasty and made his kingdom a military power.According to all the ancient sources, Gyges came to the throne after slaying King Candaules and marrying his queen, but there are several versions of the event itself. Herodotus wrote that Candaules, who was inordinately proud of his wife's beauty, compelled Gyges to see her nude. She caught Gyges spying on her and forced him on pain of death to kill her husband. In the standard version of Plato's Republic, Gyges was a shepherd who found a ring t...
</Question>
<Choice>Gyges</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor (AD 117–138), the emperor Trajan's nephew and successor, who was a cultivated admirer of Greek civilization and who unified and consolidated Rome's vast empire.
</Question>
<Choice>Hadrian</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
sixth and best-known ruler of the 1st (Amorite) dynasty of Babylon (reigning c. 1792–50 BC), noted for his surviving set of laws, once considered the oldest promulgation of laws in human history. SeeHammurabi, Code of.Like all the kings of his dynasty except his father and grandfather, Hammurabi bore a tribal Amorite name belonging to the Amnanum. Only scanty information exists about his immediate family: his father, Sin-muballit; his sister, Iltani; and his firstborn son and successor, Samsuiluna, are known by name.When Hammurabi succeeded Sin-muballit about 1792 BC he was still young, but, a...
</Question>
<Choice>Hammurabi</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hittite king during the New Kingdom (reigned c. 1286–c. 1265 BC); he came to power by overthrowing his nephew Urhi-Teshub (Mursilis III).The events of Hattusilis' accession are known from his autobiography, a remarkable document designed to justify the new king's actions. The change of rulers seems to have caused no serious upheavals in the political fabric of the empire, perhaps because Urhi-Teshub was both inexperienced and unpopular. Except for some military action in the Arzawa lands in southwestern Anatolia, the regime of Hattusilis and his influential wife, Puduhepa, was generally one of...
</Question>
<Choice>Hattusilis III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman empress who was the reputed discoverer of Christ's cross.Helena was married to the Roman emperor Constantius I Chlorus, who renounced her for political reasons. When her son Constantine I the Great became emperor at York (306), he made her empress dowager, and under his influence she later became a Christian. She was devoted to her eldest grandson, Crispus Caesar, whom Constantine made titular ruler of Gaul, but a mysterious embroilment in the imperial family culminated with the execution of Crispus and Fausta, Constantine's second wife and Crispus's stepmother. Thereafter, the story bec...
</Question>
<Choice>Helena, Saint</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
ancient Egyptian army officer and high priest of Amon at Karnak (Thebes), who founded a dynasty of priest-kings that ruled southern Egypt when the country became disunited in the last years of the 20th dynasty (1190–1075 BCE).Herihor's origins are altogether obscure. He is believed to have advanced through the military ranks during the troubled reign of Ramses XI, the last king of the 20th dynasty. It was probably Herihor who expelled the viceroy of Kush from Thebes around the 19th year of Ramses' reign. At the same time, he began a new dating scheme, probably to mark his own rise to power.Her...
</Question>
<Choice>Herihor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman-appointed king of Judaea (37–4 BC), who built many fortresses, aqueducts, theatres, and other public buildings and generally raised the prosperity of his land but who was the centre of political and family intrigues in his later years. The New Testament portrays him as a tyrant, into whose kingdom Jesus of Nazareth was born.Herod was born in southern Palestine; his father, Antipater, was an Edomite (an Arab from the region between the Dead Sea and the Gulf of Aqaba). Antipater was a man of great influence and wealth, who increased both by marrying the daughter of a noble from Petra (in s...
</Question>
<Choice>Herod</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Judaea (AD 41–44), a clever diplomat who through his friendship with the Roman imperial family obtained the kingdom of his grandfather, Herod I the Great. He displayed great acumen in conciliating the Romans and Jews.When Antipater, the son of Herod and the father of Agrippa, was executed by the suspicious Herod, Agrippa was sent to Rome for education and safety. There he grew up in company with the emperor Tiberius's son Drusus. After his mother's death he quickly spent his family's wealth and acquired serious debts. When Drusus died in AD 23, Agrippa left Rome, settling near Beersheb...
</Question>
<Choice>Herod Agrippa I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
son and principal heir of Herod I the Great as king of Judaea, deposed by Rome because of his unpopularity with the Jews.Named in his father's will as ruler of the largest part of the Judaean kingdom—Judaea proper, Idumaea, and Samaria—Archelaus went to Rome (4 BC) to defend his title against the claims of his brothers Philip and Antipas before the emperor Augustus. Augustus confirmed him in possession of the largest portion but did not recognize him as king, giving him instead the lesser title of ethnarch to emphasize his dependence on Rome.Archelaus was half Idumaean and half Samaritan and,...
</Question>
<Choice>Herod Archelaus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
son of Ahaz, and the 13th successor of David as king of Judah at Jerusalem. The dates of his reign are often given as about 715 to about 686 BC, but inconsistencies in biblical and Assyrian cuneiform records have yielded a wide range of possible dates.Hezekiah reigned at a time when the Assyrian empire was consolidating its control of Palestine and Syria. His father had placed Judah under Assyrian suzerainty in 735 BC. Hezekiah may have taken part in a rebellion against King Sargon II of Assyria (reigned 721–705 BC), which the Assyrians apparently crushed in the year 710. At the accession of S...
</Question>
<Choice>Hezekiah</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor in the West from 393 to 423, a period when much of the Western Empire was overrun by invading tribes and Rome was captured and plundered by the Visigoths. The younger son of Theodosius I (emperor 379–395) and Aelia Flacilla, Honorius was elevated to the rank of augustus by Theodosius on Jan. 23, 393, and became sole ruler of the West at age 10, upon his father's death (Jan. 17, 395). His brother Arcadius was the Eastern emperor.During the first half of Honorius' reign, power was exercised by his master of soldiers, Flavius Stilicho. In 398 the emperor married Stilicho's daughter...
</Question>
<Choice>Honorius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
last king (reigned 1319–1292 BCE) of the 18th dynasty of ancient Egypt; he continued the restoration of the traditional Amon religion that a previous ruler, Akhenaton, had replaced with the worship of the god Aton.Having served as commander of the army under Tutankhamen, Horemheb came to the throne after the ephemeral reign of Ay and completed the dismantling of the temples of the Aton built at Karnak in order to suppress what was considered an aberrant religion. At the same time, he restored many of the damaged reliefs and statues portraying the god Amon and erected three of the largest pylon...
</Question>
<Choice>Horemheb</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the Sasanian empire (reigned AD 272–273); he was the son and successor of Shapur I. Known before his accession as Hormizd-Ardashir, he acted as viceroy of the Persian province of Armenia. During Shapur's capture of Antioch from the Romans after 256, Hormizd exercised important command, presumably earning his surname at that time. During his brief reign he was apparently tolerant of the activities of the religious leader Mani, founder of Manichaeism.
</Question>
<Choice>Hormizd I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
posthumous name (shi) of the seventh emperor of the Bei (Northern) Wei dynasty (386–534/535), which dominated much of North China during part of the chaotic 360-year period between the end of the Han dynasty (206 BC–AD 220) and the founding of Sui rule (581–618). Xiaowendi sinicized his tribal kinsmen, making the Bei Wei into a Chinese-style dynasty. He also instituted a land-reform program that has persisted in its basic form into modern times.When Xiaowendi ascended the throne in 471 (the actual power was first in the hands of his grandmother until she died in 490), the nomadic Tuoba tribal...
</Question>
<Choice>Hsiao-wen ti</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
posthumous name (shi) of the eighth emperor (reigned 74–49/48 BC) of the Han dynasty (206 BC–AD 220), who ascended the throne when the designated heir apparent behaved indecorously during mourning ceremonies for his father. The Xuandi emperor strove to abate the harshness and widespread corruption that had marked the preceding two reigns. Under him the Han dynasty probably attained its greatest prosperity. Even the Xiongnu tribes on the northwest frontiers, who had been warring with China for more than two centuries, were persuaded to cease their raids during his reign. He was succeeded by his...
</Question>
<Choice>Hsüan Ti</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
in the Old Testament (II Kings 24), son of King Jehoiakim and king of Judah. He came to the throne at the age of 18 in the midst of the Chaldean invasion of Judah and reigned three months. He was forced to surrender to Nebuchadrezzar II and was taken to Babylon (597 BC), along with 10,000 of his subjects. Nearly 40 years later Nebuchadrezzar died, and his successor released Jehoiachin.
</Question>
<Choice>Jehoiachin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
in the Old Testament (II Kings 23:34–24:17; Jer. 22:13–19; II Chron. 36:4–8), son of King Josiah and king of Judah (c. 609–598 BC). When Josiah died at Megiddo, his younger son, Jehoahaz (or Shallum), was chosen king by the Judahites, but the Egyptian conqueror Necho took Jehoahaz to Egypt and made Jehoiakim king. Jehoiakim reigned under the protection of Necho for some time and paid heavy tribute. When the new Chaldean Empire under Nebuchadrezzar II defeated Egypt at the Battle of Carchemish (605), however, Jehoiakim changed his allegiance from the Egyptian king to Nebuchadrezzar. He remained...
</Question>
<Choice>Jehoiakim</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king (c. 842–815 BC) of Israel. He was a commander of chariots for the king of Israel, Ahab, and his son Jehoram, on Israel's frontier facing Damascus and Assyria. Ahab, son of King Omri, was eventually killed in a war with Assyria; during Jehoram's rule, Jehu accepted the invitation of the prophet Elisha, Elijah's successor, to lead a coup to overthrow the dynasty of Omri (II Kings 9–10). The prophetic party, headed by Elisha, was an old adversary of the royal house, as shown by the stories of Ahab and Elijah (I Kings 17–19). King Omri had built Samaria, and, thanks to an alliance with the Ph...
</Question>
<Choice>Jehu</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
high priest and ruler of the Jewish nation from 135/134 to 104 BC. Under his reign the Hasmonean kingdom of Judaea in ancient Palestine attained power and great prosperity, and the Pharisees, a scholarly sect with popular backing, and the Sadducees, an aristocratic sect that comprised the priesthood, became well-defined religious parties.Hyrcanus was the youngest son of Simon Maccabeus and thus a member of the Hasmonean dynasty (so-called after an ancestor named Hasmoneus). In 137 BC he and his brother Judas commanded the force that heroically repelled the invasion of Judaea led by Cendebeus,...
</Question>
<Choice>John Hyrcanus I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
high priest of Judaea from 76 to 40 BC, and, with his brother Aristobulus II, last of the Maccabean (Hasmonean) dynastic rulers. Under Hyrcanus' vacillating leadership, Judaea (southern of the three traditional divisions of ancient Palestine, today mostly in Israel) fell into vassalage to Rome.When his father, Alexander Jannaeus, died in 76, Hyrcanus was appointed high priest, and on his mother's death in 67 he assumed the rulership of Judaea. After a troubled reign of three months, his warlike brother Aristobulus drove him from power.Hyrcanus sought counsel from Antipater, satrap of Idumaea (...
</Question>
<Choice>John Hyrcanus II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Judah (c. 640–609 BC), who set in motion a reformation that bears his name and that left an indelible mark on Israel's religious traditions (2 Kings 22–23:30).Josiah was the grandson of Manasseh, king of Judah, and ascended the throne at age eight after the assassination of his father, Amon, in 641. For a century, ever since Ahaz, Judah had been a vassal of the Assyrian empire. Imperial policy imposed alien cults on Judah that suppressed or obscured the Israelite religious identity. After the death of King Ashurbanipal, the Assyrian empire fell into chaos; it could no longer assert its...
</Question>
<Choice>Josiah</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor from 363 to 364.Jovian took part in the expedition of the emperor Julian against Sasanian Persia. He held the rank of senior staff officer and was proclaimed emperor by his troops after Julian was killed on June 26, 363. To extricate his army from Persia, the new ruler immediately concluded a peace, ceding to the Persians all Roman territory east of the Tigris River, together with the cities of Singara (modern Sinjar, Iraq) and Nisibis (modern Nusaybin, Turkey). Some of Jovian's contemporaries, believing that the army could have fought its way out, considered this treaty to be di...
</Question>
<Choice>Jovian</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Numidia from 118 to 105, who struggled to free his North African kingdom from Roman rule.Jugurtha was the illegitimate grandson of Masinissa (d. 148), under whom Numidia had become a Roman ally, and the nephew of Masinissa's successor, Micipsa. Jugurtha became so popular among the Numidians that Micipsa tried to eliminate his influence by sending him in 134 to assist the Roman general Scipio Africanus the Younger in the siege of Numantia (Spain). Jugurtha, however, established close relations with Scipio, who was the hereditary patron of Numidia and who probably persuaded Micipsa to ad...
</Question>
<Choice>Jugurtha</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor from AD 361 to 363, nephew of Constantine the Great, and noted scholar and military leader who was proclaimed emperor by his troops. A persistent enemy of Christianity, he publicly announced his conversion to paganism in 361, thus acquiring the epithet “the Apostate.”
</Question>
<Choice>Julian</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
greatest king of the Kushan dynasty that ruled over the northern part of the Indian subcontinent, Afghanistan, and possibly areas of Central Asia north of the Kashmir region. He is, however, chiefly remembered as a great patron of Buddhism.Most of what is known about Kaniska derives from Chinese sources, particularly Buddhist writings. When Kaniska came to the throne is uncertain. His accession has been estimated as occurring between 78 and 144 CE; his reign is believed to have lasted 23 years. The year 78 marks the beginning of the Shaka era, a system of dating that Kaniska might have initiat...
</Question>
<Choice>Kaniska</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
temple name (miaohao) of the founder and first emperor of the Han dynasty (206 BC–AD 220), under which the Chinese imperial system assumed most of the characteristics that it was to retain until it was overthrown in 1911/12. He reigned from 206 to 195 BC. His wife, the empress Gaohou (reigned 188–180 BC), became the first female ruler of China.Born of a peasant family, Liu Bang began his career as a police officer under the Qin dynasty (221–207 BC). He turned rebel after the death (210 BC) of the Qin emperor Shihuangdi, who had been the first to unify China. The rebels were under the nominal l...
</Question>
<Choice>Kao-tsu</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
fourth king of the 4th dynasty (c. 2575–c. 2465 BCE) of ancient Egypt and builder of the second of the three Pyramids of Giza.Khafre was the son of King Khufu and succeeded the short-lived Redjedef, probably his elder brother. He married his sister Khamerernebti, Meresankh III, and perhaps two other queens. Although many of his relatives were hastily buried in cheap tombs, his own pyramid was almost as vast as the Great Pyramid of his father. Khafre's valley temple, linked to the pyramid by a causeway, was constructed of great monolithic blocks of granite and contained remarkable statues of th...
</Question>
<Choice>Khafre</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
sixth and last ruler of Egypt in the 2nd dynasty (c. 2775–c. 2650 BCE), who apparently ended the internal struggles of the mid-2nd dynasty.Khasekhemwy, whose name means “the two powers have appeared,” is the only king of Egypt to have selected a royal name that commemorates both Horus, the god traditionally associated with the living king, and Seth, his trickster brother; the emblematic animals of both deities are depicted above his serekh (the stylized rectangular frame in which a king's Horus name was displayed). Some scholars have interpreted this double symbol as an indication of a civil r...
</Question>
<Choice>Khasekhemwy</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
second king of the 4th dynasty (c. 2575–c. 2465 BCE) of Egypt and builder of the Great Pyramid at Al-Jizah (seePyramids of Giza), the largest single building to that time.Khufu's reign and that of his son Khafre were represented by the Greek historian Herodotus as 106 years of oppression and misery, but this was belied by Khufu's posthumous reputation in Egypt as a wise ruler. Herodotus's story of Khufu's prostitution of his daughter in order to raise money for his building projects is clearly apocryphal.Although few written sources remain, it is known that Khufu was the son and successor of K...
</Question>
<Choice>Khufu</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
early king of the Hittite Old Kingdom in Anatolia (reigned c. 1680–c. 1650 BC). Though perhaps not the first of his line, he was traditionally regarded as the founder of the Old Kingdom (c. 1700–c. 1500)—a tradition reinforced by the use in later times of his name and that of his wife, Tawannannas, as dynastic titles or throne names of subsequent rulers. Labarnas is known chiefly from a later Hittite text called the Edict of Telipinus, which states that from his capital, Kussara, in central Anatolia, Labarnas extended his territory south to the Mediterranean coast and installed his sons as gov...
</Question>
<Choice>Labarnas I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Eastern Roman emperor from AD 457 to 474.Leo was a Thracian who, beginning his career in the army, became a protégé of General Aspar. In proclaiming Leo Eastern emperor at Constantinople (Feb. 7, 457), Aspar expected to use him as a puppet ruler. Leo, who had recognized Majorian as emperor of the West in 457, withheld recognition from Majorian's successor, Libius Severus, in 461. Six years later he installed Anthemius as the Western emperor.In 468 Leo opened a disastrous joint campaign with Anthemius against the Vandals under King Gaiseric in North Africa. Leo is said to have assembled a fleet...
</Question>
<Choice>Leo I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Spartan king whose stand against the invading Persian army at the pass of Thermopylae in central Greece is one of the enduring tales of Greek heroism, invoked throughout Western history as the epitome of bravery exhibited against overwhelming odds.A member of the Agiad house, Leonidas succeeded his half brother, Cleomenes I, as king, probably in 490. He was married to Cleomenes' daughter, Gorgo, and may have supported Cleomenes' aggressions against other Greek cities.In 480 Leonidas commanded the small Greek force that resisted the advance through Thermopylae of the vast army of the Persian ki...
</Question>
<Choice>Leonidas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor from 308 to 324.Born of Illyrian peasant stock, Licinius advanced in the army and was suddenly elevated to the rank of augustus (November 308) by his friend Galerius, who had become emperor. Galerius hoped to have him rule the West, but since Italy, Africa, and Spain were held by the usurper Maxentius, while Constantine reigned in Gaul and Britain, Licinius had to content himself with ruling Pannonia. When Galerius died in 311, Licinius took over Galerius' European dominions. He married Constantine's half sister Constantia (313) and in the same year defeated the Eastern emperor M...
</Question>
<Choice>Licinius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
founder of the Shu-Han dynasty (AD 221–263/264), one of the Three Kingdoms (Sanguo) into which China was divided at the end of the Han dynasty (206 BC–AD 220).Although Liu claimed descent from one of the early Han emperors, he grew up in poverty. Distinguishing himself in battle in the great Yellow Turban Rebellion that broke out at the end of the Han, he eventually became one of the leading Han generals and a rival of the other great general, Cao Cao. Liu Bei occupied the area in central China around Sichuan. After Cao Pi, the son of Cao Cao, usurped the Han throne in 220, Liu Bei founded his...
</Question>
<Choice>Liu Pei</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Macedonian general, satrap (provincial governor), and king who, as one of the diadochoi (“successors”) to Alexander the Great, came to rule strategic parts of the divided Macedonian Empire. Lysimachus was one of Alexander's bodyguards during the conquest of Asia, and, in the distribution of satrapies that followed Alexander's death (323), he was assigned to govern Thrace. Occupied there for many years in wars against the local peoples, Lysimachus took little part in the struggles among Alexander's other successors in Greece and Asia. Not until 302, when he bore the brunt of the campaign that e...
</Question>
<Choice>Lysimachus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor in 217 and 218, the first man to rule the empire without having achieved senatorial status.His skills as a lawyer helped him to rise rapidly in an equestrian career (a step below the senatorial career in status) until he became a praetorian prefect under the emperor Caracalla (reigned 211–217). Macrinus is alleged to have prompted the murder of Caracalla by an army officer in April 217, while the emperor was fighting the Parthians in what is now Iran. Three days after the assassination Macrinus was proclaimed emperor (augustus) by his army. He fought an inconclusive battle with t...
</Question>
<Choice>Macrinus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
usurping Roman emperor from Jan. 18, 350, to Aug. 11, 353. His career forms one episode in the struggles for imperial power that occurred after the death of Constantine the Great (ruled 306–337).Magnentius was a pagan of German descent who had achieved distinction as a soldier before having himself proclaimed emperor on Jan. 18, 350, at Augustodunum (modern Autun, France). Immediately he engineered the murder of Constans (sole ruler in the West from 340 to 350) and assumed control of the western half of the empire. In June 350 he crushed Nepotianus, who had declared himself emperor at Rome. To...
</Question>
<Choice>Magnentius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Western Roman emperor from 457 to 461, the only man to hold that office in the 5th century who had some claim to greatness.Born of a distinguished military family, he served under the master of soldiers Aetius and helped overthrow the emperor Avitus (reigned 455–456). The real governmental power passed to Majorian's friend Ricimer, who became for 16 years the kingmaker at Rome.Appointed master of the soldiers in 457, Majorian quickly defeated the Alemannic invaders at Bellinzona (in present Switzerland). He was proclaimed emperor, with Ricimer's support, on April 1 and set about conscientiousl...
</Question>
<Choice>Majorian</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Eastern Roman emperor from 450 to 457, the last ruler of the dynasty begun by the emperor Theodosius I (died 395). His relatively peaceful reign, which was later viewed as a golden age in the Eastern Roman Empire, provided a marked contrast to the violence that was destroying the Western Empire.Beginning his career as a professional soldier, Marcian came to hold a high position in the service of Aspar, Theodosius II's powerful master of soldiers. After Theodosius' death in 450, Aspar and Theodosius' sister, Pulcheria, had Marcian appointed emperor (August 25). As part of this arrangement, Marc...
</Question>
<Choice>Marcian</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor (AD 161–180), best known for his Meditations on Stoic philosophy. Marcus Aurelius has symbolized for many generations in the West the Golden Age of the Roman Empire.
</Question>
<Choice>Marcus Aurelius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the Marcomanni who organized the first confederation of German tribes.A Marcomannian noble, Maroboduus spent his youth in Italy and received a Roman education. On his return to Germany, he emerged as leader of the Marcomanni. About 9 BC, to escape the threat of Roman domination, he and his people migrated from the Main River valley in west-central Germany to Bohemia, now part of the Czech Republic, where he founded a kingdom and formed a powerful confederacy with neighbouring German tribes in what is now Silesia and Saxony. After a period of hostility, the Romans recognized his kingdom...
</Question>
<Choice>Maroboduus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
ruler of the North African kingdom of Numidia and an ally of Rome in the last years of the Second Punic War (218–201). His influence was lasting because the economic and political development that took place in Numidia under his rule provided the base for later development of the region by the Romans.Masinissa was the son of the chieftain of a Numidian tribal group, the Massyli. Brought up in Carthage, of which his father was an ally, he fought for Carthage against the Romans in Spain from 211 to 206. When the Carthaginians were defeated at Ilipa (near modern Sevilla) by Scipio in 206, Masinis...
</Question>
<Choice>Masinissa</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor from 306 to 312. His father, the emperor Maximian, abdicated with Diocletian in 305. In the new tetrarchy (two augusti with a caesar under each) that was set up after these abdications, Maxentius was passed over in favour of Flavius Valerius Severus, who was made a caesar, and then, in 306, an augustus. But discontent with the policies of Severus at Rome caused Maxentius to be proclaimed princeps there on Oct. 28, 306, by the Praetorian Guard. In 307 he took the title augustus.Maximian, recalled to the throne to support Maxentius, defeated and killed Severus in 307. In 308, howev...
</Question>
<Choice>Maxentius, Marcus Aurelius Valerius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor with Diocletian from AD 286 to 305.Born of humble parents, Maximian rose in the army, on the basis of his military skill, to become a trusted officer and friend of the emperor Diocletian, who made him caesar July 21, 285, and augustus April 1, 286. Maximian thus became in theory the colleague of Diocletian, but his role was always subordinate. Assigned the government of the West, Maximian defeated native revolts and a German invasion in Gaul, but he failed to suppress the revolt of Carausius in Gaul and Britain; after the institution of the tetrarch system (i.e., two augusti, eac...
</Question>
<Choice>Maximian</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first soldier who rose through the ranks to become Roman emperor (235–238). His reign marked the beginning of a half century of civil war in the empire. Originally from Thrace, he is said to have been a shepherd before enlisting in the army. There his immense strength attracted the attention of Septimius Severus (emperor 193–211).Under Severus Alexander (emperor 222–235), Maximinus held high command in the Army of the Rhine, and, when Severus was murdered, he was proclaimed emperor by the Rhine army. Maximinus spent most of his reign fighting invading tribes along the Danube and the Rhine. The...
</Question>
<Choice>Maximinus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first king of unified Egypt, who, according to ancient tradition, joined Upper and Lower Egypt in a single, centralized monarchy. Manetho, a 3rd-century-BCE Egyptian historian, called him Menes; the 5th-century-BCE Greek historian Herodotus referred to him as Min; and two native-king lists of the 19th dynasty (13th century BCE) call him Meni. Modern scholars have inconclusively identified the traditional Menes with one or more of the archaic Egyptian kings bearing the names Scorpion, Narmer, and Aha.In addition to crediting Menes with the unification of Egypt by war and administrative measures...
</Question>
<Choice>Menes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
fifth (according to some traditions, sixth) king of the 4th dynasty (c. 2575–c. 2465 BC) of Egypt; he built the third and smallest of the three Pyramids of Giza.He was the son and probably the successor of Khafre and, according to the Turin papyrus, reigned for 18 (or 28) years. According to tradition, Menkaure was a pious and just king. Although his pyramid and mortuary temple were unfinished at his death, his successor, Shepseskaf, completed the stonework of the mortuary temple in brick. In the funerary complex were found some of the finest sculptures of the Pyramid Age, including a slate st...
</Question>
<Choice>Menkaure</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Egypt (reigned 1213–04 BC) who successfully defended Egypt against a serious invasion from Libya.The 13th son of his long-lived father, Ramses II, Merneptah was nearing 60 years of age at his accession in about 1213. Toward the end of his father's reign, Egypt's military preparedness had deteriorated. Early in Merneptah's reign, his troops had to suppress a revolt in Palestine by the cities of Ashqelon, Gezer, and Yenoam. (The action is shown by battle reliefs at al-Karnak previously ascribed to Ramses II.) Merneptah's greatest challenge, however, came from the west. Libyans had penetr...
</Question>
<Choice>Merneptah</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Babylonia 721–710 and for nine months in 703, who maintained Babylonian independence in the face of Assyrian military supremacy for more than a decade.Commencing in 728 the king of Assyria also officially held the title of king of Babylonia. During that time Merodach-Baladan, a member of the Yakin tribe, was a district ruler in Chaldea. During the unrest surrounding the accession of Sargon II of Assyria in 722, Merodach-Baladan entered Babylon and claimed the Babylonian throne, which had belonged to his forebear Eriba-Marduk. An attack by the Elamites two years later so weakened the As...
</Question>
<Choice>Merodach-Baladan II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the Salian Franks from whom Frankish tradition held the Merovingian dynasty to have taken its name. He was the father of Childeric I (d. 481/482) and grandfather of Clovis I (c. 466–511).Nothing definite is known of Merovech's life, but an early myth made him the son of a sea god. He is mentioned in Gregory of Tours's Histories and, according to later sources, fought against Attila the Hun at the Battle of the Catalaunian Plains (451).
</Question>
<Choice>Merovech</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
posthumous name (shi) of the second emperor of the Dong (Eastern) Han dynasty (AD 25–220), during whose reign (AD 57–75) Buddhism is thought to have been introduced into China.Legend recounts that Mingdi (“Enlightened Emperor”) was visited in a dream by a golden image of the Buddha Shakyamuni, seeking to be worshiped in China. The emperor is said to have responded by recruiting two Buddhist monks from India and erecting the first Buddhist temple at Luoyang, the capital of the Dong Han.Mingdi launched a military campaign to destroy the Xiongnu tribes plaguing China's northwest frontier. Through...
</Question>
<Choice>Ming-ti</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Parthia (reigned 171–138 BC); he succeeded his brother Phraates I.Before 160 Mithradates I seized Media from the Seleucid ruler Timarchus. Turning to the east, he won two provinces, Tapuria and Traxiana, from the Bactrian king Eucratides. Mithradates then captured the province of Elymais (ancient Elam) and invaded Babylonia (142 or 141). The Seleucid king Demetrius II Nicator recaptured Babylon (141 or 140) but was defeated and held by Mithradates in honourable captivity. Generally, Mithradates was regarded as a mild ruler, and his epithet Philhellene (“Greek-loving”) indicates that he...
</Question>
<Choice>Mithradates I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Parthia (reigned 123–88 BC); he was the son and successor of Artabanus II.Mithradates recovered the eastern provinces that had been overrun by invading Saka nomads during his father's reign. In the west he conquered Mesopotamia and defeated the Armenian king Artavasdes, whose son Tigranes (later Tigranes II) became a Parthian hostage and was redeemed only for the cession of 70 valleys. One of the most successful of the Parthian kings, Mithradates concluded the first treaty between Parthia and Rome in 92 BC.
</Question>
<Choice>Mithradates II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Pontus in northern Anatolia (120–63 BC). Under his energetic leadership, Pontus expanded to absorb several of its small neighbours and, briefly, contested Rome's hegemony in Asia Minor.
</Question>
<Choice>Mithradates VI Eupator</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(fl. 16th century BC) Hittite king during the Old Kingdom (reigned c. 1620–c. 1590 BC).Mursilis was the adopted heir of his grandfather, Hattusilis I, whom he succeeded on the throne. He first continued his predecessor's campaigns in northern Syria, destroying Aleppo and delivering the final blow to Mari. He then turned eastward, and by raiding Babylon he put an end to the Amorite dynasty there. This event, recorded in Babylonian sources, firmly linked Hittite chronology with that of Babylonia. Mursilis also fought the Hurrians on the upper Euphrates River and returned to his capital, Hattusas...
</Question>
<Choice>Mursilis I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hittite king during the New Kingdom (reigned c. 1346–c. 1320 BC).Son of the great Hittite conqueror Suppiluliumas, Mursilis succeeded his father after the brief reign of his older brother Arnuwandas III. Mursilis renewed the allegiance of North Syria, particularly Carchemish (controlled by his brother Shar-Kushukh) and the kingdom of Amurru; he also conducted a successful campaign against the western kingdom of Arzawa, one of the main threats to the Hittite realm. Chronic trouble with the Kaska in the north necessitated almost annual pacification operations (10 in all), and the region of Azzi-...
</Question>
<Choice>Mursilis II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hittite king during the New Kingdom (reigned c. 1320–c. 1294 BC).Muwatallis was the son and successor of Mursilis II. Although Muwatallis' accession was unmarred by the customary flurry of revolts among the Hittite vassal states, a struggle with resurgent Egypt for the domination of Syria became imminent after Egypt reconquered Palestine and made the Orontes River in Syria the Egyptian-Hittite frontier. One of the great battles of the ancient world was fought at Kadesh (seeKadesh, Battle of) on the Orontes about 1300. Although the Egyptian king Ramses II claimed a great victory, the outcome wa...
</Question>
<Choice>Muwatallis</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the Sasanian Empire whose reign (293–302) saw the beginning of 40 years of peace with Rome.Narses was the youngest son of an earlier king, Shapur I. On the death of Bahram II (293), Narses, at that time viceroy of Armenia, successfully contested the succession of Bahram's son, Bahram III. Narses later antagonized Rome by occupying the independent portion of Armenia. In the following year he suffered a severe reversal, losing his war chest and his harem. He then concluded a peace (296), by the terms of which Armenia remained under Roman suzerainty, and the steppes of northern Mesopotami...
</Question>
<Choice>Narses</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
most famous Babylonian king (reigned c. 1119–c. 1098 BC) of the 2nd dynasty of the Isin.In revenge for earlier humiliating conquests and defeats that the Elamites had inflicted on Babylonia, Nebuchadrezzar led a grand campaign that resulted in the capture of Susa, the capital of Elam. The victory marked the end of Elam's domination of the region (the kingdom subsequently disintegrated into petty states) and afforded the return of the stolen cult statue of Marduk to its holy place at E-sagila (Marduk was to become the national deity of Babylon). Nebuchadrezzar was less successful in raids again...
</Question>
<Choice>Nebuchadrezzar I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the second and greatest king of the Chaldeandynasty of Babylonia (reigned c. 605–c. 561 BC). He was known for his military might, the splendour of his capital, Babylon, and his important part in Jewish history.Nebuchadrezzar II was the oldest son and successor of Nabopolassar, founder of the Chaldean empire. He is known from cuneiform inscriptions, the Bible and later Jewish sources, and classical authors. His name, from the Akkadian Nabu-kudurri-u?ur, means “O Nabu, watch over my heir.”While his father disclaimed royal descent, Nebuchadrezzar claimed the third-millennium Akkadian ruler Naram-...
</Question>
<Choice>Nebuchadrezzar II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Egypt (reigned 610–595 BC), and a member of the 26th dynasty, who unsuccessfully attempted to aid Assyria against the Neo-Babylonians and later sponsored an expedition that circumnavigated Africa.According to the Greek historian Herodotus, Necho began the construction of a canal from the Nile River to the Red Sea, probably in response to the growth of trade in the Egyptian Delta, but an oracle persuaded him to discontinue the project. A threat developed in Mesopotamia, where the Assyrian Empire was falling to the Babylonians. Necho ordered fleets to be built on the Mediterranean and Re...
</Question>
<Choice>Necho II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
third and last king (reigned 360–343 BC) of the 30th dynasty of Egypt; he was the last of the native Egyptian kings.Nectanebo, with the aid of the Spartan king Agesilaus II, usurped the throne from Tachos. A rival pretender almost succeeded in overthrowing the new king, but Agesilaus defeated him and left Nectanebo firmly established as ruler. His most powerful enemy was the Persian king Artaxerxes III Ochus, who, after an earlier, futile attempt, swept down through Phoenicia and Palestine, entered three mouths of the Nile at once, and easily took control of Egypt. Nectanebo fled first to Memp...
</Question>
<Choice>Nectanebo II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
last legitimate Western Roman emperor (reigned 474–475).Born of a distinguished family, Nepos was sent by the Eastern ruler Leo I to govern Italy as augustus (emperor). He at once deposed the Western emperor, Glycerius, whom Leo regarded as a usurper. Nepos proclaimed himself emperor in June 474. A year later he was obliged to recognize the independence of the Visigothic kingdom centred near present Toulouse, Fr. Later that year the patrician Orestes rose against Nepos and forced him to flee to Dalmatia (August 475). Nepos lived at Salonae (near modern Split, Croatia) for five years, recognize...
</Question>
<Choice>Nepos, Julius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the fifth Roman emperor (AD 54–68), stepson and heir of the emperor Claudius. He became infamous for his personal debaucheries and extravagances and, on doubtful evidence, for his burning of Rome and persecutions of Christians.
</Question>
<Choice>Nero</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor from Sept. 18, 96, to January 98, the first of a succession of rulers traditionally known as the Five Good Emperors.A member of a distinguished senatorial family, Nerva was distantly related by marriage to the Julio-Claudian house and had been twice consul (AD 71 and 90) when, on the assassination of the emperor Domitian, he became emperor. A number of elder statesmen emerged from retirement to help him govern the empire. The keynote of Nerva's regime was a skillfully propagandized renunciation of the terrorist means by which Domitian had imposed his tyranny. An agrarian reform m...
</Question>
<Choice>Nerva</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
second of the seven kings who, according to Roman tradition, ruled Rome before the founding of the Republic (c. 509 BC).Numa is said to have reigned from 715 to 673. He is credited with the formulation of the religious calendar and with the founding of Rome's other early religious institutions, including the Vestal Virgins; the cults of Mars, Jupiter, and Romulus deified (Quirinus); and the office of pontifex maximus. These developments were actually, however, the result of centuries of religious accretion. According to legend, Numa is the peaceful counterpart of the more bellicose Romulus (th...
</Question>
<Choice>Numa Pompilius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor 283–284.He succeeded his father, Carus, in the summer of 283, in the midst of a war with the Sasanians. Numerian was emperor in the East, and his brother, Carinus, ruled the West. Numerian led the army home but contracted a disabling eye disease. Late in 284, after the army had reached the Bosporus, Numerian was found dead. His father-in-law, Aper, who had assumed command, was accused of his murder and executed, and the throne passed to Diocletian, commander of the household guards.
</Question>
<Choice>Numerian</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
prince of the Roman colony of Palmyra (q.v.), in what is now Syria, who prevented the Sasanian Persians from permanently conquering the eastern provinces of the Roman Empire.A Roman citizen and a member of Palmyra's ruling family, Odaenathus had by 258 attained consular rank and become ruler of Palmyra. When the Roman emperor Valerian was captured by the Sasanian king Shapur I (260), Odaenathus remained loyal to the Romans in order to prevent his city from falling under Sasanian control. In 260 he inflicted a severe defeat on Shapur's army as it was returning home after sacking Antioch. When h...
</Question>
<Choice>Odaenathus, Septimius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first barbarian king of Italy. The date on which he assumed power, 476, is traditionally considered the end of the Western Roman Empire.Odoacer was a German warrior, the son of Idico (Edeco) and probably a member of the Sciri tribe. About 470 he entered Italy with the Sciri; he joined the Roman army and rose to a position of command. After the overthrow of the Western emperor Julius Nepos by the Roman general Orestes (475), Odoacer led his tribesmen in a revolt against Orestes, who had reneged on his promise to give the tribal leaders land in Italy. On Aug. 23, 476, Odoacer was proclaimed king...
</Question>
<Choice>Odoacer</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
semilegendary 15th emperor of Japan, who according to tradition flourished in the 3rd–4th century. Ojin is believed to have consolidated imperial power, spearheaded land reform, and actively promoted cultural exchanges with Korea and China. It is said that highly skilled weaving techniques were brought from Korea during his reign. Chinese scholars introduced Confucianism and the Chinese writing system into the country, thus marking the beginning of Japanese cultural growth.Ojin's mausoleum, at Habikino, near Osaka, is the second largest in Japan and is noted for its splendour and historical va...
</Question>
<Choice>Ojin</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
wife of Philip II of Macedonia and mother of Alexander the Great. She had a passionate and imperious nature, and she played important roles in the power struggles that followed the deaths of both rulers.The daughter of Neoptolemus, king of Epirus, Olympias apparently was originally named Myrtale. Later she may have been called Olympias as a recognition of Philip's victory in the Olympic Games of 356 BC. Philip's polygamy did not threaten her position until 337, when he married a high-born Macedonian, Cleopatra. Olympias withdrew to Epirus, returning after Philip's assassination (336). She then...
</Question>
<Choice>Olympias</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Parthia (reigned c. 55/54–37/36 BC) who helped his brother Mithradates III murder their father, Phraates III, in about 57 BC and in turn supplanted Mithradates.When Mithradates occupied Seleucia and Babylon, Orodes stormed those towns, immediately executing his brother. No less ruthless to his attendants, he put to death Surenas, the general who in 53 BC had crushed the Romans under the triumvir Marcus Licinius Crassus at Carrhae in northern Mesopotamia (now Altinbasak, Turkey). Parthian raids into Roman Syria were checked by the death of Pacorus, Orodes's favourite son and perhaps joi...
</Question>
<Choice>Orodes II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor from January to April 69.Otho was born into a family that had held the consulship under Augustus. He married Poppaea Sabina, but when the emperor Nero took Poppaea for his mistress—she later became his wife—Otho was sent from Rome to govern Lusitania (58). For 10 years he ruled this province with integrity. Then, in 68, Otho joined the rebellion against Nero led by Galba, governor of the neighbouring province of Tarraconensis. He had hoped to be designated Galba's successor, but when Galba disappointed him by adopting Lucius Piso Licinianus (January 69), Otho prepared to seize po...
</Question>
<Choice>Otho</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Parthia (reigned AD 78–c. 115/116). Little is known of his reign, which seems to have been filled with rebellions and the rule of counterkings (Artabanus IV, Osroes, and Vologases II).In 110 Pacorus sold the Parthian client kingdom of Osroëne to Abgar VII, son of Izates, ruler of Adiabene. It is uncertain whether Pacorus was alive when the Roman emperor Trajan invaded Mesopotamia (114–115).
</Question>
<Choice>Pacorus II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
general under Alexander the Great who became regent of the Macedonian empire after Alexander's death (323).Perdiccas served with distinction in Alexander's campaigns and, upon Alexander's death, led the aristocratic party that supported the claim of the unborn child of Roxana, Alexander's widow, to the succession. After a compromise under which a division of the powers of regency was arranged, Perdiccas exercised a wide authority in Asia as “supreme general” and soon began to act as if he meant to make himself king. This move was resisted by the regional governors, Ptolemy in Egypt, Antigonus...
</Question>
<Choice>Perdiccas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
the last king of Macedonia (179–168), whose attempts to dominate Greece brought on the final defeat of Macedonia by the Romans, leading to annexation of the region.The elder son of King Philip V of Macedonia, Perseus commanded troops in his father's wars against Rome (199) and Aetolia (189). After three years of intriguing against his brother Demetrius, accusing him of coveting the succession, Perseus in 180 persuaded the king to have Demetrius executed. On succeeding to the throne in 179, he extended his influence in Thrace and Illyria but made special efforts to win over the Greek world. To...
</Question>
<Choice>Perseus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor from January to March 193.The son of a freed slave, Pertinax taught school, then entered the army, commanding units in Syria, in Britain, and on the Danube and the Rhine. He earned distinction during the great invasion by German tribes in 169. Given senatorial rank and command of a legion, he was soon promoted to the consular commands of Moesia, Dacia, and Syria, but under the emperor Commodus (reigned 180–192) he fell from favour, together with the future emperor Septimius Severus, during the ascendancy of the praetorian prefect Perennis (182–185). In the last years of Commodus'...
</Question>
<Choice>Pertinax, Publius Helvius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Argos, Argolis, who made his city an important power in the Peloponnese, Greece.The ancient Greek historian Herodotus implied that Pheidon flourished about 600 BC, but at this time Corinth and Sicyon, not the Argives, were in the ascendance. Although some later writers assigned Pheidon to the 8th century BC, most modern scholars place him in the early 7th century. He was said to have been the 10th successor to Temenus, the founder of Argos, and ruler of the whole Argolid peninsula in the northeast Peloponnese. Pheidon united this region (the “lot of Temenus”), marched across the Pelopo...
</Question>
<Choice>Pheidon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor from 244 to 249.A member of a distinguished equestrian family of Arab descent, Philip was praetorian prefect when the emperor Gordian III was killed in a mutiny (perhaps with Philip's connivance). Philip became emperor and quickly concluded a peace ending a war with Persia. After undertaking a series of campaigns against the Goths and other tribes on the Danube, he returned to Rome in 248 to celebrate the 1,000th anniversary of the founding of the city. Philip's reign saw the true beginning of the crisis of the 3rd century, which was marked by a series of barbarian invasions acro...
</Question>
<Choice>Philip</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
18th king of Macedonia (359–336 BC), who restored internal peace to his country and then, by 339, had gained domination over all Greece by military and diplomatic means, thus laying the foundations for its expansion under his son Alexander III the Great.
</Question>
<Choice>Philip II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Macedonia from 221 to 179, whose attempt to extend Macedonian influence throughout Greece resulted in his defeat by Rome. His career is significant mainly as an episode in Rome's expansion. The son of Demetrius II and his wife Phthia (Chryseis), the young prince was adopted, after his father's death in 229, by his half-cousin Antigonus Doson, who took the throne. Philip succeeded upon Antigonus' death (summer 221) and soon won renown by supporting the Hellenic League in its war against Sparta, Aetolia, and Elis (220–217). In 215 Philip, allied with Hannibal, the Carthaginian general wh...
</Question>
<Choice>Philip V</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Parthia (reigned 70–58/57 BC), the son and successor of Sanatruces (Sinatruces).On Phraates' accession, the Roman general Lucullus was preparing to attack King Tigranes I of Armenia, who had wrested several vassal states from the Parthian kingdom. Phraates refused to help Tigranes fight the Romans; instead he made an alliance with the Roman general Pompey and invaded Armenia (66 BC). Pompey at first abandoned Mesopotamia to Phraates but later reversed his stand and occupied the Parthian vassal states of Gordyene and Osroëne. Before Phraates could take any action, he was murdered by his...
</Question>
<Choice>Phraates III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Parthia (reigned c. 37–2 BC) who murdered his father, Orodes II, and his brothers to secure the throne.In 36 the Romans under Mark Antony attacked Parthia, penetrating through Armenia into Media Atropatene. Phraates, however, defeated Antony, who retreated with heavy losses. In 34 Phraates' vassal king in Media made an alliance with Antony; but when Antony later withdrew, the Parthians reoccupied Media. A revolt soon broke out in Parthia, and Tiridates II of Armenia drove Phraates from the throne, forcing him to take refuge with the Saka nomads. In 30, however, Phraates was able to reg...
</Question>
<Choice>Phraates IV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Media from 675 to 653 BC. Phraortes, who was known by that name as a result of the writings of the 5th-century-BC Greek historian Herodotus, was originally a village chief of Kar Kashi, but he later subjugated the Persians and a number of other Asian peoples, eventually forming an anti-Assyrian coalition of Medes and Cimmerians. In his attack on Assyria, however, he was defeated and killed in battle.Another Phraortes was a usurper who reigned for a short time in Media during a rebellion against the Achaemenian king Darius I in 522 BC. Darius' rock inscription at Bisitun relates that “a...
</Question>
<Choice>Phraortes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
last ruling emperor of China's Xi (Western) Han dynasty (206 BC–AD 25).Pingdi, at the time only nine years old, was placed on the throne in 1 BC by the powerful minister Wang Mang, whose daughter he married five years later. Though proof is lacking, it has been claimed that Pingdi was poisoned by his father-in-law. In any case, Pingdi's death allowed Wang to assume the title of regent to a child emperor; in AD 8, Wang finally set aside the Han dynasty altogether and established himself as emperor of the Xin dynasty.
</Question>
<Choice>P'ing-ti</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Cush (or Kush, in the Sudan) from about 750 to about 719 BC. He invaded Egypt from the south and ended the petty kingdoms of the 23rd dynasty (c. 823–c. 732 BC) in Lower Egypt. According to Egyptian tradition, his brother Shabaka founded the 25th dynasty, but Piye laid the foundations.The kingdom of Cush, of which Piye was ruler, emerged out of the Egyptianized population of the Sudan near Mount Barkal, between the third and fourth Nile cataracts. The cult of the Egyptian god Amon Re was strongly entrenched among the Cushites, and a threat by Tefnakhte, a Libyan chieftain of the Nile d...
</Question>
<Choice>Piye</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor from AD 276 to 282.The son of a Balkan military officer, Probus served with distinction in the army and apparently was eastern praetorian prefect when his troops proclaimed him emperor in opposition to Florian, who was soon killed by his own men. Probus's reign was spent in continual frontier warfare against hostile tribes on the Rhine and Danube, complicated by insurrections in Britain, Gaul, and the East. His policy of allowing outside tribes to settle within the empire proved dangerous.Fourth-century writers attest to his intense interest in agriculture. He encouraged the plan...
</Question>
<Choice>Probus, Marcus Aurelius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
governor, later king (reigned 664–610 BCE) of ancient Egypt, who expelled the Assyrians from Egypt and reunited the country, founding its 26th dynasty (664–525 BCE; seeancient Egypt: The Late period [664–332 BCE]).According to the Greek historian Herodotus, he was one of 12 corulers and secured the aid of Greek mercenaries in order to become sole ruler. After an abortive rebellion by his vassals against the Assyrian ruler of Egypt in 663, Psamtik was unexpectedly restored as governor of Athribis, a city of the Nile River delta, by the Assyrian king. Later, rejecting his vassal status, he negot...
</Question>
<Choice>Psamtik I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king (reigned 595–589 BCE) of the 26th dynasty (664–525 BCE; seeancient Egypt: The Late period [664–332 BCE]) of ancient Egypt, who conducted an important expedition against the kingdom of Kush, Egypt's southern neighbour (seeNubia).The Greek historian Herodotus, writing in the 5th century BCE, refers briefly to an Ethiopian war of Psamtik, an expedition that contemporary records prove to have been of great importance. Perhaps suspecting a Kushite threat to Egypt, Psamtik sent a large force against it. The army consisted of native Egyptians led by Amasis, who later became pharaoh, and mercenar...
</Question>
<Choice>Psamtik II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
last king (reigned 526–525 BCE) of the 26th dynasty (664–525 BCE; seeancient Egypt: The Late period [664–332 BCE]) of ancient Egypt, who failed to block the Persian invasion of 525 and was later executed for treason.The 5th-century-BCE Greek historian Herodotus, the primary source for knowledge of the reign, states that in 525 BCE, after only six months on the throne, Psamtik confronted a Persian invasion led by King Cambyses II. After the enemy had crossed Sinai with the aid of the Arabs, a bitter battle was fought at Pelusium, a city on Egypt's eastern frontier. The Egyptians with their merc...
</Question>
<Choice>Psamtik III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Macedonian general of Alexander the Great, who became ruler of Egypt (323–285 BC) and founder of the Ptolemaic dynasty, which reigned longer than any other dynasty established on the soil of the Alexandrian empire and only succumbed to the Romans in 30 BC.
</Question>
<Choice>Ptolemy I Soter</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(Greek: Brother-loving) king of Egypt (285–246 BC), second king of the Ptolemaic dynasty, who extended his power by skillful diplomacy, developed agriculture and commerce, and made Alexandria a leading centre of the arts and sciences.
</Question>
<Choice>Ptolemy II Philadelphus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
GreekBenefactorMacedonian king of Egypt, son of Ptolemy II; he reunited Egypt and Cyrenaica and successfully waged the Third Syrian War against the Seleucid kingdom.Almost nothing is known of Ptolemy's youth before 245, when, following a long engagement, he married Berenice II, the daughter of Magas, king of Cyrene; thereby he reunited Egypt and Cyrenaica, which had been divided since 258. Shortly after his accession and marriage, Ptolemy invaded Coele Syria, to avenge the murder of his sister, the widow of the Seleucid king Antiochus II. Ptolemy's navy, perhaps aided by rebels in the cities,...
</Question>
<Choice>Ptolemy III Euergetes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(Greek: Loving His Father) Macedonian king of Egypt (reigned 221–205 BC), under whose feeble rule, heavily influenced by favourites, much of Ptolemaic Syria was lost and native uprisings began to disturb the internal stability of Egypt.Classical writers depict Ptolemy as a drunken, debauched reveller, completely under the influence of his disreputable associates, among whom Sosibius was the most prominent. At their instigation, Ptolemy arranged the murder of his mother, uncle, and brother.Following the defection of one of Ptolemy's best commanders, Egypt's Syro-Palestinian territory, Coele Syr...
</Question>
<Choice>Ptolemy IV Philopator</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(Greek: Illustrious) Macedonian king of Egypt from 205 BC under whose rule Coele Syria and most of Egypt's other foreign possessions were lost.After Sosibius, Ptolemy IV's corrupt minister, had murdered Ptolemy V's mother, the five-year-old king was officially elevated to the throne; Sosibius became his guardian. According to the 2nd-century BC Greek historian Polybius, all prominent officials were banished from Egypt while Sosibius' clique announced the young king's accession and the death of his parents. The rulers of Macedonia and of the Syrian-based Seleucid kingdom, however, realizing Egy...
</Question>
<Choice>Ptolemy V Epiphanes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
GreekLoving His MotherMacedonian king of Egypt under whom an attempted invasion of Coele Syria resulted in the occupation of Egypt by the Seleucids. After Roman intervention and several ventures of joint rule with his brother, however, Ptolemy was able to reunite his realm.The son of Ptolemy V Epiphanes and Cleopatra I, Ptolemy VI ruled as co-regent with his mother, who, although a daughter of a Seleucid king, did not take sides in Syria and remained friendly with Rome. Mother and son governed effectively until her death in 176, when Ptolemy fell under the influence of two ambitious courtiers....
</Question>
<Choice>Ptolemy VI Philometor</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek“Flute Player”Macedonian king of Egypt, whose quasi-legitimate royal status compelled him to depend heavily upon Rome for support for his throne. During his reign Egypt became virtually a client kingdom of the Roman Republic. He was the first Ptolemy to include Theos (God) in his formal title. (Auletes was not part of his formal title.)Following the sudden, violent deaths of the last two fully legitimate members of the Ptolemaic family in Egypt, the people of Alexandria in 80 invited Ptolemy XII to assume the throne. Although he was known as a son of Ptolemy IX Soter II, his mother was a...
</Question>
<Choice>Ptolemy XII Auletes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Greek“Ptolemy the Father-Loving God”Macedonian king of Egypt and coruler with his famous sister, Cleopatra VII. He was killed while leading the Ptolemaic army against Julius Caesar's forces in the final stages of the Alexandrian War.A son of Ptolemy XII Auletes, Ptolemy XIII became joint ruler of Egypt with his sister following his father's death. In 49 Ptolemy, seeking to retain his father's allies, supplied the Roman general and former triumvir Pompey the Great with ships and troops. Subsequently, a court clique, headed by Theodotus, the eunuch Pothinus, and the general Achillas, gained infl...
</Question>
<Choice>Ptolemy XIII Theos Philopator</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Egypt (reigned 44–30 BC), son of Julius Caesar and Cleopatra VII. Ptolemy was his mother's co-ruler, killed by Octavian, later the emperor Augustus, after Cleopatra's death in 30.Ptolemy was the child of Cleopatra and Caesar, although a few classical authors, perhaps for political reasons, expressed doubts about his paternity. After Cleopatra's arrival in Rome in 46, Caesar himself, however, officially recognized the child as his son. When his father was assassinated in 44, Cleopatra returned with the boy to Egypt, where she probably arranged the death of her younger brother, Ptolemy X...
</Question>
<Choice>Ptolemy XV Caesar</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Hellenistic Epirus whose costly military successes against Macedonia and Rome gave rise to the phrase “Pyrrhic victory.” His Memoirs and books on the art of war were quoted and praised by many ancient authors, including Cicero.Upon becoming ruler at the age of 12, Pyrrhus allied himself with Demetrius, son of Antigonus I Monophthalmus of Macedonia. Dethroned by an uprising in 302, Pyrrhus fought beside Demetrius in Asia and was sent to Alexandria as a hostage under the treaty between Ptolemy I Soter and Demetrius. Ptolemy befriended Pyrrhus and in 297 restored him to his kingdom. At fi...
</Question>
<Choice>Pyrrhus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of ancient Egypt (reigned 1292–90 BCE), founder of the 19th dynasty (1292–1190 BCE) of Egypt.Probably descended from a nonroyal military family from the northeast Egyptian delta, Ramses found favour with Horemheb, the last king of the 18th dynasty (1539–1292 BCE), who was also a military man. As the elderly king had no son of his own, he made Ramses coregent not long before his own death. By then Ramses also was of advanced age, but his son, Seti I, was in the prime of life.In 1292 Ramses I ascended the throne and shortly thereafter made Seti his coregent to help him assume some of the mo...
</Question>
<Choice>Ramses I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of ancient Egypt (reigned 1187–56 BCE) who defended his country against foreign invasion in three great wars, thus ensuring tranquillity during much of his reign. In his final years, however, he faced internal disturbances and an attempted coup d'état.Son of Setnakht (reigned 1190–87 BCE), founder of the 20th dynasty (1190–1075 BCE), Ramses found Egypt upon his accession only recently recovered from the unsettled political conditions that had plagued the land at the end of the previous dynasty. In the fifth year of his reign, a coalition of Libyan tribes invaded the western Nile River del...
</Question>
<Choice>Ramses III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of ancient Egypt (reigned 1156–50 BCE) who strove through extensive building activity to maintain Egypt's prosperity in an era of deteriorating internal and external conditions.Upon his accession, Ramses compiled a lengthy document (the Harris Papyrus) recording his father's gifts to the gods, blessings for his son, and a survey of his reign. Soon afterward the new king undertook a vast building program. In his first year the graywacke (coarse sandstone) quarries in the Wadi Hammamat, east of Coptos (modern Qif?) in Upper Egypt, were surveyed and reopened to extract building stone. More q...
</Question>
<Choice>Ramses IV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of ancient Egypt (reigned 1104–1075? BCE), last king of the 20th dynasty (1190–1075 BCE), whose reign was marked by civil wars involving the high priest of Amon and the viceroy of Nubia. At the end of his reign, new dynasties were founded in Upper and Lower Egypt.During his reign, marauding bands of Libyans caused much of the population of western Thebes to take refuge within the fortified temple of Ramses III at Madinat Habu, and at various periods there was no high priest of Amon; even the high priest Amenhotep was ousted from office for eight months.With the high priest's eviction, The...
</Question>
<Choice>Ramses XI</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
known to history as the last of the Western Roman emperors (475–476). In fact, he was a usurper and puppet not recognized as a legitimate ruler by the Eastern emperor.Romulus was the son of the Western empire's master of soldiers Orestes. His original surname was Augustus, but it was changed to the diminutive because he was still a child when his father, after driving the Western emperor Julius Nepos from Italy, elevated him to the throne on October 31, 475. For about 12 months Orestes ruled Italy in his son's name, but eventually his troops mutinied and found a leader in the German warrior Od...
</Question>
<Choice>Romulus Augustulus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
regional emperor of India from about 330 to 380 CE. He generally is considered the epitome of an “ideal king” of the “golden age of Hindu history,” as the period of the imperial Guptas (320–510 CE) has often been called. The son of King Chandra Gupta I and the Licchavi princess Kumaradevi, he is pictured as a muscular warrior, a poet, and a musician who displayed “marks of hundreds of wounds received in battle.” In many ways he personified the Indian conception of the hero.Samudra Gupta was chosen as emperor by his father over other contenders and apparently had to repress revolts in his first...
</Question>
<Choice>Samudra Gupta</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Parthia from 76/75 to 70/69 BC, who restored unity to his kingdom.Sanatruces may have been a son of Mithradates I (reigned 171–138), the Parthian king who had established the kingdom's power. Following the death of King Mithradates II in 88 BC, dynastic struggles troubled Parthia, and the Armenians took advantage of the situation to invade the kingdom. Sanatruces sought refuge with the Sacaraucase, a Scythian tribe. Despite his 80 years, he was chosen as the prince best suited to deal with the dynastic question; he was made king of Parthia to clear up the succession and reunify the kin...
</Question>
<Choice>Sanatruces</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
ancient Mesopotamian ruler (reigned c. 2334–2279 BC), one of the earliest of the world's great empire builders, conquering all of southern Mesopotamia as well as parts of Syria, Anatolia, and Elam (western Iran). He established the region's first Semitic dynasty and was considered the founder of the Mesopotamian military tradition.
</Question>
<Choice>Sargon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
one of Assyria's great kings (reigned 721–705 BC) during the last century of its history. He extended and consolidated the conquests of his presumed father, Tiglath-pileser III.Sargon is the Hebrew rendering (Isaiah 20:1) of Assyrian Sharru-kin, a throne name meaning “the king is legitimate.” The name was undoubtedly chosen in reminiscence of two former kings of Assyria, particularly in commemoration of Sargon of Akkad (flourished 2300 BC).Although Sargon's ancestry is partly veiled in mystery, he was probably a younger son of Tiglath-pileser III and consequently a brother of his predecessor S...
</Question>
<Choice>Sargon II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first king of Israel (c. 1021–1000 BC). According to the biblical account found mainly in I Samuel, Saul was chosen king both by the judge Samuel and by public acclamation. Saul was similar to the charismatic judges who preceded him in the role of governing; his chief contribution, however, was to defend Israel against its many enemies, especially the Philistines.
</Question>
<Choice>Saul</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Macedonian army officer, founder of the Seleucid kingdom. In the struggles following the death of Alexander the Great, he rose from governor of Babylon to king of an empire centring on Syria and Iran.
</Question>
<Choice>Seleucus I Nicator</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
fourth king (reigned 246–225) of the Seleucid dynasty, son of Antiochus II Theos.Antiochus II repudiated his wife Laodice (Seleucus' mother) and married Ptolemy's daughter Berenice, but by 246 BC Antiochus had left Berenice in order to live again with Laodice and Seleucus in Asia Minor. Laodice poisoned him and proclaimed her son as King Seleucus II, while her partisans at Antioch made away with Berenice. Berenice's brother, Ptolemy III, who had just succeeded to the Egyptian throne, at once invaded the Seleucid realm and annexed the eastern provinces, while his fleets swept the coasts of Asia...
</Question>
<Choice>Seleucus II Callinicus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Assyria (705/704–681 BCE), son of Sargon II. He made Nineveh his capital, building a new palace, extending and beautifying the city, and erecting inner and outer city walls that still stand. Sennacherib figures prominently in the Old Testament.
</Question>
<Choice>Sennacherib</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
(fl. 16th century BCE), king of ancient Egypt whose reign (c. 1545 BCE) is contemporaneous with the last portion of the Hyksos dynasty, the west-Semitic conquerors who ruled much of Egypt in the 17th century BCE (seeancient Egypt: The Second Intermediate period).As shown by a literary tale of later date, Seqenenre was contemporary with Apopis, one of the last great Hyksos kings. According to the tale, the Hyksos ruler provoked a quarrel by claiming that hippopotamuses at Thebes were disturbing his sleep at his delta capital, 400 miles (644 km) away. Unfortunately, the preserved text ends with...
</Question>
<Choice>Seqenenre</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of ancient Egypt (reigned 1908–1875 BCE) who succeeded his father after a 10-year coregency and brought Egypt to a peak of prosperity.Sesostris became coregent in 1918 BCE with his aging father, Amenemhet I, who had founded the 12th dynasty (1938–c. 1756 BCE). While his father completed his domestic reforms, Sesostris undertook the conquest of Nubia, to the south of Egypt, and in the year 30 of his father's reign he led an expedition against the Libyans in the Western Desert.According to The Story of Sinuhe, the biographical writings of a court official, Sesostris learned of his father's...
</Question>
<Choice>Sesostris I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of ancient Egypt (reigned 1844–37 BCE) of the 12th dynasty (1938–c. 1756) who devoted himself to the peaceful exploitation of Nubia, Egypt's territory to the south, and initiated the development of Al-Fayyum, a great oasis-like depression west of the Nile River and southwest of Cairo.Following the established practice of his dynasty, Sesostris spent three years as his father's coregent. In year 1 of this period, a trading expedition to Punt—on the east African coast—recorded its trip on the rocks at Egypt's Red Sea port.Early in Sesostris's sole reign, the fortresses of Lower Nubia, built...
</Question>
<Choice>Sesostris II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of ancient Egypt (reigned 1836–18 BCE) of the 12th dynasty (1938–c. 1756 BCE), who completely reshaped Egypt's government and extended his dominion in Nubia, the land immediately south of Egypt.During the reigns of his predecessors, the provincial nobles of Middle Egypt had enhanced their power through royal favours and intermarriage with the families of neighbouring potentates. Around the middle of Sesostris III's reign, the rich provincial tombs, which were a mark of the nobles' power, abruptly ceased to be built. Simultaneously, the memorials of middle-class persons increased at Abydos...
</Question>
<Choice>Sesostris III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
ancient Egyptian king of the 19th dynasty (1292–1190 BCE) who reigned from 1290 to 1279 BCE. His father, Ramses I, reigned only two years, and it was Seti who was the real founder of the greatness of the Ramessids.In the early years of his reign, Seti led his army northward to restore Egyptian prestige, which had been partly lost during the troubled years of the late 18th dynasty. He battled in northern Palestine and Syria and fought at least one battle with the Hittite king Muwatallis; he subsequently concluded a peace treaty that may have established the frontier at Kadesh on the Orontes Riv...
</Question>
<Choice>Seti I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor from AD 222 to 235, whose weak rule collapsed in the civil strife that engulfed the empire for the next 50 years. His maternal grandmother, Julia Maesa, was a sister-in-law of the emperor Septimius Severus (reigned 193–211).In 218 the legions in Syria proclaimed as emperor Alexander's 14-year-old cousin, Elagabalus (Heliogabalus), who was persuaded (221) to adopt Alexander as his heir. In March 222 the Praetorian Guard—probably prompted by Julia Maesa and Alexander's mother, Julia Mamaea—murdered Elagabalus. Alexander succeeded to power without incident. During his reign the real...
</Question>
<Choice>Severus Alexander</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor in 306 and 307.After serving as an army officer in Pannonia (present-day western Hungary and northern Croatia and Slovenia), Severus was appointed, on May 1, 305, caesar (junior emperor) to the emperor Constantius I Chlorus (ruled 305–306) and given control of Pannonia, Italy, and Africa. Upon Constantius' death (July 25, 306), Severus was made augustus of the West by the remaining emperor, Galerius, who controlled the East. But the new ruler became unpopular when he imposed higher taxes on the people of Rome and of Italy. On Oct. 28, 306, a revolt broke out in Rome, led by Maxen...
</Question>
<Choice>Severus, Flavius Valerius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor from 193 to 211. He founded a personal dynasty and converted the government into a military monarchy. His reign marks a critical stage in the development of the absolute despotism that characterized the later Roman Empire.The son of an equestrian from the Roman colony of Leptis Magna, Severus entered the Senate about 173 and became consul in 190. At the time of the murder of the insane emperor Commodus on Dec. 31, 192, he was governor of Upper Pannonia (now in Austria and Hungary) and commander of the largest army on the Danube River. He remained inactive while the Praetorian Gua...
</Question>
<Choice>Severus, Septimius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Kushite king who conquered Egypt and founded its 25th (Kushite) dynasty (seeancient Egypt: The 24th and 25th dynasties). He ruled Egypt from about 719/718 to 703 BCE.Succeeding his brother Piye, in Kush (in modern Sudan), Shabaka moved north, captured Bocchoris, the second king of the 24th dynasty, and, according to tradition, burned him alive. He probably made Memphis, near Cairo, his capital and adopted the titles of the traditional Egyptian pharaohs. He contributed numerous religious buildings at Thebes, home of Amon-Re, his dynastic god.Following Piye's ideals, Shabaka fostered religious o...
</Question>
<Choice>Shabaka</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Assyria (reigned 858–824 BC) who pursued a vigorous policy of military expansion.Although he conducted campaigns on the southern and eastern frontiers, Shalmaneser's main military effort was devoted to the conquest of North Syria. His progress was slow. In 853 BC he fought a coalition formed by the kings of Hamath, Damascus, and Israel in a huge-scale, but indecisive, battle, and he did not penetrate the west until the coalition had broken up.In 841 BC he defeated Hazael and, after failing to capture Damascus itself, marched to the Mediterranean coast where he received tribute from Tyr...
</Question>
<Choice>Shalmaneser III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Assyria (reigned 726–721 BC) who subjugated ancient Israel and undertook a punitive campaign to quell the rebellion of Israel's king Hoshea (2 Kings 17).None of his historical records survive, but the King List of Babylon, where he ruled as Ululai, links him with Tiglath-pileser III, whose son he may have been. When King Hoshea of Israel rebelled (2 Kings 17), Shalmaneser marched via Bit-Adini to besiege Samaria and attack Tyre. For three years he laid siege until “he broke the resistance of Shamara?in” (Samaria). However, he died shortly before the capture of the city, which was claim...
</Question>
<Choice>Shalmaneser V</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Persian king of the Sasanian dynasty who consolidated and expanded the empire founded by his father, Ardashir I. Shapur continued his father's wars with Rome, conquering Nisibis (modern Nusaybin, Tur.) and Carrhae (Harran, Tur.) and advancing deep into Syria. Defeated at Resaina (now in Turkey) in 243, he was able, nevertheless, to conclude a favourable peace in 244. In 256 he took advantage of the internal chaos within the Roman Empire and invaded Syria, Anatolia, and Armenia; he sacked Antioch but was repulsed by the emperor Valerian. In 260, however, Shapur not only defeated Valerian at Ede...
</Question>
<Choice>Shapur I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
10th king of the Sasanian Empire of Persia, who withstood Roman strength by astute military strategy and diplomacy and brought the empire to the zenith of its power.
</Question>
<Choice>Shapur II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
according to Jewish and Islamic traditions, ruler of the Kingdom of Saba? (or Sheba) in southwestern Arabia. In the Old Testament account of the reign of King Solomon, she visited his court at the head of a camel caravan bearing gold, jewels, and spices. The story provides evidence for the existence of important commercial relations between ancient Israel and Arabia. According to the Bible, the purpose of her visit was to test Solomon's wisdom by asking him to solve a number of riddles.The story of Bilqis, as the Queen of Sheba is known in Islamic tradition, appears in the Qur?an, though she i...
</Question>
<Choice>Sheba, Queen of</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first king (reigned 945–924 BCE) of the 22nd dynasty of ancient Egypt (seeancient Egypt: the 22nd and 23rd dynasties).Sheshonk was a general under Psusennes II, the last king of the 21st dynasty (1075–c. 950 BCE), and came from a line of princes or sheikhs of Libyan tribal descent whose title was “great chief of the Meshwesh” and who appear to have settled in Bubastis in the eastern Nile River delta. Sheshonk probably ascended the throne without a struggle, making Bubastis his residence and marrying his son Osorkon to a daughter of Psusennes II.According to the Old Testament, “Shishak king of...
</Question>
<Choice>Sheshonk I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
emperor (reigned 221–210 BC) of the Qin dynasty (221–207 BC) and creator of the first unified Chinese empire (which collapsed, however, less than four years after his death).
</Question>
<Choice>Shih huang-ti</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king (reigned 1335–32 BCE) of the 18th dynasty (1539–1292 BCE) of ancient Egypt, probably in coregency with Akhenaton, his predecessor, for most of the period. Smenkhkare's origin and identity remain among the unresolved issues of the Amarna period.The ephemeral Smenkhkare appears only at the very end of Ahkenaton's reign in a few monuments at the royal capital of Akhetaton (Tell el-Amarna). He shares the same coronation name, Ankhkheperure, with another royal individual called Neferneferuaton (part of the expanded name of Nefertiti). Since coronation names are generally unique to one individu...
</Question>
<Choice>Smenkhkare</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
first king of ancient Egypt of the 4th dynasty (c. 2575–c. 2465 BCE). He fostered the evolution of the highly centralized administration that marked the climax of the Old Kingdom (c. 2575–c. 2130 BCE).Snefru came from a family in Middle Egypt, near Hermopolis, and probably ascended the throne by marrying the royal heiress, his predecessor's daughter. Records of his reign are sparse, but it is clear from extensive cemeteries around his own and his son's pyramids that members of the royal family were appointed to the highest administrative offices. The office of vizier became especially importan...
</Question>
<Choice>Snefru</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
son and successor of David and traditionally regarded as the greatest king of Israel. He maintained his dominions with military strength and established Israelite colonies outside his kingdom's borders. The crowning achievement of his vast building program was the famous temple at his capital, Jerusalem.
</Question>
<Choice>Solomon</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
regent (394–408) for the Roman emperor Honorius and one of the last great Roman military commanders in the West. He fought in several campaigns against the barbarians, opposing the invading Visigoths under Alaric in the Balkans and Italy and repelling an Ostrogothic invasion of Italy in 406.Stilicho was half-Roman, half-Vandal by birth. Making the army his career, in 383 he served on an embassy to the Persian king Shapur III, afterward marrying Serena, the favourite niece of the emperor Theodosius. He was appointed count of the domestics (commanding the Emperor's household troops) c. 385 and t...
</Question>
<Choice>Stilicho, Flavius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Hittite king (reigned c. 1380–c. 1346 BC), who dominated the history of the ancient Middle East for the greater part of four decades and raised the Hittite kingdom to Imperial power. The son and successor of Tudhaliyas III, Suppiluliumas began his reign by rebuilding the old capital, Hattusas (Bogazköy in modern Turkey), and consolidating the Hittite heartland.Suppiluliumas' military career was almost exclusively devoted to struggles with the kingdom of Mitanni in the east and the reestablishment of a firm Hittite foothold in Syria. After an unsuccessful exploratory raid, he schemed to circumv...
</Question>
<Choice>Suppiluliumas I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of the Masaesyli, a Numidian tribe (in North Africa). Formerly a Carthaginian dependent, he rebelled in 214 BC in consultation with Publius Cornelius Scipio and his brother Gnaeus, who were fighting Carthaginian forces in Spain at the time. In 206 Syphax expelled his neighbour and rival Masinissa. When Syphax married Sophonisba—daughter of the Carthaginian commander Hasdrubal, son of Gisgo—Syphax returned his allegiance to Carthage.When Scipio Africanus, the son of Publius, invaded Africa near the end of the Second Punic War, Syphax opposed him at Utica, on the coast of what is now Tunisi...
</Question>
<Choice>Syphax</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
traditionally the fifth king of Rome, accepted by some scholars as a historical figure and usually said to have reigned from 616 to 578.His father was a Greek who went to live in Tarquinii, in Etruria, from which Lucumo moved to Rome on the advice of his wife, the prophet Tanaquil. Changing his name to Lucius Tarquinius, he was appointed guardian to the sons of King Ancus Marcius. Upon the king's death Tarquin assumed the throne. Eventually Ancus' sons had Tarquin murdered. Tanaquil then managed to put her son-in-law Servius Tullius in power.The legends maintain that Tarquin increased the numb...
</Question>
<Choice>Tarquin (5th king of Rome)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
traditionally the seventh and last king of Rome, accepted by some scholars as a historical figure. His reign is dated from 534 to 509 BC.Tarquinius Superbus was, in Roman tradition, the son (according to Fabius Pictor) or grandson (according to Calpurnius Piso Frugi) of Tarquinius Priscus and son-in-law of Servius Tullius. Tarquin supposedly murdered Tullius and established an absolute despotism—hence his name Superbus, meaning “the proud.” In the reign of terror that followed, many senators were put to death. Eventually a group of senators led by Lucius Junius Brutus raised a revolt, the imme...
</Question>
<Choice>Tarquin (7th king of Rome)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
early Achaemenid Persian king (reigned c. 675–c. 640), the forefather of the great kings Darius I and Cyrus II.He was, perhaps, the son of Achaemenes, whose name was given to the Achaemenid dynasty. Teispes ruled the district of Anshan in Elam (north of the Persian Gulf) and tried to maintain a neutral position between the powerful kingdoms of Elam and Assyria. At his death, Teispes either divided his kingdom between his sons, Ariaramnes and Cyrus I, or provided for an alternation in succession between the senior and junior lines.
</Question>
<Choice>Teispes</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
last king of the Hittite Old Kingdom in Anatolia (reigned c. 1525–c. 1500 BC).Telipinus seized the throne during a dynastic power struggle, and during his reign he attempted to end lawlessness and to regulate the royal succession. His stipulations, now called the Edict of Telipinus, form one of the best sources available for a study of the Hittite Old Kingdom. In his edict, Telipinus designated the pankus (a general assembly) as high court in cases of constitutional crimes. In the case of murder, even the king was subject to its jurisdiction. The initiative seems to have been successful, for t...
</Question>
<Choice>Telipinus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor of the East (379–392) and then sole emperor of both East and West (392–395), who, in vigorous suppression of paganism and Arianism, established the creed of the Council of Nicaea (325) as the universal norm for Christian orthodoxy and directed the convening of the second general council at Constantinople (381) to clarify the formula.
</Question>
<Choice>Theodosius I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Eastern Roman emperor from 408 to 450. He was a gentle, scholarly, easily dominated man who allowed his government to be run by a succession of relatives and ministers.The son of the Eastern emperor Arcadius (reigned 383–408), he was made coemperor in 402 and became sole ruler of the East upon his father's death in 408. At first the able Anthemius, praetorian prefect of the East, was regent for young Theodosius. Anthemius dropped out of sight in 414, when the emperor's sister Pulcheria received the title augusta and assumed the regency. Throughout his reign, control of the government remained...
</Question>
<Choice>Theodosius II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
18th-dynasty king of ancient Egypt (reigned 1493–c. 1482 BCE) who expanded Egypt's empire in Nubia (in present-day Sudan) and also penetrated deep into Syria.While Thutmose was the son of a nonroyal mother, he may have strengthened his claim to the throne by marrying Ahmose, perhaps a relative of his predecessor, probably some time before his accession. He also possibly was associated with his predecessor as coregent for an unspecified period, as is attested by a chapel found at Thebes. On his accession day, he communicated his new titulary and coronation in a letter to the viceroy of Nubia.In...
</Question>
<Choice>Thutmose I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
18th-dynasty king (reigned c. 1482–79 BCE) of ancient Egypt who suppressed a revolt in Nubia, Egypt's territory to the south, and also sent a punitive expedition to Palestine against some Bedouins.Thutmose was born to Thutmose I, his predecessor, by one of his secondary queens, Mutnofret. Thutmose II married his fully royal half-sister, Hatshepsut, at an early age. According to an inscription from Aswan dated year one, a chief from northern Kush, around the Second Nile Cataract, fomented a revolt against Egyptian suzerainty and threatened the garrisons stationed in Nubia. The king dispatched a...
</Question>
<Choice>Thutmose II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king (reigned 1479–26 BCE) of the 18th dynasty, often regarded as the greatest of the rulers of ancient Egypt. Thutmose III was a skilled warrior who brought the Egyptian empire to the zenith of its power by conquering all of Syria, crossing the Euphrates (seeTigris-Euphrates river system) to defeat the Mitannians, and penetrating south along the Nile River to Napata in the Sudan. He also built a great number of temples and monuments to commemorate his deeds.
</Question>
<Choice>Thutmose III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
18th-dynasty king of ancient Egypt (reigned 1400–1390 BCE) who secured an alliance with the Mitanni empire of northern Syria and ushered in a period of peace at the peak of Egypt's prosperity.Thutmose IV was the son of his predecessor's chief queen. As prince, he was assigned to the military operational base at Memphis, near present-day Cairo, where he spent his leisure time in hunting and sports near the pyramids on the western desert. During a rest near the great Sphinx (seesphinx), he dreamed that the god Horus, whom the sphinx was believed to represent, asked him to free it of sand that ha...
</Question>
<Choice>Thutmose IV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
second Roman emperor (AD 14–37), adopted son of Augustus, whose imperial institutions and imperial boundaries he sought to preserve. In his last years he became a tyrannical recluse, inflicting a reign of terror against the major personages of Rome.
</Question>
<Choice>Tiberius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Assyria (745–727 BC) who inaugurated the last and greatest phase of Assyrian expansion. He subjected Syria and Palestine to his rule, and later (729 or 728) he merged the kingdoms of Assyria and Babylonia.
</Question>
<Choice>Tiglath-pileser III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Armenia from 95 to 55 BC, under whom the country became for a short time the strongest state in the Roman East.Tigranes was the son or brother of Artavasdes I and a member of the dynasty founded in the early 2nd century by Artaxias. He was given as a hostage to the Parthian king Mithradates II, but later he purchased his freedom by ceding 70 valleys bordering on Media, in northwestern Iran.Thereafter, Tigranes began to enlarge his kingdom, first annexing the kingdom of Sophene (east of the upper Euphrates River). He also entered into alliance with Mithradates VI Eupator of Pontus, whos...
</Question>
<Choice>Tigranes II The Great</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Arsacid prince of the Parthian Empire who revolted against King Phraates IV and drove him into exile (32 BC) among the Scythians. The next year Phraates returned, and Tiridates fled to Syria, taking Phraates' son as hostage. The Roman emperor Augustus returned the son, but not Tiridates, to Phraates. In the spring of 26, Tiridates launched an unsuccessful invasion of Mesopotamia, and he may have returned to Mesopotamia early in 25. Augustus, preoccupied with Spanish affairs, had no more use for Tiridates. By May of 25, Phraates seems to have regained power.
</Question>
<Choice>Tiridates II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
grandson of the Parthian king Phraates IV and an unsuccessful contender for the Parthian throne. He was captured by the Romans, taken to Rome as a hostage, and educated there. In AD 35 the Roman emperor Tiberius sent him and an army under Lucius Vitellius, governor of Syria, against the Parthian ruler Artabanus III, hoping to place Tiridates on the Parthian throne. The Romans entered Seleucia, and Tiridates was crowned king. In 36, however, Artabanus III returned to Mesopotamia, and Tiridates fled to Syria.
</Question>
<Choice>Tiridates III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor (79–81), and the conqueror of Jerusalem in 70.After service in Britain and Germany, Titus commanded a legion under his father, Vespasian, in Judaea (67). Following the emperor Nero's death in June 68, Titus was energetic in promoting his father's candidacy for the imperial crown. Licinius Mucianus, legate of Syria, whom he reconciled with Vespasian, considered that one of Vespasian's greatest assets was to have so promising a son and heir. Immediately on being proclaimed emperor in 69, Vespasian gave Titus charge of the Jewish war, and a large-scale campaign in 70 culminated in t...
</Question>
<Choice>Titus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor (98–117 CE), the first to be born outside Italy. He sought to extend the boundaries of the empire to the east (notably in Dacia, Arabia, Armenia, and Mesopotamia), undertook a vast building program, and enlarged social welfare.
</Question>
<Choice>Trajan</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
founder of the short-lived Wei dynasty (AD 220–265/266) during the Sanguo (Three Kingdoms) period of Chinese history.The son of the great general and warlord Cao Cao of the Han dynasty (206 BC–AD 220), Cao Pi succeeded his father as king of Wei upon the latter's death in 220. At the same time, Cao Pi formally proclaimed the end of the Han and the inauguration of the Wei dynasty, of which he was the first emperor. He retired the last Han emperor with great honours and married the emperor's two daughters. He then undertook administrative reforms in his domains. Cao Pi's Wei dynasty never control...
</Question>
<Choice>Ts'ao P'ei</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of ancient Egypt (reigned 1333–23 BCE), known chiefly for his intact tomb, KV 62 (tomb 62), discovered in the Valley of the Kings in 1922. During his reign, powerful advisers restored the traditional Egyptian religion and art, both of which had been set aside by his predecessor Akhenaton, who had led the “Amarna revolution.” (SeeAmarna style.)The parentage of Tutankhaten—as he was originally known—remains uncertain, although a single black fragment originating at Akhetaton (Tell el-Amarna), Akhenaton's capital city, names him as a king's son in a context similar to that of the princesses...
</Question>
<Choice>Tutankhamen</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
last king of the 5th dynasty (c. 2465–c. 2325 BCE) of ancient Egypt and the first pharaoh to inscribe the interior of his pyramid at ?aqqarah with religious and magical texts known as Pyramid Texts. According to later king lists, Unas was the last ruler of the 5th dynasty, but the innovations in his pyramid complex and the use of blocks from his predecessor's monuments in his own pyramid have led some to consider him the founder of the 6th dynasty (c. 2325–c. 2150 BCE), or at least a transitional ruler.The reliefs and texts in Unas's burial chamber and other rooms were meant to assist the dece...
</Question>
<Choice>Unas</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Eastern Roman emperor from 364 to 378. He was the younger brother of Valentinian I, who assumed the throne upon the death of the emperor Jovian (Feb. 17, 364). On March 28, 364, Valentinian appointed Valens to be co-emperor. Valens was assigned to rule the Eastern part of the empire, while Valentinian took the throne in the West. Soon Valens was challenged by the pagan Procopius, who had himself proclaimed emperor in Constantinople (September 365). When Valens marched from Antioch to confront the usurper, Procopius was deserted by many of his troops; on May 27, 366, he was betrayed and put to...
</Question>
<Choice>Valens</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor from 364 to 375 who skillfully and successfully defended the frontiers of the Western Empire against Germanic invasions.Valentinian, who was the son of an army officer stationed in Pannonia (in central Europe), joined the army and served with his father in Africa. According to some sources, when Valentinian was a tribune in the forces of Julian the Apostate (emperor 361–363), he was disgraced for refusal to renounce Christianity. He did serve, however, in Julian's Persian expedition of 363, and was promoted by Julian's successor, Jovian, who died soon afterward (February 17, 364)...
</Question>
<Choice>Valentinian I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor from 375 to 392.Valentinian was the son of the emperor Valentinian I and his second wife, Justina. On November 22, 375, five days after the death of his father, the four-year-old Valentinian was proclaimed emperor at Aquincum (modern Budapest). The declaration was made without the knowledge or consent of the two reigning emperors, Valens and Gratian, but they later accepted Valentinian and allowed him (through his mother) to rule Italy, Africa, and Illyricum. In 383 Gratian was put to death by the usurper Magnus Maximus. In 384 Valentinian ruled in favour of Ambrose of Milan and...
</Question>
<Choice>Valentinian II</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor from 425 to 455. At no time in his long reign were the affairs of state personally managed by Valentinian. He was the son of the patrician Flavius Constantius (who ruled as Constantius III in 421) and Galla Placidia. When his uncle, the emperor Honorius, died in 423, the usurper John ruled for two years before he was deposed. Then Placidia controlled the West in her young son's name until 437, although the powerful patrician Flavius Aetius became the effective ruler toward the end of this regency. The most important political event of these years was the landing of the Vandals in...
</Question>
<Choice>Valentinian III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor from 253 to 260.Licinius Valerianus was consul under Severus Alexander (emperor 222–235) and played a leading role in inducing the Senate to risk support for Gordian I's rebellion against the emperor Maximinus (238). He may have been one of the 20 consulars who successfully defended Italy against the emperor. He is not again mentioned until the reign of Decius (emperor 249–251). Under Gallus (emperor 251–253), Licinius Valerianus held a command on the Upper Rhine and was summoned to bring the northern armies to aid in the struggle against the rival emperor Aemilian. He arrived to...
</Question>
<Choice>Valerian</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
chieftain of the Gallic tribe of the Arverni whose formidable rebellion against Roman rule was crushed by Julius Caesar.Caesar had almost completed the subjugation of Gaul when Vercingetorix led a general uprising of the Gauls against him in 52 BC. Vercingetorix was named the king of the Arverni and general of the confederates. After an initial defeat at Noviodunum Biturigum, Vercingetorix used guerrilla warfare to harass Caesar's supply lines and cleverly offered to engage Caesar's forces on terrain unfavourable to the Romans. He successfully held the Arvernian hill-fort of Gergovia against a...
</Question>
<Choice>Vercingetorix</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor jointly (161–169) with Marcus Aurelius. Though he enjoyed equal constitutional status and powers, he did not have equal authority, nor did he seem capable of bearing his share of the responsibilities.Lucius was the son of a senator, Lucius Ceionius Commodus, whom the emperor Hadrian adopted as his successor under the name Lucius Aelius Caesar. When Ceionius died on Jan. 1, 138, Hadrian designated Antoninus Pius as his successor. He ordered Antoninus to adopt as his heirs Ceionius's son Lucius and his own nephew Marcus Annius Verus (the future emperor Marcus Aurelius), who was als...
</Question>
<Choice>Verus, Lucius</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor (AD 69–79) who, though of humble birth, became the founder of the Flavian dynasty after the civil wars that followed Nero's death in 68. His fiscal reforms and consolidation of the empire generated political stability and a vast Roman building program.
</Question>
<Choice>Vespasian</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Roman emperor, the last of Nero's three short-lived successors.Vitellius was the son of the emperor Claudius's colleague as censor, Lucius Vitellius, who was also consul three times. Aulus himself became consul in AD 48 and proconsul of Africa (c. 61). The new emperor, Galba, appointed him imperial governor of Lower Germany in 68.The troops in Germany were not friendly to Galba, and Vitellius won them over with generosity. On Jan. 2, 69, his men proclaimed him emperor, and the armies of Upper Germany, as well as most of the governors of Spain, Gaul, and Britain, soon gave him their support as...
</Question>
<Choice>Vitellius, Aulus</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Parthia (reigned c. AD 51–80), the son of the previous king, Vonones II, by a Greek concubine.Vologeses gave the kingdom of Media Atropatene to his brother Pacorus and occupied Armenia for another brother, Tiridates. Parthian control of Armenia, however, led to a long war with the Romans (AD 54–63). A peace was finally concluded by which Tiridates was acknowledged as a Roman client king in Armenia. The power of Vologeses was further weakened by an attack by the nomadic Dahae and Sakas, a rebellion of the Hyrcanians, an invasion by Alani tribesmen in Media and Armenia, and the usurpatio...
</Question>
<Choice>Vologeses I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
one of the rival claimants to the throne of the Parthian king Pacorus II.He first presented himself as the ruler of Parthia in 105/106 and seems to have been able to persist in his claim throughout the reign of Osroes (c. 109/110–c. 128/129). On the death of Osroes, Vologeses was able to overcome another rival, Mithradates IV, and to secure the greater part of the Parthian realm, which he ruled until his death.
</Question>
<Choice>Vologeses III</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Parthia (reigned 148–192).In the early part of his reign he was able to restore the internal unity of the Parthian empire; in 161, however, he invaded Cappadocia and Syria and as a consequence was attacked by a powerful Roman expedition (162–165). Doura-Europus and Seleucia were destroyed, and the Parthian royal palace at Ctesiphon, in Babylonia, was burned; the Romans even advanced into Media. Continued sporadic fighting in Babylonia and Armenia led to further reductions of Parthian influence, and in the peace treaty northern Mesopotamia was ceded to the Romans. Vologeses was succeede...
</Question>
<Choice>Vologeses IV</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Parthia who reigned 191–208/209.He first appeared in 191 as a rebel against his father Vologeses III, whom he succeeded in 192. In 193 he stirred up a rebellion in the Roman client kingdoms of Osroene and Adiabene, but in 195 the Romans under Septimius Severus recovered the districts. After the Roman army departed, Vologeses again swept through Mesopotamia and restored his suzerainty over Adiabene. Subsequently Septimius Severus launched another campaign (197/198–202), advancing into Mesopotamia, occupying Nisibis, and plundering Ctesiphon. He failed, however, in his attempts to conque...
</Question>
<Choice>Vologeses V</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Parthia (reigned 209–c. 212).The son of the Parthian king Vologeses V (or IV), he succeeded his father in 209. Vologeses VI ruled for only about four years before his brother Artabanus V rebelled against him and became master of the greater part of the Parthian empire. But Vologeses VI did manage to maintain himself in parts of Babylonia; his dated coins extend in time to AD 228–229.
</Question>
<Choice>Vologeses VI</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Parthia (reigned AD 7/8–11).Vonones was the eldest son of Phraates IV (q.v.) and was in Rome as a hostage when the Parthian king Orodes III died in about AD 7. The Parthians requested the return of one of the sons of Phraates IV, and the Roman emperor Tiberius sent Vonones. But Vonones' foreign manners and dependence on Rome alienated the Parthians. Artabanus III, king of Media Atropatene, revolted and entered the Parthian capital at Ctesiphon in Mesopotamia about AD 12. Vonones fled to Armenia, where he secured the Armenian throne, but because of pressure from Artabanus he was forced...
</Question>
<Choice>Vonones I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
founder of the short-lived Xin dynasty (AD 9–25). He is known in Chinese history as Shehuangdi (the “Usurper Emperor”), because his reign (AD 9–23) and that of his successor interrupted the Liu family's succession of China's Han dynasty (206 BC–AD 220); as a result, the Han is typically divided into the Xi (Western) and Dong (Eastern) Han periods.
</Question>
<Choice>Wang Mang</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
posthumous name (shi) of the fourth emperor (reigned 180–157 BC) of the Han dynasty (206 BC–AD 220) of China. His reign was marked by good government and the peaceful consolidation of imperial power.A son of Liu Bang (the Gaozu emperor), the founder of the Han dynasty, Liu Heng was the prince of Dai when he was chosen emperor over several other contenders for the imperial throne. His reign of 23 years made him the first Han emperor to rule for such a long period of time and gave the dynasty a stability it had hitherto lacked. The Wendi emperor further weakened the power of local dukes and othe...
</Question>
<Choice>Wen-ti</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
father of Ji Fa (the Wuwang emperor), the founder of the Zhou dynasty (1046–256 BC) and one of the sage rulers regarded by Confucian historians as a model king.Wen was the ruler of Zhou, one of the semibarbaric states on the western frontier of China, long a battleground between the civilized Chinese and nomadic invaders. At some point he had assumed the title Xi Bo (“King of the West”) and had begun to threaten the Shang dynasty (c. 1600–1046 BC). Soon thereafter he was captured and imprisoned by Zhou (or Zi Zhou), the last Shang ruler. During the three years of his imprisonment, according to...
</Question>
<Choice>Wen-wang</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
posthumous name (shi) of the autocratic Chinese emperor (141–87 BC) who vastly increased the authority of the Han dynasty (206 BC–AD 220) and extended Chinese influence abroad. He made Confucianism the state religion of China.Liu Che was probably the 11th son of the Jingdi emperor, the fifth ruler of the Han dynasty. Not being the eldest son, he would normally not have ascended the throne, but relatives of the emperor secured his designation as heir apparent at age seven. From his relatives and his teachers, the future emperor absorbed influences from two basically antagonistic schools: the Da...
</Question>
<Choice>Wu-ti (emperor of Han dynasty)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
posthumous name (shi) of the founder and first emperor (265–290) of the Xi (Western) Jin dynasty (265–316/317), which briefly reunited China during the turbulent period following the dissolution of the Han dynasty (206 BC–AD 220).Sima Yan was the scion of the great Sima clan to which the famous Han historian Sima Qian belonged. He became the most powerful general of the Wei dynasty (220–265/266), the northernmost of the Three Kingdoms into which China had divided at the end of the Han. In 263 the Wei kingdom absorbed the second of the Three Kingdoms, the Shu-Han. In 265 Sima usurped the Wei th...
</Question>
<Choice>Wu-ti (emperor of Chin dynasty)</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
reign name (nianhao) of the founder and first ruler (1046–43 BC) of the Zhou dynasty (1046–256 BC). He was regarded by later Confucians as a wise king.Ji Fa succeeded his father, the famous Wenwang, as head of the semibarbaric state of Zhou, located on the western border of China. Wenwang had assumed the title Xi Bo (“King of the West”) and had begun to plot against the Chinese Shang dynasty (c. 1600–1046 BC). The Wuwang emperor continued his father's work and formed a coalition with eight other border states, which defeated the evil last ruler of the Shang. The final battles were said to have...
</Question>
<Choice>Wu-wang</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Persian king (486–465 BC), the son and successor of Darius I. He is best known for his massive invasion of Greece from across the Hellespont (480 BC), a campaign marked by the battles of Thermopylae, Salamis, and Plataea. His ultimate defeat spelled the beginning of the decline of the Achaemenid Empire.
</Question>
<Choice>Xerxes I</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
king of Judah (597–587/586 BC) whose reign ended in the Babylonian destruction of Jerusalem and the deportation of most of the Jews to Babylon.Mattaniah was the son of Josiah and the uncle of Jehoiachin, the reigning king of Judah. In 597 BC the Babylonians under King Nebuchadrezzar besieged and captured Jerusalem. They deported Jehoiachin to Babylon and made Mattaniah regent under the name Zedekiah. Zedekiah thus held his throne as a vassal under an oath of allegiance to Nebuchadrezzar, but under local pressure he began to intrigue against the latter in concert with the neighbouring states of...
</Question>
<Choice>Zedekiah</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
Eastern Roman emperor whose reign (474–491) was troubled by revolts and religious dissension.Until he married the Eastern emperor Leo I's daughter Ariadne (in 466 or 467), Zeno had been known as Tarasicodissa. As such he led an Isaurian army that the Emperor relied upon to offset the influence of German troops under the powerful patrician Aspar. In 469 Zeno was appointed consul and master of the soldiers. On the death of Leo I early in 474, Zeno's seven-year-old son reigned as Leo II; the child died before the end of the year, after having appointed his father co-emperor.Zeno made a lasting pe...
</Question>
<Choice>Zeno</Choice>
</item>
<item>
<Question>
queen of the Roman colony of Palmyra, in present-day Syria, from 267 or 268 to 272. She conquered several of Rome's eastern provinces before she was subjugated by the emperor Aurelian (ruled 270–275).Zenobia's husband, Odaenathus, Rome's client ruler of Palmyra, had by 267 recovered the Roman East from Persian conquerors. After Odaenathus and his eldest son (by his former wife), Herodes (or Herodianus), were assassinated in 267 or 268, Zenobia became regent for her own young son Wahballat (called Vaballathus in Latin, Athenodorus in Greek). Styling herself queen of Palmyra, she had Vaballathus...
</Question>
<Choice>Zenobia</Choice>
</item>
</topics>